SPEAKER: In Caesar, your task is
going to be to encipher or encrypt
some text by shifting all of the letters
in that text by a certain amount.
What your program is ultimately going to
do is it's first going to get the key--
the amount that we should
shift each character by.
Then we're going to prompt the
user to type in some plain text.
Then we're going to
encipher that plain text
by shifting all the letters by the key.
And finally, we're going to print
out the resulting cipher text.
What does this look like?
Well, if the key is 2, then
for any plaintext character,
we're going to shift that character
by 2 letters in the alphabet.
So if we had a plain
text capital A, that
would become the ciphertext capital
C, because we're shifting it
by 2 letters from the alphabet.
B would become D. C would
become E. So on and so forth up,
until X would become Z.
And then when we get to Y, if we
were to shift Y by 2 characters,
we would go past the
boundary of the alphabet.
So what we'll instead want to do is wrap
around to the beginning of the alphabet
so that Y becomes A
when we shift it by 2,
and Z becomes B when we shift it by 2.
What does this mean for how your
program should actually work?
Well, if we were to run ./caesar and
then provide, a command line argument,
the number 2--
meaning we'd want to use 2 as the
key, shifting everything by 2--
and we were to type
in the plain text ABC,
then your program should
print out the ciphertext CDE--
the same as the plain text, but with
every character shifted by 2 letters.
If we were to instead run ./caesar2
and provide the plain text of "hello,"
for example, --
then the ciphertext
should be this J-G-N-N-Q,
which is each of the letters in
"hello" shifted by 2 letters.
Let's take a look at one last example.
If I were to run ./caesar with a key
of 2 ans input a plaintext of "This is
CS50," then the ciphertext
should look like this.
And there are a couple
of things to note here.
One is that we're preserving case.
If a character is an uppercase
letter in the plaintext,
then it's also an uppercase
letter in the ciphertext.
And likewise, a character that's a
lowercase letter in the plaintext
is also a lowercase
letter in the ciphertext.
And any character that's not an
alphabetical character at all--
so things like spaces or
numbers or punctuation marks--
those don't change.
The spaces stay spaces.
The 50 stays 50.
The exclamation point
stays an exclamation point.
Only the alphabetic
characters are changing.
So let's go through each of
the steps of the caesar program
to figure out how you can actually
write the code to do this.
The first thing you'll want your
program to do is to get the key--
get the amount that we should shift
each of the individual letters by.
How is your program going to do that?
Well, remember that your program is
going to take the key as a command line
argument, meaning that when the
user is running your program,
they're going to run your program
as something like ./caesar,
followed by a number representing the
key of how many characters to shift
each of the letters by.
How do you access those
command line arguments?
Well, recall that in a C program your
main function can take arguments.
It can take an argument
called argc, which
is going to represent the argument
count-- the number of command line
arguments-- and also
an array of strings,
called argv, representing each
of those command line arguments.
So for example, if I were to run
./caesar2 and then the number 3
as the key, argc would be 2.
I typed in two things--
./caesar2 and 3.
And argv is going to be
the actual array of strings
representing those arguments.
And recall that when
you have an array, you
can access an individual element of that
array using square bracket notation.
So argv[0] is going to be the
first string in the argv array--
which, in this case, is ./caesar2--
and argv[1] is going to be the
second thing in that argv array--
which, in this case, is the string 3.
So that's how we might access the key.
Now, when we get the key, you'll want to
ensure that only a single command line
argument is provided, and that
that argument contains only digit
characters before you actually take that
argument and convert it to an integer.
What I mean by that is that if the user
runs ./caesar, and then 2 and then 8,
providing more command line arguments
that's expected, your program,
rather than doing anything else,
should just print out a usage message
reminding the user that in
order to run the Caesar program,
they should run ./caesar2,
followed by a key.
And you should do this anytime they
don't use the correct number of command
line arguments.
But even if they have the correct
number of command line arguments,
that argument might not
be entirely numeric.
If the user runs something
like ./caesar20x,
where the command line argument
is not entirely numeric,
you should also display a usage message
reminding the user that they need
to run ./caesar,
followed by a valid key.
How do you check if the key is valid?
Well, you'll probably want to
take that command line argument
and check each of the
individual characters
in that string to make sure
the character is a digit.
And you might want to
think about what functions
might be helpful for checking if an
individual character is or is not
a digit.
Once you've checked to make sure that
the command line arguments are correct,
the last thing you'll need to do here is
actually take the command line argument
and convert it into an integer.
Notice that argv[1] right
now, representing the key,
is not the number 3,
but the string "three."
Recall that in C, every
variable has a type.
Some variables are ints, and other
variables are strings, for example.
And here, argv[1] is the string
"three," rather than the integer 3--
which we'll probably want to use in
case we need to do some math with that
number, for example.
So what we'll need to do is convert
the string into an into an integer.
To do this, you can
use the A2I function,
declared in standard lib.h, that
takes a string, like the string 3,
and converts it into the
number 3, for example.
So that function might be
helpful for making sure
that your key is in fact an integer.
After you've gotten
the key, the next step
is to prompt the user to
type in the plaintext.
To do that, you can use
a call to get string,
asking the user to type in what
plaintext they want to encrypt.
Once you've gotten that
plaintext, the next step
is going to be to encipher that
plaintext, shifting all of the letters
by the key to get the ciphertext result.
But before we talk about how to
encipher the entire plaintext,
let's just talk about how to
encipher one particular character.
How are we going to do that?
Well, there are a couple of cases
that we might want to consider.
If the character is an alphabetic
character, like an uppercase letter
or a lowercase letter,
for example, then we'll
want to shift that plaintext
character by the key,
making sure to preserve the case.
If it was originally
an uppercase letter,
it should stay in uppercase
letter, for example.
Of course, if the character is
not alphabetic-- for example,
if it's a space or a
punctuation mark or a digit--
then you can leave the character as is.
Nothing actually needs to change there.
But how do you know if a character
is an alphabetic character
or an uppercase character
or a lowercase character?
Well, it turns out, there are
a number of functions that you
can use that might be helpful here.
Functions like is alpha,
is upper, and is lower.
Is alpha is a function
that takes a character
and returns a Boolean
value, true or false,
depending on whether or not
that character is alphabetic.
And likewise, is upper checks to
see if the character is uppercase
and is lower checks to see
if a character is lowercase.
If we call is alpha, is upper,
and is lower on capital A,
for example, is alpha
of capital A is true.
It is an alphabetic character.
Is upper of capital A is
also true because capital A
is an uppercase letter.
And is lower of capital A is
false because capital A is not
a lowercase letter.
And so that can help you to figure
out, given a particular character,
is it an uppercase character
or is it a lowercase character?
And every character, uppercase
and lowercase, has an ASCII value.
Recall that ASCII is just a
mapping from characters to numbers
that represent them, where we've
decided that capital A is represented
by the number 65, capital B is
represented by the number 66,
so on and so forth.
And lowercase letters
have a mapping as well.
Lowercase a is represented by the
number 97, lowercase b by the number
98, lowercase c by 99,
so on and so forth.
And you can treat any
individual character
as equivalent to the
number that represents it.
So what does that mean in code?
Well, it means that if I have a
character in a variable called
c that I set equal to the character A--
capital A-- and I print out that
character using %c to mean I want
to substitute a character into this
string, then what gets printed out,
as you might expect, is the character
A. But this character A is really just
the number 65 inside of my computer,
and I can treat this character like
the number 65.
And like any number, I can do math
with it, adding or subtracting
numbers from it, for example.
So I can take capital A and
add 1 to it, for example.
Capital A is represented by 65.
65 plus 1 is 66.
So if I print out the
character corresponding
to the number 66, what's
ultimately going to be printed out
is the character B because B in ASCII
is represented by the number 66.
But what happens if I try to take a
character like the character capital Z
and shift that by one?
If I take the ASCII value corresponding
to the letter Z and add 1 to it,
I don't get the ASCII
value corresponding
to capital A. I get something
that's outside of the range of all
of the capital letters.
What I'd really like to
happen here is that once I
try to shift past the letter
Z, I want to wrap around back
to the beginning of the alphabet, back
to the letter A. But how do I do that?
Well, to do this, we can
take advantage of a formula.
And here's the formula that
we're going to use to convert
the plaintext into the ciphertext.
It looks a little bit complicated, but
we'll break it down piece by piece.
c sub i here represents the ith
character of the ciphertext.
How do we determine what the ith
character of the ciphertext is?
Well, we're going to start by taking
the ith character of the plaintext
and we're going to add k
to it, where k is the key.
And we're going to take that whole
result and take it modulo 26.
This %26 means we're going to take the
remainder when we take this whole value
and divide it by 26.
Why does this work?
Well, for sake of example, let's say
that a is represented by the number 0,
b is represented by the number 1, c is
represented by 2, so on and so forth,
up until z, represented
by the number 25.
So how might I go about
taking the character z
and shifting it by 1,
using this formula?
Well, here is the formula.
And the plaintext
character I want to shift
is the character z, which is here
represented by the number 25.
And I want to shift it by the
key k, which in this case is 1.
So I have 25 plus 1, which
is the number 26, and 26--
mod 26-- is what's the remainder
when I divide 26 by 26?
Well, the remainder is just
0, so I'm left with 0, which
corresponds to a in the above chart.
The result is that I'm
able to take a character,
shift it by a certain amount.
And by using modulo 26, I'm able to
get the remainder when I divide it
by 26, which allows
me to loop back around
effectively to the beginning of the
alphabet so that z wraps around to a.
And this mapping of a to 0,
b to 1, c to 2, et cetera,
you can call an alphabetical index.
Where I might say that a's
alphabetical index is 0,
b's alphabetical index is 1, c's
alphabetical index is 2, and so forth.
But of course, in our computer, we
don't use the alphabetical index
to represent each character.
We use ASCII, where A is
65 and B is 66 and C is 67,
and so we can't directly
apply this formula.
So what do we need to do in
order to take an ASCII character
and shift it by a certain
amount, while still preserving
this wrap-around effect of going
from the end of the alphabet back
to the beginning?
Well, here's what we might try to do.
We might first convert an ASCII
character to its alphabetical index
so that capital A becomes
the number 0, for example,
and capital B becomes the number 1.
And you might want to think about what
math you could do to make that work.
Once you have an alphabetical index,
you can shift that alphabetical index
using the formula, adding the
key and taking the result mod
26 to get the new character's
alphabetical index.
And finally, you can take the
resulting alphabetical index
and convert that back
into ASCII, so that 0
becomes A, 1 becomes
B, so on and so forth,
being sure to preserve the case--
uppercase letters
should remain uppercase,
lowercase letters
should remain lowercase.
And that will allow you to
encipher one alphabetic character.
If it's alphabetic, you'll want to
shift it to its alphabetic index,
then shift it using the formula, then
convert the result back to ASCII.
But how, then, instead of
enciphering just a single character,
do you encipher all of the
characters that are in the plaintext?
Well, recall that the plaintext
is really just a string.
And when you have a string, you can
access individual characters by using
array-like notation, where I can say
text[0] will get me the first character
of the string text, which in
this case is capital T. Likewise,
text[1] is lowercase h, text[2] is
lowercase i, so on and so forth.
And I can use this
notation to access any
of the characters inside of the string.
How do I know how many
characters are in the string?
Well, there's another function called
strlen, short for string length,
that will take a string and tell
you how many characters are in it.
In this case, 12.
So by combining this, knowing
the length of the string,
knowing how to access an
individual character in the string,
and knowing how to encipher an
you should be able to implement this
Caesar program by first figuring out
what the key is, then
getting the plaintext,
then enciphering that plaintext by
shifting all the alphabetic characters,
and printing the result. My name
is Brian and this was Caesar.