BRIAN YU: The next filter that
you'll implement is called edges.
In edges, what you're going
to do is take an image
and apply the Sobel edge
detection algorithm to this image
in order to highlight all of
the boundaries between objects.
Notice that we've highlighted
the boundaries of the bridge
in this case and some of the plants
that are surrounding the water here.
And this is the algorithm that
you're going to try to create.
But how do we take an
image and figure out
where the boundaries between
objects actually are?
Well, let's first look
at a simplified image
to try to get a sense for how we can
detect boundaries between objects.
Here we have two objects, a
blue rectangle on the left
and a red rectangle on the right.
And as you might guess,
this middle purple line you
can think of as a boundary
between these two objects.
How do we know it's a boundary?
Well, it's a boundary because the
colors on the left side of the line
are different from the colors
on the right side of the line.
And the same thing
could be generally true
when we start to think about edge
detection in more complex images.
If we have a line where, on the left
side of the line, colors are one value,
and on the right side of the line, the
colors are a very different value, that
indicates a major change
in color across pixels,
and therefore, might indicate a
boundary between objects in that image.
So you recall that every pixel is
composed of color values of red, green,
and blue, but let's first
just look at red values,
and look at the red value
for each of these pixels,
and take a look at how
those values change
as we move from left to
right inside of this image.
So if we just look at
the red values, you'll
notice that all the pixels
on the left, the blue pixels,
have a red channel value of zero.
All the red pixels on the right-hand
side have a channel value of 255,
and in the middle, they're somewhere
in between with a red channel
value of 128, for example.
How are we going to determine
whether, at any particular point,
we're noticing a change in color from
one red value to another red value?
Well, to do that, we're going to use
what's called a convolutional matrix.
Here, for example, is
the convolutional matrix
called gx, which is going
to determine whether or not
there is some sort of change in
color or boundary between objects
as we move in the x
direction in the image,
moving from left to right, for example.
And the idea of this is going to
be very similar to the algorithm
that we applied in blur
where we took a pixel
and looked at the nine pixels that
formed a square around that pixel
to compute a new value
for that same pixel.
We're going to do the same thing here,
except rather than just averaging
all of the values
around the middle pixel,
we're instead going to multiply
each of the surrounding
pixels by a different value.
Let's take a look at an example.
So here, we're going to apply
this gx convolutional matrix
to try to compute what the value
of gx should be for this red pixel
right here.
Now, notice that this red pixel
does not have a whole lot of change
happening around it.
To the left and to the right of it, it
still has a lot of red surrounding it,
so we should expect that
this gx value that we compute
will be very low, indicating that there
is not much change in the red color
as we move from left to
right along this pixel.
So what does this actually look like?
Well, we're first, much
as with blur, going
to form a 3-by-3 grid of pixels
that surround the center pixel,
and then we're going to
do some calculations.
We'll take our gx convolutional
matrix and first look
at the value in the upper left.
It's negative 1, and so we're
going to multiply negative 1
by the red value in the upper left
of this 3-by-3 grid of pixels,
in this case 255.
Then we'll move on and
say, all right, let's
take the top pixel in this 3-by-3 grid.
The matrix says that we should multiply
its value by 0, so we have 0 times 255.
And then we have 1 times 255.
And we're going to repeat this
process of adding up negative 2
times the red value of the pixels
on the left, which in this case
is also 255, plus 0 times
255, the pixel in the middle.
Then the right is going
to be 2 times 255.
Then the bottom left is minus
1 times 255, plus 0 times 255,
plus 1 times 255.
And if we do the math, performing
all these multiplications
and adding all these numbers
together, what you'll notice
is that everything cancels out.
All of the plus 1 times 255s cancel
out with a minus 1 times 255,
and the plus 2 times 255 cancels
out with a minus 2 times 255.
So the result of all this
after we do all the math
is that we get the number
0, implying that there's
no change in the red values
as we move from left to right.
And that's to be expected here,
because as we look at this grid,
we see that all of the pixels are red.
What might happen, though,
if we instead try to apply
this matrix to a different pixel--
say, for example, this pixel
here in the middle, where
you'll notice if we take a look
at the 3-by-3 grid of pixels
that surround this middle pixel, we
see that the color values do change?
There's an increase in red
from 0 on the left-hand side
to 255 on the right-hand side.
That's a big change in
the red channel value,
so we would expect that after we do
this calculation of the value of gx
that we would get a large value.
So how do we do the math here?
Well, again, we'll do
negative 1 times the value
of the pixel in the upper left, 0, plus
0 times the value of the pixel on top,
128, plus 1 times the value of
the pixel in the upper right,
255, and then repeating this process
for each of the other pixels--
minus 2 times 0, plus 0 times
128, the pixel in the middle,
plus 2 times 255 for
the pixels on the right,
and then repeating the same
process for the bottom row.
After we do all of that math and
calculate it, the answer that we get
is 1,020, a big number
that's going to represent
the fact that as we move from
left to right along this pixel,
we see a large change
in the value of red.
And that's pretty good evidence that
there is some sort of boundary that's
happening here.
So how do we take this and
apply it not just to one pixel,
but to all of the pixels in the image?
Well there are a couple of things
that we need to keep in mind.
First of all, we've so far only done
this calculation for red values.
And you'll imagine
you'll probably also want
to do the same calculation for
the values in the green channel
as well as for the values
in the blue channel.
But also, thus far, we're only
looking at changes in the x direction
as we move from left to right,
taking a look at whether there's
a big increase or a big
decrease in the value of red,
green, or blue, for example.
But you could also imagine
that there might be boundaries
as we look in the y direction,
from the top of the image
to the bottom of the image.
We might find places where
there are horizontal lines where
we go from low values to
high values or vise versa.
So in addition to a gx
convolutional matrix, which
is going to look for
boundaries in the x direction,
we're also going to want to
introduce a gy matrix, which is going
to look for changes in the y direction.
And the gy matrix is going
to look very similar.
Just rotate it.
Here we're going to say, take all
the values in the three pixels
below this middle pixel, and multiply
them by 1, 2, and 1 respectively,
and take all the values in the row of
three pixels above this middle pixel
and multiply those by negative
1, negative 2, and negative 1
respectively, the result of which
is that we'll compute a value that
will approximately represent how
the value of red or green or blue
is changing as we move from the
pixels above a pixel to the pixels
below a pixel.
And so we'll use these
two matrices, gx and gy,
to compute how much colors are changing.
How do you use these results
to actually determine what
the new value of each pixel should be?
Well, for each pixel,
you're going to want
to compute gx and gy for each
channel of red, green, and blue.
So ultimately, you're going to
be computing six different values
by applying the gx matrix
to all of the red values,
then to the green values and the blue
values, and doing the same for gy.
Of course, as in the
case with blur, there
will be situations where we're looking
at a pixel at the border, in the corner
or at the edge of the image where there
isn't a perfect 3-by-3 grid of pixels
that surrounds it, for example.
In that case, for any pixels
that are at the border,
you should treat any
pixel values that are
beyond the border as having all
zero values or being pure black,
for example.
So for the pixel in the corner,
in the upper left corner,
for example, the pixel immediately
above it, which doesn't exist,
you should just treat as having all zero
values, as being a solid black pixel.
Once you've computed
these gx and gy values
for each of red, green,
and blue, you need
to use those values to somehow compute
the total amount of red, green,
and blue that should be in the
new pixel in the resulting image.
So to do that, we're
going to use this formula.
You're going to compute each new
channel value as the square root of gx
squared plus gy squared.
So to compute the new value
of red for a particular pixel,
you're going to compute gx for that
red pixel based on the original image,
and you're going to compute gy for that
square them both, add them
together, and take the square root.
We're squaring each of them to make
sure that the magnitude we end up with
is a positive value because
regardless of whether there's
a big increase in red or
a big decrease in red,
we still want to represent that as
a potential border from a lot of red
to a little bit of red or vise versa.
And squaring the number makes sure
we end up with a positive value.
And we're taking the
square root to normalize.
Of course, as with the other filters, it
may be the case that the value you get
exceeds the maximum
channel value of 255.
And in that case, you
should be careful to make
sure to cap the value you
get at the number 255.
And you'll repeat the same
process for red and green and blue
for each of the original
pixels, computing gx and gy
based on the original image in order
to calculate a new channel value
for each pixel in the resulting image.
After you've done all of that, you
should be able to test your program
by running ./filter, -e for edges, and
then providing the name of an input
bitmap file as well as an output bitmap
file that you're hoping to generate.
And if all goes well, you should
see that you take the original image
and highlight where all of
the edges in that image are.
My name is Brian, and this was edges.