BRIAN YU: In Movies, you are going to
write a number of different SQL queries
to answer questions based
on a database of movies
that we are going to provide to you.
When you begin the
problem, we'll give to you
a file called movies.db, which is a
SQLite database file, inside of which
contains a number of pieces
of information about movies
and the people in those movies, as
well as ratings for those movies,
provided by IMDb.
So what tables are
inside of this database?
Well, first, there will
be a table of movies,
a table of people for people that are
in those movies, a table of directors,
of people who have directed movies,
of stars of people who have starred
in movies, and then finally,
a table of ratings for ratings
for each of those individual movies.
Let's now take a look at each
of these tables one-by-one
to see what columns are
in these tables and how
the tables relate to one another.
And we'll start with the movies table.
Inside of the movies table,
we'll have rows of data
where every row has three entries--
an ID, a title, and a year.
So for example, your table might
look a little something like this.
The IDs are probably different,
but here in this example,
we have a row that
represents the movie Titanic,
which is movie ID number 1, as well
as the year in which that movie was
released, 1997.
And then we have another entry
for each of the other movies
inside of this database.
In addition to a table
for movies, we also
have a table for people-- for
people that were somehow involved
with the development of those movies.
And so inside of the people
table, we have three columns--
an ID column, a name column,
and a birth column, where ID--
again, it's just a unique identifier
representing that individual person.
Name is the name of the person
that's being represented in that row.
And then birth is going to
represent that person's birth year.
So here, for example, we have
at least six different people.
Again, in the database we provide to
you, these ID numbers may be different.
But here's just a sampling of
what the table might look like.
So now we have a table of movies
representing movies inside
of the database, as well
as a table of people
representing all of the people
involved with those movies.
But now we need some way of
relating these two tables together.
And to do that, we're going to
use what's known as an association
table, or a join table.
And the first of these join tables we'll
take a look at is called directors.
And directors is going to be a
table that maps movies onto people.
In other words, this
table is going to tell us
which people directed which movies.
There are two columns in the
table, movie_id and person_id.
And the table might
look a little something
like this, where for every row we just
have one number representing a movie ID
and one number representing a person ID.
How do you interpret this information?
Well, in order to understand
it, we need to look back
to those previous tables
we've just taken a look at--
the movies table and the people table.
This first row in the directors
table says that movie ID 3
was directed by person ID 2.
So if we take the number 3, which
is the ID in the movies table,
and look that up, we see that movie ID
3 is Finding Nemo, released in 2003.
Who is the director of Finding Nemo?
Well, movie ID 3 maps onto person ID 2.
And so if we look in the people table
and look at the entry with an ID of 2,
we see Andrew Stanton, born in
1965, as the director of that movie.
And likewise, if we look at the
second row, mapping a movie ID of 2
to a person ID of 6, we can see
that Jurassic Park was directed
by Steven Spielberg, for instance.
So this table that maps movie
IDs to person IDs, in combination
with the movies and
people table, will tell us
which people directed which movies.
Likewise, we are also going to
have a join table that represents
who starred in each of the movies.
And so for this, we'll
have another table
called stars that has the exact same
structure as the directors table--
just two columns, a movie_id
column and a person_id column,
where every row in that table means
that this particular person starred
in that particular movie.
So here, for example, our
first row says that movie
ID 1 had a star given by person ID 4.
And so if we again look at
those movies and people table,
we'll see that person ID with number
4 is Leonardo DiCaprio, born in 1974,
who starred in movie ID 1,
Titanic, released in 1997.
So using these tables
in combination, we're
able to identify not only who
directed each of the movies,
but also who starred
in each of the movies.
And of course, a movie could
have more than one star
and more than one director.
And likewise, an individual person might
direct or star in more than one movie.
So you might see these IDs repeat across
these join tables, directors and stars,
as well.
The final table that
we'll take a look at here
is the ratings table,
which represents the rating
for each of these individual movies.
This table will have three columns--
movie_id, rating, and
votes, where movie_id
represents the ID of
the movie being rated,
rating is the rating given to that movie
by IMDb on a scale from 0 up to 10,
and votes is the number
of people who have voted
for a rating for that particular movie.
In combination with the
movies table, these two tables
can tell us, for any particular
movie, what its rating is.
So if, for example, we wanted to
know what Jurassic Park's rating is,
we would first look for Jurassic
Park in the movies table
and find out that it has an
ID of 2 in the movies table.
Then we would go and
look at the ratings table
and look for a row with a
movie ID of 2, and find out
that that movie has a rating of 8.1,
with about 800,000 people or so who
have voted on that particular movie.
So the movie_id column
in the ratings table
corresponds to the ID
inside of the movies table.
And so now with all of
these tables combined,
we can take any movie and figure
out which people directed it,
which people starred in that movie, and
also what rating that movie received.
And using that information, we
can begin to answer questions
by writing SQL SELECT queries
that are able to select data
from all of these tables to get
the data that we are interested in.
If you'd like to try running
some of these SELECT queries,
then inside of your Terminal, you
can run the command sqlite3 followed
by the name of the database--
in this case, movies.db--
in order to execute any
individual SQL query.
So what are you going
to do for this problem?
Well, for each question
that we ask you, you
are going to write a single SQL
query that will answer that question.
And importantly, your query should
just be, one, a single query, but two,
it should only output the data
that is explicitly asked for.
So if we only ask you for
the title of the movie,
then you should output only
the titles of the movies
and not also the years in which those
movies were released, for example.
And finally, be careful not to
assume the values of any IDs.
You'll notice that every person,
every movie inside of your database
has a particular ID.
But you shouldn't assume
what those ID values
will be when you're writing your query.
You should write your
query in such a way
that even if the IDs
were different, you're
still able to get the correct
answer by running your query.
What are some sample
queries you might write?
Well, in general, your queries are going
to follow a format kind of like this.
If you're selecting
something from a table,
SELECT * FROM table1, where
table1 is the name of a table,
is perhaps the simplest
query you could come up with,
just to select everything
from one of the tables.
If you only want to
select particular columns,
you could specify, using a
comma-separated list of columns,
which columns you would like to select.
So if col1 and col2 are names
of columns in that table,
then this query would extract
from that table all of the rows,
but only looking at
those particular columns.
If you don't want to get all of the rows
and only want to get some of the rows,
you might filter this table
based on a particular condition
with a query like this--
selecting particular
columns from that table
where column 3, which is some
other column, for example,
is equal to a particular
value, where that value might
be a number or a string
or whatever value it
is that you care about searching for.
For more complex queries, though,
where the answer to your question
might not just come
from one table but might
come from a combination of
multiple different tables,
it might be helpful to nest one
SQL query inside of another.
So in this case, for example, if you
don't know what the value of col3 is,
you could instead replace
value with a nested SQL
query where you might replace
it with another SELECT query
where you're selecting a
particular value, for example,
and then checking to see if
col3 is equal to that inside
of a different table.
And you can do this over and
over again, nesting SQL queries
inside of one another in order
to build up more complex queries.
If your inner nested query doesn't
just return a single result,
but maybe returns a list
of possible results,
you can also use the IN keyword to
find out if the value of column 3
is in some list of possible values that
that column could take on, for example.
And that might help you to
broaden your search parameters
to search for more possible rows inside
of table1, in this particular case.
Other things that might prove useful
are ordering the results in some way.
And so you could also
say ORDER by col3 to say
that when you're selecting from table1,
you would like for all of the rows
to be in order based on their
value for col3, for whatever name
column 3 happens to be.
And you can also add the DESC keyword
to the end of that for descending order
if you want to go in reverse order
instead of increasing order, which
is the default.
Finally, you might find it useful
to join two tables together,
where oftentimes these tables have
fields that correspond to one another,
and so you might want to take
two or three separate tables
and join them together
into a single table
to make it easier to select
and filter that table based
on particular conditions.
So to do that, the syntax is going
to look a little something like this,
where you're going to select from
table1 but join it with another table,
in this case called table2.
And then you need to tell SQL how
to join these two tables together.
So here we're saying table1.col1
corresponds to table2.col3.
So you'll need to figure out
which column from the first table
corresponds to which other
column from the second table.
You'll write each of these queries in
individual .sql files that then can be
executed on your SQLite database.
And if you'd like to test
running one of these SQL files
on your SQLite database, you
can run a command like this.
cat 1.sql will output
the contents of 1.sql,
and this vertical bar
is called the pipe.
We're sending data from
1.sql into sqlite3 movies.db,
which will run the query inside of
1.sql on your movies.db database.
So you can test each of your individual
SQL queries using this syntax.
And that's it.
Once you've written SQL
files that have queries
that will answer each
of the questions, you
can try running those SQL
queries on your database
to see if the results are
what you would expect.
My name is Brian, and this was Movies.