BRIAN YU: Let's take
a look at readability.
In readability, your task is going
to be to write a program in C that
can take some text and assess the
approximate reading level of that text.
So for example, you might run
your program as ./readability.
Your program should then prompt
the user to type in some text.
And after the user
types in a few sentences
maybe, your program is going to produce
as output the approximate US grade
reading level for that particular text.
Maybe this text for instance, is most
appropriate for a third grade reading
level.
But if instead the user were to type
in a more sophisticated text, then
your program might output
something like this
is more appropriate for a fifth
grade reading level, for example.
But what does it really
mean for a text to be
appropriate for a third grade reading
level or a fifth grade reading level?
Well, taking a look at these examples,
we might make a couple of observations.
We might observe the
first, longer words tend
to mean that a text is more
appropriate for a higher reading level.
We might also observe that if
there are more words in a sentence,
in other words, the longer sentences,
that too generally tends to correlate
with a higher reading level.
In fact, there are formulas
that we can use in order
to calculate based on any particular
text what grade level might
be appropriate for that text.
One such formula that we'll use
here is the Coleman-Liau Index,
which is calculated as follows.
It's calculated as 0.0588 times
L minus 0.296 times S minus 15.8.
Where here L represents the
average number of letters
per 100 words in this
text, and S represents
the average number of sentences
per 100 words in this text.
So in order to determine the
readability of a particular text, what
we need to do is calculate the number
of letters, words, and sentences
in that text and then use
the commonly index formula
to figure out what grade level
might be most appropriate.
So let's take a look
at each of those three
in sequence beginning with figuring
out how many letters are in the text.
In this case, we're
going to count the number
of uppercase and lowercase
letters in the text
to determine the total
number of letters.
And recall that if you have some
text as a string, for example,
we can treat that string
as an array of characters.
So if we have an array
of characters and we
want to find out how
many letters there are,
we might start by
creating a variable, I'll
call it letters, that's going to
keep track of how many letters
we found inside of this string.
At first, letters is going to be 0.
But we can loop through
this string one character
at a time checking each character
to see whether or not it's a letter.
The first character is a letter.
So we can increase
the count from 0 to 1.
The next character is also a
letter it's a lowercase letter.
And so the count increases from 1 to 2.
And we can repeat that
process for every character.
Notice though that if we come across
a character that is not a letter,
like a space or a number
or a punctuation mark,
we don't want to count that in
our total account of letters.
So we shouldn't increment letters here.
But when we get to the next
character that is a letter,
then we can increment the count.
And we'll do that for
the rest of this string
until we end up with a final
count of the number of letters
that are inside of this text.
You might find that C has some
helpful library functions declared
in a file called ctype.h that might
help you for taking a character
and assessing whether or
not it is in fact a letter.
Once we figured out how many letters
there are inside of the text,
the next step is going to be to
calculate how many words there
are inside of the text.
And this gets a little bit
trickier because we first
need to decide what does it
mean for something to be a word.
And for the purposes
of this problem, we're
going to count the number
of words in a sentence
by assuming that a word is
any sequence of characters
that is separated by a space.
So every time you see a space
appear in the text, that's
going to be an indication
that a new word is coming.
And so if we were to take a string
again, just an array of characters
and try and find out how
many words there are,
we might start by looking to see
how many spaces there are inside
of this string.
And if we were to loop
through this string checking
for the number of spaces, we might
find that there are four spaces inside
of the string, for example.
But we shouldn't jump to then
saying that there are therefore
four words inside of this string.
After all, spaces
appear in between words
and there's a space after
each word, but there's
no space after the last
word in the string.
You can assume that the
string we provide to you
won't start or end with a space.
So even though there are four
spaces inside of the string,
there are actually five
words in the string.
And in general, we can
take the number of spaces
and add 1 to it to figure out
how many words there are inside
of any given piece of text.
After we figured out how
many words there are,
the final step in terms of
what we need to count up
is counting up the number of sentences
that appear in that text as well.
And again, for the
purposes of this program,
we're going to assume that any period,
exclamation point, or question mark
is going to indicate
the end of a sentence.
So figuring out how many sentences
there are in a particular text
is just a matter of counting up how many
times do we see periods, exclamation
points, or question marks.
So for example, let's take this text.
Congratulations!
Today is your day.
In this particular string, you'll notice
that there are two punctuation marks
that denote the end of a sentence.
We have one exclamation
point and one period.
And so as a result, we could conclude
that based on this particular string,
we're able to find two
sentences inside of that string.
Once we've counted up the number
of letters, words, and sentences
that appear inside a
given text, the next step
is going to be to use those values
to calculate what the Coleman-Liau
Index should actually be.
In order to do so, you're going to take
these three values: letters, words,
and sentences and plug them into
the common layout index formula.
Again, that formula is here.
That's a result of multiplying the
average number of letters per 100 words
by a particular value and
subtracting the result
of taking the average number of
sentences per 100 words multiplied
by a value as well and
subtracting 15.8 at the end
in order to get an estimate for
what the approximate reading
level of a particular text is.
Ultimately, your program should
output what that grade reading
level is but be sure to round your
score to the nearest whole number.
So for example, if your
index is 2.8, you're
going to round that and say that it's
about a third grade reading level.
And your program should output
squared X, where X corresponds
to the reading level of that text.
But we do want to set a
minimum and a maximum here.
If it turns out that your output
would have been less than 1,
your program should just
output before grade 1.
And if the output is 16 or
higher, then your program
should output grade 16 plus.
But anywhere in between
grades 2 through 15,
your program should output grade 2,
grade 3, grade 4, et, cetera, as it
corresponds to the reading
level of the program.
Once you follow these steps, you should
have a completed readability program
where you can type in some
text, and your program
will calculate what US grade
reading level would be most
appropriate for that particular text.
My name is Brian.
And this was readability.