CARTER ZENKE: Hello, one and all.
And welcome to CS50's very
first super section for week 1.
My name is Carter Zenke.
I'm the course's preceptor.
I'm joined here by many of
our wonderful staff members
that are going to
stand up and say hello.
[APPLAUSE]
Yeah, a round of
applause for these folks.
They're wonderful.
They'll be helping you through
this super section today.
This is our first super
section for the course.
On a normal week, you actually
attend your own section
online by course's head teaching fellow.
You signed up for those
online at Harvard.
And you'll attend those
starting next week.
But this week, given
the odd schedule, we
thought we'd come together
for one large section overall.
So here are these details here.
You're going to email if you've got
any questions, heads@cs50.harvard.edu.
And all of our slides and intros
for today will be at this URL
down here on the course website,
going to the super section page there.
To kick things off, though,
I thought we'd actually
have you all talk to each other and
think about these two questions.
So think back to lecture and
think about this first question.
What did you find exciting
from that lecture?
And what are you still confused about?
What do you still have questions about?
So turn to somebody, perhaps who you
don't know and talk about those two
questions for 2 minutes here.
One, what are you excited about?
Two, what do you still
have questions about?
Let's come back from
these conversations.
So glad you are having this
wonderful discussion here.
And let's hear from a
few different groups
on what you were thinking
about for these questions here.
Thank you, all.
Let's actually turn to
this left-hand section.
Could one group over
here tell me what you're
excited about for this week and
one thing you're still wondering
or you have questions about?
One group from this side of the room?
Can I narrow it down to somebody
from the front row perhaps?
What are you interested in?
What do you still have
questions about for this week?
Yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: I think it's more of the-- and
less of the code, the syntax itself.
Because that, you can kind
of pick up quite quickly.
I think the hardest thing is probably
to how you construct efficient code.
You sometimes just have to
think in a different way.
CARTER ZENKE: Nice.
STUDENT: That's something
that I guess, we'll
really take some time to come to terms.
CARTER ZENKE: Totally, yeah.
So there's a question, how
do you write efficient code?
And later today, we'll actually
work on the course's lab,
this practice problem to
help you see how we can
write efficient code in that instance.
You can work together on this practice
problem and get ideas from each other
as we go through.
Let's hear from maybe one
more group over on this side,
maybe somebody in the second
row back here, if you mind.
One thing you're interested
in, yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: I'm really interested
in also this kind of stuff,
but also creating stuff, just
coding to have a the final product.
And now I'll get opportunities
to make a final product.
And somebody else to
think about lecture,
I feel like there's so
much syntax to learn.
And that's sort of giving me pause.
It's like, I don't even
know what's out there.
I think somebody said,
actually in the orientation,
sometimes like students
will go something
all the way out because they don't
even know that there's a program for it
already.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, exactly.
So there's this idea of how
you take this idea you have
and what you want to build
and turn into the syntax,
like actually write to make the computer
do what you want it to do, right?
So all these are good questions.
And here are a few we'll
actually dive in to today.
The first is, why are we using C?
Why we're using this ancient language
to start off programming with?
And how do we learn and
read its syntax here?
How can we actually learn how to create
and read these variables, these loops
and conditionals, and so on.
As we go through that, we'll talk about
this particular instance of a data type
because C requires us to tell what
type each pieces of our data are.
We'll also talk about compiling C
programs, taking them from source code
to machine code.
And then finally, at
the very end, we'll talk
about how many years it will take
to double our number of llamas
that we have in the lab.
So to kick things off here, we can
go back to actually lecture zero,
I think, back to our
contact application.
So in this application we stored names
and phone numbers and other things too.
What else could we store
in a contact's application?
Could I ask maybe somebody from the
second row, in this middle row here?
What can we store in a
contact's application?
Yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: Phone numbers.
CARTER ZENKE: Phone numbers,
right, other things too.
Maybe somebody in the row up now.
STUDENT: Emails.
CARTER ZENKE: Emails, OK.
Other things?
Let's go one row up again.
What else can we store?
STUDENT: Addresses.
CARTER ZENKE: Addresses, nice.
So all these things we can store
in our contact's application.
But let's say you want to
store the number of times
I want to actually have made a call
before in my application, on my phone,
right?
So here we have an instance of a
variable, some number or some value
that can change.
And I'm going to give a name
to it, in this case, calls,
number of times I called somebody here.
So this is our mental representation
of what a variable is.
It's some name for a
value that can change.
But in C, we have a particular
syntax I'll use to make variables.
As you all go through and work
on the course's problem set,
build your own programs, you really
should get familiar with this syntax
and how to read and write it here.
So here we have the syntax in C to
create this variable named calls.
And there are some components to it
that we should actually dive into here.
So the first part is
the variable's name.
This name is calls.
Notice how it's in the
middle of this sentence here.
We also have the variables
type, this int type.
And what does this int type stand for?
What kind of number are
we going to store in here?
Could I ask somebody from down here?
Yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: An integer.
CARTER ZENKE: An integer,
so a whole number, right?
Then we have the value, in
this case, 4, that value we're
putting inside this variable here.
But there's one piece we're missing,
we haven't talked about yet.
What haven't we named here yet?
Could I ask somebody from
maybe this side of the room?
Take a guess?
We talked about the name of the
variable, the type, the value.
What syntax haven't we shown yet?
Yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
semicolon [INAUDIBLE]..
CARTER ZENKE: The semicolon, right?
So this is a statement in C. And
every closing statement that we have,
we want to include a semicolon there.
The other thing we haven't
talked about, the one
piece we haven't talked
about here, could I
ask somebody from down here now?
We have the semicolon, the
value, the name, the data type.
One more thing, yeah.
STUDENT: The equals sign.
CARTER ZENKE: The equals sign, and is
it an equals sign, could I ask you?
No, you're shaking your head.
STUDENT: It's and assignment.
CARTER ZENKE: It's an
assignment operator, right?
So we'll say this is going to assign
the value 4 to the space we've
created for this variable named call.
So if you say this in
English here, we're
going to create an integer variable.
Notice how this type
aligns with this type here.
Named calls, the name lines up here.
That gets, or that kind of stores
this value 4, in this instance.
So let's try again with
another value here.
Int x equals sign 50, and let's actually
say this one all together, if we could.
How do we say we create a what?
STUDENT: Integer.
CARTER ZENKE: (CLASS
REPEATING AFTER) Integer
that called x that gets the value 50.
Nice.
That's what it would be in English here.
Amazing.
Yeah, high fives all around.
So why does C care so much
about data types though?
The very first thing we say here
is not the name of the error
but actually the data type.
So we saw briefly this
idea in lecture, but let's
go ahead and talk to
the person next to you.
Why do you think C cares so
much about these data types?
Why is it the first thing
we tell the computer when
we make this variable here?
We'll come back in just a minute.
OK, let's come back and hear
some ideas for why does C
care so much about data types?
Why is it the very first thing
we put in a given line of code
to make a variable in this case?
And can we go back to maybe
this side of the room now.
And anyone in particular
like to share what
your group talked about, what ideas
you had for this question here?
Yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: Basically, we said
that C wants to know data type.
That's in order restrict
the values that we input.
For instance, if we're talking
about [INAUDIBLE] input
3.5, so for [INAUDIBLE].
So it limits [INAUDIBLE].
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, there's some
value for specificity, right?
I want to be able to
make sure that I'm not
putting in some value I couldn't
store in this variable, like a text,
for example.
Other reasons too.
Could we go to maybe down here?
Yeah.
STUDENT: The computer needs
to know how much memory
to allocate to the [INAUDIBLE].
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, and
why would that matter?
Can I ask you, get a little deeper too?
Why does this size matter?
STUDENT: Because I think an
integer is a lot less size than--
a lot less [INAUDIBLE].
CARTER ZENKE: Totally, so using--
or storing different values
makes that value take away
different space in a computer's memory.
So integers take up maybe
32 bits, but a character
might take up only eight bits.
And so it tells the
compiler how much memory,
how much space to reserve here too.
One other reason that we saw a
little bit in lecture as well is we
have some binary here, these eight bits
that can represent a certain, well,
really anything.
What does this represent here?
Anyone know off the top of their head?
Yeah.
STUDENT: No, sorry.
CARTER ZENKE: Oh, no, OK.
I'd be surprised if you do.
But one thing this represents is
the number or the integer 65, right?
But as we saw in
lecture a little bit too
is this can also represent the letter
A. Those same binary bits can represent
both 65 and this character
A. So it's important we
tell C which thing we're talking about
here by giving us our data types.
So that's the reason we
have these data types here.
If we want to go further into variables,
we can update them if we'd like.
And here we have on this very first
line the declaration and initialization
of this variable calls.
And down below we just
update that value.
So notice the type is on that top
line, but it's not on that next line.
And why would that be, if I can ask
somebody from this side of the room
now?
Why is it on that top line
but not that second line?
Yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: On the first line
you're initiating the variable
and telling the computer
what the data type is.
On the second line, you're
reassigning it to the new value,
and it already knows that
that variable [INAUDIBLE]..
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so the computer
is pretty good at remembering things,
right?
And once you've told it that this
variable has a certain type, no need
to tell it again.
It already knows that.
We can just keep going as we go.
So here we're going to initialize
and declare the variable calls.
But when we use it again, we don't have
to tell it the type as we go through.
Now, if we wanted to change that
value, we could do it like this.
We also have some
operators at our disposal.
We could add 1 to it
using this plus sign.
We could even subtract some numbers.
We could maybe multiply some
numbers using that star operator.
We could even divide
some numbers, and so on.
So feel free to take a look at those.
If you go through the course, I'm
sure these come top of your head
as we go through.
But when it comes to assigning some
variable, what looks like a function,
right, that's where things
get a little bit weird.
We saw in lecture we're trying to
get some input from a user, right?
And we didn't say that maybe
string name equals quote "Carter."
We said it equals this,
maybe, function, get string.
Or here, if we wanted to store
a value in calls, get int.
And in this case, before
we're reading left to right.
But in this case, it's actually
better to read right to left
when you see this function
call on the right-hand side.
So what's happening
here is, when you have
this function on the
right-hand side, this function
is wanting to run and then
give us back some return
value that will be stored inside
this variable on the left-hand side.
So before anything else, we run
this function on the right-hand side
with some certain arguments,
some input to that function
tell it what exactly to do.
That function runs.
Maybe it asks the user for
this integer number here.
And we then store that value right
where that function was called.
And it then goes into that variable.
And now we're back to simple
variable assignment here.
So usually, if you're simply assigning
numbers, you can read left to right.
But if you have these function
calls, best to read right to left,
and knowing that your function runs
first and then assigns that value
as we go through.
So questions on this
before we dive even deeper.
Seeing none.
So now that we have these values
stored in these variables,
it's probably worthwhile to think
about how we print them to the screen.
And here's what we saw a
little bit in lecture as well,
this % and then this i here.
And what is this doing for us?
Could I ask somebody from
this middle section here.
Let's go to the first
row, if you don't mind.
Yeah.
STUDENT: It's a placeholder
for our variable call.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah,
placeholder for your calls.
And why is it %i?
Do you know?
STUDENT: Because it's
an integer [INAUDIBLE]..
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah.
STUDENT: i represents [INAUDIBLE].
CARTER ZENKE: Right, so %i.
This % is kind of saying like,
hey, this is a placeholder.
And that i specifies
what kind of variable
can go inside of that placeholder there.
So because call is an integer, it's %i.
And that's called, more specifically
a format code, as we might have said.
And we have this value that we can
store in that format code there.
We could have multiple format
codes and multiple values.
We just separate them by commas.
So you can imagine, for example, I
have %i here and maybe %i later on.
I could have calls and then
comma, some other variable.
And those would go inside
those placeholders one
by one, aligning with whatever order
I put them in as we go through.
Now, it's not worth
memorizing any of these,
but there are a great number of
format codes for different data types.
And as you work with a
variety of data types,
best you can maybe reference
these once in a while.
So here on the left-hand
side, we have number
format codes, like ints and
longs, floats and doubles,
and the right-hand side
some chars and strings,
where chars are individual characters.
And strings are collections of
characters as we go through.
One thing we haven't quite seen as
much yet is this long and double.
Anyone want to hazard a guess
as to what that might be here?
Could I ask somebody from
this middle row again?
What is this long and
double doing for us?
Yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: Does the long
[INAUDIBLE] more room [INAUDIBLE]
you have to have the
long to [INAUDIBLE]??
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, exactly.
So here we had an integer that could
store up to four billion values.
But when that's not
enough, we might want
to have a longer value, in
this case, called a long,
that will have twice
as much space for us.
We can store twice as many different
combinations as we go through.
Really, more than that.
We're just having twice as many
bits to represent that information.
And similarly, for the float,
that's a decimal number.
But this double is called a
double precision floating point.
So we'd have twice as many
decimals, twice many binary digits
representing that decimal
number there for us
as well, so just more space
for us to use as we go through.
Now, what we'll do here
is a brief exercise
and invite you to load up
code.cs50.io on your own laptop here.
And you should see something
that looks a bit like this.
Maybe you have a File Explorer
on the left-hand side.
But you should certainly
have a terminal down below.
I see a question.
Yeah.
STUDENT: I'm not sure if this
was a typo to be like this.
But if you go back to the slide--
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, yeah.
STUDENT: So the double says
f, and the float says f.
Is that correct?
CARTER ZENKE: That is correct.
So both the float and the double
have the same format code, yeah.
Good question.
STUDENT: So how does
the computer [INAUDIBLE]
recognize between [INAUDIBLE]?
CARTER ZENKE: How does the
computer recognize each one?
In this case, it doesn't quite
matter because, in this case,
the float and the double
are both decimal numbers.
And so the computer knows when it sees
%f, I'm printing a decimal number.
It just so happens to be that
the double is twice as long.
And so it just prints that many more--
well, it can print that many more
spaces after the decimal point
if you'd like it to.
Yeah, other questions
here before we move on?
All right, so we'll work
on a brief exercise here.
And once you've loaded up
your IDE in code.cs50.io,
you go ahead and create an
application called phonebook.c.
And the goal is to prompt the
user for these three things
and then print them back out
to the user as confirmation
that this data is
stored in your program.
So if I wanted to do this, I would
first go down to my terminal down below.
And I would make a new file.
What would I do to make
a new file down here?
Could I ask somebody from maybe
this right-hand bottom side?
How can I make a new file
in this program here?
Yeah.
STUDENT: Code and file name.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah,
code and the file name.
So I could do code,
if it will load here.
Let me refresh.
But on your own, you could certainly
do code and in the file name here.
And for our purposes, I'll do
code space maybe phonebook.c.
But you could call your program whatever
else you'd like to call it here.
And maybe yours is doing the same thing.
We'll be back in just a minute here.
Now, once you have your file, what tends
to go at the very top of that file?
What's the first thing you might add?
We saw this in lecture.
Yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: The header.
CARTER ZENKE: The header files
or these libraries, right?
And do you remember the syntax for that?
STUDENT: Hashtag include,
and then the caret thing.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, hashtag
include this little caret thing.
Let's see if this one is loaded now.
Not quite, but this
hashtag include is saying,
I'm going to try to get some
file in my computer's memory
that has these functions declared for me
that I will then use in my own program
here.
So what two header files might you
want to include in your program here?
Yeah.
STUDENT: Standardio.h [INAUDIBLE].
CARTER ZENKE: Nice, so two off
the bat that you often want to use
are standardio.h or stdio.h cs50.h.
Both of these have some
pretty common functions
you'll be using as you
write your own program.
And we'll wait for this to continue
connecting, and what we'll actually do
is, now that you maybe
hopefully have your file open,
you have your header files at
the top, we'll take some time,
let's say maybe 10 minutes,
to work on this on our own.
I'll put the slide back up.
And we'll come back in
those 10 minutes and share
how you approached this problem.
Maybe if the staff would like to
run around and help you as you work.
Feel free to raise your hand.
We'll come around and help you out.
All right, let's come back.
And we'll be working in a
slightly different environment
just because the internet is
not quite what we want it to be.
But we're going to make here our own
phone book file where we can actually
store the data we want to store.
So if you remember our
slide back here, we
wanted to store a few different things.
You wanted to store the user's
name, their phone number,
and I think it was their address.
Let me actually take a look at that
slide again, if we go back over here.
A name, an age, and a phone number.
So here we have this
template for our program,
but what are we missing right now?
We have our header files,
these libraries where
I have functions we're going to use.
What else are we missing
in this program right here?
Could I ask somebody from--
Yeah, down here.
STUDENT: Int main void.
CARTER ZENKE: Int main void, right.
So I'll type int main and void up here.
And this just symbolizes--
this is the kind
of when flag clicked block in Scratch.
This is going to be the main
part of our program here.
We're defining this new
function called Main that
will be the main part of our program.
Now, the first thing we
want to do is probably
prompt the user for some information.
So what functions did you all use to get
the user's name, or that contact's name
we're trying to story here?
Could I ask over here?
Yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: Get string.
CARTER ZENKE: Get string.
And how did you make your
variable in this case?
STUDENT: So because our variable
is a string, I put string.
And then I titled my variable name.
CARTER ZENKE: Nice.
STUDENT: And then I said equals
get string what's your name.
CARTER ZENKE: Get
string, what's your name.
So something like this?
STUDENT: With a space after the name.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, and why
would you have that space there?
STUDENT: Just for readability.
CARTER ZENKE: Just readability, right?
If we don't have that space
there, if we maybe remove this,
the user will be typing
in their name right up
against that question
mark there, which is not
what we want to have happen here.
So it seems pretty logical to
represent a name with a string.
But how about the age here?
Can I go maybe to this side of the room?
How did you all work on getting
the users the contact's age?
Yeah.
STUDENT: I did int age equals get
int, and then in brackets I had--
CARTER ZENKE: What's your
age with a space, right?
And then the semicolon.
Perfect.
So that'll close that statement.
And again, this function on
the right will be called.
It will run and then give us
back some return value, which is
whatever the user typed in, and store
it inside of this variable named age.
And then comes one with some--
question here?
STUDENT: Can we also write
string age [INAUDIBLE]??
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so
did you try that one here?
STUDENT: Yeah, what's the [INAUDIBLE]?
CARTER ZENKE: Good question.
So we could do either of these here.
One is an integer.
One is a string.
But you could imagine, if I later
wanted to do something like this,
let's say I wanted to actually increase
every person's age in my phone by one,
maybe it's their birthday next year.
So I say age equals age plus 1.
Is that going to work with
a string, do you think?
STUDENT: No.
CARTER ZENKE: No, because I'm going to
add 1 to this quote unquote maybe 40,
for example.
And I can't add numbers to strings.
That's not going to happen for me.
So it's best when you're
making these to just think
about what you want to do with them
as you work in your program here.
So I want to maybe change
my age as I go through.
So I'll actually maybe make this an
integer here and say get int instead.
And now for the phone number.
If you go to this middle
section here, how did you all
choose to represent the phone number?
Yeah.
STUDENT: Long number
is equal to get long.
CARTER ZENKE: Long number
And you'd ask maybe
what's your phone number.
STUDENT: Yeah.
CARTER ZENKE: And I think
I'm most curious here
about why you chose a long.
Why would you have that?
Yeah.
STUDENT: Because it's
more than 2 billion,
so you need the extra [INAUDIBLE].
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so
a phone number is what?
Maybe 10 digits long.
And so if I had any phone number that
begins with anything higher than two,
that's going to be
higher than two billion,
which is the highest positive
number I can have as an integer.
So I want to actually have a long here.
Yeah, question.
STUDENT: Could you use a string to--
CARTER ZENKE: You absolutely
could use a string.
And why would maybe you
advocate for using a string?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
CARTER ZENKE: Nice, so hyphens.
You could also include, if you're
maybe in different countries,
plus 1 for this country code
plus other country codes as well.
You could even have parentheses if you'd
like to put the area code in front.
Yeah.
STUDENT: Also, I think that if
you use an integer or a long,
you are supposed to be able to
calculate stuff based on that number.
And usually, you don't add stuff
or divide the phone number.
So there is no actual purpose
to ask for a [INAUDIBLE]..
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, definitely.
So we tend not to add
things to phone numbers.
So why store it as number we could
add things to or subtract things
to or divide or whatever
we'd like, right?
Good question there.
So we have it as a string here.
The string also preserves
things like leading zeros.
Maybe there's an odd chance
that somebody has a 000 number,
and we could store that with a
string but not, for example, a long.
We tend to remove those
leading zeros in that case.
Yeah.
STUDENT: But [INAUDIBLE] to
use the long [INAUDIBLE] one
that doesn't really require that?
CARTER ZENKE: If I were to
say maybe long age here?
STUDENT: Yeah.
CARTER ZENKE: And maybe
get long to have parity.
Nothing bad would happen here.
I'm probably just using twice as
much space as I would need to.
So generally, I don't think people
have an age above two billion.
And so I would probably want to just use
a regular integer to store that value.
Nice.
Other questions on these representations
of this information here?
OK, so we'll go with this integer.
And then just real quickly
to review our format code,
so let's say I wanted to
print out some of this data.
I could say printf.
And let's say, maybe age is--
what would I then say?
Maybe just call it out.
STUDENT: %i.
CARTER ZENKE: %i, OK.
Age is %i.
I'm going to put period here.
Name is %s.
And let's go ahead and say
phone number is %s, all right?
And now to store this,
as we saw earlier,
I could simply just put these
variables in the same order
I want them to show up in
those placeholders here.
So I could say, OK, age is first.
So I'll say age, then name.
So I'll say name.
And then finally number, so I'll
say number and close everything out
with the semicolon here.
And I were to make this, I just
type make phone book and run it.
I would then see this information
printed back out to me on the screen
as such.
So questions on this before we move on.
All right, so one of the
other building blocks
that we have besides these
variables and representations
here are these conditionals
and these loops.
And we saw these in
lecture as well, but we'll
use these now for the course's
lab to work on together.
So first thing here,
we have this question.
Have I called less than one time?
And if I have, then I'll
say call more often.
But just to get some
vocabulary down here,
this on the inside of that
conditional is our Boolean expression.
It's either yes or no.
Have I called less than one time or not?
On the outside here is
that conditional itself.
So conditionals have these Boolean
expressions on the inside of them.
I could make this a little
more advanced though,
and I could have this
else in the middle.
And what would that do for me?
Could I ever execute these
two things at the same time?
Could I ask over here?
Could I ever do these two
things at the same time?
Shaking your head no.
Right.
So these two things
are mutually exclusive.
If I have this else here, I'm
saying it's either one or the other.
If calls is less than 1, I
will do that first thing.
If it's not, I will
do that second thing.
You can chain these statements
together if you saw-- even in Scratch.
You could say if and then
else if and then else if,
and finally, it's long else.
In general, we have these if
statements followed by these else
if statements, followed by if you
need them, that final else to say,
like a catch all for everything else
that we could happen have happen here.
For loops though, if you wanted
to do something multiple times,
we have something that looks a
bit like this, this while loop.
And what would this print to the screen?
Could I ask somebody from
maybe this side of the room?
What would you see on the
screen with this loop here?
Yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: 0, 1, 2, 3 up to 9.
CARTER ZENKE: Up to
9, and why not the 10?
STUDENT: Because it's
while i is less than 10.
CARTER ZENKE: Nice.
Yeah, so we wouldn't see the 10
because we're going to stop while--
we're going to stop if this is not true.
And so 10 is not less
than 10, so we would stop
and we wouldn't do the
code on the inside, right?
So to break things down even further,
we have our initialization of this loop.
I is first set to 0.
Then we have our
Boolean expression, this
question we're going to
ask, either yes or no.
Is this case true or is it not?
And then finally, this implementation,
changing that value as we go through.
And finally, when our Boolean
expression is no longer true,
we will not be inside
of that loop there.
This is really handy.
We can actually try to make our
code run a certain number of times.
And this is so handy that C
actually has our own syntax
to write this kind of loop
in even abbreviated format.
So here we call a for loop that has
all those same elements but now just
on one clean line.
We have this initialization,
this Boolean expression,
and then this incrementation here.
And we'll do whatever a piece
of code is on the inside
as long as this Boolean
expression is true.
So questions on this kind
of syntax for these loops?
Pretty good.
And finally, I just wanted to
get a little more advanced.
We have this-- yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: I have a question [INAUDIBLE].
Why int [INAUDIBLE]
parentheses [INAUDIBLE]??
CARTER ZENKE: Good question.
So you saw the int here?
STUDENT: Yeah.
CARTER ZENKE: And why
is that there, right,
because previously, we had the
int i already done for us, right?
So these are actually
two different contexts.
So here, I have created
this variable named i,
and I'm going to use
it inside of this loop.
And this variable i, because
it's outside of this while loop,
will persist as we go
through my program.
So I could use this variable i again.
In the for loop though, if I were
to create this variable i anew,
I can only use it inside this for loop.
I could not use it
outside of that for loop.
So as long as it's inside for
loop, I can't use whatever
variable I create here outside of it.
It has to be limited to the
inside of that for loop there.
Does that help?
Great.
Other questions here too.
STUDENT: I see no semicolon
at the end of the for loop.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, why
is there no semicolon?
Well, probably a rule of thumb is this.
Semicolons come after
complete statements.
And this for loop is kind of
setting up some set of statements.
It's saying, I'm going to eventually
have something I want to do,
but it's not there yet.
So I'm going to actually
have these braces
to tell what statements I want to
execute sequentially as I go through.
So you'll get used to this as you
go through and write more code.
But in general, statements
end with a semicolon,
but things that set up
statements generally don't.
They might have these braces, yeah.
Yeah.
STUDENT: So you mentioned
[INAUDIBLE] variable
i only exists within the parameter.
CARTER ZENKE: Exactly.
STUDENT: Does that mean when you
do multiple for loops in a row
not with [INAUDIBLE]?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah,
it's a good question.
So let's say if I go back to my
actual programming environment here,
let's say I have a loop.
And I'm going to say four int
i equals 0. i is less than 10.
i++.
So now, I can access i
inside of these two braces.
That's something called scope.
It's a scope of the variable.
It persists in this space here.
I can't use i out here.
So I can't access it there, but I could,
for example, have another for loop
on the inside.
I could say for int j equals i.
That's totally valid because
i's inside this loop.
Maybe j is less than 10 in
this case, and then j++.
And I do something else in that.
And actually, j is not accessible here.
I can't do that, but it is
accessible inside that loop there.
Other questions here too?
Yeah.
STUDENT: I'm a little confused.
Where's the part that, I
guess, senses what i is?
It just appears [INAUDIBLE].
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, can you tell me
what you mean by senses what i is?
STUDENT: Right, so because
it's like a Boolean expression,
right, whether i is greater than 1 or
less than 1, like that kind of thing.
So where's the input of whether it's
going to be 1 or i what value it is?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so probably
best to think of it like this,
where my code is read top to bottom.
And when it gets to this for loop,
it's read kind of left to right.
So the first time I get to this for
loop, I'm going to make this variable i
and set it to 0.
Then I'm going to ask the
question, is i less than 10?
OK, it is, so I'll actually
go inside this for loop
and maybe run this code on the inside.
Once I get to the bottom of this for
loop here, I'll then go to the top.
And I'll do this.
I'll increase i by 1.
And I'll ask the question again.
Is i less than 10?
It is.
OK, I'll do this code again.
Once it finishes, I'll increase i by
1 again, ask the question, keep going,
and keep going.
Does that help?
STUDENT: OK, got it.
So the input was i equals 0
first, and then [INAUDIBLE]..
CARTER ZENKE: Exactly,
this is our initialization.
This is the first time for loop
runs, set it to this value.
Every time this code on the
inside finishes running, ask--
or actually, before we start running
this code, ask this question.
If this is true, run this code.
And we get to the bottom, increase
i by 1 or do whatever is here, yeah.
STUDENT: This should do it 10 times?
CARTER ZENKE: This should
do it 10 times, right?
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
It won't do 10 because
that is not less than 10.
STUDENT: Is this called a do while?
CARTER ZENKE: It's called a for loop
just because of the 4 on the-- right
there.
Yeah, but we do have the do while loop,
if we could go just quickly to that one
here.
The do while loop has the
words do while in it, right?
And what this is going to do is
actually not ask a question first.
Just unconditionally, run this piece of
code and then ask the question later.
And this is handy for trying
to get some input from the user
because it'll always ask
the user that question.
What input do you want to give me?
And then maybe reprompt them, depending
on whether that input is invalid or not
what you want it to be, all right?
So down here we would say this is the
condition under which our input is
invalid.
And we should go back up
and do it all over again.
So questions on these
kinds of loops still.
Yeah.
STUDENT: Would this be good, the
do-while loop if you were to--
you were asking a
question within the while
loop that didn't say
you're doing [INAUDIBLE]
same with [INAUDIBLE] while
loop give a given number?
Would there be an easier way to
terminate the function if say
you don't [INAUDIBLE] the right age?
CARTER ZENKE: And by
terminate do you mean like--
STUDENT: Terminate the funct--
like it just stops.
If you use-- say you're looking
for the age range from 25 to 30,
and then if it's in there,
you go to the while loop.
Would you then have the
while loop-- would there
be a way to stop the while
loop from [INAUDIBLE]??
CARTER ZENKE: And so,
if I'm understanding
what you're asking
correctly, it's often better
to check for what we don't want to
have happen than to check for what
it is we do want to have happen.
So for example, I might
not want to do this.
I might not want to say int
age is get int age, here.
And then ask the question, if, let's
say, age is between-- what did you say,
like 15 and 20?
STUDENT: Yeah.
CARTER ZENKE: If age is between 15
and 20, then do the rest of my program
because what I'm doing here is
I'm separating my program from--
I'm indenting it by a lot, and
maybe I have more conditions.
Maybe I also want to say,
if the name starts with A,
and then it keeps getting
more and more indented.
So what I could do instead is
I could do something like this.
I could say, well, let me do this.
Let me create this variable named age.
Let me get some value for it.
Whoops.
And while the age is not what I
want, let me keep reprompting.
Is that answering your question?
STUDENT: Yeah, i got it, yeah.
CARTER ZENKE: OK, so age is like less
than 15, or age is greater than 20.
Let me reprompt, right?
OK.
Yeah.
STUDENT: Is that [INAUDIBLE] to
write age less, equal, between?
Or is it better time to
say age less [INAUDIBLE]??
CARTER ZENKE: Probably
depends on the context.
So the question was, is it better style
to use this less than or this less than
or equal to?
In general, when you're writing for
loops, where you just want something
to repeat a certain
number of times, we tend
to use the less than
and always start at 0.
So let's say I want something
to repeat five times.
I'll say int i equals 0,
i is less than 5, i++.
And the math on this just works, right?
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, that's five times.
If I were to do something like
this, let's say int i is 1,
then I'd have to do
less than or equal to 5.
And because programmers start counting
at 0, meaning this absence of anything.
It's starting from the very basics.
We're not going to actually have
this less than or equal to sign here.
Is that helpful?
Yeah.
OK.
All right, so with these
building blocks of these loops,
we'll spend some time working on our
lab for the next 10 minutes or so.
In our lab-- if I go
back to my slides here--
we're going to be asking this
question of how many llamas
do we currently have?
And how many years will take us to get
to an aspirational number of llamas,
some gold number of
llamas for ourselves here?
So if we look at this, you can find
the lab at this URL right here.
It's on the course website.
Go to the lab page.
And in that lab, you'll
find these questions.
Actually, sorry.
Within this lab page, you're going
to work on this problem all together.
But we'll get started working
on this up front here.
So the first thing that
we'll do for this lab
is think about how we're going
to work an example ourselves,
and then walk through
and write our code.
When you're working on your
problems, often good to think
about how you're going to
write your algorithm first,
and then write your code.
So these seven steps can help you,
whether you're working on the lab,
in the problem set, or so on.
And notice how more
than half of these are
about writing things down, thinking
through them, not necessarily
programming.
But these final three steps are all
about translating that idea into code.
So we'll do that here today.
If we look at our llamas, we
have a certain number of llamas.
We want to figure out
how many years it'll take
to get to another number of llamas.
And we know that every year, maybe
a third of our llamas are born,
and 1/4 of our llamas
sadly pass away, right?
And let's take a look at
this particular example here.
We have 12 llamas.
And so in this current year, 12
over 3 new llamas will be born,
and 12 over 4 llamas will pass away.
And the question is, how many years
will it take to get to 13 llamas?
So to work this example,
we have these 12 llamas.
And now, what would we do?
We want to birth a 1/3 llamas.
So how many more will we add here?
STUDENT: Four.
CARTER ZENKE: Four, OK, let's add 4.
And how many would pass away?
STUDENT: Three.
CARTER ZENKE: Three, so
we'll take away 3 here.
And we are at 13 llamas now, right?
And that was one year overall.
We birthed our four more llamas,
and three llamas passed away.
Now, we're at 13.
So as you go and write this program,
we'll get started up here in a minute.
We want to first prompt the user
for this starting number of llamas,
ask them for a goal number of
llamas, and then do some math perhaps
in a loop to figure
out how many years it
will take to get to that
goal number of llamas,
and finally, print out
that number of years.
So if you are in your code space, you
might go over to your environment here.
You might type code population.C
to open up that file.
Here I have mine.
You might then type, include
standardio.h to print something
to the screen later on.
And you might also do the cs50
library, cs50.h here as well.
What else do we need for
this boilerplate code?
STUDENT: Int main.
CARTER ZENKE: Int main void, right?
So I'll say int main void.
And I'll leave this rest up to
you, but make sure you're asking--
your prompting the user for
a starting number of llamas,
prompting them for an ending
number of llamas, and then
finally, maybe using some kind of
loop to figure out how many years it
will take to get to the goal.
And keep in mind that every year a
1/3 of our current llamas are born
and 1/4 pass away.
All right, so work on this for,
let's say, 10 minutes or so.
And we'll come back and
work the example together.
OK, so I hope you've made some
good progress on this lab.
Let's come back and work
the example together.
We had a few steps to work through,
the first one being prompting the user
for a starting number of llamas.
And could I ask maybe a group
from this side of the room, maybe
towards the back, if you don't
mind, how did you prompt the user
for your starting number of llamas?
Yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: So the first [INAUDIBLE] start.
And we ran a do-while loop.
So it says starts equals
get int and then start size.
And then the condition was
while the start was less than 9.
CARTER ZENKE: Gotcha, so
while start is less than 9.
And why did you choose
less than 9 for that case?
STUDENT: Because the lab said that
the minimum number that the start
size could be was 9 or else the
population would fail to grow.
CARTER ZENKE: Right, so we want to
reprompt the user if they give us
a number less than 9, right?
That seems pretty good.
And then similarly, how could we prompt
them for an ending number of llamas?
Could I ask maybe in
the middle this time,
somebody from maybe
the back few rows, how
did you try to prompt for an
ending number of llamas here?
Yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: I created an
int variable called n.
CARTER ZENKE: Nice.
STUDENT: And then I
used a do-while loop.
[INAUDIBLE] had n equals
get int, and then end size.
And then the condition for the while
was while end was less than start.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, and
then just to ask you
why would you have that in
your conditional down there?
STUDENT: Because in the
lab it wanted us to keep
prompting if the ending size that
the user inputs is less than starting
point.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, totally.
So we can't have fewer
llamas than we began with.
So just checking to make
sure that is the case here.
And if not, we reprompt the user.
And then our final bit down here
was keeping track of how many years
it will take to get to our goal
number of llamas now stored
in this variable called end.
And how did you all choose
to represent the year,
or how many years have
passed in your program?
Could I ask somebody from
this side of the room now?
What kind of variable did you use
to count the number of years here?
Maybe somebody from the first few rows.
Yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: As an integer.
CARTER ZENKE: As an integer, and did
you give it a special name or anything?
STUDENT: i called it int years.
CARTER ZENKE: Int years, OK.
And what did you set it first to?
STUDENT: Zero.
CARTER ZENKE: Zero, OK.
And now we have some math to do.
If we look maybe--
this group [INAUDIBLE] mind.
How did you all add
llamas, subtract them?
How did you adjust your population
of llamas as the years went on?
Any ideas for how you might
do it or how you did do it?
Yeah, go ahead.
STUDENT: Just add 112 llama each year.
CARTER ZENKE: Added
112 llamas each year.
Nice.
So can you tell me, if we
look at our program here,
we have a starting number of llamas,
so how would you adjust that here?
STUDENT: You would go,
like you said, at start--
CARTER ZENKE: Start.
STUDENT: It would be start equals--
I'm sorry, plus equals.
CARTER ZENKE: Start plus equals.
STUDENT: Start divided by 12.
CARTER ZENKE: Start divided by 12.
And how did you get start divided by 12?
What kind of math did
you do to get there?
STUDENT: Common
denominator of 1/3 and 1/4.
And then you're adding
1/3 and subtracting 1/4.
CARTER ZENKE: Nice, so
ultimately, every year we're
just adding 1/12 new llamas after
we add a 1/3 and subtract a 1/4.
It comes out to 1/12
new llamas every year.
But we need some kind
of loop to run this.
Anyone want to help me out
here with this final piece?
How do we have the
loop to increase this--
llama, know when to stop too.
Yeah.
STUDENT: We could do while start
is less end [INAUDIBLE] start.
And after that [INAUDIBLE]
add [INAUDIBLE]..
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah,
and so add 1 to year?
STUDENT: Yeah.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so we could say
years++ for increase years by 1.
And at the very end we ultimately
want to print out the number of years.
So I'll say printf %i.
And maybe just to clarify,
years percent and then years
down at the bottom here, with
a backslash n at the end.
And if I make this make
population, run ./population,
I'll type in maybe 12 and 13.
And I get one year, as we expected.
Yeah, question or comment.
STUDENT: What is the plus equal
[INAUDIBLE] start plus equal start?
CARTER ZENKE: Good question.
This is basically
shorthand for doing this.
I could say start equals start +
start over 12 because I'm trying
to add to start as we go through.
So this plus equals
is simply saying, let
me add to what start currently is
this value on the right-hand side.
Does that makes sense?
STUDENT: Yes, thanks.
CARTER ZENKE: Gotcha.
Now, there's one question here, which
is, let's say, I have-- oh, yeah,
go ahead, somewhere over here.
Yeah.
STUDENT: I have a question
regarding this start in line 12.
We have one part that
is the [INAUDIBLE] form
and one part that is
[INAUDIBLE] our time.
Therefore, you need to round the first
part and then round the second part
because you cannot have half a
llama die and 1/3 being alive.
So in some cases, where the number
is divisible by one part of it
and not divisible by the other,
could create some differences.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so maybe it is
better for us to add start over 3
and then subtract maybe start over 4
STUDENT: Yeah, but what if you--
CARTER ZENKE: --and keep going.
STUDENT: --round these numbers?
I guess divided by 3
[INAUDIBLE] or 3.3333.
So you need to round it
3 because, otherwise,
you cannot have 1/3 of
a llama [INAUDIBLE]..
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, we don't
want 1/3 third of a llama.
So we got to round this in some way.
And I think what we want
to do is always round down,
which brings us to some feature
or, in some cases, a bug in C--
you might run into
this-- called truncation.
And we didn't see this as much in
lecture, which to highlight it here,
in C, when you divide two integers,
you will always get back an integer.
So if I divide perhaps maybe 2 and
3, 2 divided by 3, both integers,
I won't get 2/3.
I'll get 0.
Always round down, cut off
the rest of that data there.
So to show an example of this,
I might do code truncation.c.
And I will have the same
boilerplate code, standardio.h.
I'll include cs50.h.
And I'll say int main void.
And I'll type in maybe
int a is, let's say, 2.
Int b is 3.
And let's print out the result
of dividing them like this.
Let's say-- actually, sorry,
int c is a divided by b.
And I'll say this gets
the result c here.
I'll say make truncation
and do ./truncation.
And I'll get 0 and not 2/3.
So always rounding down here.
If I do want the decimal
though, what I can do
is I can convert on the fly
one of these to a decimal.
So I could say, actually,
I want a to be a float
and then complete this division.
And as long as one of
your numbers is a float,
you'll get a float in the very end.
So I'll say maybe %f here.
I'll do make truncation.
Whoops.
Let me say this is actually
now a float in the end.
Make truncation, I'll say ./truncation,
and I will get that 0.6667.
If I were to not do this, if I were to
not do this, I would get 0 all around.
So just something to keep in
mind as we go through here.
Happy to stick around and answer
any questions that you all have,
but this should bring us to the end
of our lab today and our super section
as well.
Thank you all for coming.
It's wonderful to see you here.
Hope to see you next week in section.