CARTER ZENKE: All right.
Well hello, everyone.
It is so wonderful to see you.
My name is Carter Zenke.
And I am the course's preceptor.
I'm joined here by all of you all.
So all that we do is just
take a minute to unmute and do
something unusual for Zoom, which
is say hello all at the same time.
So on the count of three, I'd like to
invite you to unmute and say hello.
One, two, three, and
AUDIENCE: (IN UNISON) Hello!
CARTER ZENKE: Amazing.
So it's good to have this nice
chorus of voices here today.
Everything we'll do today is
here at this URL right here,
CarterZenke.me/section.
You'll find all of the
slides we'll work on.
The exercises we'll work on together.
If you like to get in touch
with me in particular,
you can email me at
Carter@cs50.harvard.edu
and feel free to email me there.
So I thought we'd start off with, it's
just a kind of refresher on lecture.
And so I invite you to think back
to two questions from this week's
past lecture.
The first is, what did you
find exciting from lecture?
What are you interested in?
And next is, what are you
still confused about or what
do you still have questions about?
So take a minute to think about
those two questions, again,
what are you excited about and what
you still have questions about?
And we'll come back in
maybe 30 seconds or so
and share out a few of these ideas here.
So we'll come back in 30 seconds.
[MUSIC PLAYING] (SINGING) Need to close
your eyes here too, and I at the time
doesn't matter, we don't
care about the others.
You stay on my mind because
you know you're my lover.
Oh, baby you'll love it
and I can't ignore it.
A light and you can notice,
my body gets carried away.
I know what it is, yeah.
You know the feel of me.
All right.
And I don't want to leave.
Talk, tell me maybe what you would do.
Dance, dance.
And wear your feeling's high.
So hot.
So hot, so hot.
CARTER ZENKE: All right.
So I think that'll be enough time to
do some thinking on this past lecture
this week.
I hope you don't mind if
we do a few warm/cold calls
to get a feel for what
we're interested in, what
we're wondering about this week.
So if you wouldn't mind, can I
go to maybe Elena and ask you
what you find exciting, what you
are still wondering about this week?
AUDIENCE: So I think this week,
something that was pretty interesting
was I thought the section about
debugging was pretty interesting.
I definitely had to do a
lot of that for my presit.
I'm not really wondering
so much so far, I think.
I think we kind of just getting
intro to things, but yeah.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, that's good to hear.
So some interesting
debugging and how we do that.
Well, I think we'll do a little
bit of that today in section,
write some programs and hopefully
de-bug the errors we'll find in them
and maybe could we go to
Dewey, if you don't mind.
Maybe something you're interested
in or things you're wondering about?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, no problem.
I guess, like, the most interesting
thing from the lecture this week
was actually the command line arguments.
So I've programmed before, but I've
never actually used command line
arguments in a program that I've made.
So that was actually really cool.
And then what I'm looking
forward to, I guess, just
working on some more
complicated assignments
because those tend to be quite fun.
So yeah.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, yeah.
Very cool.
So we saw command line arguments which,
again, are these inputs to your program
that we can type in the terminal
itself before your program runs.
And those then decide
how the program will run,
gives it some options
to work with as it runs.
Just a few questions for
us here today as well.
Something we'll talk about
in section today are,
what are the steps
involved in compilation?
So we take the source code, this code
written in C and convert it to binary.
But how do we do that
and why do we do that?
We'll dive deeper into
arrays, what are they?
Why would we use them?
We'll talk about strings,
particularly in the context of arrays.
And finally, to Dewey's point earlier,
we'll talk about command line arguments
as well.
And throughout this, we'll hope to
figure out what makes for good design.
In this course, we'll
talk about correctness,
which is, does your code
work, but also about design,
which is how well does your code work?
So we'll figure out what good design
looks like in a few different contexts
here.
Kick things off with compilation though.
We saw this program in lecture,
if I can go to full screen here,
and can have somebody just shout
out what would this program do?
If I were to run this program,
what would you see on your screen?
Maybe could I ask McKenna,
if you don't mind?
Do a warm/cold call.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, you were
just saying "hello, world".
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, just
saying "hello, world", right?
And go back to this here.
Now if we were to compile this
from C to machine code, to binary,
we'd have a few steps along the way.
So we saw this lecture.
We saw that this source
code first gets converted
to assembly code, this kind of esoteric
language here that isn't quite binary,
but is almost there.
And in the next step, we end
up getting down to this binary
that your computer actually runs.
So we have this maybe,
Hello.C file that then
gets converted to this regular hello
file that's written in binary here.
And to do this, we have this
program called Clang, or C-language,
C-language compiler here.
And if we were to run
Clang like this, we
would probably need to provide
a little more context for Clang
because Clang wants to
actually take some source code
and convert it to machine code.
But here, it wonders what source code
should I convert to machine code.
So we might use an example
of a command line argument
here and actually tell it
what we want to convert.
We can type Clang hello.c to tell it we
want to convert this hello.c file down
to binary.
But we could also be more specific.
We could say, I want
not just the a.out we
would get from this we saw in
lecture, but more specifically, a file
called "hello".
So I could say "clang-o"
and then "hello"
to say this is the output file I want.
And then finally, the hello.c
file we would actually
want to compile from source
code to machine code here.
And all of this can get
a little bit complicated,
this isn't the full command we need
to compile all of our saved programs.
We might want to link in some libraries.
And there's a lot of other
things you might type here
to make your compilation successful.
So what we've done is we've given you
this command called "make" that sort
of simplifies a lot of that for you.
So "make" runs in the background.
Clang, along with a lot of
options behind the scenes
to compile your program
to binary, ultimately.
But in this class, and even if you
do more programming in the future,
you'll probably use a
command called "make"
to simplify that and keep yourself from
typing all this stuff in the terminal
as you go.
Now what questions do you
all have on compilation,
or on converting from source
code to machine code, if any?
All right.
So seeing none here,
and I imagine you've
gotten to do this a little
bit so far in the class.
So let's dive a little more
deeply into arrays now.
So if we talk about converting
source code to machine code,
getting down to like the low
level details of computer.
And arrays themselves are the most
basic data structure we can have.
The most basic way we
can organize our data.
So I'm curious to hear your
thoughts on what is an array?
What would you define as an array?
And can we go maybe to
Bianca, if you don't mind?
What in your mind is an array?
AUDIENCE: OK.
So this was the most confusing
part of lecture for me.
But I think it compiles like--
it's like smaller pieces
that are like elements,
so it compiles all the
elements into essentially,
so that they're all next to each other.
And it also sorts, for lack of a
better term, elements of the same value
so that they're next to each other.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah.
So I like a few things
about what you said there.
So I like that you said that it combines
these elements, these pieces of data
that we have.
And it puts them back to back in memory.
So let's take a look at an example here.
One CHT final project was
this one called SleepS50.
And the goal of this project
was to actually store
the number of hours somebody
has slept every day.
So somebody might come back
to this application and type
in, I slept eight hours last night.
They come back the next day, they
type maybe nine hours, or seven,
depending on how much they slept.
And if we wanted to store this data,
at least currently in our story so far,
we would need a whole
bunch of variables.
We'd have to say, OK, I need hours
one, I need hours two, hours three
and so on as that we're
going through the days here
to store all of this data.
But what is not so well
designed about this?
Where would this go wrong?
And maybe could I ask
Elena, if you don't mind?
AUDIENCE: I'm not too sure.
CARTER ZENKE: OK.
So we're trying to store
all this data, right?
And if we had to keep track
of all of these variables,
let's say I wanted to have a sixth day
of hours, what would I have to do now?
AUDIENCE: You have to add another line?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, add another line
and presumably, another variable.
But that would get pretty messy,
pretty quickly because assuming I
want to keep track of maybe like
a whole year's worth of sleep,
I wouldn't want to have
hours 1 through hours 365.
That would just be a whole lot
of individual variables, right?
And so to Bianca's point
earlier, these arrays
help us keep track of this
information all in one piece.
So let's take a look at an
example of an array here.
Here we have one called "hours".
And as we're thinking
about these arrays,
this really good mental model is this
long line of individual pieces of data.
So here we have those same five hours,
but now under one block of memory
that we're going to call "hours".
And when we're trying to
create this block of memory,
there are really three things you're
going to need to take care of first.
So the first one is
the name of this block.
What are we going to call this array?
So here, we're going to call it "hours".
And maybe I'll turn it over to you all
for the other two that matter here.
We have a name for the
array, but what else
do we care about if we're going to
try to create this block of memory?
Could I ask maybe you, Dewey?
Yeah, go ahead.
AUDIENCE: You would need
the length of the array.
So here, we would probably want seven
because there are seven days in a week.
CARTER ZENKE: Yes, so
probably seven days in a week.
So we could make maybe
this array of length seven
to store seven hours of sleep every day.
In this case, we'll probably
just go with a week day calendar.
So we'll have five in this case.
But the size is certainly
something we care about here.
And there's one other thing we
care about too, the name, the size,
and what else would we need?
Could I maybe ask you, McKenna,
if you have any ideas here?
AUDIENCE: I'm honestly not sure.
CARTER ZENKE: That's OK.
No worries.
AUDIENCE: This is like a topic from
lecture I was a little confused on.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, yeah.
Other thoughts here?
AUDIENCE: The type of value?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, totally.
So we need the type that
we're actually storing here.
So three things we care about
for arrays when we make them.
The name, the size, how many elements
are we storing and then also what
kind of type are we
storing in this array?
And the type matters because we want
to know how much space to allocate
to our array.
Different types have different
numbers of bytes that represent them,
like an integer might have 32 bits,
or maybe 4 bytes, in that case.
But maybe just a character would
have only 8 bits, or one byte.
So the type depends--
the type matters for how much memory
we're going to allocate to our array
here.
So with this in mind, we keep in
mind the name, the size, the type.
We have some syntax we would
use in C to actually create
this space for the array.
And this is what that
would look like here.
Up top, we have "int" and what
would "int" represent in this case?
Could I, maybe, go back to you, Dewey?
What would "int" represent here?
AUDIENCE: It would
represent the data type
of the stuff stored inside the array.
So we're storing integers
so we want "int".
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, nice.
So similarly to how we declare
our variables with the type first,
so similarly, for our arrays,
we say what type do you
want to put in this array first?
And then next is the name of the array.
So "hours".
And then what is inside these brackets?
Maybe could I ask you, Bianca?
Do you mind telling me
what's inside these brackets?
What pieces of the puzzle is that?
AUDIENCE: That's the size of the array.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, it's
the size of the array.
So here, we're saying we
have an array called "hours"
that will store integers.
And it will be of size five,
so we'll store five integers.
And this is all well and good,
but one thing to keep in mind
is that our array isn't quite
useful unless we can access
individual elements of the array.
So we have this syntax that
also uses this bracket notation.
And we can see it a little
bit down below here.
So if we wanted to get the very
first element of our array, we'd say,
hours[0].
If we wanted to get the next one,
we'd say hours[1], and so on.
And all the way at the end
here, we have hours[4].
But why would we not have hours[5]
to get that last element there?
How does that make sense?
Maybe Elena, would you
have any thoughts here?
McKenna, I see your hand raised.
AUDIENCE: Well since we start
from 0, like if we want 5 pieces,
if we count all the way up to hours[5],
then we actually have six pieces.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, totally.
So if we counted from 0 to 5 inclusive,
well, that's actually six elements.
But we only have five in our array.
If we start from 0 and count up to four,
well, that's five distinct elements.
And so that is the length
of our array, meaning
we're not going beyond the
length of our array here.
And if we wanted to go ahead
and add some data to this array,
it'd be a simple assignment.
So here, I might say, I want to put
seven in the very first array spot.
Hours[0] gets the value seven.
Remember, we read this equal
sign as a "get" in English.
And then we could say, OK well,
hours[1] should get the value 9
and so on and so forth.
And so we fill up our array as we go.
Now we could fill up the
entire array at once,
if we wanted to enough to have
all these lines of code here.
We could do this.
We could say, let's create this array
named "hours" that has five elements.
And let's have it "get" this set
of numbers here, 7, 9, 8, 7, 8.
And overall, that would give us the
entire array filled up for ourselves
here.
And even then, we might not even specify
the size in this case because we know,
well, there are five elements over here.
So we could just have C infer how
much space our array takes up.
You take out that five
there and say, well, we just
have these five elements here, we'll
make sure we have an array of size 5.
So I just want to pause
here for any questions
you all might have on this array
syntax, or how arrays are working here?
All right.
So seeing none so far.
Let's keep going then and get
to an exercise in just a bit.
One thing we might want to do with our
arrays is, again, access each element.
And sometimes, we want to
start at the very first element
and then keep accessing
things as we go through.
And a for loop is a great way
to do that because a for loop
lets us specify a variable
that can increase.
And we can then use that variable to
access individual parts of our array.
So here, I might have the
same array, "hours" up at top.
And now this for loop
here, that is starting at I
equals 0, going up to, but not
including I will be equal to 5.
And then we'll go ahead and print
out whatever is at hours[i] here.
And so a question for the
group now is what would this
print out if I were to run this?
What would I see on my screen?
And feel free to raise
your hand if you'd like.
What would I see on my screen
for to run this for loop?
Yeah, Dewey?
AUDIENCE: You would see and, then a
new line, 9, new line, 8, and then
onwards until the end of the list--
array, technically. yeah.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, yeah.
And I'm curious, you said a new line,
so what is indicative of the new line
here?
There's a slash, n.
So that means-- that tells the
computer to start a new line.
CARTER ZENKE: Right, so in this print
statement here, we have that %i,
which is like a placeholder for
an integer that will print out.
And we'll specifically add in the
hours bracket I integer there.
And we'll make a new line here to say,
OK, once you're printing that integer,
let's go to a new line, print
that one, go to new line,
print that one and so on
and so forth right here.
So with that in mind, let's
go ahead and try and exercise
in small breakout rooms here.
And this exercise is called powers of 2.
So the goal here is to make an
array that has a certain size, maybe
given to us by the user.
And then we'll want to create
an array where every element is
2 times the previous number.
And we can start the array at one.
So we might have an array like,
1, 2, 4, 8, 16, 32 and increasing
by two times every time we go through
and add this new element here.
And let's go ahead and get
started on this one together.
So if you want to ahead and pull up
code.csu.io, that would be great.
And you can follow along over
here while mine boots up as well.
And what we'll do once your code
space loads is create this file
called array.c.
Go ahead and make this
program where we'll
have this array that will be every
element two times the previous one.
And just to kick us off here
in a discussion, what kind
of boilerplate code would
we really need here,
and by boilerplate, I mean default
code we want to have in every program
that we write?
Maybe at the top of our file, what's
the first thing we would do here?
Can I ask maybe Sotanalie,
if you don't mind?
What would we have to have the
top of every area of our programs?
And I'll have mine booted up here.
So what we want to do very first is
make sure we have our program up.
So we can type code array.c.
And that will make sure we have
this new file called array.c.
And that ".c" is important there.
That means this is a C file.
And now at the very top of our
programs, what we're going to need?
Can I maybe turn to
Elena, If you don't mind?
What would we want to incorporate the
very top of our file in most programs
we write?
AUDIENCE: You would have
to include from the one,
the packages, like,
from like CS50 and ST--
I forgot it.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, yeah.
You're totally right.
So we want to make sure we include
some libraries or some packages
perhaps in our program
because we actually
use those functions in our program.
So we might first include the
CS50 library by #include CS50.h.
And we might also want to
include the standard I/O library.
The first standard input and
output, meaning some functions
we can use to get user input and then
print something out to the screen here.
And then what else would we
need, kind of template here?
What kind of function is going to be
the core part of our program here?
How would we do that?
Could I ask McKenna?
I'm so sorry.
For the core part of our program,
we would need main void, right?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, totally.
"Int main void".
So I could type "int
main(void)" here and then
have this to dileanate where I'm
going to type the rest of my program
inside of these curly braces here.
And we'll see why in particular, we
type "int main(void)" just a little bit.
We saw it briefly in lecture two.
But for now, we want to make sure that
we're going to get some user input.
So I might have you all
finish this part together
before sending you off to work on
the actual array building piece.
But what kind of function would we
use to get user input in this case?
We want to get a number that we could
use for the length of our array.
So what kind of function have we seen
in CS50 that could help us with that?
Do you mind if I ask maybe Bianca if
you have an idea, or maybe some steps
forward for us?
AUDIENCE: Can you repeat what you said?
I'm sorry.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, yeah.
So we want to make sure we have user
input to get the length of the array.
So what kind of function could we
use to get a number from the unit
that we've seen so far?
AUDIENCE: A number you said?
CARTER ZENKE: A number.
AUDIENCE: The "get int".
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, "get int".
So we could say I want to maybe
create the length of this array
and I want to make sure I
get an "int" from the user,
maybe prompt them for a length, right?
And here's a question of design.
What if these are typed
in a negative number?
Well, I can't have a
negative length array
so I should probably do my best to
make sure they give me a good number
and not assume that
they're going to cooperate.
So I might do this.
I could say, "do", I want to make sure
that I get the length from the user
here.
And I'll make sure to
declare my variable up above.
But then before moving
on, I want to make sure
that this length is definitely
going to be at least one.
So I'll say if the
length is less than 1,
I want to re-prompt the
user as we go through.
This just ensures that
you just don't type
in negative 1 or 0, like values that
are invalid for our right length.
So we have some initial
code here and feel free
to jot this down on
your own array.c file.
But we'll do next is we'll
break out into a few rooms
and we'll come back in
maybe five minutes or so.
But the goal here will be
to finish this prompt here.
So you're going to create an array that
is of size, whatever the user typed in.
And then we'll make sure that every
number is two times the previous one.
Yeah, Dewey?
AUDIENCE: Would it be possible
for you to copy and paste
the prompt into the chat
so that we have it on hand?
CARTER ZENKE: Absolutely.
I'll make sure to do that.
Yeah.
All right.
So let me go ahead and
type that in the chat,
but once we do that I'll send you all
to breakout rooms and come we'll come
back in maybe 5 or 10 minutes or so.
AUDIENCE: Can I ask you
a really quick question?
Because I know for the lab, we had a
folder that we unzipped to invest code,
is there something like
that for this section
or should we just create our own file?
CARTER ZENKE: Good question.
Yeah, so normally for
a problem that you're
working on in a problem set or a lab,
you might download a file, unzip it.
Here, we're just making our own file.
So if you want to, you
can go to your terminal
down below, just type "code array.c"
and that should make you this new file.
You can type in your code as we go.
AUDIENCE: OK.
Thank you.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, yeah.
So let me type this in the chat.
So we'll create a program that
prompts the user for a size.
And then we're going to
create an array of that size
where each element is 2
times the previous one.
And you can start the array at 1.
And your goal is to ultimately print
the array of integer by integer.
So I hope that's helpful.
I'll send you all into breakout
rooms in just a second here.
We'll come back in let's
say, about five minutes.
Welcome back, everyone.
I hope you got the to make
at least some progress here,
but no worries if you didn't
get all the way there.
What we'll do now is work on
this together a little bit.
So here I have-- go
back to my view here--
where we left off in our program.
And again, the goal was to make
this array that every element was
2 times the previous one.
And it had the length of whatever
the user gave us in this case.
So going back to some of the slides
that we just talked about earlier,
how would we even declare or make
space for this array in our program?
We want to have an array
that stores integers
of a certain size and a certain name.
And maybe could I have
Alena, if you don't mind,
you want propose our array name
and length and what it stores?
AUDIENCE: So for the type, it
would just be "int" I think.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, exactly.
Storing integers.
AUDIENCE: As for the size, I think the
size would need to be the user input.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, definitely.
So it would be the variable length here.
And before we can give it a size
though, we have to give it a name.
So you propose a name for us?
AUDIENCE: I don't really
know what you would name it.
But--
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, I
mean, it could be anything.
We could call it--
I would call it-- well, for
fun, we call it "twice",
like twice the previous number.
But you could also call it
array, you could call it
whatever you want to call it.
Here we'll say it has a certain
length and that length is literally
this variable length here.
So whatever we type in, that
will be the length of our array.
Now if we wanted to go through
every element in the array,
what loop might we use here?
We want to go through
every element and we
want to make sure that we set each of
those elements equal to some number.
So what kind of loop could we use?
Could I ask maybe Bianca if you might
have some thoughts here or ideas?
AUDIENCE: I want to say a for loop,
but or maybe another dua loop, unsure.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so for
loop is the right intuition.
And why is because if we know how
many times we want to do something,
we know we want to go through
every element of the array
and it's like a fixed size, a for
loop is great because a for loop
can do something a
certain number of times.
So here, let's say I want to
loop from maybe I equals 0,
all the way on up to
I is less than length.
And increase I every time I go through.
And so here's what that looks like here.
And the goal here is, maybe we're
accessing every element of twice.
By going from I is 0, all the way
up to I is not length, but one less
than length.
So it goes to every
element inside of "twice".
But what should every
element inside of "twice" be?
How do we complete this statement here?
It should get a value, but
what value should it get?
Could I ask maybe McKenna
if you have any ideas here?
AUDIENCE: Sorry, could you repeat
the question one more time?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, yeah.
So we're just trying to figure
out what number should we
put into each element of
this array called "twice"?
We know that we want it to be two times
the previous number, but how would
we actually put that in code
if you have any ideas here?
AUDIENCE: Two times i minus 1.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, nice idea.
We could say two times twice I minus 1.
And this is going to do is
say, OK, let's make sure
that the current space we're
looking at inside of "twice"
is going to be two times the
previous value that's in twice here.
So for example, if I is 1, then
we'll look back at 0, index 0 here.
Multiply that by 2 and make that
the value of "twice" at the index 1.
So let's go ahead and try running
this if I type "make array".
Let's actually try printing
out this value as we go too.
So I'll say, not only do we want to
set the value, I want to print it out
as we go.
So I'll say %i and then twice[i].
I'll then recompile my program and
I'll do a ./array, maybe a size 5.
But I get just 0s.
Any ideas about this bug in our program?
Yeah, Dewey?
AUDIENCE: Forgive me,
sorry, I had to unmute.
So essentially, we need to set a value
for the first element in our array.
Otherwise, it's just going to
take 0 and then just multiply it
by 2, which is obviously 0.
CARTER ZENKE: Right.
Yeah, so we need to set
a first element here.
And more specifically, what's
happening is let's say i is o, well OK,
twice[0] should be 2 times twice[-1].
And so negative 1 will look one
space in memory before our array.
And really, who knows what's there.
It could be 0, it could
be some random number.
If I were to try re-running this
program, I get a different answer.
Still 0, we run this again.
Still 0, but we might get some
random number there eventually
because we're not really sure what's
one space memory before our array.
So to Dewey's point, let's
actually first set twice[0] to 1.
That first element of
twice, set it to 1.
Then we'll go ahead
and start from i equals
1 and look one behind us, multiplying
that by 2 as we go through.
So I'll do "make array".
I'll do a ./array of size 5.
And now I get something
that looks pretty good,
but I don't think I have
the full array here.
What else do I still need to do?
Let me go back my terminal
I only see 2, 4, 8, 16.
Any thoughts, Dewey, if you want
to finish the debugging here?
AUDIENCE: Give me a second.
Let me just pull up--
OK.
So we're not seeing the
entirety of the array.
So we're only seeing up until the
last four, even though we want five.
So it's not showing the
zeroth element, which is 1.
So we should probably should
printf twicE[0], for instance.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so we've got
to print it out here as well.
So I'll say print out
whatever's in twice[0],
right after we set its value there.
So basically, we're going to fill in
the very first element of our array
on lines 15 and 16.
Then we're going to fill in the rest
of our array on lines 18 through 22.
So now if I compile this,
"make array", I'll run array.
And now I'll see every
element inside of that array.
So what questions are there on
this program, or arrays in general?
Any lingering thoughts or questions?
AUDIENCE: Could you go back to
where you had after "int twice",
the line of code you have after that.
And explain that, if you don't mind?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, totally.
So here, let me actually comment the
code, just to make it little clearer.
So here, we're going to get
the length from the user.
Now once we have that
length, we're going
to declare our array, which
means make some space for it
in our computer's memory.
And here what we're doing is
going to set the first value.
So our array should start at 1.
And so we'll take the
very first element inside
of twice using that 0 index here.
Remember, we start from 0 and go on up.
We'll say that gets the value 1.
I will then print out that value.
And then we'll look at
the rest of our array.
We'll start at i equals 1
instead of i equals 0 here.
Move on up to the length,
increasing i as we go.
And as we do it, let's go ahead and make
the current element twice the previous.
And then we'll print
out the current element.
Does that make sense?
Nice.
Other questions on this one?
All right.
So let's keep moving in that case.
And our next topic following through
on arrays is this idea of a string.
And what are strings really?
We saw this in lecture a little bit.
Strings are these collections of
characters, like a name, like Carter,
or maybe a location, like Harvard.
But what data structure are they really?
Maybe could I ask Elena if you
have any thoughts or guesses here?
AUDIENCE: From what I understand,
I just thought of strings
as strings of characters
instead of just one character.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, totally.
So a string is like a
string of characters.
We've taken some individual characters
and strung them together, so to speak.
And this name comes from the fact
that we have some characters now all
grouped together.
And so similarly, how
we had these hours that
were previously individual
variables, but now I
put them in this array called "hours",
we can do the same for strings.
We're taking these
individual characters,
putting them together into
this one, big array here.
So if I take a look at this
string, this string is "Emma".
And if we take a look
at the entire string,
we'll see it's basically
the same idea as an array.
We have this name for the array.
We have some elements inside each
individual block of that array.
And we have that same
syntax to get access
to individual elements of that array.
So name[0], name[1], and so on.
But what's kind of special
about this string here?
If we take a look at that
last element, does anyone
remember what that last
element was called?
Just to show you again,
looks like a "slash 0".
What was that called?
AUDIENCE: Wasn't it the null character?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, right.
It was the null character.
And you remember what its purpose was?
Maybe go ahead, Dewey, yeah.
AUDIENCE: It marks
the end of the string.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, It
marks the end of the string.
So otherwise, we wouldn't
really quite know where
to stop if we were looking at a string.
We have to have some way of knowing,
OK, this is the end of our string now.
But here, we have this null
character tell us, OK, that
is going to be the end of our string.
If we want to make this
same string, we could do so
by making an array of characters.
So here, we have up above,
this array called name.
And it's full of characters.
And we've given it some elements here,
E, m, m, a, and that null character.
So we've composed this string
ourselves from individual characters.
And this syntax here, string name gets
the value "Emma" is kind of some sugar
that we've given you to make
it easier to declare an array.
This is based in the CS50
library, but on your own,
if you were off into the world
and programming C more generally,
you might make strings a
little bit more like this,
or you might use some libraries
to simplify things for you,
but basically, under the hood,
this array is this array--
or the string is this
array of characters.
And notice similarities here
between this array called "name",
and this array called "hours".
It's much the same
thing, just here we're
storing integers versus
storing characters.
That's handy because we
can do all the same things
we could do with arrays earlier.
We can have name[0] to
get that first character,
name[1] to get that second
character, and so on.
And so just curious here,
any questions on strings
or how they're similar to arrays
or the syntax that we've seen here?
All right.
AUDIENCE: Sorry, just
one quick question.
You can't circle through a string in
the same way you can with an array?
Like in a string, you couldn't
say the first character
with square brackets for stricter--
square bracket 0 and then 1.
That's unique to arrays?
CARTER ZENKE: It's unique to arrays.
Arrays are the only data structure
that have that bracket notation,
but the nice thing about a string
is a string just is an array.
So you can get that same functionality.
So here, even if we didn't do this, we
didn't spell out the array like this,
we just did string name gets the value
"Emma", we could still do this syntax.
Name[0] gets that capital
E at the beginning,
name[1] gets that second
character, that m there and so on.
Does that make sense?
Nice.
Other questions too on these strings?
OK.
So one of the interesting
things about these characters
is that they're represented ultimately,
by binary, everything in the end is.
But in C, we have this
dual representation
of characters, where this capital
A is represented by the number, 65.
Lowercase a is represented
by the number, 97.
And somebody came up with this, The
American Standard Code for Information
Interchange, I believe.
I'm not misremembering there, or ASCI.
And so ASCI defines these
relationships between these characters
and these numbers.
And the interesting thing is, if I
were to go to my code space here,
let's say I wanted to make
a file called "string.c",
I could include all the
files I need, like this.
I could make my main
function, and let's say
I did have this string called
Emma, well, what I could do
is I could print out every
letter, kind of like this.
I could say for int i is
zero, i is less than--
oh.
Well, how long is Emma?
How many characters should I go?
We don't-- I mean, you could
look at it and say it's for.
But there's a better way to do it.
And we saw a function in lecture.
What could we do?
Yeah, Dewey?
AUDIENCE: Str len?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, we need str len.
str len is this function
in the string.h library.
We might say strlen,
kind of for short here.
And we want to get the
length of our strings.
We could say this new variable, called
length, gets the length of name.
And now we can kind of finish for loop.
We could say, i is less than the
length of that string, i plus,
plus, it's increasing by 1 as we go.
And now we'll say, OK, print out
for me whatever character is inside
of name[i].
And so however, to make this,
compile it to machine code.
I could run .string and I see E, M, M,
A. All of these individual characters.
But what I could do
too is I could say, I
want the integer representation of this.
I want to print this as an integer.
I could recompile this.
And I'm going to actually add this new
line at the very end of my program now.
I could say, "make string"
and then "./string".
And now I don't get E, M, M,
A, I get 69, 109, 109, 97.
So whenever you're
working with characters,
you can also treat them as numbers.
And we can do this
interchangeably as we go through.
I could say is a certain number--
or is a certain character more than
or less than some number, or things
like that.
It'll be useful for us as we
work on this next exercise
here where we're going to try to
figure out if a string characters are
in alphabetical order.
So what do we notice here if
we go back to this ASCI chart?
We look down at this lowercase half.
What do you notice as the numbers
get further in the alphabet?
What happens to the numbers?
Can I ask maybe Bianca,
if you don't mind?
How are these numbers changing
as we go further in the alphabet?
AUDIENCE: They increased in value.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, they
keep increasing in value.
So to figure out if a strange character
is in alphabetical order, what
we could do is just check to
see is each character greater
than the one behind it?
So let's go ahead and get
start on this one together.
We could maybe go to our terminal
here and code up alpha.c.
And this would be our new file,
not downloading anything, just
making a new file here.
And we could say I want to
include the CS50 library.
I want to include standard
IO.h to print things out
and I want to have this
main function still.
This main part of my program.
And now what I could
do is I could say, I
want to get some string from the user.
So I could say, string
word is going to get--
what?
What kind of function can
we use to get a string
from the user from the CS50 library?
Maybe Elena, do you
have any thoughts here?
AUDIENCE: So I'm not sure.
CARTER ZENKE: It's OK.
We're trying to get a
string from the user here.
So how could we-- what kind of functions
in CS50 library might be useful for us?
AUDIENCE: Get string.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, get string.
So we could say, "get string".
And maybe in this case, enter a word.
And the rest of our program
I might leave up to you.
But again, the goal is to
check if a lowercase strings
characters are in alphabetical order.
And if they are, print "yes".
If they aren't, we'll print "no".
And you might want to have
some kind of loop that
goes through a every character and
does that check for you, checking
to see if each character is more
than or less than the one behind it
and making a decision based
off of that to figure out
if it's in alphabetical order or not.
So I'll go ahead and paste this one in
the chat for you all, but any questions
before we begin here?
Not seeing any I'm just
finishing typing in the chat.
And you might find ASCIchart.com
useful to go ahead and take
a look at the representation of these
characters as numbers in this case.
So we'll go back into some breakout
rooms for, let's say, five minutes.
We'll come back afterwards to do
this together and then talk more
about command line arguments and yeah.
So let me go ahead and open these
up and I'll see you in a few.
All right.
Welcome back, everyone.
Again, I hope you made at
least a little bit of progress
or you learn something while
you were working on this.
It's a little bit more
on the advanced side.
So what we do is take
a look at a solution
together, walk through what it does and
see what questions come up as we do so.
So here is one way of
approaching this problem.
I can Zoom in a little bit here.
And what we'll do is we'll first get
our string from the user on this line 7.
And then we'll go ahead and
figure out how long that word is.
Now what we'll do is we'll go
through every character front to back
and say, OK, let's check if the
character is not alphabetical.
Often in computer science, it's
easier to check for something
that if it's not true, then it is to
check for something if it is true.
So here we're going to say, I want
to see if it's not alphabetical.
And if it is, I want
to go ahead and print
"no" it's not alphabetical and return
0, meaning I'm going to exit my program.
Nothing else will happen here.
But assuming I actually get through
this loop, all the way through,
I'll go ahead and print "yes".
The key intuition here is that we
know if something's not alphabetical
when the current character
has a value that's greater
than the character that's before it.
So here, if I were, to example,
say look at-- actually, yeah,
before the character that is--
yeah, so here, I would look at
B and say, OK, B in this case
is greater than A. If we look
at that chart from earlier,
let me go back here.
Open this up.
We could see that B is a 98 and A is 97.
So in this case, if we ever
find that this character here
is greater than the
character ahead of it,
we know that we've found a
non-alphabetical sequence.
And we can go ahead and say "no".
In this case.
Assuming we get all the way through
though and we don't ever trigger this
and we don't ever end
our program early, we
could assume that everything must
be alphabetical unless "return 0"
at the end.
So questions on this or places you were
getting stuck as we were going through?
Yeah, Dewey?
AUDIENCE: You don't need the
return 0 at the end, right? like,
after the "print yes".
You need it for the "print no" I
think, but not the "print yes".
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, we
don't really need this here.
Maybe it's good for completeness
sake to have some return value there.
But C will automatically
return 0 as soon
as you hit this bottom
semicolon of your main function.
The return 0 here,
though, as you said, is
necessary because it
ends our program early
and keeps us from printing no, no, no,
no, no as we go through our program.
AUDIENCE: Could you explain--
CARTER ZENKE: Other questions?
AUDIENCE: Could you explain one more
time how you need to do string length
as the first--
like at the top?
CARTER ZENKE: Oh, yeah.
Like up here?
Yeah.
So in general, when you
want to do something
for every character in
a string, you generally
want to have some form of strlen.
And strlen is going to tell you how many
times you should loop in your for loop.
So here, for example, if I wanted
to figure out how do I do something
for every character in my array?
Well, I have to know how
many times to loop and thus
I have to know how long my string is.
So I know I need strlen
to figure that out for me
and I can use that variable
in my for loop later on.
Does that make sense?
Nice.
OK, other questions here too?
All right.
So not seeing any there.
So let's go ahead and move on
to some command line arguments
just to wrap up our section today.
I know there was some excitement
around command line arguments.
They're pretty cool actually.
You could actually use them
to modify our program behavior
as we type it in at the terminal.
And so maybe you're used to using a
GUI or a graphical user interface,
but you'll get used to, as you do
more programming, using this terminal
interface.
You can type in a
program's name and then
go ahead and give it
some options to run with.
And we saw Clang earlier, this
compiler for the C language.
And Clang does take some
command line arguments.
So we saw it could take this
argument called Mario.c.
And this is a command
line argument because it's
given to the program at the terminal,
it's not an option we give to a program
as it's running, it's given
to our program before it runs.
We could also give more.
We could say the output of
this compiler should be Mario,
this file called Mario.
And even make itself takes
command line arguments,
that Mario right there at the very end.
And we could even have another program
called "initials", for example.
Actually no, I think we--
we'll get to initials
in just a minute, sorry.
But the intuition behind
command line arguments
comes from this idea of these functions
that take their own arguments.
So in an earlier problem, you maybe
saw this calculate quarters function.
And here, this calculate
quarters function
takes this argument called "sense".
And this program or this function
takes that input and then
does something different
because it's given
that input, this argument over here.
Similarly in our programs,
we have this main function
where this is the
function that gets called
as we type the name of our
program in the terminal.
So if I were to type
maybe ./mario, again,
my main function is being called.
Now Mario didn't take any command
line arguments and because of that,
we typed "int main and void, where
void says no input to our program
is given at the command line.
We do return something from
this function, an integer,
kind of like a status code
that we saw in lecture.
But the input to this program
is void, is currently nothing.
If we did though want to give our
program some input it could run with,
typically, in our programs
we would write something
like this, "int argc" and "string Argv".
That's an array.
And the reason we do this, we often
want two pieces of information
as our program starts.
We want to know how many
arguments were given,
and that's argc for argument count.
Notice how it's an integer
called argc for argument count.
That's how many arguments you've
given at the command line.
And we're also given this
array of those arguments called
argv, which stands for argument vector.
And so argument vector,
argv is this array
of strings that have been given to
our program at the command line.
And we can use those in our
program to modify its behavior.
Now for example, if we were to go
in and make our own program here.
I could do maybe "code CLA"
for command line arguments.
And I could then do all the usual stuff.
I could include "stdio.h".
I could include maybe "CS50.h".
And I could do "int
main", but this time, I
want to take command line argument.
So I could say, "int argc, string argv".
And what this will do for me is allow me
to figure out what else was typed along
with my program?
And to do so, I might do the following.
I try to go through every
element of this argv array.
So I could say "for int i is zero".
I is less than argc, I plus, plus.
Let me loop through every
argument I've been given here.
And then go ahead and print out,
as a string, whatever is inside
of argv at that location here.
Let me fix this.
And let me just make it a little clearer
here, even too I could say, maybe argc
is--
and then some number.
And argv is, or sorry, argv-- let
me actually makes this clear--
so you can say "argv, bracket,
whatever we're currently looking,
at is whatever's inside of argv.
So here, when I run this program,
I'll see argv, bracket, 0, bracket,
1 is whatever's at that location here.
So I'll then go to my terminal.
I'll compile this.
I'll say, "make CLA".
And I'll run "/cla".
And now I see argv,
bracket, 0, is ./CLA.
But if I did ./CLA, maybe, Carter
Zenke, well now I see more.
I see argv, bracket, 0, is ./CLA.
Argv[1] is Carter. argv[2] 2 is Zenke.
So I've been given this array
that contains everything
I typed in to the terminal here.
Just to make this even clearer, I could
go back to this diagram over here.
When we "make Mario", that very
first make over here is argv[0],
the very first element of argv, or
argument vector, or argument list.
And argv[1] is that
second element there.
We can get using our program here.
And often that you'll see when you
write your own programs in CS50,
you might want to maybe kick off
your program with some number.
Maybe in Caesar, you might
type a number to help
us figure out how much to rotate
a certain cipher, and so on.
And this is helpful for actually
making our programs change behavior
as we go through.
So I just wanted to pause here
and ask for your questions
on command line arguments.
Maybe you've tried them already,
maybe you haven't, but what
questions do you have about why
they're used, or how we use them?
OK.
So seeing none so far.
Let's go ahead and try to do a bit
of brief exercise together here.
We want to write this program
called "initials", where
if I were to run it with
some command line arguments,
I would get back the initials
in the certain name here.
So here, I would get
back CZ, for example.
And notice how we have, again,
this argument vector that
has every element inside of it.
And if we want to access individual
characters inside of these strings,
we can just have another
bracket notation appended.
We could say argv[1][0] gives me that
very first element of that second
element in our argv.
And similarly, argv[2][0] gives me
that very first element of that third
element inside of argv.
So we're kind of nesting
these arrays as we go through.
And towards that end, let's try
to actually implement this program
together.
So we'll go over to our terminal
here and type "code initials.c".
And I'll do all the same stuff.
I'll do "include CS50.h.
I'll do, "include stdio.h.
And finally, I'll do "int main, not
void, but int argc and string argv.
I want to eventually, do
something like this, ./initials.
Carter Zenke.
So let's try printing out
first this very first C.
How could I print that piece out?
Could I ask maybe, McKenna,
if you're feeling up for it?
How could I try to print
out that very first C here?
AUDIENCE: Wouldn't you do like
printf, something having to do with
the argc[1][0], right?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, totally.
So you want to print out a character.
So we'd use this format code
for a character, like %c.
And now I have to say, OK, what
goes in this placeholder here?
And we could do the
following, we could say,
well I know I want to look inside my
argument vector, this list of strings
I've been given.
This we know is that very first one.
So that's argv[0].
This one is argv[1], which
is getting us closer.
But we don't want to print
out the full name here.
So if I were to do this, for
example, print out a string.
Let me do, "make initials".
And then run it--
and just a minute, oops,
let me add a semicolon.
Make initials, do ./initials.
Whoops!
./initials Carter Zenke.
Notice I get back the
full string Carter.
But I don't want that.
I just want the actual first character.
So I could then, as you were
saying, we go ahead and say,
bracket 0 to get that very
first character in there.
And I'll go ahead and add a /n here.
So I'll say, "make initials".
Run initials with Carter's Zenke, and
now I get backseat, which is nice.
But maybe to finish things out, could
we go to Bianca, if you don't mind?
Maybe figure out how we could
get that second initial here?
AUDIENCE: So you would
do the same thing that we
have instead of the one and
the zero, you would do one--
well, the first one, is that from the
Carter, or is that from your last name?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah so
this one here, if we--
yeah, so when we ran
this, this is from trying
to get this initial C here, right?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
CARTER ZENKE: So now
I want to get the z.
AUDIENCE: Got it.
OK, so you would do the same thing,
but instead of argv[1] and 0,
you would do two and 0.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, two and 0.
And the reasoning here is that
we're going to first index
into that argument vector
this argument list here.
And here, we're going to get that
third element, this index of 2
gives us a third element.
And then within this string
here, that is also an array,
we're going to get that
very first element.
So we'll go to the z here.
And if we do this, I would
tend to maybe make initials.
And then I could do
./initials, Carter Zenke.
I would see C, Z, and then I would
C, Z. So there's much more to this.
If you like, you can
maybe use a loop here
to go through and do multiple
Clang line arguments,
but I think for now,
we'll leave it here.
This is going to conclude
our section, officially.
It was wonderful to spend
time with you all today.
And this was CS50 for now.
There are also going to be labs,
tutorials and office hours this week.
So make sure you go to all of
those to get help as you need it.
I hope this was helpful for you.
I'm looking forward to seeing
you all throughout the term
and again, thank you all for
joining us on Zoom today.