CARTER ZENKE: Well, welcome everyone
to our week seven, CS50 section.
My name is Carter Zenke.
I'm the Course Preceptor here on campus.
And the goal of these sections is really
to help bridge the gap between lecture
and this week's problem set.
So the goal of the day
is to dive into more SQL
to give you more practice writing
queries, working with databases,
and hopefully, at the
very end, you'll feel
prepared to tackle this
week's problem set.
Now actually, this week seven, is one
of my favorite weeks in the course.
And I like this week so much
because it's all about data,
and data is often about real people,
real things in the real world.
So it's like really good
connection between computer science
and how things actually
work in the real world.
It kind of brings these questions
about how we design things,
makes them all the more important.
Because we're actually going
to talk about real people,
real students, real
things in this world,
and we're going to represent
inside of our own programs now.
So thinking about data and
representing real people,
let's actually take a look into a
fantasy world, one in Harry Potter.
And if you're familiar
with Harry Potter,
maybe you're familiar
with the Hall of Prophecy,
which is this place where all of the
prophecies go to, live, and reside.
The place of we're they're going to
store lots of different prophecies.
And maybe be one of these
prophecies is this place of where
Hogwarts students, people who go to
the Hogwarts School of Magic, will be
could have housed, where they're going
to actually live during their time
at Hogwarts.
So, let's think about how we might
store a database of Hogwarts students
inside of the different
houses of Hogwarts.
And if you're familiar, there's like
Slytherin, Gryffindor, Hufflepuff,
and Ravenclaw.
And all these students live
in these various houses here.
So if we think of a database,
we think of this space
that is maybe currently empty, we
could fill it with some things.
So let's go ahead and call this
space, for the sake of our discussion
here, as roster.db.
We're going to have
some students in here,
and they're going to go into different
houses inside of this database.
So all databases have some
tables, some places that we're
going to store data inside of them.
And in this case, let's say we have
this table that looks a bit like this.
And if you can see that, we see
we have Adelaide Murton, who's
in the house for Slytherin.
And the head of the Slytherin house
is a professor named Severus Snape.
And down below and
kind of row three here,
we have Anthony Goldstein,
who's in Ravenclaw.
And the leader, the head of Ravenclaw,
is Filius Flitwick, a professor
at Hogwarts School of Magic.
So here, we have a table.
And often, in our
databases, tables are named.
So let's maybe call this one students.
And now, we have our full database.
We have a name for our
database, roster.db,
and we have a table inside of
it, this one called students.
But what we might want
to do with this table?
What are some things we might
want to actually do to this data.
If want to chime in and chat, what's
the point of storing data in this way?
What could we do with it?
Yeah.
So I'm seeing somebody messaging me.
So you could maybe
actually try to figure out
what else is inside of this table.
You query the database.
We could try to ask what's inside of it.
And to do that, we can
actually use these SQL
keywords that begins with a select.
How do we select data from this table?
So let's dive into selecting data
from tables as we saw in lecture.
Let's go a bit more
deeply into it this time.
So if I wanted to select all the
data from this particular table,
does anyone know what kind of
query I could use for this?
I'm seeing in the chat.
I'm seeing some select, which is good.
I'm seeing some stars,
which is also good.
And now, let's go
ahead and try this out.
So if I go to my own VS code over here,
I can see that I have my own roster.db.
So I'll go ahead and open this up with
SQLite, this kind of database engine
we can use to execute SQL
queries on this database,
so I'll do SQLite3 roster.db.
And now, just to show
you, if I type dot schema
to see the kinds of tables
I have inside the database,
I see I have this table called students.
It has the very same
attributes or columns
we saw earlier in our visual back here.
So, the hypothesis right now is
we could kind of select everything
in this table using this
syntax I see from the chat.
We could say SELECT star.
We can select everything
from this students table.
So let's go ahead and do that.
And we end all of our queries
in SQL with a semicolon.
So this is the end of our thought.
This is our entire query.
Select everything from
this students table.
I'll hit Enter now.
And now, I can see kind
of, if I zoom back out,
all of the students who
are inside of this roster.
So if you scroll through, we
have about 40 students here,
and we see some of that very same data.
So we see that Anthony Goldstein is
in Ravenclaw, led by Filius Flitwick.
We've got in all data from inside
this table, so that's pretty good.
Let's create a visual for this.
So if you said we had this
roster here with a table
called students, if we do SELECT
star FROM students, what we'll see
is the entire table
will select everything
in this kind of yellow highlight here.
But we could also get more
specific, because it's often not
good to select everything.
Often we care about some
particular set of students
or particular column in general.
So let's say I just wanted the
student names, like how can I
get student names from this list,
disregarding the house and the head
and whoever else is in this database?
How could I just get student names?
I'm seeing some WHERE, and that is true.
We could use WHERE for other cases.
But here, I just want to get all of
the student names from this roster.
Nice.
So I'm seeing some syntax here
that looks a bit like this.
We could say SELECT
student_name FROM students.
So often, we use select.
After we say SELECT,
we have a column name,
like the column we want to
actually select from our table.
So in this case, if we looked
at student's table here,
we have a column called student_name.
So if you want to select that column,
we could say SELECT student_name FROM
this table called student.
So if we go back to our SQLite prompt
here, we actually type in SQL commands.
Only we now type SELECT
student_name FROM students.
And what should I end this with
now, because it's a SQL query?
A semicolon.
Good.
So I'll hit semicolon
here, and I'll hit Enter.
And now, notice how my table
just has that single column.
It doesn't have every column now,
but just that student_name column.
So often, we're using SELECT.
If we want to include the column
name, we're selecting from our table.
And if we just want
everything, we can say star.
SELECT star, meaning select
everything from our given table.
Now, to kind of focus in on
getting particular students,
let's say we cared not just
about every student's name,
but only those who are
in a particular house.
If you go back to our table here, we
have student names, houses, and heads.
So maybe we care about the students
who are in Slytherin house.
How could we find the students
who are in that house?
Any ideas?
We just care now about
students who are in Slytherin.
Yeah.
So here, we can bring back that
WHERE clause that we saw before.
So, if we want not just an
entire column of students
as we see here but some rows,
depending on a certain condition
in another column, we can use WHERE.
So WHERE will give us back only
certain rows from our table.
So let's try this.
We could say, let's
SELECT student_names.
Let's get that student name column
from the student's table now,
but let's go ahead and get
only those students where
the house is equal to what we're
going to call Slytherin in this case.
So if we go back to our table
now and I type this query,
I could say SELECT student_name,
and I can type this all in one line.
For the sake of argument here,
I could say FROM students.
And let's do WHERE house is Slytherin.
OK, my query will wrap here.
So we kind of go around the edge,
but it's all one line, theoretically.
Semicolon here.
What do we see?
We see only the students
who are inside of Slytherin.
And just to prove this, let's go
ahead and actually update our query
and let's show you how could
do it on multiple lines.
So we can say SELECT
student_name and house.
We could say student_name and house.
We want this in the same
query here separated by comma.
Well, let's get this
FROM our students table.
And let's say we only want the
rows where that house column is
going to be Slytherin in this case.
So I'll do a semicolon
here and I'll hit Enter.
And now, I do see that these same
student names do belong to Slytherin.
So with SELECT, we can
always try to select
not just a single column, but
also multiple columns separated
by commas here.
Now, what questions are there
so far on these SELECT, or does
it seem pretty straightforward so far?
Any questions in the chat?
OK, not seeing any right now.
But let's try to go a
little more advanced now.
So we've seen how we
can select some data.
We've seen how we can get
different rows back from our table.
But what if we're not kind
of sure exactly what we
want to look for in our table?
Maybe we want to get just the
students whose last name is Potter.
Well, how could we do that?
Any ideas what kind of
clause we could use,
if you want to find the students
whose name end with Potter?
Somebody said we should use LIKE.
And as we saw in lecture,
LIKE is this query
that kind of lets us do
a fuzzy match, meaning
that we get all the rows
that kind of roughly
match some clause or some string
we might give to our query here.
So to do this, let's go ahead
and look at our table again.
For Slytherin, we got kind
of a result like this.
But now, let's look at
how we could use it, LIKE.
So if we're interested in students
whose name ends with Harry Potter,
well, we could do a query like this.
We could say, SELECT student_names,
obviously, FROM our student table.
And now, we're only
going to take the student
names that are like Potter with
this kind of percent sign in front.
And I want to recall what that
percent sign is doing for us here,
if you want to chime in the chat.
Why can we not just say
LIKE Potter, and why do I
have to say LIKE percent Potter?
Yes, I'm seeing that people are
calling this a wild card character.
And basically, this
percent sign says that I
can match any character
ahead of this string Potter.
It could be Harry Potter.
It could be Lily Potter.
It could be, really, any name
as long as it ends with Potter.
And putting that percent
sign at the beginning,
well, that says that I can have any
characters I want before Potter.
And someone can maybe just have Harry
and then percent sign after Harry,
and that would give me all of the names
that begin with Harry in this case.
So let's go ahead and
take a look at this.
We can say SELECT
student_name now, and we
want to take student name
FROM our students table.
And then after this,
let's say, OK, we want
to get the student names that
are LIKE, not equal to but LIKE,
this string we're going to give
called Potter, percent Potter.
Meaning, we can get any character
before Potter as long as at the end,
we see Potter exactly,
so I'll hit Enter now.
And we see that there's really only one
student whose name ends with Potter,
which is Harry James Potter.
But you might also see other
characters in the Harry Potter universe
whose names also end in Potter too.
Now, maybe a better question here,
to get more students in this query,
is this one.
So we could say, find
the names and houses
of students whose names begin
with H. So let's try this one.
We're trying to find students
whose names begin with H.
So we want to select again names.
So I'll say, OK, I want
to SELECT a student_name
from my student_name column, and
I also want to select the house.
So I'll say comma house,
and I'll get back now
in this query student_name and house.
Where am I going to get
this data from though?
Any ideas?
Where am I selecting from in this case?
In the chat?
From students.
So I'll say FROM, students here.
Now to finish this off, I only want
the students whose names begin with H.
So I could say WHERE to
kind of subset my rows,
get a certain number of rows who
only meet a certain condition.
And now, the column I care
about, the student_name.
And I'm seeing in the chat, I could
say, not equals, not particular H here.
I don't want students
whose name literally
is H. I want students whose name is LIKE
H and then any other characters that
come after it.
So I could hit Enter here.
And now, I'll do this.
Now, we see we have Hannah
Abbott, whose name begins
with H, Harry, and Hermione
also begins with H.
And they're H in Hufflepuff for
Hannah, and Harry and Hermione
are in Gryffindor.
A question, is this case sensitive?
It's a good question.
Let's go ahead and try it.
So we could say, SELECT
student_name, and we're
going to select also the houses FROM
the students table, where the student
name is LIKE, and we saw
capital H beforehand, like this.
But now, let's try a
lowercase h and see if we
get any students here or any different
results, now that it's lowercase.
So let's hit Enter now, and we
still get the very same results.
So what do you think?
Is LIKE case sensitive?
Does it matter what case I use?
No, it doesn't seem to.
I could use the capital H.
I could say the lowercase h
and I get the very same results here.
So that's a great question.
And now, I'm seeing another question.
We need to use keywords like
SELECT, like WHERE in all caps,
and why is that so?
So here, you'll see that I'm
using SELECT in all caps,
I'm using FROM in all caps,
and using WHERE in all caps,
and LIKE in all caps.
And the convention here
is, is that if you're
typing in a SQL keyword, some kind of
command to SQL, like SELECT or FROM
or WHERE or LIKE, well,
you should capitalize
that to denote it as a SQL keyword.
I can keep my column names
though or my strings in lowercase
because if I look at
my table here, well,
these literally are in lowercase,
student_name, house is lowercase.
So I want to make sure
that casing matches there.
But for a SQL query, I
should, by convention, sort of
capitalize these keywords.
I could very much do this.
I could say SELECT star
FROM students and I
would get the very same
results if I zoom out a bit,
but it's just not quite as clean.
It's hard to tell.
Let's say, if I do this, select
student_name, house from students.
It's kind of hard to tell
where my keywords begin
and where my column
names actually join in,
like it's hard to tell which
what thing is which here.
So always capitalize your SQL
keywords as you go through.
Great.
Another question, when do we use LIKE?
So as we've seen before
here, we use LIKE--
let me actually just
finish the query here.
We use LIKE when we want to
actually fuzzy match something, kind
of roughly match something.
So if I know that I want students whose
name begins with H but isn't exactly H,
LIKE is a good use case for that here.
Other questions on selecting then?
I'm just going through
the chat here to be sure.
All right, so I think that's
most of our questions on this.
So there's a main
question about, is there
a way to make search case sensitive?
There is.
So we saw before that LIKE is generally
not case sensitive, but let's try this.
If I do a search for Harry James
Potter, who we know is in our database,
I could do SELECT, the
student_name, FROM students,
WHERE the student_name is
exactly Harry James Potter,
and I'll hit semicolon here.
And I should get, well, none
other than Harry James Potter.
But what if I did this, what if I said
SELECT student_name, FROM students,
WHERE the student_name is now
all lowercase harry james potter,
hit Enter now, and no one
seems to match that exactly.
So equals, when you're using
that, is case sensitive,
but LIKE, by definition, is not.
So that seems to be most of what you
might want to use our selecting for.
We can use WHERE and we can
use LIKE to kind of narrow
our matches from our table.
But what else could we
do with these queries?
So one thing I want to do, as we
saw in lecture, is kind of order
our students, put them in
like alphabetical order
or kind of roster order and so on.
And we can use some new school
keywords for that exactly.
So we can not just select,
we can also order our data.
So we saw before, we can just kind
of get every student we want to.
I guess by SELECT star FROM students
give us all the students here.
But at very end of this
query, once it's complete,
we could have tacked on
this other keyword called
ORDER BY to tell SQL what column
I want to sort this data by.
So I'll get every column, but if I want
to sort the data by particular column,
I could say ORDER BY that
particular column name.
So here, if I do this,
ORDER BY student_name, well,
I should get the names
in alphabetical order.
So, I think if I select everything,
SELECT star FROM students,
I might already have these names in
alphabetical order by virtue of how
they were added to this data set.
But if I were to do this,
SELECT star FROM students,
I'll zoom in down below here.
Zoom in here, SELECT star FROM students,
and then ORDER BY student_name,
well, I kind of get the very same thing.
But it's important to
keep in mind, you keep
in mind that when you use ORDER
BY by without kind of anything
after it, like this here, we're
getting the names in what's
called ascending order.
So ascending, in SQL, means from kind
of the lower Ascii value, like A,
to the higher Ascii value,
like Z, so A to Z in this case.
But if I wanted to flip it,
not having A to Z, but Z to A,
well, I could change this,
not to order by ascending,
but to order by descending, like this.
So by default, SQL always order
by the ascending order like this.
But if you want to
order by descending, you
could simply say descending at
the end or DESC for descending.
So let's try that now so I
can actually see the results.
So I'll go, clear my terminal,
zoom in a bit, and I'll say SELECT.
I'll say SELECT star FROM
students, and then I will say,
ORDER BY student_name, now descending,
so from Z to A. Now, let's try this.
I'll hit Enter.
And now, if I zoom out, you should see.
I start with Vincent now, whose name
is towards the end of the alphabet,
and I go up to Adelaide, whose
name is at the top of the alphabet.
In this case.
And I mean there are other things
we could sort of sort by here.
So we don't have to just sort by student
name, we could also sort by house.
So maybe we want to sort by this.
We could say SELECT student_name,
or sorry, SELECT-- let's
just select everything here,
SELECT everything FROM students.
Whoops, my internet's
a little wonky here.
I'll SELECT star FROM--
I'm going to give my code
space a minute to breathe here.
I'm going too quickly
through these SELECT.
I think we're back.
So we'll do SELECT star FROM students.
And now I'm going to order by,
not student name, but by house.
And so now, I should see, if I zoom
out, my data organized by house.
I have all the students in Gryffindor,
all students in Hufflepuff,
and all the students in Ravenclaw,
and all the students in Slytherin.
So a question now is, let's say
we wanted to sort the student
data in alphabetical order, but have
it first sorted by house, and then
by student name.
So ideally, we should have
all of our data from our table
viewed now, but sorted first
by house, alphabetical order.
And then, inside of each
house, sorted by name.
So how could we do this, do you think?
Do you want to chime in the chat?
How could we have this kind of
multiple, multi-layered sort going on?
I've seen a few options, and one
that I like here is this comma.
We could use a comma,
something that we did before.
We could say, if we
start off in SELECT, we
could do SELECT student_name,
and house, or we could
do the very same thing for ORDER BY.
We could ORDER BY multiple things at
the very same time, so let's do this.
We could do SELECT everything
FROM students, and let's ORDER BY
first house, and then by student_name.
So with the comma here is saying is that
the very first thing before the comma
is the first thing I will sort by.
Then afterwards, student name is
the next thing I will sort by.
So inside of my sorted list of houses,
I will then sort student names,
so let's try this.
And now, we can see, if I zoom out,
well, we have Gryffindor all sorted.
And inside of the students
who are in Gryffindor, well,
we have those students in
alphabetical order, CDGHHLN and so on.
So let's try it maybe with
a more advanced technique.
We could go in and say SELECT
everything FROM students.
But now, we just want to
get the houses as they are,
SELECT ORDER BY house,
and then the student_name,
but in reverse alphabetical order.
And how can I get reverse
alphabetical order now?
Descending, right.
So I could say DESC here.
And now, I'll hit Enter.
And now I see, I'm still sorting by
house alphabetically, G, H, R, and S.
But now, inside of
each house, notice how
I'm going from the bottom of
the alphabet to the very top.
So questions on these sorts?
What do you wonder about?
I could write this sort case sensitive.
Let's check that one out actually.
So we see-- we can do SELECT star FROM
students, and now, I'll do ORDER BY.
And because we said house before,
why don't we just try capital H house
and I'll hit semicolon and Enter again?
And that still seems to work.
So when you're talking
about SQL column names,
those also are not going to
be case sensitive for you.
And the question, what will happen if
I switch between house and student_name
in that query?
That's a great question.
So before, we had a query like
this, SELECT star FROM students,
and then we did ORDER BY first
house and then student_name?
But what if we did this, what if we
did, first, student_name and then house?
So what do you think
will happen in this case?
In the chat, if you want to
chime in, what do you think?
What will happen if we
flip this order now?
Yes, so somebody says it'll first
sort by name and then by house,
so let's try running this.
We'll hit Enter here and I'll zoom out.
And notice how my student names
are in alphabetical order.
But within the C's, for example, I now
have my houses in alphabetical order,
so Hufflepuff, Ravenclaw,
and Gryffindor.
Or let's see, we have a lot of M's.
So here, we have Ravenclaw, Slytherin.
Well, that didn't seem to quite
work in this case actually.
Why did that not work?
MRR, interesting.
Oh, yeah, so somebody--
it's a good point.
So somebody asked, there's
no two identical names.
So what happened here is, this
isn't quite useful for us,
and I'll see if I can explain this.
Because what SQL will do is not sort by
the very first letter of student_name,
but sort by the entire string.
And so, in order for the houses
that we see in alphabetical order,
we have to think the
exact same student name.
So not just the same first
letter, but the same student name.
And because no two student
names are exactly alike,
we probably won't actually
see the results in this case.
So good catch from
somebody in the chat here.
Other questions on ordering then?
A good question here.
So what if a name starts with
a number, kind of unlikely,
but a good case to consider.
So if we had a name search
with a number, well,
it's going to go by the Ascii
value for that number, I believe.
So in this case, numbers
would likely come before A
or come before, certainly
before Z, and so on.
So first, numbers and symbols,
and then the alphabet.
Any question here?
Can we order one column by ascending
and the second by descending?
You absolutely can.
So we could say this.
We can say SELECT star FROM students.
Let's go ahead and ORDER BY
house, descending, and then
we could ORDER BY student_name
ascending, like this.
So certainly, if you're
free to apply your
own ascending or descending to each of
these multiple arguments to ORDER BY
here.
And another question before
we move on, so one is, how
are lower or uppercase letters sorted?
So I think, in this case, it would
be uppercase would come first
because I think uppercase is
lower in the Ascii alphabet.
If you remember how letters
correspond to Ascii numbers,
I think uppercase is lower
there, so it would come first
in the default ascending
order of these characters.
So let's move on from
ordering, and let's think
about one keyword that's actually
kind of useful along with ordering.
That's the use case of a limit.
So if we have some query, and we won't
get back just a certain number of rows
from that query, all we could do
is simply apply this limit one
or limit five or limit
10, whatever number
you want to limit at the
very end of that query.
This is helpful for finding the
top 10 of something, for example,
because you can order
by a certain column
and then take the top 10 that show up.
So, let's go back to our query here.
We can maybe say, let's
want the first 10 students
whose name is first in the alphabet, the
first 10 students from the very first,
alphabetically.
So we say SELECT star FROM students.
I'm going to order by
student_name, and then we'll
limit our query to only 10 students.
I'll hit Enter here.
And now, I should see only 10
students, those whose names
are the very first 10 in the alphabet.
And somewhat I could change this.
I could say, let's not get
the first 10 alphabetically,
let's get the last 10 alphabetically.
So I could do SELECT star FROM students.
Now, let's order by student_name,
but in descending order.
And then let's go ahead and
limit 10, and we should see,
we get the very last 10 students
in our alphabetical order.
So limiting is helpful
along with ORDER BY
to kind of at the top or the bottom
sort of segments of your data
set, as long as you order by a certain
column that you care about here.
Question in the chat is,
what if you don't have an ID
and you select 10 queries, but
you want to see the number,
is there a way to do this?
Just so I can understand the question,
I think we're talking about these IDs
here on the left hand side.
And as we'll see later
in section, these IDs
are the primary keys, the unique
identifiers for each of these students.
And generally speaking, every student
should have their own unique ID.
If they don't have an
ID, well, you might have
some problems with database design.
But if we're talking about ordering
by here, ORDER BY student_name,
for example, we're not really
caring about the student ID
just the student name, in this case.
We could certainly ORDER BY ID if
we like to, ORDER BY ID descending,
ORDER BY ID ascending.
But in this case, it so
happens to be that the student
ID corresponds to the student name
kind of alphabetically sorted.
All right, and I'm seeing a
question about the last 10 students.
So this actually is going
to work somewhat similarly.
So if I wanted the last 10 students
alphabetically, I could do this.
I could sort SELECT star FROM
students, and then go ahead
and say I want to ORDER BY
student_name in descending order
to get those bottom 10
students, and then whoops,
and then I could limit
10 at the very end.
Other questions too on limiting?
Let's keep moving then.
And what we could do here is we often--
it's nice to get the
individual student names,
but one thing we often care about
is how many students are there?
What's like an average test score?
Trying to aggregate our data,
not just take individual rows,
but see kind of the bigger
picture from our data.
And for that, SQL has a variety of
keywords you can use to get that data,
get that aggregate data, so to speak.
So here, we'll talk about
aggregating, where aggregating
means taking those individual
rows, as I said before,
but kind of summing things
up or averaging them
or kind of seeing the
whole larger picture.
So if I wanted to count the rows I
get back, well, we could do this.
I could say SELECT COUNT
star FROM students.
And this will take everything in our
table, force selecting everything,
and return the count of it,
the number of rows that I have.
So for example, to figure out how
many students are in this table,
I can say SELECT COUNT star FROM
students, semicolon, hit Enter.
And now, I see, I get 40 in this case.
There are 40 total students.
And this is kind of not very
pretty, like the COUNT star.
I'd love to just say like
number of students, for example.
So how could I change this column
names, anyone know in the chat?
Yeah, I could use AS.
So I can say SELECT COUNT star AS in
this case, maybe number_of_students,
and then I could say we want to
select that from the student's table.
So now, I see I get
the very same answer,
but now my column is
called number_of_students.
So again, what we're doing
here is selecting everything
from our students table, counting it
up, and returning that as a column named
number_of_students, in this case.
So what if we only wanted
particular students,
like let's say we just wanted to
count students from Gryffindor?
Well, how could I do that?
In the chat, if you want to chime in,
counting just students from Gryffindor.
So I'm seeing the use of
WHERE, which is helpful.
Other ideas too?
Yeah.
So I'm seeing-- I want to use COUNT.
I probably use WHERE here
too, and we'll get to what
we call GROUP BY in just a moment.
But let's try WHERE first.
So normally, to get all
the things in Gryffindor,
I would do a query like this.
I could say SELECT star FROM
students WHERE, in this case,
house is Gryffindor, and
then semicolon Enter.
And now, these are all
students who are in Gryffindor.
But if I wanted just the count of
these, not every individual row,
what could modify my query, and to
not SELECT star but SELECT COUNT star,
so like the count of everything here.
SELECT COUNT star FROM students,
and then I'll say WHERE.
In this case, the house is
Gryffindor, semicolon, Enter.
And now, I see I have 11 students
who are in Gryffindor here,
and that's all pretty good, but we
also have to care about Slytherin.
So let's say we want to
SELECT the COUNT star FROM
students where the house is Slytherin,
and that would give us also 11.
But how could I get all of
the houses in one place,
like not just individual areas for
each house, for how many students
are in them, but actually
have it all in one query
and have a table that says
Slytherin has this many students,
Gryffindor has many students?
And I'm seeing, in the
chat, this GROUP BY
keyword that we're going
to explore now here.
So GROUP BY is helpful if you
want to get the number of students
by a certain attribute.
So we want to kind of group our
data by house and figure out, well,
how many students are in each house?
So let's try this.
We can use GROUP BY as follows.
I can say SELECT star FROM our
students table, and let's go ahead
and GROUP BY, in this case, house.
We want to group our data
by house, and I think
we might have messed up slightly here.
Let's go ahead to the query.
We'll just hit Enter here.
And now we can see where
we have individual houses,
but there's something weird going
on with this student_name over here.
We have much fewer pieces
of data, but I'm just not
sure why we're getting
student_name over here.
Well, instead of searching everything,
why don't we select the count
from each of our houses?
So SELECT COUNT again FROM our students
table, and then we'll GROUP BY house.
I'll hit Enter here.
And so I get back 11, 5, 13, and 11.
What do you think this
means, in this case?
Any ideas in the chat?
It's the number of students in
each house, but it's hard for us
to tell which house is which.
Lets include the house name in our
query, so let's not just select
the count of everything.
Let's select the house in our query too.
Let's order it like this.
Let's first select the
house, and then select
the COUNT of everything FROM students,
as long as we're grouping by house.
I'll Enter here.
And now, I get Gryffindor,
Hufflepuff, Ravenclaw, and Slytherin,
where each one has a count next
to it, like 11, 5, 13, and 11.
So this is the total number of students
in each group, as somebody in the chat
is saying, that we're going
to first group by house
and then take the count by every house.
Other questions on these GROUP
BYs or this aggregation here?
So it seems like we have most
questions answered there.
And now that we've kind of
seen a variety of SQL keywords,
we've kind of reviewed them
from lecture, let's dive
into something about database
that probably isn't great for us.
Like if we select everything
here, SELECT star FROM students,
let's just zoom out a
bit and think about what
isn't very well designed about this
database if you take a look at it.
What could be better designed about
it, or where do you see some repetition
that we maybe can get rid of?
Yeah, so I'm seeing some
people saying that there's
some repetition in the houses.
We have Slytherin here, Slytherin
again, Ravenclaw, Slytherin, Hufflepuff,
like a lot of these names are repeating.
And similarly for the heads, notice
how we have all the heads kind of
repeated throughout this data set.
And maybe, ideally, we
wouldn't actually have
to repeat Severus Snape, Severus Snape,
all the way through our data set.
We could just put Severus
Snape in one place
and reference Severus
Snape from other places.
And maybe for the house,
we could say, well,
Slytherin shows up a lot of times.
What if we just had
Slytherin in one table,
and we reference
Slytherin in this table?
So the goal is to avoid repeating
ourselves over and over again
in this data set, like having
Slytherin so many times
or Hufflepuff so many times.
I just want to make our own tables for
individual pieces of our data sets.
So if we're thinking about how we
could better design this table,
let's look at a few design
principles we could use
to actually improve this table here.
So go back to our slides.
Let's think about database design.
So one principle for a
database is that every table
you have inside of your database
should only represent a single entity,
and we've actually kind
of broken that rule here.
So if I go back into my table,
well, I have students in this table.
It's a table of students.
But I also have houses, I
have heads, like there's
lots of things going on here that
don't just belong to students.
So ideally, what we could do is
try to simplify this a little bit.
Let's try to have a single table for
students, a single table for houses,
and then a single table for the
assignments of students between houses.
So in this case, students wouldn't
also have the house assignment.
And similarly, houses wouldn't
have the house assignment.
But we have this extra table
called student-house assignments
that sort of tells us how these students
and houses relate to each other.
So as a visual here, let's dive in.
Let's say-- this is what
we currently look like.
We have a student's table that
has student names, houses,
and the head of each house,
but we want to break this up.
We only want to have a single
thing inside of each of our tables.
So let's break this up.
Let's say get rid of the
houses and heads here.
Those are gone.
Let's just have students in this table,
but where should we put our houses now?
Let's make a new table called houses.
And this one we'll put
here, we'll call it houses.
And notice how in this
table called houses,
well, we have some new IDs
for each of these houses.
But now, we have, well, in this
case, it's called student_name.
Let me fix that.
That should be house in
this case, house called
Gryffindor, Hufflepuff,
Ravenclaw, and Slytherin, and then
the head of that house in this
case, like Minerva, Pomona, Filius,
and Severus.
So, we now have our own
separate table for houses.
And we could even go one
step further and say, well,
how do we now know where
students are assigned.
And for that, we could
make our new table,
this one called assignments, down below.
So you can see that I have assignment
1 to 4, where student ID is 1
and house ID is 4.
So what do you think this table
now is telling us down below?
If I give you the full screen below
here, if you type in the chat,
what is this table telling
us, only this first row?
It's telling us that Adelaide,
Adelaide Murton, belongs to Slytherin.
And how do you know that in this case?
How do you know that Adelaide
belongs to Slytherin now?
Because of the IDs.
So we saw before that here, we have ID.
Student ID is one, but which
student has the ID one?
Well, it seems like it's Adelaide
if you look at that table.
And I look at the 4 here for the
house ID, in which house is 4.
Well, that's Slytherin.
So we know that Adelaide has a
belonging to Slytherin in this case.
Adelaide is assigned to Slytherin house.
So this brings us to
another design principle
here, which is that,
ideally, we only want
to have every piece of
data stored in one place.
And then from thereafter, refers
that piece of data by its ID.
So notice how we have, in the students
table, an ID for every student.
In the houses table,
an ID for every house.
And now, in our other tables, we
just have to reference that ID.
We don't have to actually reference
Slytherin or the student name anymore.
If those things change, we
change them in one place.
And now, the relationship,
we can sort of
define elsewhere and
update that as we need to.
And this is a good
segue into what people
are saying in the chat, which is
primary keys and foreign keys.
So what is the primary key
now in each of these tables?
Where do you see a primary key?
Yes, so you're seeing in the
ID columns for every table.
So here in students,
students is primary key.
The unique ID for every
student is just that ID column.
And for houses, the primary key is
that ID column as well, and similarly,
for assignments.
But now, student_id
is not a primary key.
It's not a unique identifier
for every student here.
What is it instead?
It's a foreign key.
So it's saying that this references
a primary key in another table.
It's references the
unique ID in students now.
And similarly, this house ID 4,
well, that reference the primary key
in houses.
So we're going to say is that
the primary key is that unique ID
inside of the table,
and a foreign key is
a reference to that primary key
from another table, a separate table
in this case.
So if we wanted to update this
table, we could do it as follows.
Let's actually go through the work
of trying to update this table.
Currently, looks like this.
We have just a single table here.
But we ideally want to
make a different table
for houses, a different
table for assignments,
so let's explore some syntax to
actually make that happen for us.
Now, we could create a table a bit like
this, and something's missing here.
But the general consensus
is it looks a bit like this.
We could say CREATE
TABLE, call it houses,
that has four, actually
three different columns now,
one called ID, one called
house, and one called head.
So the table called houses
will have a column called ID,
a column called house,
and a column called head.
And what is this last
bit doing for us here?
Any ideas?
What is that specifying about our
table, at fourth kind of row here?
Yeah, so it's going to say
this will be a primary key.
This is going to be our unique
ID inside of this house's table.
So ID should be always
unique for every row.
It should never change for every row.
So, if you want to do this, we could try
this, but it won't quite work for us.
That's because in SQL,
there are also data types.
So if we kind of table if
we say, what kind of type
we're storing in each of our columns?
So here, we might say not just
ID, but that ID is an integer,
or not just house, but that house is
a piece of text, and so it's head.
So now, we're saying that we're going
to have these three columns, ID, house,
and head, and that ID is
an integer, house is text,
and head is text as well.
And we could even get
more fancy with this
and apply some constraints, which
means we could kind of make sure
that as we insert data to this
table, we adhere to some rules
that we set beforehand.
And maybe one of these rules
is that each of these columns
should never be null.
No meaning empty, meaning that
every column or every time we
add a new row, no column can be blank.
We can't have a house without a name,
and we can't have a house out ahead.
That wouldn't make sense.
So every row has to have each of
these three columns in order for us
to insert it.
And so, kind of a translation here is
that not null is similar to required.
We have to make sure this
column name is required
when we insert some new data here.
So let's try this soon,
but what questions do you
have so far on this great table syntax?
Let me see.
A good question here.
So if we update the particular
house's ID in the house table,
can that update the ID
and the assignments table?
So let's go back to our visual here.
It's a great question.
If we looked at the ID
for Slytherin, that is 4.
And in the assignments
table, we have the ID 4.
Now, if I changed Slytherin
ID to be 5, well, this
is assignments table would
not automatically update
for me, at least if I do it naively.
If I just go in here and I say that
this row here, Slytherin, should now
have the ID 5, that will
mess this reference up.
We'll now actually know
what to point to anymore.
What I could do perhaps is better is
let's say, OK, Slytherin-- perhaps it's
no longer called Slytherin anymore.
Maybe it's called a
different kind of name.
I could change this,
well, this house now.
Let me fix that typo here.
Fix this house, and I could
call it something else.
And now, if I reference
that same ID, I'll
get a different name
for the student house,
but I should never change
the primary key in general.
And I see a question
to our primary keys.
So is it good practice to have an
auto increment for the primary key?
Meaning that if I add a
new row, like let's say
if I add a new student over here,
that the ID automatically increases.
It's a great idea.
We always want to make
sure that our ID is unique.
And so as we add new rows, we'll make
sure they're always increasing our ID,
and SQL will handle that for you.
If I go back to my
create table statement
and if I have this primary key
ID constraint down the bottom,
that will mean that this ID column
will always auto increment for me,
and often it actually
won't ever be null.
So primary key handles some
of these constraints for me
by saying that, look, this
column should never be null.
It should also never be a random
value, which always auto increment as I
add new rows.
Great questions here.
Other ones too?
A good question here.
So when we chose to
introduce, to distribute
the database into three tables,
why is this the best distribution?
So if you go back to our visual
again here, why is this the best?
I actually won't say this is
the very best we could do.
There's probably some more
updates we could make here,
but this is simply better.
Because in this case, we're
reducing some of our redundancies,
and I could more easily change
my data set if I'd like to.
So notice how, here,
going back to our example
of changing some names of houses, well,
if I change the name of Ravenclaw,
in my prior data set
like this one, I would
have to go through and update all
of these names, like individually,
to find Ravenclaw, Ravenclaw,
Ravenclaw, update that every time.
But if I have this kind
of arrangement, well, I
can just change Ravenclaw in one table.
And now, that name has changed on
my entire database as I go through.
So it's helpful to not repeat
ourselves while we're having
these databases design questions here.
So let's try actually
creating this table now,
and our goal was to create
a table called houses that
had some of these constraints here.
So let's go ahead and go back to our
SQLite database, and let's try it.
Let's go ahead and CREATE
TABLE, this one called houses.
And now, I'll add my
parentheses to say what
columns should be inside of houses.
I'll hit Enter here.
And now, I'll kind of, by
convention, indent four spaces.
I'll hit 1, 2, 3, 4.
And the first column I want to
have, that one is called ID.
That one will be an INTEGER.
And ideally, I want it
to be NOT NULL, never
should be able to have a
blank ID in this table.
Next one, I want to have
a name of the house.
This one, some text.
And I also want to
make sure that I can't
have this ever be null, never blank.
And similarly, I want to
have a head, head name.
This one called, this up type
TEXT, and also never NULL.
And there's one more thing I need
to add here, and what is that?
A primary key.
So I can say PRIMARY KEY id, and
then close this out down below
in my parentheses, and hit
a semicolon, and hit Enter.
And now, if I type dot
schema again, well, I
should see I have a table for
students now and a table for houses.
And what we could do
if we have more time
is spend some time actually
updating this database,
like take data from our students
table, insert into houses,
make sure the students table removes
the house and head columns as well.
We won't spend too much
time on that here today,
but the goal is simply to show
you how we can add more tables
and insert some data.
But on with inserting some data, how
could we actually add heads here?
Because if I do SELECT star FROM
houses, well, there's nothing in there,
nothing shows up.
So how should I add some data here?
I'm seeing insert, so let's actually
see what that could look like.
I could go here, and I could say
our picture right now is like this.
We have a blank houses table
that has the right column names,
but no data, so let's
actually insert some data.
So in general, inserting
looks like a bit like this.
Insert into the table name, followed by
some columns I want to add data into,
and then some values want
to add to those columns.
And to add in let's say
Gryffindor, I could do this.
INSERT INTO the houses table on the
house and head columns Gryffindor
for the house and McGonagall
for the head, so let's try that.
I could say, down below,
INSERT INTO houses.
And which columns we want to
insert into now for houses?
Head and house.
Let's do it in the right order.
Let's first do house and then
head, let's then do the values.
Let's say, OK, what should
go into the house column?
Gryffindor.
And what should go into the head column?
McGonagall.
And then we'll hit
semicolon, Enter here.
And now, let's select.
Let's SELECT star FROM
houses, and now, we
see Gryffindor as the house and the
head is McGonagall, with the ID of 1.
That primary key has
auto incremented for us.
Let's maybe add now, whoops--
let's maybe add now Slytherin.
We could say INSERT INTO houses with
the VALUES Slytherin and Severus Snape.
And now, if we SELECT
star FROM houses, we
should see our ID has auto
incremented, and we now
have Slytherin with
Severus Snape as the head.
So questions on these inserts
or these creating tables?
Question, what if one insert
more than one row at once?
I believe that that is a good use
case for something like Python.
So we saw in lecture, not so much today,
but in lecture, how we can use Python
to kind of automate SQL queries.
You could imagine, for
example, having a Python loop,
like a for loop, that
kind of runs INSERT query
command over and over again to add
multiple rows over and over again
there.
So more on that next week,
when we work on like--
actually in later weeks
like with Flask and so on.
But for now, I would refer
back to lecture and look at how
we can use Python along with SQL.
So to close us out here,
what we'll do is just
figure out how we can actually
modify our queries to fit
this kind of more complex database.
Now that we have data in all
kinds of different tables, well,
how do we query it?
How do we get actually the
information we want to get out of it?
Something like this in the very end.
How do we get the data
we want out of this?
And there are a number
of ways we could do this.
And let's take a look at actually
an already complete database.
So I'll go ahead and
I will get a database
that I've already created here for you.
I'll do roster.db, copy it here.
And now, if I do SQLite3
roster.db, type dot schema,
you should see that now we have
this brand new schema for our table.
So we have a student's table
with a student name and an ID,
a houses table with the house
name and a head name and an ID.
And then finally, it's
assignments table, where
we say that a foreign
key, called student_id,
references the ID column in
the student's table like this,
and then the house_id column here
references the ID column in houses
just like this.
And if I SELECT star FROM houses,
notice how we have all of our houses
and heads.
If I SELECT star FROM students, notice
I have all of my students and their ID.
If I then SELECT star FROM
the assignments table,
well, I then just see all of the student
IDs and the house ID they belong to.
So a bit more complex
now, but the goal was
to reduce our repetition, to make sure
we have every entity in a single table.
But how do we then get the
data that we want out of this?
Well, there are a few
ways we could do it.
One way is to use these
selects and these joins.
Maybe we would actually try to
figure out the number of students
in Gryffindor, like how many
students are in Gryffindor?
We tried it out before, but now we
have this new schema, this new table
organization.
So how should we change our approach?
Well, we could use these
selects and we can actually
make sure our select are kind
of nested inside of each other,
like have one select work first and
then feed the result to another select
later on.
So let's try this.
Let's say I want to figure out how
many students are in Gryffindor.
Well, I should probably first
notice that the ID column in houses
corresponds with the house_id
column in assignments.
So maybe, what I should
first do is figure out, well,
what is the ID of Gryffindor?
And to do that--
any ideas for a query to find
out the ID for Gryffindor?
What query could I use, assuming
I couldn't see it before?
Assuming I don't know what that ID is,
how could I find the ID for Gryffindor?
Here's our schema again.
So maybe one thing I could do is I'd--
I don't the ID of Gryffindor off the
bat, but I could try to select it.
I could say SELECT maybe
the ID from the houses table
WHERE the house name is Gryffindor.
I'll hit Enter and I get
back 3 and does that match?
Let's see.
SELECT star FROM, in this case, houses.
And I see Gryffindor in this case is 3,
although admittedly, over here is one.
That's a little confusing.
But in our actual table,
it is 3 over here.
And now that I have the idea of
Gryffindor, well, how could I find
all the students who are in Gryffindor?
I could try to do this.
I can maybe say select the
count of the student IDs.
That's the count of student_ids
from the assignments table WHERE
the house_id, in this case, was 3.
Gryffindor in this table here is 3.
I'll hit Enter, and I get 11
students, which seems right.
So this query could still
be better designed though,
because here, we're talking
about this number three,
but what could we do instead?
How could we maybe not hard
code this number three,
if you recall from lecture?
Any ideas in the chat?
We could use a JOIN.
We'll see those later on,
but what else could we do?
I'm seeing some ideas of kind
of nesting these queries.
So as an example here, let's
say we first run this query.
SELECT if FROM houses WHERE
the house is Gryffindor.
Give us the ID of Gryffindor.
Then let's feed the results of
that query into a larger query.
This one, the above.
So here, notice how we have
some parentheses saying
that this query first will
be run at the very beginning.
The result of this
will then be passed up
to our larger query, our query
that's kind of nesting this one.
So I'll run this first query.
I'll go back one, at
least in this table,
and then I'll say that in this case,
the house_id for Gryffindor is 1.
And now, there's a
query itself completes.
I could say, it's like COUNT the
student_id FROM assignments WHERE
house_id is one in this case.
So let's try it out.
I could say SELECT.
I know they're beginning the count of
student_ids FROM the assignments table.
But now, I need to figure out
what's the ID of Gryffindor?
Well, I know I want a house ID
and I want it to equal something,
but what is that something?
What I could do in this case is I could
say, well, I don't really quite know.
I could instead--
I could say, well, go
ahead and first find me,
that ID for Gryffindor,
SELECT id, in this case,
FROM the houses table WHERE the
name or the house is Gryffindor.
And then I will go ahead and hit Enter
here, close the query with a semicolon
here, hit Enter, and I
still get that same result.
This is better now, because if
the idea of Gryffindor changes,
notice how in this table it's
three, but in this table it's 1.
If the idea of Gryffindor
changes, well, now, I
can just figure out what I'm
looking for without actually caring
what the ID of Gryffindor actually is.
So thoughts or questions
on these nest and selects?
What questions do you have?
A question here, can we
nest without any limit?
You theoretically can have as
many nestings as you want to have.
So we could maybe have a
query here, if I look up here.
Like maybe we don't know
something about this query,
we could say, OK, run
another query to give me
that result, to kind of nest them
and nest them over and over again.
You can absolutely do that.
It comes at a cost
though of performance.
You want to make sure that you're kind
of limiting your number of nestings
to make sure you're not just
looking up arbitrary data
that you don't actually
need in this case.
So, no theoretical limit
really, but there is a limit
if you're concerned about
performance, which you should be.
So this was one way of
approaching this problem,
counting students of Gryffindor
with this new table using a nest
and selects.
But another way-- this maybe
a little more intuitive.
In some ways, it's going to be
this JOIN that we saw earlier.
So this will bring us almost
to the very end of our lecture,
to look at JOINs here.
But instead of using SELECT,
we could use this idea
of putting these tables together.
Here in our select, which we're
treating them still as separate tables.
But with JOINs, we could say, let's
actually put our tables together
and think of it as one
bigger table in this case.
So if we look at our visual again,
counting students in Gryffindor,
we're going to see something like this.
So we have three different
tables, but it would be helpful,
like ideally as a human, we could
just simply take these tables
and put them together, like just
kind of LEGOs stick them together
so they fit right next each other.
We can see which houses
align with which IDs.
So let's again notice that in
this case, the ID column in houses
corresponds to the house_id
column in assignments,
and we just want to pair them
up like put them right there
and see that larger, bigger table,
and that's what join does for you.
So a JOIN, once you run
it, look a bit like this.
It'll put your two tables
together and have them online
based on the ID you specify.
So here I'm saying, give
me the assignments table
and JOIN houses onto it.
So notice how on the
left hand side here, I
see assignments, that is
the assignments table,
and I see houses, which
is the houses table.
But they're corresponding,
they're now next each other,
based on the fact that house_id in
the assignment table corresponds
to or references that
ID column in houses.
So SQL knows which rows to put together
with which rows in each table based
on this ID we specify.
And the syntax for this
looks a bit like this.
We could say SELECT everything
FROM the assignments table.
But first, JOIN on the houses table,
and make sure we use this column
as the corresponding column in this
case, like the assignments.house_id,
meaning the house ID column
in assignments, and houses.id,
meaning the ID column in houses, making
sure that these correspond to each
other in this case.
So notice how I go back
to our visual here.
We have the ID column
with houses corresponding
to the house_id column in assignment.
So let's try this in SQL.
Let's go ahead and SELECT star
FROM our assignments table.
But first, let's go ahead
and JOIN on the houses table,
and let's join houses
on a certain column.
Let's say we want the houses.id
column to match up with
the assignments.house_id column.
And here, we do this.
And if I zoom out a bit,
you'll see the very same table.
We have a student_id, the house_id, the
ID of the house in the house's table,
the house name, and the head.
So what can we do now to figure out how
many students are inside of Slytherin
or Gryffindor in this case?
I'm seeing some longer
queries, which is good.
We could simply count up student IDs.
I'm sure we can do this,
but let's try this one.
We could say, I want to SELECT
the COUNT of the student_ids
that I have from the assignments table.
But I first want to JOIN in.
I want to JOIN in the houses table,
making sure that, in this case,
the houses.id column matches
up with the assignments table
with the house_id column.
And now, with that bigger
table, well, I only
want the rows where it seems
to be that the houses' house
column, the house column in
houses is equal to Gryffindor.
Now, hit Enter here.
and now, I get back
11 still, and I could
do the very same thing for Slytherin.
I could just change Gryffindor for
Slytherin or Hufflepuff and so on.
But the idea here is that we're
trying to see our tables not
as individual tables anymore,
but now as one bigger table,
and we can use that to figure
out, well, what kinds of columns
can I query to get the
result that I want now.
So what questions are there on
these JOINs, either on the syntax
or how they look?
A good question-- so here
we say, so it does not
matter when we say JOIN on a
foreign table in a primary table?
Let me try to parse this question.
What we could do--
notice how in this above query, I said
houses.id equals assignments.house_id.
And the reason for this was that if
I have two ID columns in two tables,
well, those columns are
unambiguous in their own tables.
But when I JOIN them, those
columns of the same name
are now ambiguous, meaning
that they have the same name
and there are two columns, so we
have to differentiate them somehow.
So if we say houses.id and
assignments.house_id, well,
if I had two columns with the same
name, maybe it's just ID in assignments,
I could say, houses.id equals
assignments.id and therefore get
the appropriate column
name as we go through.
A question, how not
to show identical IDs,
like the house_id in the house
table and assignment table.
So if I do this, go back to SELECT star,
SELECT everything FROM our assignments
table, joining in the houses table on
houses.id equals assignments.house_id,
notice how we had some repetition here.
We had house_id and we had ID.
In the way that SQLite works, this
is just the way it adjoins tables.
You're always going to get
those duplicate columns here,
but maybe helpful if you
narrow down your SELECT.
You could say maybe
not select everything,
but maybe SELECT the house_id.
You could SELECT student_name and so on.
So you could narrow your
SELECT, not select everything.
But in general, when
you JOIN two tables,
you are going to get those duplicate
columns because SQL needs know
which columns to JOIN by.
Does that makes sense?
And a good question, can you give an
example of a JOIN with a GROUP BY?
So we absolutely could.
So notice how--
I remember how an earlier
in section, we tried
to have this GROUP BY that
figured out how many students are
in every house as a whole, like
Slytherin, Gryffindor all in one table.
We could do the same query now, but
with a JOIN, with our separate tables.
We could say, to be first,
SELECT for me the houses,
the house like the actual
house name, and the COUNT
of the student_ids in that house.
And what I'll do now is I'll say I want
to SELECT that FROM the assignments
table.
But I want to first JOIN in the houses
table so long as the house's ID column
corresponds with the
assignments.house_id column.
And now, what I could do is I
could just simply GROUP BY house,
or to be more specific, I
could GROUP BY houses.house,
the house column in houses.
But I'll just say house for now, for
consistency, and I'll hit Enter now.
And now, I see that very same thing.
Gryffindor has 11 students,
Hufflepuff has 5, Ravenclaw has 13,
and Slytherin has 11.
So good question there.
If we just treat our JOIN table
as a regular big old table,
well, we can do the very
same, arithmetic as before.
A good question here, so can we
use AS when we JOIN the two tables?
Let's try it.
So, let's say SELECT house--
SELECT star, sorry, from,
let's say, assignments.
And then let's go ahead and JOIN on
the houses table with houses.id equals,
in this case, assignments.house_id.
And the question was,
can we use AS here?
Can we say AS?
Let's just call all of this
ID, and let's see what happens.
We'll hit Enter here.
And I don't think we can
do that, because we're
trying to kind of rename these
columns out or joining them.
SQL expect the actual column
names, not the aliases
that we're going to use while we're
joining, so a good question there.
Other questions on these joins?
For a visual for folks, if you are
still wrapping your mind around this,
it's helpful to see in this case that
we're trying to simply figure out
which IDs are sort of matching up with
each other, and this part of our query
is actually doing that matching for us.
Can you join a table more than
once, is a question in the chat.
You absolutely can.
So if I wanted to have more
than one table in my joint,
I can certainly do that.
I could maybe get back my entirety
of that original table we had before.
I could say SELECT star FROM students,
originally, but then I want to join,
let's say, the assignments
table, where the, let's see,
it would be students.id is corresponding
to the assignments.student_id.
Let me zoom out a bit,
so that JOIN is ready.
Now I'll also JOIN to this table.
I'll JOIN on the houses table so long
as the houses.id column corresponds
to the assignments.house_id column.
And now, I should get back my entire
table, joining these two back together.
And now, it's kind of big
and kind of redundant now,
but I do see that very same table we
had before, everything joined together,
originally.
Can you alias table name?
I don't believe--
I'm not quite sure.
If you were going to
try it out yourself,
I don't think you would be
able to do that in this case,
often because they don't show up in the
query itself or the result of the query
itself.
Difference between JOIN and a UNION.
We probably won't dive
into unions so much here.
But a UNION is good for
finding out things that
are in common with different data sets.
Let's say you have
one table and another,
and both tables have some
intersection, like datas [INAUDIBLE]
a UNION would be good for that, whereas
a JOIN is just good at simply combining
your tables together as you go through.
Other questions on
joins before we wrap up?
I'm happy to stay after as well.
So, why don't we wrap officially here?
Well, this was the end of our
section for this week seven.
Thank you all so much for coming.
It was wonderful to see
you over Zoom this week.
I'm happy to stay on and
answer questions in the chat,
but otherwise, we'll
see you in the future.
Thank you all.
Recording stopped.
And thank you for all of
your wonderful questions.
I appreciate them in the chat.
If you'd like to ask any others,
I'm happy to stick around
for a few more minutes.
And thank you for that congratulations.
I appreciate that.
A question on GROUP BY,
let's go back to that.
The question was, how
does GROUP BY work?
What's the point of GROUP BY?
It's maybe helpful if I show you
how it would work in this context.
Let's go ahead and join--
back to we have before, let's select
everything from our students table.
And let's go ahead and also JOIN in
our assignments table ON assignments
dot, in this case, student_id
is equal to students_id.
And let's join the, I can't remember,
the houses table on houses.id equals
assignments.house_id.
So now, we have our big, big table.
But let's say we want to group
that data or do something
with that data within a certain
group, so we could say this.
GROUP BY, often this case
makes sense as GROUP BY house.
And this is saying that if I wanted to
count up anything or average anything
or figure out how many of
something I have, well, normally,
if I didn't say GROUP BY, I would just
get the count of all the students.
But if I instead GROUP
BY house, what I'll get--
and my code space is kind
of glitching right now,
but I will get back that
same count, but only
looking at the smaller subset
of data within each group,
so looking at how every
house individually
and counting up within that
house group, if that makes sense.
And if that doesn't
quite make sense yet,
I encourage you to experiment with it
more to figure out how GROUP BY works,
and there's still some resources on
the web you could learn from as well.
Yep.
And we will certainly
share the recordings
for these in [INAUDIBLE] 2023, so it
will be very early January as well.
So other questions here?
A question, are commands
with capital case?
That's by convention,
so it helps us note
between the capital of SQL
keywords and our column names here,
so by convention.
Are sorting and GROUP BY similar?
Sorting is helpful if you like ORDER
BY, like is that an example of sorting?
I could order my data.
And that is kind of helpful
for seeing groups in my data,
like seeing what groups there are.
But if I want to count
something up within each group,
well, I should still use
GROUP BY in that case.
So GROUP BY is often used with these
aggregators, like count or average.
Here, I don't have that up
here, but I would normally
type like COUNT star, AVERAGE star,
and then a GROUP BY, so good question.
Well, so glad this is
helpful, and thank you all.
It's great to see you over Zoom.
I hope to see you next week.