CARTER ZENKE: OK.
Hello, everyone.
It is so good to see you
here for our Week 5 Section.
If you don't remember,
my name is Carter Zenke.
I'm the course's
preceptor here on campus,
and it's so delightful
to see you all over Zoom.
I thought what we'd do
just to kick things off,
assuming you can hear me this
time, is to on the count of three,
we'll all unmute at the same
time and say a big hello.
So on the count of three, we'll
do one, two, three, hello.
AUDIENCE: Hello.
CARTER ZENKE: All right.
CARTER ZENKE: It is so wonderful--
AUDIENCE: Hello.
CARTER ZENKE: Hello.
It is so wonderful to see you all here.
AUDIENCE: Hello.
CARTER ZENKE: And we'll
go ahead and mute.
AUDIENCE: Hello.
CARTER ZENKE: OK.
All right.
So if you'd like to participate,
feel free to do so via the chat.
You're welcome to type in the chat
to ask questions via the chat.
Again, the goal for these
sections is really to make sure
that you're able to ask the
questions you want to ask
and for us to dive into
this learning together.
So today, focused on data structures.
And this week, you build your own data
structure with a speller problem set.
And I want to focus on this big
idea behind data structures.
Why would we use them?
What are the trade-offs
between them, and how
to actually use them in the real world.
So to that end, we'll have three
questions during our section today.
The first will be this idea of the
trade-off between data structures.
When should we use one data
structure versus another?
The second question will be
about these linked lists.
We saw these in lecture, but how
can we build our own linked lists?
What can we do with them?
And how can we better figure out how
to actually use them in our code?
And then, finally, our
third question will
be this idea of how do we build our
own hash table where hash tables rely
on a lot of fundamentals that
linked lists can give us here,
but can run maybe a little
bit faster, as we'll
see in the problem set for this week.
So to really dive into things here and
to make things a little more concrete,
we saw all kinds of data structures.
But often, when you're actually
programming in the real world,
you might choose one or another,
depending on the scenario, what
you're trying to build something.
And in this case, what I'd like
to do is show you all one scenario
we can think about here.
So imagine that you are working
for some software company
and they are making this digital
assistant that runs on a mobile device.
Maybe it's something like,
hey, Siri, or hey, Google,
or something that
responds to people's voice
over time on their personal device.
You can do something for that person
as they activate this assistant.
Now, you've seen, or you've heard, that
people who are using this assistant
aren't often able to wake
it up at the right moment.
Maybe it sometimes doesn't work
if I were to say maybe, hey, Siri,
or, hey, Google.
It doesn't quite work as I want it to.
And so this is sort of a problem
that we're running into here.
But what we ultimately want
to do is figure out, OK, well,
how could we fix this?
And maybe the first solution
is to try to improve this
by adding more words that could
wake up this voice assistant.
We want to store more data, more
words, that could activate this voice
assistant for ourselves.
And the question that you might run
into as a software engineer is, well,
how could we best store
all of these phrases
we want our voice
assistant to wake up to?
What kind of data
structure would you use
to actually store these phrases that
might activate our voice assistant?
And we saw a few tools in our toolkit,
a few structures in our toolkit.
And one of these was the linked list,
one of these was the try, one of these
was the tree, and so on.
So there's lots of ways we can do this.
But let's think first about the
different priorities we might
have for this data structure, right?
If we want to actually make this.
Well, what do we want
to prioritize here?
So let's think about this.
If we to add lots of
words, we could really
think of trying a few
different approaches here.
We could think of, well, a
few different aspects, like,
if our data structure is going
to do a certain number of things,
we might care about different aspects
of how data structures are formed.
Like, do we care about
deleting things quickly?
Do we care about
inserting things quickly?
Do we care about searching
for phrases quickly?
Like, for example, if I were
to have this voice assistant
and I'm trying to do something with it,
do I care about deleting words quickly,
or do I care about
inserting new words quickly,
or do I care about maybe if I were
to speak something, if I can search
and find that word really quickly?
So often, when we're
choosing data structure,
we care about these
kind of three things.
How fast does it perform
in these three areas?
And so here, we run into
our first question, right?
If we want to figure out
which way to prioritize,
well, we could maybe say that
we care about search the most.
We want to be able to search and
find a phrase really quickly.
Maybe if the user speaks some word,
we want to be able to figure out,
is that word in the wake word list.
Or maybe we really care
about the user being
able to quickly add a new wake word,
like, I could say not just, hey,
but hello, or hi.
And I want to be able to program this
data structure to sort of respond
to that quickly.
Now, what priorities might you have
if you were faced with a scenario?
If you want to chime
in in the chat, which
would you prioritize here between
a fast insertion, a fast search,
a fast deletion, if
you're trying to do this?
Feel free to chime in in the chat.
OK.
I'm seeing one person for search, OK,
lots of searching, some insertion, too.
Yeah.
And so these are things we could
probably reasonably disagree on, right?
If I want to prioritize
searching for some word,
being able to speak it and have my
assistant recognize it really quickly,
well, that seems reasonable where
we can make search our top priority.
Or maybe it's also
reasonable to say, well,
I want people to make their
own custom wake words.
And so inserting something is
really important to me, too.
So it depends on what
you're trying to build here.
And so let's take a look at some
of these tools in our tool kit.
So the first one we said before
was this idea of the linked list.
And here's the linked list in full here.
And the idea behind the
linked list was that we're
able to have these nodes where
each node has a certain phrase
inside of it-- at least in this
case, trying to store phrases now
in our linked list.
And we have these nodes kind
of follow each other in memory.
They're no longer back-to-back,
like, in an array,
but they sort of build
on top of each other
and sort of follow each other
throughout memory, being woven
in to our bits and bytes, thereof.
So if we were to use a linked list
here, which of these three priorities
would be kind of
well-served by this linked
list, like, what would a link list be
good at in this case, do you think?
Feel free to chime in the chat.
OK.
So I'm seeing some insertion.
And, yeah, it's correct.
So linked would be really
fast to insert something into.
In fact, we saw in lecture that all
it takes to insert into a linked list
is to simply make a new node
and put it at the very front.
And that's, basically, a
constant time operation.
It takes a fixed number of steps.
So inserting into
linked list is very fast
and could be a good priority
for our insertion here.
But, again, what's the trade-off here?
If we were to go with
a linked list, what
would be slower because we
used the linked list now?
Maybe insertion is fast,
but what's not fast?
Well, deletion is not very fast, right?
But at least in this scenario,
let's say we don't really
want to care about deleting wake words,
what's the other ones we can use,
a little bit slow for us?
Yeah.
So I'm seeing search, right?
Search would be pretty
slow because, again, we
have to sort of start
at the very first node.
Like, hey, and ask, OK, is
this what the user said?
No, it's not, let's
go onto the next one.
Oh, is this what the user said?
Oh, it's not, let's
go onto the next one.
So we can only do linear search,
basically, with a linked list.
And this is a bit of
simplification for how we actually
do kind of voice recognition.
But you get the idea,
nonetheless, that we're
trying to find and go through phrases
that the user could have said.
In a linked list, we have to go
through every single node that we have,
which, as I see in the
chat is indeed going
to be in big O of n
going through n nodes
to find a certain element inside of it.
OK so we have linked lists here.
But let's actually think
of a new data structure.
What if we use something
like the hash table?
And the hash table
looks a bit like this.
I'm going to go to the
full screen mode here where
it's a bit like a linked list.
But what we've done
is sort of categorize
our linked list based on
the very first character.
And not all hash tables use
the very first character,
but this one, for example, does,
and it is helpful in some ways.
Like what would now be faster
because we're using the hash table?
What would be faster now?
Feel free to write in the chat.
OK.
So I'm seeing some search,
like, search is faster.
And why is search faster, if you
want to write in the chat quickly?
Why would search be faster
with this hash table now?
So I'm seeing some of these
ideas of indexing, right?
And so-- right.
If we look at the side of our hash table
in this array on this left-hand side
here, we've kind of split our linked
list into several indexes, like, H, I,
J, K and L.
And in the computer's memory, these
are represented with, actually, like,
H, I, J, K and L. They're
assigned some number.
And we have a hash function
that finds the number for each
of these values on the left-hand side.
But the idea here is that we're
able to use indexing to figure out,
OK, if I want to find the
words beginning with H,
I know right where to go, and
I can only search those words.
Or if I want to find the words beginning
with L, I can search in that location,
just find the words beginning
with L. So indexing here
is helping us breaking
down our linked list
into lots of smaller linked lists, too.
So it seems if we were to
insert into this hash table,
it's also pretty quick, right?
It's both faster searching
and faster insertion.
So why would we just not always use
a hash table over a linked list?
Like what's the problem
with the hash table now?
What's the trade-off here?
Yeah.
So I'm seeing this idea of memory.
Like this hash table is going to take
up much more memory than our linked list
assuming, maybe, we have some buckets,
some indexes that aren't really filled
with these phrases.
But it's also going
to take us more memory
to have all the different
indexes possible here
that we might want to actually have
in order to make our lookup really,
really fast.
So it's a trade-off
here is memory, as well.
And now, it's got one other
structure to consider,
which would be this idea of the trie.
And here's some brief visual of a trie.
Would you like to point out some
words you see inside of this trie,
reading from left to right?
What words do you see?
You see hello, you see hey.
Any other ones?
We see help, certainly.
Yeah, there's a few
other ones in here, too.
So this trie worked by trying of storing
a node for every letter in our words.
And this is very fast for lookup, right?
If you want to figure out
if hello is in this trie,
well, all we have to do is see, OK,
I see H, I see E, I see L, I see L,
and I see O.
Well, hello is in this structure, right?
We know that it's in Here.
So look up is very fast.
And similarly, insertion
is also really quickly.
If I wanted to add Hi to this trie,
well, I could simply go to the H node
and say, OK, well, that
covers the first letter.
Now, I'll add I, maybe somewhere
up above, and that's it.
I've inserted Hi.
So insertion and search are
also really fast in our trie.
But again, what's the trade-off here?
Why wouldn't we always use the trie?
Yeah.
So I'm seeing this idea of memory again.
Like, this is going to
take up a lot more memory
to store all the combinations
of all the letters
that could make up all the words
we might want to have as our wake
word for our assistant, right?
And even beyond that, beyond
the computer's memory,
if you think about
the time it would take
to make a trie, a more
complex data structure,
well, that's real human time
that you have to work on this,
and might actually delay your
shipment of some new feature, right?
And
So it's going to matter, not just how
much time it takes for the computer,
but also how much time it takes
you to make the structure,
if you wanted to actually make
some feature for your own program,
or your own company in the end.
So questions on these structures so far?
Happy to take some in the
chat, if you have any.
What questions do you have?
A question about, does
AI use data structures?
Yes.
So a lot of how AI
can work so quickly is
because we choose to organize data
in these really efficient ways.
And so by getting creative with
the ways we actually make our data
structures beyond even just
linked lists and tries and trees,
we can actually make
AI a lot more quickly--
run a lot more quickly
because it has access
to this data structure
laid out in such a way
that it can run quickly in the end.
So, yes, it makes use of a lot of
different data structures, too.
And this question about memory
being so cheap these days.
It is true.
So memory is very cheap, right?
If we wanted to make
the trie here, maybe we
don't care how much memory it takes
up because memory is so cheap.
But it also takes us time
to allocate that memory,
to put things in that memory.
And so, perhaps, it's
not always the case
that because we have so much memory, we
should just be kind of loose with it.
We really need to take
care that we're not
using too much memory when we
could, theoretically, maybe
use less, if we wanted to.
Nice.
OK.
So this is some of the ideas
of trade-offs here, choosing
one or the other, often going
to cost us one thing or another.
But, really, behind
all of these structures
is the idea of a node, where, if we
look back at our structures here,
we had maybe a trie, we had
a link, we had a hash table,
and we had a linked list.
And it was composing all of these
was this idea of some kind of node,
some place we store data.
And along with that, a pointer
to some other pieces of data.
So we saw last week, in
Week 4, that pointers are
helpful for pointing certain locations.
Well, now, we're seeing the
application of those pointers.
Why would we even want
pointers in the first place?
Because we can build these much
more complex data structures.
So let's think about building these
very first building block for these data
sets, which is called this node.
And in our code that we'll
see in just a minute,
we have this new idea of
creating this node in code.
And we've seen this kind
of syntax before, right?
Here is the code we would use to
make a structure called a node.
And we're seeing that
same syntax for structs,
like, we created a
struct for candidates,
we created a struct for people earlier.
Now, we're using that same
syntax to create a node.
And what do you notice here?
So first, we're going
to look at the top.
And C reads this top to bottom.
So as it reads this code,
it'll do the following.
It'll say, OK, here I'm
seeing we're going to define
a new structure called a node.
That seems OK so far.
And then inside of the
structure called node,
we're going to ensure we have
the following pieces of data.
We're going to make
sure we have a phrase.
If we look at this, we're going
to have space for a phrase that
is going to be a string.
And then we also have some space
for a pointer to a node called next.
And, again, we can store,
like, Hi or bye in here.
But we also have some new space
for next, a pointer to a node.
And that could have a real address
in it, like, 0x123, or 0x456.
But it has to point to
some kind of node, right?
So now inside this node, we
have a phrase and a next portion
currently empty, but we could
put this data inside of it.
And then once we finish reading this,
we're going to say, all of this,
everything we've done so far, the
phrase, the next portions that
are-- all of that to be wrapped
up into this thing called a node.
So we've created kind of here
a template for what a node is.
A node has a phrase in it
and some next pointer in it.
And we're going to call
all of that a node.
Now, you could change this.
You can make sure it
has an integer, you can
make sure it has some
character inside of it.
You could even store more attributes,
if you'd like, inside a single node.
But for now, I'll focus on phrases,
trying to store these activation
words for our voice assistant for now.
Now, questions on this structure so far?
Yes, I'm seeing a question, is the next
location inside the computer's memory?
Is it actually in the byte below?
Like here in our picture
here, we see that the phrase
portion is kind of first, and
then comes the next portion.
Are these two really next
to each other in memory?
And the answer for that
is, generally, like, yeah.
So these are going to be very
close to-- they're in memory.
They're going to be kind
of right next to each other
as we create this node throughout.
And a question about, well,
could we have a before field,
like, a pointer to a before?
And we absolutely could.
So if we wanted to modify
this, we could simply
add a new attribute called
before, and we could theoretically
point to linked lists that are--
to nodes that are behind us,
as well, in our current node.
And that allows us to make more
even more complex data structures
overall, too.
Now, a question here, we see a
struct node if we go back here.
So struct node, star, next.
Is that a pointer to the struct,
or just a simple pointer?
And the answer here is
a pointer to the struct.
So here, we're seeing that
this is a node pointer.
And a node, technically, is a structure.
So we're going to have a
pointer to that node that
is itself a structure combined
with a phrase and another pointer
to another node.
So good questions there.
All right.
Any other questions on
this structure here?
OK.
So that all seems pretty good so
far, and kind of a simple template
for a node.
But keep in mind that just
this code doesn't actually
create the node for us.
It gives us a template for the
node, but we haven't actually
created it in code yet.
So let's actually go ahead
and see how we might do that.
If you were to go ahead and create
our own linked list, let's say.
Like, let's say, out of all these three
structures, we chose a linked list now.
We could start by making
a single node and have
that be at the head of our linked list.
So to create a linked
list, we'll often do this.
We'll often create a
new pointer to a node
and first set it equal to null
because it's pointing to nothing.
There are no nodes in our linked list.
But once we've done that, well, we
probably want to add at least one
node, right?
So let's go ahead and do that.
Let's make a new pointer,
this one called n,
and make sure we have some
space in which to store it.
So let's read this from right to left.
Let's call malloc first.
And malloc will give us some space
in memory to actually put this node.
So you can see at the
visual right below we
have some new space
our program could use
to actually store this node inside of
and add a phrase, or some next pointer,
right?
But now if we go all
the way to the left,
we're going to see this pointer called
n will then point to that space.
And notice how n is a type node star.
It's pointing to some
space for a node, right?
OK.
So that makes our first node.
But what we probably want to do
is actually add some data to it.
Currently, it's empty, right?
So what can we do?
Well, we can actually use this
new syntax, this arrow syntax,
to actually add in some data.
So down below, we could say, n
arrow phrase gets the value high.
And what does that mean?
So if you look at our
visual here, we could see--
OK, we see n, and we see an arrow.
And now, we're going to go to the phrase
portion of this new piece of memory
we've allocated and make sure
we put the phrase Hi in there.
So n arrow phrase is saying,
start with that pointer
and follow it to the
structure that you have,
go to that phrase attribute,
that phrase portion,
and make sure that says
Hi in the middle, right?
And that's all fine and
good, but now, we also
have to include the next portion.
Like, currently it's empty,
but we want to have some value.
And if this is our first
node, what's the logical value
for this next attribute for our node?
This is our very first node.
What could we set it to?
All right.
So I'm seeing null in the chat.
And the correct version is the
N-U-L-L, not N-U-L. N-U-L is nul,
and the concept of character
is like a nul character.
But N-U-L-L is null in
the context of an address.
So this is an empty
address, zero address here.
So if we say n arrow next gets the value
null, we'd see something like this.
Here, we have our new node n, it's
phrase is Hi, its next pointer is null.
It's the very first node in our list.
So any questions on this so far,
actually, making up our first node?
To your question on the arrow
syntax, so again, the arrow syntax
is kind of best visualized by
actually reading from left to right.
So if we look at the very
first thing, we see n.
OK. n is a pointer.
Now, the arrow says, let's follow
that pointer to our structure, right,
because n is pointing to a structure.
And let's go to the next
field, that next attribute,
and set it equal to some value
we put on the right-hand side.
So here we said, start with n, follow
n's pointer to our node structure,
and go to that next attribute
and set that equal to null,
as we see down below here.
OK.
So there's one more
step, though, which is
our list is still looking pretty empty.
We have our node, but our
list is still empty over here.
So what could we do to actually
add this node to our linked list?
What kind of code do we need here, or
where do we want list to point now?
Feel free to type in the chat
if you think you might have it.
So I'm seeing two
competing opinions here.
So one opinion is that we
should say list equals n,
which would be list gets the value n.
And I'm seeing n equals list,
or n gets the value list.
Which one do we think might work here?
Let's try one.
So let's say, first, that
list would get the value n.
So list equals n, and let's try that.
So here we have that up
here and let's execute it.
And now we'll see, OK, we'll list
an n point to the same thing.
Because n is a pointer
and list is a pointer.
If we set list equal to n, though,
both point to the very same thing,
which is our very first node.
What would happen if we did
it the other way around?
If we said n equals list, instead of
list equals n, where would n point to?
Any ideas in the chat?
So I'm seeing null, right?
If list is currently null, it's
pointing to really nothing in general,
well, if we say n
equals list, we're going
to make sure that end points to null
and we'll have lost this node over here
that we just had, right?
So we probably don't want to do that.
So this will be our last
step in adding our node.
And now we have our
very first node inside
of our linked list, which is great.
Questions on this here,
too, before we keep going?
OK.
Not seeing too many here, so
why don't we keep on going.
And if we want to kick off the very
first node, this is how we would do it.
But let's say we wanted to actually
keep adding more and more nodes.
We could start thinking about
inserting nodes to our linked list.
And there are a few ways
we could do even that.
So if we think back to our
picture as it is right now,
let's say we wanted to create
this new space for a node.
We could say, OK, I'm going to
have this new node called n,
and I'm going to use malloc
to give me some space for it.
So same thing we did before.
We're going to say, get some
space, make sure n points to it.
And now, how could we best
actually add this node to our list?
Would we add it at the end maybe, or
the beginning, which do you think?
Could we add n at the beginning or
the end, and which would be faster?
So I'm seeing some competing opinions.
I'm seeing end and I'm seeing beginning.
Now, if you think about
a longer linked list,
let's say we had not one node
but really like 50 nodes.
Would we want to add it at the end?
And if so, how many steps
would it take to add this node
at the end of that linked list?
If we have 50 nodes,
how many steps would it
take to add this node at the end?
It would take 50, right?
And that reason is that you have
to actually find the last node
and then add it there.
So to find that last node, we have
to go through all 50 of our nodes.
So if we want the very quick
insertion we talked about
before, we have to add
a node at the beginning,
right, make sure that
this new node points
to the current first node in our list.
So let's actually do that here.
We have some space for a node,
we have a pointer to that node.
But let's see how we might add it in.
So we probably first give
this node a phrase, like, Hey.
We'll say, OK, n arrow
phrase gets the value Hey.
And now, we want to say, hum, where
should we point n's next pointer to?
If we look at this picture here, where
should we point n's next pointer?
In the chat, if you will.
Yeah, to list.
So we want to make sure
that this new node called
n points to the very first node in our
list, that being called, well, just
list.
So here we'll say, OK, n arrow
next gets the value list.
So now we're saying that n
is a node, it has the phrase,
Hey, and its next arrow
is pointing to this list
node, the very head of our list here.
All right.
But now, you'll notice that our
linked list is not quite in the state
we want it to be in, like, list is
still pointing to our second node.
So what's the next
step here, if you want
to make sure our list now
includes this very first node?
What should we do?
We should point list to n,
as I'm seeing in the chat.
So let's make sure we have
list pointing to n now.
So we'll do this.
We'll say, list equals n, and
we'll run this and we'll see,
OK, list gets the value n, meaning
list now points to this new first node.
And now we have our own linked
list of more than one node, right?
We went from one to two.
And now, I could even do the same
thing, three, or four, or five,
even 500 times, if we wanted to.
So questions on this,
inserting this new node here?
OK.
So not seeing too many here.
Let's actually try to
translate this bit to code.
So this is all fine and
good with our visual,
but let's actually try it out in code.
I'll go over to my Visual
Studio code over here.
And here, I have my terminal,
a file already called list.c.
So I'll code up list.c.
And if we take a look at
this file, what we'll see
is a very basic kind
of linked list file.
Here at the top, I have my headers.
And down below, I have my
structure called a node.
And this is the same as
we saw before, right?
We have a new structure called a
node that's going to hold a phrase,
and it's going to have a
pointer to the next node.
And we're going to call all of this node
throughout our code using this typedef
syntax up here.
Now, down below, we have some
functions to actually implement.
One is called unload,
that we'll see in a bit,
to actually make sure we're
not using too much memory,
we're actually freeing it as we go.
And the other down here in main is
actually add items or add phrases
to our linked list.
And as we do, we have this
function down here called
visualize that I wrote
myself and should actually
help you see what's happening
inside of our link list.
Don't worry about all this
kind of scary syntax down here.
We'll see what happens as we
add nodes to our linked list.
So currently, if we wanted to add
some phrases to our linked list,
well, we could just kind of run
this program and see what happens.
Well, first, I could--
let me bring up my terminal here.
And I could say, I want
to make list like this.
And let's go ahead and
make this full screen.
I'll say ./list to run it.
And now, what phrase should we add?
Maybe we add Hi, exclamation point.
So I'll hit Enter.
And it doesn't show anything, right?
Nothing's here yet.
What if I did Hello!
I could say Hello!
And nothing's there.
OK.
But why is nothing there yet?
In the chat, why is nothing here?
Yeah, we didn't add anything.
So if you go back to our
program here, we still
have a to do, to add phrases
to a new node in this list.
So here, if we look back,
very familiar syntax,
we're creating our
very first linked list.
And initially, this list is null.
There's nothing in it.
So that's why, when we
ran this program before,
we didn't see anything
inside of our linked list.
But now, what we're going to
do is iterate list size times
to ask the user for some phrase
and add it to our linked list
and visualize that addition.
So how big is list size?
Well, list size is 2.
We'll iterate two times.
And each time, we'll go ahead
and add some new phrase, right?
So let's think first-- how are
we going to make this new node?
We first probably want to
actually create some space for it.
So how could we do that here?
We're trying to add a new node now.
So we're going to need malloc, OK.
So we're going to need
malloc in some form.
And how much space should
we ask for, do we know?
So we want to create
some space for a node.
And maybe a node is--
I don't know-- I could guess
and say it's five bytes.
But is that right?
Or maybe it's 10.
I mean, I don't know.
It could be anything.
We don't really quite
know, and so that's
why we want to use this
function called sizeof.
And we can pass sizeof a
certain type, like, node, right?
I don't know how big a
node is, but sizeof does.
It'll tell malloc how much memory to
create to have this node in place.
But now that I've asked for
memory, I should probably
keep track where that memory is.
So I need some variable
to store that location
memory, which might be called what?
What could we store here?
Maybe we could have a node pointer.
Let's call it n.
So we could say, OK, this is
going to point to some variable--
point to some new piece
of memory called n.
And we're going to make sure
it points to a node, right?
This is going to be some new
chunk of memory where n points to.
All right.
So we do that kind of first bit, and
now we have some space for our node.
But what do we need now?
We need to make sure
that we add in a phrase.
So how can we do that?
We would probably use our arrow
syntax like we saw before.
So we could say, n arrow phrase.
And let's store the phrase
that we have right now inside.
And similarly for the next
portion, we could do this.
We could say n arrow
next gets the value.
But what should it get, if
this is our maybe first node?
I'm seeing a few different ideas here.
So I'm seeing one for null.
Let's try that.
So we'll say, OK, n arrow next is null.
It's our first node.
And now what we want to
do is make sure that list
points to that very first
node we just made up above.
So let's try it.
Let's go ahead and compile this.
We'll open up our terminal again.
We'll say, make list and--
oops-- we forgot our
semicolon, so we'll do that.
And we'll go back here
and we'll say, make list.
And then we'll do ./list.
And I'll say, OK, my first phrase is Hi!
And that seems all right, like, I
have this new node at this location.
It's phrase is Hi!
And its next pointer is null.
That seems OK.
What if I did this?
What if I said Hello!
now.
And I'm seeming to actually
be missing my very first node.
It kind of went away.
What happened here?
Any ideas in the chat?
Yeah.
So I'm seeing we didn't
quite add this node.
Because if we take a
look at our code, we're
always setting the next pointer
for our new node to be null,
and that means nothing.
So whenever we add a new
node, well, we're just
going to make sure that
the next pointer is null,
like, it doesn't point to anything?
That isn't quite right.
So let's make sure we actually update
this to point to the head of our list.
Our first node should point to whatever
is the first element in our list.
So let's say this, n arrow
next gets the value list.
And how will this work at the beginning?
So notice how list is
null at the beginning.
Then we'll go through
and add our first node.
We'll say, OK, let's
get a phrase, and let's
make sure we have some space
for this new node called n.
Let's make sure this n has the
phrase that we've been typing in.
And now, n arrow next is equal to
list which, in fact, is null, right?
So our very first node
will still have null
as its sort of beginning next pointer.
And then we'll go ahead
and make sure list
is updated to have the very
first node at the head.
But then if we do it again,
if we go through again,
we'll say that, OK, this list
pointer's next is actually pointing
to the previous node we just created.
So now I can actually have the
string together as we go through.
And let's visualize this now.
So let's go back to our terminal.
Let's say, make list,
and let's do ./list.
And we could say Hi!
And then we could say Hello!
And now we see our list being built.
So notice how our very first node here
is at this location.
It has the phrase Hello!
And the next pointer is this, it's
pointing to some new location here.
But notice how this is now
in our next node, 56f0.
And the phrase here is Hi!
And the next pointer is null here.
OK.
So that seemed to work for us.
Let's go back to our code.
What questions are there on this?
A good question.
So is this some kind of recursion?
This isn't quite recursion
because, again, recursion
involves having a function call itself.
And here, we're really inside of a loop.
So it isn't quite recursion.
But you're onto an idea, which
is that every node that we add
is going through that same process.
So this really could potentially
be a recursive function,
if you wanted it to be.
But here, you're just noticing that
the same thing we're doing for one
node, we're doing for another,
as we add it, as we go through.
And that's a good question, too.
Is the last node we
add becoming the first?
That is also true.
So here if we were to say, Hi!
And then Hello!
Well, Hello! becomes our
new first node, right?
That's because we're trying to
insert new nodes at the front
where the first node we
add becomes the first--
sorry-- the last node we add becomes
the first node in our list, ultimately.
OK.
So there is one final
thing to do here, which
is to make sure that if
we're asking for memory,
we do want to make sure that this
memory is actually given to us.
And before we go ahead and
use this pointer called n,
we do want to make sure that we're
not getting back some null value.
So if n is null, what
we want to do is simply
print something like couldn't
allocate memory for node,
or whatever you want to type
here, some descriptive error.
And then we could return 1 to symbolize
that something went wrong here.
OK.
A question then, is this a stack?
Well, it has the beginnings of
a stack where if you remember,
a stack is this data structure
where the first thing we add
becomes the last thing we get out.
Or otherwise, the last thing we
add is the first thing we get out,
which is the case here.
So we're saying that the last
node, the last phrase we add,
is going to be the first
node we see in our structure.
But it also depends on how
we access this linked list.
If we always access it
from the very first node,
well, that could be kind
of similar to a stack.
But if we always want to access it by
looking at the very last element first,
well, that could be then a queue, right?
So a queue in a stack kind of
depends on how you actually
use them, and not so much what you
build kind of underneath the hood.
All right.
So let's keep going here.
And I would say that this
code is mostly correct.
But if I go down to my
terminal and I now do this,
I do make list again just to compile it.
And then I say, let's
try to memory check this
and see if there are any memory errors.
Well, I could do valgrind./list.
And let me type in, let's say,
once it loads, I can type in Hi!
Right?
And now that seems OK.
I can type in Hello!
And my program ends, but it seems
I've definitely lost some bytes.
I've definitely lost 16 bytes.
And I've indirectly lost 16 bytes.
So what happened here?
What did I fail to do in my code?
Yeah, I didn't free the memory.
So if I look back at my program, if I
do this and I say, OK, well, unload.
I trust that unload
will work for me, right?
But if I actually look down
here, it's still a to do.
I didn't actually free any nodes here.
And if I look above, well,
I used malloc several times.
I used it twice.
And I didn't call free
any of those times.
So every time we call malloc, we
want to make sure we call free,
and that's what unload is
going to do for us down below.
We're making our own function that
takes in some pointer to a list
and should go through and
free every node in that list.
We can give back that
memory to the computer.
So let's visualize, if we're
actually writing it in code.
If we go back to our
slides here, we could
think about actually trying
to free this linked list.
And maybe your initial
thought is, let's do this.
Let's actually just free the list.
Let's say this.
But why would this be bad?
If we say free the
list, what goes wrong?
Here's the original picture.
Here's freeing the list.
What happened here?
Yes, I'm saying we lost the other nodes.
So notice how in this picture, if you
go back, well, the very first node
is still pointing to that next node.
And the only reason we know
where that next node is located
is because it's in the next
portion of our very first node.
But if we free that, if we get rid of
it, well, where is that second node?
We don't know.
So if that's going to
be a problem for us,
what we don't want to actually
just free the head of the list,
we want to make sure we're going
through and freeing nodes step by step
and keeping track of where
the rest of our nodes are.
So instead, one way we could
approach this is as follows.
We don't want to do this, just
free the head of the list.
What we could do, instead, is
say, let's make a new pointer,
let's add that to the equation.
Let's do this.
So let's say that-- let's make a
new pointer, just called maybe ptr,
for example.
And that will point to whatever the
head of our list is, the next node.
So now, a pointer is pointing
to that second node in our list.
And now, we could safely free list.
We could do this.
We could say, OK, free
up list, and that's gone.
But what is still pointing to the
rest of our list now, which variable?
Maybe in the chat?
Yeah.
So ptr is pointing to that
second node in our list.
So we still have this in our memory.
We know where all the
rest of our nodes are.
OK.
So that's all good.
But now, we want to actually
get back to the head of our list
and make sure that we're
actually kind of moving forward.
So what we'll do is say that
list gets the value for ptr.
So we're going to update what our
list looks like and say that we're
going to move this over here.
So now, the head of our list points
to whatever pointer points to.
And we could, perhaps,
do this in a loop.
We could say, OK, in this case, well,
pointer will get list arrow next again.
And what would pointer be now, though?
If pointer is list arrow next,
what is pointer going to be?
It will be the second node of
the node after the first one.
But what's the actual value right now?
Yeah.
It'll be null, or [INAUDIBLE]
because notice how right now list
is pointing to this
very, now, the first node
in our list, whose next value is null.
So if pointer equals list arrow
next, well, pointer will be null.
OK, that seems OK for now.
But if we wanted to kind of keep going,
let's say we free list, all right.
And then we say, well,
list gets pointer.
What is list now?
There's nothing left, so list
would also be null, right?
So what we've done, we've
kind of gone full circle.
We've made-- we've gone from the very
first node to our very last node,
and we've ended when
list equals null, when
there's nothing left to free, back at,
for example, the same place we started.
If we go back to our code, we could
see that the very place we began
was with list equaling
no, no nodes in our list.
And now, if we unload them, we also want
to end in that very same place, right?
OK.
So let's try implementing this in code
now so we can get rid of those memory
errors.
If we go down below here, we're going
to free all of our allocated nodes.
And we know we want some
kind of loop to do this.
But let's hold off on that for now.
We know, first, we want to make
this new pointer to our next nodes.
We can do this.
Node star pointer equals whatever
list is pointing to and getting
that next value there.
Then we could safely free list because
pointers pointing the rest of our list.
And, finally, we could
say, list updates to 0.2,
what pointer is now pointing to.
But how long do we want to do this?
How do we know when to stop?
Maybe in the chat?
This seems good for one node,
but want to keep doing this.
Yeah, we want to keep doing
it until our list is null.
And we don't really know how
many times we want to iterate,
so a while loop seems
like a good choice.
A while loop we can do something
until something else is true.
So we could say, while
list doesn't equal null.
While we still have
nodes, essentially, let's
go ahead and make sure that we
have a pointer to the next node.
Let's free the current
node, and then let's
update the current node to point
to whatever it was previously,
the next one.
So we could do something like this.
And now, if we run our code, if
we go back to our terminal here,
we'll make list.
We'll run valgrind on ./list.
And what do we get if we type in,
let's say, Hi! here, and then Hello?
We see, successfully, all
heap blocks were freed.
No leaks are possible down below here.
So what questions are there on
this, if you look at our code
for unloading here?
Yeah, a good question,
is nil the same as no?
So if we look at our terminal
and we actually run this again,
call it a make list, I'll
run ./list, and I'll say Hi!
And notice how this very first
node has the next pointer of nil.
Nil is simply the terminal
representation of null.
So nil means null in the terminal.
All right.
And now, I'm seeing another question,
is this a recursive function?
So this still is probably
not a recursive function,
because a recursive function would kind
of call itself like this function might
then call unload somewhere in here.
So it's not quite recursive,
but you are correct in noticing
that this is a good
application for recursion
because we're doing the very same
thing for every node as we go.
So you could certainly
write this recursively.
Here, we're going to
iteratively using a loop.
OK.
Other questions on this?
So let's keep going on.
And we've seen linked lists now.
We've seen these really
two core operations
for linked lists, like, how
do we add some data to them,
and how do we unload them?
What you might ask, though,
is how can we speed this up?
And that's where hash tables come in.
So hash tables are simply
an array of linked lists.
We take linked lists, we break
them into smaller pieces.
And so let's get a
visual for that and see
if we can make this run even faster.
So if we go back to our slides here
and we see this idea of a linked list,
we have maybe, Hey!
Hello!
Lo there!
Different kind of activation
words for our voice assistant.
Well, what we could do is try
to make sure we can access
certain parts of this linked
list faster to make sure
we can actually search
this linked list faster.
And we could for that use a hash table.
So recall from earlier that a
hash table looks a bit like this.
We have some array on
the left-hand side.
And we have different, what
we call, buckets in here,
where a bucket might, in this
case, be a letter of the alphabet.
And that letter of the alphabet is
maybe the first character in a word.
You could have other buckets, other ways
of assigning these phrases to buckets.
But for now, let's focus
on this alphabetical hash
function here and
alphabetical hash table.
So with this, we have different
letters for every hash bucket.
And how does C know where in
the array H, I, J, K and L are?
If we wanted to add some nodes
to a certain bucket, well,
how do we figure out
where that bucket is?
Anyone in the chat want
to chime in on that?
Yes.
So it seems to be that they're ordered.
They're certainly in the
right alphabetical order.
That's helpful.
Other things, too, for how we know
where H is located, or L is located?
Yes, we could use maybe
ASCII numbers and so on.
And we're on the right track here.
But because if you look at the
left-hand side, this is just an array,
and we've kind of ourselves as
humans assigned those array buckets,
those array segments, some letter.
But we have to assign them some
number, really, some index.
And so you might recall from very early
on, all arrays have these indices,
right?
So maybe zero to however
big your array is.
And now we have, in this case,
maybe H corresponds to the 7 index
in our table, or I corresponds
to the 8 index, and so on.
And so in those indexes, we can
actually add in our linked list.
And so here, if we notice
that H corresponds to 7,
well, H is the eighth
letter of the alphabet.
But if we were counting from
zero, it would be the seventh.
So in this case, H corresponds to zero
as that seventh letter of the alphabet
counting from zero here.
That's how we know how we actually
add in these linked list nodes.
Now, if I were to give you some new
phrase, not Hey! or Hello! or Lo there!
How would you figure out
where to put it in this case?
Maybe in the chat?
If I gave you some new
phrase, what could you
do to figure out where to put it?
Yeah.
So I'm seeing maybe at the start.
I don't really know until
we see the phrase, right?
And that's where this idea
of a hash function comes in.
So in order to figure
out where Hey! and Hello!
and Lo there! go, we need to have some
kind of function that takes our phrase
and gives us back some number
that tells us where to put it.
So here we have, maybe, the phrase Hey!
And our hash function
should ideally give us
some number that tells us
where to put that given phrase.
So if I gave you not Hey!
or Hi! or Hello there,
maybe I gave you the name Carter.
Well, that should give us some
new number that then corresponds
to an index in our array, or
we could start this new linked
list that might have all
the C words, for example.
So let's actually take a look
at this kind of in code now.
If we go back to our Visual Studio code
over here, I'll open up this new file,
this one called table.
So I'll code table.c.
And it's already a bit done for me.
But notice how we have
a few different things.
We have the same node structure from
before for making our linked lists.
And now, we have this new
array of pointers to node.
And we're calling this a table.
And notice how we have
26 buckets, 26 places
in which to have a linked list now.
And we can figure out
where these new phrases
should go by running this function
called hash that we'll see down below.
So let's scroll down.
We see that, here, we have
this function called hash.
And hash is right now
just returning zero.
Because if I give it a new phrase,
I haven't really finished this yet.
I just want to return zero
for every phrase I get.
And ideally, if I run this
program, I should type in a phrase
and see the index that I should place
this phrase inside of my hash table,
and then print out, OK, this phrase
hash is to whatever number I have.
So let's see an example.
So if I go to my terminal now,
I could make this full screen
and I could simply type, make a table.
And now, I'll run ./table,
and I'll type in Hi!
And I get zero, which is maybe OK.
But let's try now--
let's try Lo there! as we
saw before, and we get zero.
So why would this be bad?
Besides it being unfinished, why
would we not want Hi! and Lo there!
to kind of hash to that same value?
Any ideas in the chat?
Yeah.
So I'm seeing that this is kind
of similar to a linked list,
if we were to do this.
Like, if we have--
back to our visual here.
If we have some array of linked
lists, but every word hashes to zero,
well, we have all this other
space to put our linked lists,
but we're just putting everything
in the zero bucket, which it makes--
turns us back into this picture, which
is just a single linked list, right?
The goal of this hash function is
to have many shorter linked lists,
and that's the goal of
trying to put things
in different buckets,
different indexes here.
So ideally, we don't want to have
everything hash to the same value,
we want to have different hash
values for different phrases
that we might input.
So one way to do this, as
we're seeing right now,
is trying to make sure we have different
linked lists that depend on the very
first letter of the phrase we add.
And let's go back to our hash function
and figure out how we could do that.
So let's exit our program here.
And let's go ahead and go back here.
And let's try to implement hash so that
we get a value 0-25 for a given phrase.
So here, let's try this.
Let's actually try
returning not just zero,
but let's say, depending on the
very first letter of our phrase,
we return that and see how that goes.
So here we have returning
phrase, bracket zero.
And we'll go back to our terminal now.
We'll say make table, and then
./table, and let's try Hello!
And we see 72.
Is that-- I mean, it's better.
Right now, I have actual number.
And if I type in Carter, well, that's
a different number, which is good.
And Lo there! perhaps, is
also a different number.
So we're off to a good start.
But what's wrong with this?
If I get 72, and 67, and
76, I go back to my code
and I look at my table, what's wrong?
Yeah.
So I'm seeing I only have 26 buckets.
So if I wanted to, let's say, get
a phrase and put it in my bucket
somewhere, well, I can't really do
that because maybe Hello! hashes to,
what was it if we look at it?
72.
Well, that's not a
valid index in my table.
So I need to actually make
this shorter a little bit.
And one way to do that is
maybe just subtract A from it.
So I could do something like this.
And what this will do
is, maybe if you recall
how A maps to 65, well, if I get A
as the very first character, well,
what is 65?
A minus A is zero.
If I get B, B is 66 in ASCII.
So B minus A is 1.
And if I get all the way down to Z,
well, Z minus a is going to be 25.
And if I wrap back around to A,
well, that's just zero again.
So what I've done now is I've
made sure that every index I get
is going to be inside the kind
of length of my table here.
I won't get any indexes that
are out of bounds for this list.
And now, if I kind of go back here,
we run this code, I'll do make table.
I'll run ./table, and I'll do Hello!
now, and I get 7, which is better.
Now, I'll do maybe Lo there!
and I get 11.
And now, I'll type in just Z to
see how that works, and I get 25.
So that seems to be
pretty good for myself.
But what still am I missing here?
What could go wrong?
Any ideas?
Yes.
So lowercased letters--
right now, I'm working
with phrases that are all capital.
But let's say someone wants to
add a phrase that is in lowercase.
So I could actually open a
terminal again, make table.
I'll do ./table, and I'll do
maybe hello! in lowercase.
And I get 39, which
isn't quite what I want.
So what could I do instead?
Maybe any ideas in the chat?
What can I do instead?
I could, perhaps, maybe
standardize on capital letters.
So I could say, I want to make whatever
this first letter is uppercase,
and then subtract that capital A. So if
I go back to my terminal, I could say,
make table.
I could say ./table.
And now I want for it to be the case
that lowercase hello and capital
Hello! hash that same value.
So I'll type hello here, and capital H
Hello! here, and I get 7 in both cases.
So that seems to work for me now.
All right.
Any other-- if we go back
to our terminal here,
that will tell us where
to put individual phrases.
So questions on this
hash function so far?
All right.
So not seeing too many questions here.
Why don't we do this?
So let's go ahead and think about
what makes for a good hash function?
So if we think about this as
our very first hash function,
this idea of putting nodes
into individual buckets,
well, it's not going to be
quite what we want it to be.
And if we actually go
through down here and we
think about how could
we try to make sure
we actually better hash function
than this, what we could do
is actually make sure we have a good
distribution of values across it.
So if you think about
our buckets here, we
want to try to have-- to make sure
that every node in our linked list
is kind of going to go
in every bucket here.
Like, we actually have a lot of I words,
a lot of J words, a lot of K words.
And here, the way we hash this
isn't going to quite do that for us.
We're not going to actually have any
words that start with I, or J, or K,
so we probably think of a new
hash function to use in this case.
And if we go back over here, we
can think of some good points
for our hash function.
We can think of, OK, we always try to
get the same value for a given input.
We always want to produce an even
distribution across the buckets,
and we always want to make sure that
we use all the buckets that we're
given in this case.
So these are some ideas
for a good hash function.
Here, what we'll actually
do is let you all
go off and write your own hash functions
to go off and build your own overall.
So if we think of some
other ideas here, you
could use the length of the phrases,
you could make sure you maybe
add up their values, and so on.
But what we could do is
go ahead and have you all
do that for the rest of this week now.
And I think that will probably
conclude us for this section.
It is so good to see you all here today.
Thank you all for joining us.
We will see you next week.