CARTER ZENKE: OK, well,
hello one and all.
It is so good to see you
here over Zoom today.
My name is Carter Zenke.
I am CS50's preceptor here on campus.
I'd love to see you all over Zoom.
I thought we'd do is beginning with
a bit of an unusual thing for Zoom,
which is on, the count of three,
everyone unmute and say hello.
We'll hear a chorus of voices, and we'll
all be here together in this Zoom room.
So again, on the count of three, feel
free to unmute and you all say hello.
1, 2, 3, unmute and say, hello.
AUDIENCE: Hello.
CARTER ZENKE: Hello.
All right, it's so good to hear
your wonderful chorus of voices.
We're here today for a CS50
section, and the goal of sections
will be to review lecture content
interactively, to ask questions,
to dive into exercises.
And so today what we'll
do is do exactly that.
We'll dive into algorithms.
We're doing some things
more interactively
and talking amongst each other
for how we might solve some
of these problems in computer science.
All right, sorry.
Hello, everyone, I was unmuted.
I was muted.
So here what we're going to
do is talk about CS50 section.
So the goal of section is
really to dive into lecture
content interactively, to review
content, to ask questions,
to do so through exercises
and through each other.
And so today we'll be diving into
algorithms and data structures
and a little bit more in
terms of recursion as well.
So let's begin, and let's see
a few questions for today.
So here, our first question is going
to be, how can we compare algorithms?
In lecture, we saw binary search.
We saw linear search.
We also saw things like
selection sort and bubble sort.
So how should we compare
algorithms and figure out
which one's better than
the other for which case.
We're also going to talk about structs.
Why are structs useful?
When would we even use them?
And we'll then talk about recursion.
What is recursion?
How do we build our own
recursive algorithms,
and have an exercise for
ourselves and actually
write our own recursive algorithm here.
So let's dive first into this idea
of how do we compare algorithms.
So we saw in lecture this idea of
trying to search for some value.
So here I have maybe an array of
different colors from this white color
here to this dark green color.
And let's say I want to find
the color white in this array.
Now, knowing we have some
indices here, like 0,
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6, where is
this white color in this array?
If you have to type in the chat, where
is the white color in this array?
What index is it at?
OK, so I'm seeing 2, right?
And it seems pretty obvious here.
We can just see that this
white color is right here
in this third spot but index 2.
And maybe, how would we
know that this is there?
We eyeball it as humans.
But a computer doesn't
necessarily have access
to this entire array of information.
It can only look at one thing at a time.
And so going metaphorically,
we might think of the computer
as shining a spotlight on
some numbers as we go through
and try to find this white color.
So if we're doing linear
search here, trying
to search this array from start
to back, we might start on,
let's say, the left side
of this array, right?
We might go to that very
first location, index 0.
So we'd shine our spotlight
on that color there.
Is this white?
Have we found our color?
I'm seeing some head nods.
Maybe in the chat, I'm seeing no.
This is not the color white, so
what are we going to do next?
Which number should we go to after
0, if we're doing linear search?
I'm seeing some 1's, right?
OK, let's go to 1 and see what's there.
So let's shine our spotlight there.
And that is not white either.
Maybe we're getting closer.
Maybe not.
We don't quite know.
What's the next one to go to though?
Index 2.
So let's go to 2 now.
So let's go from 1 to 2,
adding 1 to our index.
And oh, there is the color white.
So we found it here.
Now, how many steps did it take us
to do this linear search to find
the color white?
I'm seeing three steps.
OK, so keep that number in mind.
It took us three steps to find
white using linear search here.
All right, so that's one
algorithm we could use
to find this color white in this array.
But now let's say this array is sorted.
So we're going from maybe
light to dark green now.
And we want to, again,
find the color white.
But now that the array
is sorted, it enables
this new algorithm called binary search
we saw in lecture and through a phone
book example, right?
So if we're going to
dim the lights again,
we have to shine our
spotlight somewhere.
Now, where should we
first shine our light
if we're looking for this first
element in binary search now?
I'm seeing this idea of the middle, OK.
We're trying to find the
middle of this array.
And if we know that we have--
let's go back a little bit--
index 6, all the way on this
side, maybe our middle index
would be 6 divided by 2.
So 3, right?
That will be the middle index here.
So let's go to 3.
So we'll dim the lights.
We'll then look at 3.
Now, is 3 white?
I'm seeing no, right?
So where should we look now?
If we know that we're sorting
our array from light to dark,
we might want to look left, right?
But at what index should we look now?
We might divide 3 in half again.
So 3 divided by 2 is-- well, it's 1.5.
Maybe we round down
and go to one, right?
So let's go from 3 down to 1.
And we're not quite there.
Where do we go again now if we're
sorting from light to dark green?
I'm seeing some left in the chat.
OK, let's go one on the left.
1 divided by 2 is 0.5, but
we can't go to index 0.5.
Let's round down, and let's go to 0.
So we found white here
now at this 0th index.
And now, again, how many steps did
this binary search take in this case?
Again, took us three steps, right?
So if we're trying to
compare these two algorithms,
we might talk about
their running time, which
is how many steps they take for us to
find the number or color that we're
looking for in this case.
Well, we might compare linear
search in binary search like this.
How many steps did they
take us in this case?
And so again, linear search,
how many steps does that
take us for this particular case here?
I'm seeing some 3s.
So linear search took us three steps.
And binary search, how many
steps did that take us again?
Also took us three.
OK, so which algorithm
is better than the other?
Anyone want to raise their
hand, we can call on you
and maybe tell us which algorithm
you think is better here?
Or maybe type in the chat if you'd like.
Which algorithm would you choose?
So I'm seeing some binary.
And now my question here is, why
would we choose binary, right?
Each one, linear search and
binary search, took three steps.
So is one really better than the other?
Maybe on the chat, what do you think?
So I'm seeing binary
search is more dynamic.
It depends on the arrangement.
So there's this idea that
the input we had right now
was a very particular input.
And for this single input,
linear search and binary search
did take the same number of steps.
But this isn't quite
the question we want
to be asking when we're talking
about running time for algorithms.
Often, what we want
to ask instead is not
how many steps we take
for a single input
but, in general, for any input,
what is the most number of steps
my algorithm will ever take, right?
And another way of asking
this question is, for maybe
the worst case input, if I
were to give my algorithm
a completely unsorted list, what number
of steps would always run faster then?
So let's take a look at this.
If we call this the upper
bound for our algorithm,
meaning that this algorithm will never
run slower than this number of steps,
we might say that linear
search takes how many steps?
Let's assume we have maybe
n elements in our array.
In this case, this most
recent example, we had seven.
How many steps would linear
search take in this case?
So I'm seeing about n steps, right?
Let's say we have seven elements,
it would take us maybe seven steps
in the worst case to find
that number if it's all
the way at the very end of our array.
So linear search might take
7 steps in the worst case.
Or in general, if we
have n elements, it might
take n steps, one step for
every element in that array.
But binary search though
might be a little different
because we're dividing the
problem in 1/2 and 1/2 and 1/2.
And so what are we seeing now?
So I'm seeing maybe it takes n over
two steps, and that's a little close.
Any other ideas for how many steps
binary search might take in this case?
I'm seeing n minus 1.
I'm seeing log n.
And indeed, so binary search
would take about log n steps
if we had n number of
elements to search for here.
And people who said n over 2,
you're not quite wrong, right,
because what we can do is we can
take our array of seven elements.
We can divide it in 1/2.
We've looked at one element.
Let's divide it in 1/2 again
and divide it in 1/2 again.
And this idea of dividing
things in 1/2, in 1/2, in 1/2
is a logarithm that we need twice
as many elements to do one more
step in our algorithm now.
So binary search in this case, in
the very worst case, the upper bound
of the binary search
algorithm is log of n steps.
And now the question becomes,
which one would you rather do?
Would you rather do linear search,
or would you rather do binary search?
And so I'm seeing
binary, right, because we
know that, for these
really worst case inputs,
binary search might, in fact, be better.
And this is OK for now, and we
can talk about things in terms
of the number of steps they take.
But in computer science, to
be a little more precise,
we try to say that something
is in the running time,
on the order of something.
And this is because,
in computer science,
we're often not trying to search
an array of seven elements
or an array of eight elements.
We're often trying to search an
array of maybe a billion elements
or a million elements.
And so who cares if something
takes maybe a billion
plus 1 steps or a billion minus 1 steps.
It's on the order of about
a billion steps, right?
And so we saw in lecture this
idea of these algorithms that can
take a certain amount of running time.
And here, if we look at the
bottom of our graph here,
we have the size of the problem going
up as we go to this side and the time
to solve that problem going
up as we go up as well.
So notice how maybe we have two
different algorithms, this red line
and this yellow line, one taking n
steps, one taking n over 2 steps,
this other one here taking
log 2 of n steps here.
Now, that's all fine and good.
We can be that precise,
but often, when working
with a billion elements, a
million elements, and so on,
we might talk about things being
on the order of some number here,
often n or log n, removing those terms
like divided by 2 or plus 2 or minus 2,
and so on.
So here, we might say that this
is the upper bound, noting that
with the big O notation.
And when we do that, we
get rid of that division.
We say, OK, we don't need
that divided by 2 there.
And then similarly, we might
also do something like this.
We might say, if we zoom out,
these n over 2 and the n,
they look very similar.
So let's maybe call those both O of
n and the second one here that still
looks very different log n over here.
So we might then characterize linear
search and binary search like this
as being in big O of n and
big O of log n, respectively.
So what questions do you
all have on this big O
notation or these running times?
Happy to help answer some of these.
All right, seeing none so far.
Oh, I'm seeing some
question in the chat.
Does binary look at
all the possibilities?
So binary search doesn't necessarily
look at all of the possibilities.
What it does instead is it takes
for granted that a list is sorted.
And because of that we don't need
to look at every possible element.
If we know that we go
to the middle one and we
find maybe a number that's too
high or a color that's too dark,
well, we know we should look
to the left of that number.
If though we're looking
for a number that
is greater than that number
or darker than that color,
we can look to the right and keep
dividing in 1/2 and in 1/2 again.
And so binary search doesn't take
n steps, one for every element.
It only takes log n of steps, dividing
in 1/2 and in 1/2 and in 1/2 again.
I'm also seeing what if
it's an unordered list?
What will be the running
time of binary search?
And by unordered perhaps
we mean unsorted.
So let's say maybe our list is not
maybe sorted from light to dark
or from lowest to highest, and so on.
Well, in that case, binary search
breaks down, doesn't quite work.
So the prerequisite for binary search
is that our list is indeed sorted.
If it's not sorted, what will happen
is it will go to that middle element,
and we won't really know anything about
where the other elements might be.
We won't know if we can
look left or look right.
And so binary search really
breaks down in that case.
And we're forced to use linear search
of looking at every element step by step
by step here.
And a question about what is
the use of big O notation?
Why would we even care about
having this big O notation here?
Well, one reason we
might care about this
is because we care about
this question earlier about,
for any input, what is the most number
of steps my algorithm will ever take?
What is the very worst case
running time of this algorithm?
And so this big O notation
is saying, OK, this
is going to be the number of steps your
algorithm will always run faster than,
so to speak, will never run
more than this number of steps,
in general, on the order of
this many steps, so to speak.
All right, so let's keep going.
And we have this question of
what is the most number of steps
this algorithm will ever take?
But also, we can ask
another question of,
what is the least number of tests
my algorithm could ever take?
So we answered this one
already using big O notation.
But using omega notation, this different
Greek symbol, this other question.
What is the least number of tests
my algorithm will ever take?
Or another way of saying this
is, for the best case input,
how many steps will my algorithm take?
And so for example here, we could go
to linear search and binary search,
and each one maybe takes one
step in the very best case.
And what kind of case
would this be where
linear search takes one step and
binary search takes one step?
What kind of input would we give here?
Anyone in the chat?
Maybe another way of phrasing
this is, at what point
will we get lucky with linear
search or binary search?
Yeah, so maybe-- I'm seeing--
so maybe with linear search,
maybe our element is that very
first one at the zero index, right?
In that case, linear
search took one step.
We can end early.
And similarly, for binary search, maybe
our element is right in the middle.
So we can just go right to the
middle and find the element there.
So this is why, in the best case,
our lower bound for linear search
and binary search will be one step.
These algorithms will, in
effect, will never be, let's see,
never be slower than--
well, let me think about that.
In the very best case, lower bound
will be one step and one step here.
And so what we often use for
this notation is this omega of 1.
So we're saying this is on
the order of about one step
or a finite number of steps for
linear search and binary search here.
All right, so what questions do you
all have on this omega notation?
All right, so seeing no
questions here, let's keep going.
And let's try to find--
let's try to analyze the
runtime of a new algorithm
that we did see in lecture, of course,
one called selection sort, right?
So in selection sort, we want to
basically go through every element
and sort this list.
And here we have an array
that is currently unsorted.
But we do want to sort it in the end.
And selection sort has an
algorithm that works like this.
It will say, let's start by
looking at that very first element,
and let's go through and find the
very smallest element in our list
and put it at the very beginning now.
So currently, if we can only look at
one element, let's say this 5 here,
well, that's currently
the smallest number.
But let's look at 3.
Is 3 smaller than 5?
Give me a yes or a no.
Yeah, so 3 is smaller than 5.
So 3 is our new smallest number.
So let's go again.
2 is certainly smaller
than 3, and so is 1.
And if we were to go
through this entire list,
we would see that 1 is indeed
that smallest number here.
So what do we do with 1 if
we want to sort this list?
We found the smallest one currently.
Where do we put the 1?
Move it to the very first
element, or swap it with 5.
So we'll say, let's put 1
where 5 is and 5 where 1 is.
So now we know that 1
is in the right space.
Now, our list is not quite sorted.
We have 1, 3, 4, 8, 2, 5.
That's not quite what we want yet.
What we'll do instead is
keep going through that list.
We'll say, OK, well, let's find
the smallest number in this list.
3 seems pretty small.
4 is higher, but 2 is smaller.
And 2, right, as people are saying, is
going to be our smallest number here.
So what do we do with the 2 now?
2 will swap with 3.
So we'll put the 2 in the 3's
place and the 3 in the 2's place.
And now we're getting a little
closer to having this list sorted.
So what we'll do is we'll go
ahead and find the next smallest
number in the numbers that remain.
We'll look at 4, 8, 3,
5, 7, and 6, and we'll
find that ultimately 3 is
that new smallest number.
What do we do with 3?
Swap it with 4, as people are saying.
OK, now let's find the 4.
Let's put that, top it with 8.
Now, we'll find the next
smallest, which will be 5.
Then we'll find, in this case, 6.
So 6 will go up here.
And finally, we'll try to
find the smallest again.
That's 7.
Smallest again, and that's 8.
All right, so this is selection sort.
And we might want to analyze
the runtime of selection sort.
How many steps does this take?
If we were to give an upper bound in
omega notation, or not omega, sorry,
in big O notation, what
would selection sort run in?
If we're doing maybe a certain
number of steps for every element,
what might we do here?
OK, so I'm seeing
something like n squared.
And let's get some intuition for this.
So let's say, if we go back
up to these slides here,
notice how, if we go back
to this unsorted list,
we started by looking at
the 5 and trying to find
the very smallest element in this list.
That took us n steps.
We had to go through every
element to find the smallest.
That's n steps here.
So n steps to put the
1 in the right place.
But now we have to go
through another about n steps
to put the 2 in the right place.
And have to go through another n
steps put the 3 in the right place,
and another n steps to put
the 4 in the right place.
And so we're doing n
steps how many times?
How many times are we doing n
steps to find that smallest number?
We're doing it n times or,
in this case, 8, right?
So if there are eight elements,
we're doing it n times.
So here, we're thinking of selection
sort really is big O of n squared.
For every element we're doing another n
steps, n times n, about O of n squared.
OK, now though, we need to figure out
the omega notation, that lower bound.
How could we figure that out?
Or if we gave it maybe an
already sorted list, in the best
case, what might selection sort do?
Yeah, so I'm seeing a few answers.
I'm seeing O of 1.
I'm seeing O of n, O of n squared.
And in this case, if
selection isn't optimized,
selection sort will take
an already sorted list, one
that looks a bit like this, and
still try to do those swaps,
it'll take it a whole n steps
to find that smallest number,
put it in the right place,
go to the next number,
do another n steps to put
it in the right place.
And so selection sort isn't quite
smart, at least as we've seen it so far.
It isn't going to end early.
And so selection sort will
still be in omega of n
squared, meaning that the upper bound
and the lower bound for this algorithm
are really the same.
And that's where we might
use this theta notation
that I saw some people
referencing earlier
to say that these upper
bounds and these lower bounds
are the same in this instance.
So what questions do you all have
on upper bounds and lower bounds
and selection sort in this case?
So I'm seeing a question
about how do we reason
about spending time sorting
a list in order to be
able to use a faster search later on?
It's a good question.
So we saw that with binary search
that's faster than linear search,
but it takes time to
sort something, right?
So how do we reason about that?
Well, we might do is figure out what
are the upper bound and lower bound
for our sorting algorithm?
And are we willing to
spend the amount of time
to then get that much faster
algorithm for searching later on?
And if you are maybe
often searching, maybe it
makes sense to spend that time to sort
first and then have that faster search.
If though you're only
searching occasionally or maybe
you're not even really
searching a data set at all,
maybe it doesn't make sense
to sort it in that case.
So maybe it comes into
play with what do you
want to do with your list in that case.
Yeah, and so I'm seeing what's the main
difference between the big O notation
and omega notation?
So really, the main difference is that
they're asking two different questions.
The big O notation is asking,
in the very worst case,
how about how many steps
will my algorithm take?
The omega notation is asking,
in the very best case, about how
many steps of my algorithm take?
And we often say that the
big O notation symbolizes
the upper bound for the algorithm,
meaning that our algorithm will never
run slower than this.
And similarly, for
the lower bound, we're
saying that our algorithm will
never run faster than this,
will never run faster then, at
least, the omega notation down here.
Answer your question too about
how do we use this in practice?
Would we compare algorithms
or things like that?
And certainly, you would.
So let's say you're working on an
application and you want to figure out,
is it worthwhile for me to use
this algorithm or that algorithm?
And often, what you'll do is,
before you even write some code,
you'll figure out what
algorithm you want to use.
And so these running times can be a
clue to you what kind of algorithm
is best for your particular data set.
And once you know that, you can
then go off and find the time
to write that algorithm.
But often, it's good to
know which one to choose
before you spend all that time writing
the algorithm you want to write here.
All right, so these are
all really good questions.
What we'll do now is spend just a
bit of time on this idea of structs.
So if we look at this idea of structs,
we saw this newly in lecture this week
where a struct is simply some
combination of data types.
And a question we might ask is,
when would we even use structs?
If we already have strings, we already
have INTs, we already have Booleans,
why do we need a struct, this new
structure we could use in our program?
And to that I might ask you, let's say,
how would we represent maybe these two
people in our program?
Let's say we want to
write a program that
represents maybe political
candidates, as you might work on
in the problem set this week.
How could we do this?
Or what information would we
store about these candidates?
So I'm seeing names.
We might want to store names.
I'm seeing your party.
Might want to store their party.
Other things too I want to reference
about these candidates here.
Maybe gender, position,
maybe their height, right?
So there are lots of things we
could store about these candidates
to represent them in our data structure.
And often, I would bet you that
we can't represent a candidate
with just a single data type.
I could represent
their name, but there's
other information I want to couple
with that or put together with that
that I need to use a struct for.
So for example, let's say we wanted
to make this structure for candidates.
We wanted to make this new type, so to
speak, called candidate in our program.
Well, what we could do is
use this kind of syntax.
We could say let's make ourselves,
essentially, a new type, roughly
a type, not necessarily a
type like a string or an int,
but a new combination data type we
could use throughout our program.
And this typedef is helpful because
it's basically helping us define--
that's where the def comes from--
a new type, right?
The next piece we see is this struct,
that struct keyword at the very top
there.
And that's saying we're going to
have some combination of basic types,
like string and int, that
will form our candidate here.
So we'll have the name of that down
below, our candidate right here.
And then on the inside we'll say, what
are the basic types that are inside
of this structure?
In this case, we'll have a candidate
be maybe a string for their name
and an integer for their votes.
And these two pieces of
data will be tied together
in this new structure
called a candidate.
And this is helpful
because we can actually
have maybe a single variable
that keeps track of both
of these information at the same time.
So let's say we want to make a
new variable called president.
Well, president has this
type called candidate
that we just defined earlier, right?
And we know that a candidate has
a name and a number of votes.
So if we wanted to keep these two
pieces of data together, their name
and their votes, we could do this.
We could say, maybe the
president's name is Alyssa.
And the president has maybe 10 votes.
And so here we're using
this new dot syntax,
president.name gets the value Alyssa.
And president.votes gets the value 10.
And so in this single variable called
president that is of type candidate,
we are storing now a name
and a number of votes
close to each other in memory here.
What questions do you all have on this
syntax or what structs are so far?
So your question about the
maximum arguments for a struct,
and maybe to go back here and
show just some vocabulary.
Here we often call this
the attributes of a struct
or the fields of the struct.
And so here, there's really no limit to
the number of fields we could define.
But often want to keep things reasonable
and compact for ourselves design-wise.
It's a good question of design to
figure out how many elements do we need
or how many fields do
we need in our struct.
And so in this case, we might have 2, 3.
And you can get up to maybe, I don't
know, maybe tens of fields or so.
But often, if you're doing that, your
struct might be a little too complex.
I'm seeing some other questions here.
Is the C code we need to use in
our code just key value pairs,
like a dict in Python?
This is maybe similar to
a dictionary, if you're
familiar with that,
in Python in the sense
that, when we say the
president's name is Alyssa
and the president's votes
is 10, we can later on just
get that same value by referencing
president.name and president.vote, so
similar in spirit to a dictionary where
we're trying to have a key, like name,
correspond to a value, like Alyssa.
Question about the dots.
Why do we have these dots, president
dot name, president dot votes?
Simply speaking, long
ago, it was decided
that we would have this
dot syntax to reference
the fields or the attributes of
a struct, so president dot name,
president dot votes.
And as you get used
to it, you'll probably
see it's pretty handy
just to type that little
dot there to get access to that
individual attribute of that struct
there.
A question, can we use
struct without typedef?
Indeed, you could.
So if you go back to
this syntax here, we
saw that typedef was the very
first syntax piece we typed here.
But if you didn't want to
maybe reuse this struct,
you want to just use a struct
once, no need to use typedef.
Typedef lets you specify
a candidate, in this case,
define a name for this new
structure that you're building,
and then reuse that name.
So let's say I wanted to do
this at the top of my program.
I could do that.
Later on, I would then
be able to reuse the name
candidate to refer to this structure.
But maybe I don't want to reuse it.
Maybe I only want to use it once.
In that case, you could just have
the struct there and not the typedef
and you could use it just
once in your program there.
All right, I'm seeing a question,
are structs similar to objects?
There are some distinctions
between structs and objects.
You're familiar with
this idea of an object
and maybe you've done Python
programming or Java programming
and you've seen this idea of an object.
Structs are a bit like objects, but
you cannot tie a function to a struct.
So objects in Python and Java might
have methods or functions tied to them.
Structs, though, do not
have that distinction.
They don't have functions tied to them.
All right, so let's keep going
on with these structs here
and figure out what else
we can do with them.
Let's actually do a little
exercise here, work on this
together, where we'll create
our own get candidate function.
So you maybe are familiar
with this function
get string or get float
in the CSFD library
where you can use those functions
to get a string, get a float,
get an integer, whatever you
want to get from the user.
And similarly, we'll actually
write our own function
called get candidate that will return
to us a new candidate that the user has
created for us by being prompted for
some information about that candidate.
So let's go on over to our code spaces.
And if you're like me, you'll need to
wait a little bit for yours to load.
And once you get there,
let's go ahead and open up
this file called candidate.c.
So once you get there, feel free
to type maybe code candidate.c,
or make a new file and
title that one candidate.c.
And once you do that, what
are you going to include
at the very top of your file?
Can anyone tell me in
the chat what you often
want to include at the
very top of your program
So I'm seeing some--
yeah, some libraries, right,
like standard io, cs50.h.
Certainly, you want to use these
libraries inside of our own program
here.
So all right, now I have
my terminal up and running.
So if you're following along
with me, what you can do
is simply type maybe code--
oops, let me go clear that.
you do get rid of the
activity bar there.
What we'll do is do code candidate.c,
and now we'll get to make a new file,
again, called candidate.c up here.
And that dot c is important.
That means there's a c file here.
So what we'll do, as
people have suggested,
we'll include some libraries up here.
We'll say, include maybe the cs50
library to get access to functions,
like get int and get string, and so on.
Maybe we'll also include standard
io.h to be able to print things
to the screen, use printdef.
All right, now often
what we'll do is we'll
declare our struct at
the very top of our file
below our includes or
our libraries here.
So what syntax would we need here?
We might want to create
a new type, right?
So we'll type typedef, and
we want to make a struct.
So we'll say this is a new struct.
And what are we going to
put inside of this struct?
What attribute did we have earlier?
If you want to type in the chat.
We're trying to make a candidate here.
All right, so name and votes.
So maybe name is a string.
So let's say this
attribute is called name.
It's of type string.
And then we'll also say, let's
give a new attribute called votes,
and that will be of type int.
And now finally, we'll need to close
this out with a name for our struct.
So we'll call it candidate down here.
All right, so now we can
re-use this idea of a candidate
throughout our program
because we've used typedef.
We can say, I want to
create a new candidate using
this new amalgamation of types
that we're going to call candidate
throughout our program here.
All right, and now what is the
main part of our program now?
We have our libraries.
We have our struct.
What kind of function do we need now?
Maybe in the chat, feel free to type.
Yeah, we need our int main void.
So we need the main
function for our program.
So we'll do int main void and
have some space there for us
to write our program.
But here, if we go back
to our slides, our goal
is to make our own function
called get candidate.
So what we want to do is
probably define that down below.
And what you'll notice
about defining new functions
or declaring new functions
is that their signature here,
or we call this line here,
has a few key elements to it.
So it has the type that
this function gives back
to us, that it returns to us.
It has the function's name, and
it has the function's inputs.
So if we're trying to write a
function called get candidate,
what name would we type in?
Maybe an obvious answer
here, if we type in the chat.
What name would we type
in for get candidate?
We probably should type
get candidate, right?
Get candidate is the
name of our function.
And now, what type does it return to us?
I'm seeing a few--
I'm seeing string, and
I'm seeing candidate.
So notice now, we're not
going to return a string.
We're actually going to return
an entire candidate because we've
defined a candidate as this combination
of a string that is called name
and an integer that is called votes.
So here, we're going to give back
to our program a whole candidate,
not just a string, not just an int,
but a whole candidate, those two types
put together.
And because we use typedef,
we can say this down below.
We can say get candidate.
And now, we can go ahead and define
this function called get candidate,
but we need one more step now.
We need to give some inputs
or some arguments here.
And if we're using our modeling
off of get string, for example,
we might want to take a prompt.
We could say, maybe it takes a
prompt that is a string here.
All right, so what questions
are there on this so far?
All right, seeing none so far.
Now, let's go ahead and try to fill in
the rest of our get candidate function.
So ideally, we want to be
able to use it like this.
We could say, within my main function,
I want to create a new candidate.
Maybe I'll call this one president.
But to actually fill in that
variable, to give it a value,
I'll call get candidate, similar to
what I did for get string, for example.
Here, I could say maybe Enter
a candidate is the prompt.
And now I'm seeing a question.
Is candidate a type because we've
declared it above the main function?
Indeed.
So we've used typedef here, which is
that key word that says, all of what
follows should be considered
reusable in our program.
So here we're saying that this struct
that we're going to call candidate
is a bit similar to a type that
we can use throughout our program.
We can say that a function
does indeed return
an entire candidate and
not just those basic data
types, like a string or an int.
All right, and so we're going to be
able to use get candidate like this.
We'll create a variable called
president that is a candidate
and then have get
candidate returned to us
that new candidate that we've created
with get candidate down below.
OK, so we now have this
function get candidate,
but we need first to be able to
print out the prompt to the user
so they know what to type in.
So here I might say, OK, let me print
out the prompt with a new line here.
So I'll say, whatever the user
gives to me as the prompt,
let's say this string here,
I'll then print it back
out to the user when I run Get
candidate, and I'll make a new line.
Now though, I need to do the work
of creating this new candidate
and filling in its attributes
and ultimately returning
that candidate to my main function.
So what we could do is we could say,
I want to create a new candidate.
And it's like a throwaway candidate.
I'm just going to create it
here, add some attributes
and return it back to our main function.
So I'll just call it candidate c.
Maybe we can come up with a
better name, but we'll just
call it candidate c for now.
This is a new candidate variable I've
created in my get candidate function.
And now what I could do is this.
I could say c.name should be what?
What kind of function could I use
to fill in the value for name?
Remember, it's a string.
Ah, I could use get string, right?
I could say get string and,
let's say, Enter a name, right?
So now the candidate's
name will be filled
in by the user when they enter
in some text after get string.
And now here we'll see c.votes.
And how could I fill in the votes?
What kind of function would I
use here, maybe in the chat?
Get int, right?
So I could do get int and
then enter a number of votes.
Awesome.
And now finally, I've created
this new candidate called c.
I've added in the name,
the number of votes.
What's left to do?
I need to give it back
to my main function.
So what would let me do that?
Return, so I'll return c.
And now what will happen here, if we
go back up to the very top, line 13,
this new variable called
president that is a candidate
will first call get candidate.
We'll go ahead and prompt the user.
Then we'll create this new candidate,
fill in the name of the votes,
return that candidate,
and ultimately, store it
in this variable called President.
So what I should be able to do
is maybe type in, for example,
print maybe the name.
So I'll say president.name.
And then what I'll do is I'll
print, let's say, the votes.
I'll say president.votes.
And when I run this, I should be
able to see that result there.
So let's go ahead and
go down to our terminal.
I'll type make candidate.
Oh, and I got an error.
What did we forget to do?
If you take a look at this error here.
Seeing a few answers.
What did we forget to do here?
Implicit declaration of function
get candidate is invalid in C99.
Yeah, so I'm seeing I'm missing
the prototype for this function.
So notice how we got
ahead of ourselves here.
We went and defined our
function down below,
but we actually use it
before it is defined.
So what we should do is
really go to line 10,
after our definition
of this candidate here.
And we should say something like this.
We should say, let's copy and paste
the prototype for this function,
the prototype being what it returns,
its name, and any arguments it has,
and put a semicolon to say that,
look, this function will come up.
I promise to you, I will
define it later as this
a compiler reads our code from
top to bottom in this case.
All right, so let's go back in.
Let's go ahead and clear
our terminal window.
Type make candidate.
Oop, and we still have an error.
Let's see this one.
Hmm.
President.votes, this
error is a little cryptic.
But if the format code
for a string, you'll
know that this is maybe
the wrong format code.
I'm seeing we need %i right there.
Good, so I'll click my terminal again.
I'll type make candidate.
And now, it seems to work.
So what I can do is I
can do dot/candidate.
I now see the prompt Enter a
candidate that I typed up above here.
I can say maybe the candidate's name is
Carter, and maybe the number of votes
is 10.
And I'll hit Enter, and now
I see those same elements
here in my program or my terminal.
OK, so what questions are
there on this program so far?
All right, so seeing none right now.
But what we might want
to do at the very end
is, maybe we don't just
want one candidate.
We want, actually, an array of
candidates or a list of candidates.
And you'll see this in the
problem set for this week of CS50.
What we can do is we can actually
use this same type we've defined
to create an array of that type.
So we could say, I want
an array of candidates
that I'll call the candidates array.
And I want to have
three of them in there.
So notice how, if I
zoom in again, you'll
see we're going to define an
array called candidates array
that is full of these candidate
types that we've declared up above.
And it has space for
three of them, right?
So what we could do in
this case is actually
go ahead and fill in the array.
We could say, let's start at index 0.
Let's go on up to but not
including that third index.
So we'll go 0, 1, and 2, and
increase i by 1 as we go.
And as we do that, we'll say, OK, maybe
the candidates array at location i,
first 0, then 1, then 2 is
going to use Get candidate.
So I'll say get candidate, and
let's say, Enter a candidate.
And now what I can do is, if
I were to run this program,
I would get prompted
again and again and again
to enter a candidate
until my array is full.
Now, if we were to do
that and also to access
some of these candidates
inside that array,
we need some combination of
the syntax we've seen before.
So what we might do is, in
the problems that you'll
see maybe an array of candidates like
this, like name and number of vote.
And to access the candidate as a whole,
like Alice as well as Alice's votes,
you would just type candidates bracket
0 to get that very first element
in this array here.
But if I wanted to get maybe
just the candidate's name,
I could do as follows.
I could say candidates
brackets 0 dot name,
or, similarly, candidates
brackets 0 dot votes.
And that would allow me to get,
not just the whole candidate
at that array location, but the actual
attribute I'm interested in here
as well.
All right, other questions on this.
All right, so seeing
none so far, that will
conclude our little brief
foray into structs her.
And certainly, we can
take a minute to go back
if there are questions towards the end.
But for now, with our last bit
of time, what we want to do
is figure out how we can use recursion.
So recursion is not
necessarily an algorithm.
It's more so an approach to problem
solving in computer science.
There is no single recursive
algorithm, but there
are algorithms that use recursion.
So recursion is simply a
way of solving problems.
And recursion, more specifically,
is about taking a large problem, one
that seems a little daunting, and
breaking it up into smaller pieces
that we know we can solve.
And so one example of this is
often used when teaching recursion
is this idea of a factorial.
So if we look at a factorial, if you're
not familiar, we can say 1 factorial
is 1, right?
We can say 2 factorial is 2 times 1.
And we can say 3 factorial
is, well, 3 times 2 times 1.
And if you're not getting the
pattern, 4 factorial might be?
Well, just 4 times 3 times 2 times 1.
So a factorial is multiplying a
number by 1 less than that number
and moving down until we get to 1,
right, so 4 times 3 times 2 times
1 for 4 factorial, 3 factorial,
3 times 2 times 1, and so on.
Now, what do you notice about this
problem, particularly in 4 factorial?
What do you notice, or
what do you see if we're
trying to use recursion on this
problem, trying to find a smaller
problem within 4 factorial?
Maybe type in the chat if you'd like.
What kind of pattern do you see when
you look at 2 factorial, 3 factorial?
So seeing a few ideas, right?
I'm seeing it's
repeating the same steps.
It's a little repetitive.
And I'm seeing, more particularly,
if we look at 4 factorial,
we actually see that 3 factorial
is included in 4 factorial, right?
3 factorial is 3 times 2 times 1.
Well, that's actually right there
in 4 factorial, 3 times 2 times 1.
So if we were to look
at the problem this way,
we might make it a little
more obvious, right?
4 factorial really has the
solution 3 factorial inside of it.
And similarly, 3 factorial
has 2 factorial inside of it.
And then finally, 1 factorial,
that's just kind of on its own.
It's just 1, right?
We know that for a fact.
This is really a good
place for recursion
to come in because recursion is all
about taking this larger problem,
like 4 factorial, and breaking
it down into smaller pieces.
So let's look at it from
a recursive standpoint.
Let's go ahead and say we
want to find 4 factorial.
Well, what is 4 factorial?
Well, it's 4 times what?
What's the smaller problem
within 4 factorial?
4 times 3 factorial,
I'm seeing in the chat.
So 4 factorial is just
4 times 3 factorial.
But what then is 3 factorial?
So this is where what comes in
as we call it a recursive call.
This is saying we are going to
solve this smaller problem before we
can solve this larger problem, right?
We can't solve 4 factorial until
we know what 3 factorial is.
So let's go ahead and solve 3 factorial.
Well, what is 3 factorial?
That is just 3 times what?
3 times 2 factorial, right?
So that's fine, but what is 2 factorial?
Well, 2 factorial is?
2 times 1 factorial.
And what is 1 factorial?
At some point, we do have to stop here.
Otherwise, we'll keep finding smaller
and smaller problems and never end.
Well, 1 factorial, in
this case, is just 1.
We know that for a fact.
And so this down at the bottom
is what's called our base case.
This is the problem that we know
how to solve just for a fact.
1 factorial is 1, no
computation necessary,
no need to break it down
into a smaller problem.
And now, once we've gone
down to that base case,
well, the rest follows, right?
We know that 1 factorial is 1.
So let's go ahead and make sure
that we can solve 2 factorial.
And we're going, what we
call, back up the call stack,
where we made a recursive call earlier
to go ahead and solve a smaller
problem.
Now we've found our base
case, so we'll go back up
this stack of calls we made
to find the answer here.
What we'll do is say, OK, 2 factorial,
that's actually just 2 times 1.
We know that now because
1 factorial is 1.
Well, 3 factorial, that's
actually just 3 times 2 times
1 because we know now that
2 factorial is 2 times 1.
And similarly, for 4 factorial,
we know that, in this case,
3 factorial is just 3 times 2 times 1.
So now we can say 4 factorial is
just this expression, 4 times 3 times
2 times 1.
And that, as a whole, is 24.
All right, and so I'm seeing in the
chat, it's like backwards logic.
It is a little backwards logic.
We have to go down to the bottom
first and then work our way back up.
So let's work on this one together.
Let's actually see what might
be able to work on with here.
And what we'll do is write our
own function called factorial,
where factorial should take an integer
and return the factorial of whatever
number we pass in as a parameter.
So if we pass in 4, we should
find 4 factorial, or 5,
we should find 5 factorial here.
All right, so let's go ahead and
actually open up our own program.
We'll go ahead and go
back to our terminal.
We'll type code factorial.c to open
up this new file called factorial.
And let's get the same
template code in there.
We need to make sure
we have cs50 library.
We need to have standard io.h.
And we also need to have, of
course, our int main void function,
that main function in our program.
And now we can also make sure
we have our factorial function.
So I'll zoom in just a little bit more.
We might want to have a factorial.
What type is factorial returning
to us, do we know in this case?
If you want to type a chime in the chat.
An integer, right?
So we'll say int, and then the
name of this function, factorial.
And then does it take any inputs?
What kind of input does it take?
Yeah, it takes a number
that is also an integer.
So I could say int, maybe,
number in this case.
So here we have this
function, again, called
factorial that takes a argument
called number that is an integer.
And it returns to us an integer,
that number factorialized, right?
And now we know from our past
mistake we need to actually go ahead
and include this prototype up
at the very top of our file
in order to use this
function in our code.
OK, and let's just go ahead and
fill our main function here.
Let's make sure we maybe
prompt the user for a number.
So we could say, let's give
ourselves maybe int n is get int,
and we'll say type a number to our user.
And then what we'll do is
maybe print the resulting
integer that comes
from running factorial
in this case, so factorial of n.
Now, it's up to us to actually
implement factorial down here.
And when we think about
implementing recursive functions,
we often want to start
first with our base case.
What is the thing we know to be a fact?
And if we look at our factorial
call stack here, what was our thing
we know to be a factor down here?
Feel free to type in the chat.
Seeing 1.
So yeah, 1 factorial is 1.
We know that.
That is always true.
So what we should do is go
back to our factorial function
and then say, OK, well, if number is
1, if it's equal to 1, let's go ahead
and just say the answer.
Let's say the answer is 1.
So now, if I were to type in
1 and pass it to factorial,
I would get the right answer.
1 factorial is 1.
But there's more to do here.
If I were to type in factorial
of 3 or factorial of 4,
that wouldn't quite work
because I haven't figured out
how to solve that piece yet.
Now, if we go back to
our diagram here, what
did we notice about how
each factorial problem is
composed of some other problem?
What should be our recursive step here?
Yes, I'm seeing
something like n minus 1.
And if you notice, you'll look
at maybe 4 factorial, and see,
well, 4 factorial is really
just 4 times 3 factorial.
And 3 factorial is just
3 times 2 factorial.
So it's really whatever
number we're at times
the factorial of a number minus 1.
Now, there is a way to
use a loop here, and that
would be called what
an iterative approach
using a loop to solve this problem.
But here we'll actually
use a recursive solution,
which is one that calls
itself in the definition.
So factorial will call
the factorial function
to try to solve this problem here.
So if we know that we don't
have the answer already,
if we know that we aren't at 1
factorial, what we can do instead
is try to solve this problem by
breaking it down into smaller pieces.
We could say, well, we know that a
certain number factorial is really
just that number times that number
minus 1 factorialized like this.
If I go full screen here, we'll see
that really the solution is just
number times the factorial
of that number minus 1.
And let's go ahead and
try to get a visual here,
but just first confirm it works.
So I'll say make factorial
and run./factorial.
And maybe I'll type in 4, and I get 24.
So let's type n factorial of 3, and I
get 6 because 3 times 2 times 1 is 6.
But why is this working?
It seems a little odd that we
can just solve this problem
with only a single if
statement and this expression
down here that uses itself
in the definition, right?
So to visualize this, we actually want
to use something called a debug50,
if you're familiar with that.
Debug50 lets you step through
your code and go through
and see how things are working here.
So while we're at it, let's
set a breakpoint right
at this point in our code,
meaning we'll stop at this point,
and then we'll step
through piece by piece
to see what's happening
in the computer's memory.
So we'll go ahead and
run this using debug50.
And we'll wait for
debug50 to pull itself up.
And we'll step through
our code in a minute here.
All right, let me zoom
out just a little bit.
OK, so I'm seeing type
a number in my prompt.
So I'll go ahead and type
in the number for, right?
All right, so notice
debug50 on the side here.
We now have number 4,
and what we've done
is we've given our program a number.
Now, we're at this stage.
We've called factorial
with n is 4, which
means that number here is equal to 4.
And if we look down at our
call stack, that vocabulary
term we learned earlier, we
see that we first called main,
and then we called factorial, right?
But we still need to call
probably factorial again
because, if we go in here,
we see that number is not 1.
Number is 4 right now.
It's not 1, so we can't return 1.
We will instead need to
do this line of code.
But we can't solve this line of code
until we run the factorial function
again with number 1 less than that.
So what we'll do is we'll step
into this function factorial.
And now, see in our call stack,
factorial shows up again.
We call factorial once,
we're calling it again.
But now, what's going to happen?
Number is 3, so we're getting closer.
We're not quite there.
3 is not 1, so we're going
to continue down again.
We'll go ahead, and we
can't return 1 there,
but we can figure out
what is 3 factorial?
Well, to find 3 factorial,
we've got to find 2 factorial.
So we'll dive in again.
We'll say, OK, let's go
deeper in our call stack.
Notice how if we scroll down,
factorial is being called yet again.
we've called it the third time now.
Now, number is 2.
OK, let's keep going.
Number is not 1 yet.
To find 2 factorial, we
got to find 1 factorial.
Let's go dive in again.
Look at our call stack.
We've called factorial four times now.
But at this point, we know
number is 1, and so we
can simply and safely return 1.
We know the answer now, right?
So we'll do that, and
then, that's correct,
we called this number 1 our base case.
We've hit our base case now.
We can start going
back up our call stack.
So we can say let's finish
that call of factorial.
Now, we're back at our third
factorial call where number is 2.
Well, we solved that problem.
We know that 2 factorial
is just 2 times 1.
And now we can return that 2 times 1.
Now, we're at that later
version of factorial,
that second call where number is 3.
We know 3 factorial now
is 3 times 2 times 1 based
on the earlier calls of factorial.
We're going to go again.
Now, we're at that very first
call a factorial, number is 4.
Well, the answer here we now
know is 4 times 3 times 2 times
1 based on this call stack we've done.
And now we can finish that
program and type out 24.
So a bit of a leap of faith
wherein you're trying to take for
granted that your program
knows exactly what to do.
And it will eventually
hit this base case.
If it doesn't hit that
base case, we'll know
that maybe our program will keep
running, keep running, keep running.
And that's not a good thing.
So we always need this
base case here to stop
the call stack from growing and growing
and growing and growing and always
finding that end case there.
But certainly, feel free to take
some time thinking about this one.
So what questions do you all
have about how this works
or how the recursion is working here?
Yes, so your question about,
you know how recursion works,
but how do you know if a recursion
is a good approach to a problem?
And what I encourage you to do
is really try to draw things out
before you end up trying to
code a recursive function.
So similarly, if we go back here, we saw
that factorial was we drew things out.
We saw, hey, I notice that 3 factorial
is embedded inside of 4 factorial.
So maybe it's a good use of
a recursive algorithm here.
If you can find a problem
and you find that problem
is made of a smaller problem that
can be solved in the same way,
that's a hint you might want to
use recursion in that instance.
What other questions are there
on recursion in this case?
Let's see.
I'm seeing, what do we call
the thing we did on line 4?
So if you scroll up to the
top here in our program,
we'll see on line 4 we
declared the function.
We gave the compiler our prototype.
So this right here is called
our function prototype
and, more specifically,
putting this piece right here
is declaring our function.
We're telling c, hey, we have this
function that returns an integer.
It is named factorial
and takes an argument
called number that is an integer.
And that in respect we're
declaring our function there.
Is there a way to make
this code shorter?
Perhaps.
I won't go out on a limb
and say that this is maybe
the most short you can make it.
Maybe there is a way to do it.
But certainly, if it seems
well designed for us here.
And another question is,
can we use a loop here?
We actually could use a loop here.
So let's say we didn't
want to use recursion.
Maybe it feels a little too
much like a leap of faith.
So what we'll do is we'll, maybe
instead of this, we'll say,
OK, we know that, when number is
1, we'll go ahead and return 1.
But otherwise, we know that factorial
is really just that number times 1
less than it times 1 less than it.
So we could do this.
We could say something like a for loop.
We could take for.
Maybe we'll start at i is equal
to our number and go until i is--
maybe, let's say, as long
as i is greater than 0,
and then keep subtracting
from i as we go through.
So what we could do is maybe
say that our solution is going
to be first probably equal to number.
And then we could say solution is equal
to that solution times some other--
times i, I believe.
And feel free to correct me if
I'm doing anything wrong here.
I think what might happen though,
is we have solution times number.
Something like this, number
minus 1, and so on and so forth.
But basically what we're doing
here is trying to make a loop out
of this, trying to say, OK, let's
start with 4 and multiply 3 to it
and then 2 to it and then
1 to it through a loop.
And we could do that.
But often what happens is that maybe
recursion is more elegant solution
here.
This seems like much more lines of code.
So maybe, in this case, we could use our
recursive solution that we had before.
And a question related to this is, can
all recursions be rewritten as loops?
It's a good question.
I would say that at least some of them
could be, as we demonstrated here.
I think there are some problems
though where recursion is really
going to be helpful for you
because what recursion does
is it allows you to
have a whole new smaller
problem to work with and take
a big chunk out of that problem
and work with that smaller one.
So often, in computer science,
we want to solve bigger problems
by first solving smaller ones.
And a loop might not always
give you that same leverage
that you might have by
breaking down a big problem
and making it into a smaller one.
But a great question.
Other questions to you
on this recursion here?
All right, so that does just about
bring us to the very end of our section.
We talked about algorithms,
how we compare them.
We talked about structs
and how we might use them.
We talked about recursion, how we can
identify recursion and ultimately write
our own recursive functions.
As you go off into this
week, you will, in fact,
do your own kind of algorithms
that involve structs,
that might involve recursion, that might
involve all these different elements.
And so I wish you the very best
as you're going off and working
on your own work this week.
Thank you so much for
joining us over Zoom.
It was wonderful to see you all here.
Hope to see you in the
coming weeks, and I'll
be happy to stay around
and answer questions.
Thank you all.