CARTER ZENKE: Well, hello one and all
and welcome to our week four section.
My name is Carter Zenke.
I'm the course's
preceptor, and today we'll
dive into memory, little details of
how a computer actually stores things
inside of its own memory in this case.
So jump in.
We'll take a look at
a few questions today,
and these questions
look a bit like this.
First we'll talk about
these ideas of pointers.
What is a pointer, how
do we use it, what's
their syntax we should get used to?
Second, we'll think about how it
can read and write data from a file.
How do we take data stored inside
a file, put it inside our program.
And then how do we take data from our
program and put it inside of a file?
And then finally, we'll talk
about this idea of dynamic memory.
How do we use these new tools like
malloc and when should we use them?
Even really, why should we use them?
Why do we care about them?
So to jump in, let's take
a look first at pointers,
where pointers is this
idea of trying to store
the address of some variable inside a
new variable, in this case a pointer.
So to get started with this,
let's think back to what
we talked about first with variables.
What is a variable?
If a pointer is to variable,
what first is a variable?
Well, we saw earlier--
we had this contact application.
We're trying to store some
variables inside of like people
with names, addresses,
phone numbers, et cetera.
Or even the number of
times we had called them.
So let's go back to that idea first.
Let's take a look at
this syntax where we
had some variable named calls that is
an integer, and it has the value four.
And we broke this
variable down as follows.
We said that we can give this
variable a name-- in this case, calls.
It also has a type called int for
integer, it stores integer values.
And it also has a value,
in this case, four.
So calls is simply some name
for some place in memory
that has the value four.
But the picture is a little more
complex than that, as we now know.
In fact, instead of simply saying that
calls is located someplace in memory,
we can tell you very specifically
where it is in memory
using this new tool called addresses.
So similar to how homes or businesses
have addresses, so do variables.
And in this case, we'll see
that calls has the address
0x1A, kind of by random choice here.
But in this case, we use hexadecimal
format, where we see zero x in front
to note that this is in base 16.
And programs have used
hexadecimal because it's
more convenient to talk
about memory locations
given how many location
memory there can possibly be.
It's easier to use base 16
than, for example, base 10.
And so we denote that
using that 0x in front.
So calls has this location, 0x1A.
But how do we actually
make use of this location?
Well we could actually use what
we call now a pointer, where
a pointer is simply a
variable as we know it,
but it stores not a regular value
like an integer or a character,
but some address in memory.
So let's take a look at this visual now
where we have this pointer called p,
and we know it because we're calling it
p in our syntax on the left hand side.
This is the name for our variable.
We also have, similarly,
a type for this pointer.
This is an int star.
So we know int is an
integer value, integer type.
We also have characters and so on.
But in this case, we see int star.
So whenever we see one
of those basic types,
in this case like char
star or int star, we
can infer that this is not a char or an
int, but a pointer to a char or an int.
In this case, p is a
pointer to an integer.
That star notes this is a pointer we're
talking about, not the actual value,
in this case, an integer or a character.
Now to that end, notice how the
value of p is itself an address.
So we have 0x1a.
So p will get this address
and store it wherever
it has located itself in memory.
And so not to get too
in the weeds, but we
know that if pointers
are themselves variables,
they're a special kind of
variable and they store addresses,
but this pointer itself also
has an address in memory.
We won't really talk too
much about this idea.
It's not often we try to get
the location of a pointer
that itself is a location in memory.
But just so you know, because this
p variable is a variable, it does,
of course, have an address in memory.
Now let's think about
how we could use this.
So we have this idea of storing
values and variables, in this case,
addresses in pointers, but
what do we do with them?
What syntax can we use for them?
Let's take a look at this.
Well, we know we can always
get the value of a variable,
simply kind of saying its
name in code after we've
declared it and initialized it.
So in this case, we're simply
getting the value of calls.
If we ever say calls
in our program, that
gives us back the value at that
variable location-- in this case,
the value for calls.
Now if we want the address or the
value inside of our pointer, p,
we could do the same.
We could say, give me
whatever's inside of p.
And in this way, we can
keep track of, for example,
where this variable calls is.
If we know that we have a variable, a
pointer called p that points to whoever
calls is, we could simply use
the syntax, p, to figure out
where, in this case, calls is located.
We could, similarly, use some new syntax
we've seen in this case, ampersand.
where ampersand stands for
the address of some variable.
And I like to remember this by saying
that ampersand begins with an a,
and so does address.
Ampersand and address.
So in this case ampersand
calls tells us, OK,
where is calls located, just in general?
Maybe it's not inside a variable
yet, but where is calls?
So if we look at the slides
here, we'll see that calls
is located at 0x1a, as we saw before.
Ampersand calls will give us not
the value of calls, not four,
but in this case, the address, 0x1a.
Now thinking similarly, we
could run the same on a pointer.
We could say, what's the address of this
pointer, and get back, perhaps, 0xf0,
or wherever this pointer
is located in memory.
It's not often we'll do this.
It's not often that we'll
get the address of a pointer
that, again, itself has an address,
but you can do it if you're curious.
Now let's think about this, then.
If we have a way to get the value of the
pointer and the address of the pointer.
I mean, what do we
actually use a pointer for?
Well, often, we'll use a pointer to
instead go to wherever it's pointing to
and get the value from there.
And for that we use
this syntax, this star.
It's a little bit confusing because
we saw a star before, like int star
and char star to declare a pointer.
But in this case, we're actually
going to use it to follow
a pointer to the locations pointing to.
Now the visual for this
is a bit like this.
If we say star p, we first think,
OK, what is inside of star p?
What is the value of star p?
And think to yourself for a minute here.
What is the value of just p, first.
0x1a.
And now, putting the star
in front of it, we say,
let's go to that value
that is stored in p.
Let's go to whatever address is
stored in p-- in this case, 0x1A,
and let's get that value there.
So let's follow the arrow,
follow the pointer so to speak,
and get that value, in this
case, four, from our pointer, p.
This is handy, of course.
We build up really large
and complex data structures.
And this simple example might seem
redundant but as you go off and build
your own linked lists and
hash tables and so on, it
can be really useful to be able
to call a pointer like this
to be able to see OK, where is
this value stored, how can I
get the value it's pointing to?
Now as you go off a few things
to remember about pointer syntax
as we just saw now.
First, type star, whether
it's int star or char star,
is a pointer that stores the
address of a certain type.
If you say int star, it
stores the address of integer.
If you say char star, it's
the address of a character.
Now additionally, star x takes a
pointer-- in this case called x,
and goes to the address stored at
that pointer, as we just saw recently.
Star p finds that pointer, p, and
says, what's the value inside of p?
Let me go to that address
and find the value there.
And finally, ampersand x takes whatever
variable you have, in this case
called x, and gets its address.
Ampersand for address, the
two A's together there.
Now let's take a look
at an example exercise
we can do to make sure we're
practicing this syntax as we go.
And this is a pointer
prediction exercise.
So often, it's helpful when first
starting out to look at a program
and predict what it might do.
And only afterwards, we run
it and check your assumptions.
So today, we'll take a look at
this file called pointers.c.
And I encourage you, before you run
this file, to read through the code,
line by line, and act like a computer.
In your mind or on a piece of paper,
write down, what's the value of a?
What's the address of a, for
example, inside this points.c file.
And then once you've done that,
go ahead and run it and see
if your assumptions are correct.
Now let's do this a bit together here.
Here we have the code
on the left hand side
and this visual on the right hand side.
And again, your job is to take a
few minutes, maybe pause the video,
read through this code top to
bottom and work like a computer.
Fill in the potential address
of A and the value of a.
The potential address of b and
the value of b, and so on for c.
It's OK if you need
to make up addresses.
You can certainly do that.
But at the end of running this program,
quote unquote, in your own head,
you should have some addresses for a, b,
and c, And some values for a, b, and c.
So go ahead and pause the
video here, work on this,
and we'll come back
to this one together.
OK, so by now you might have, in your
mind, some potential values for a, b,
and c.
And let's go ahead and
run this program, again,
called pointers.c to actually
see what will happen here.
I'll open up code.cs50.io,
in which case, I already
have a folder called pointers.
And inside of this
folder, I have pointers.c.
You too can download pointers.c and
get it inside of your own code space.
In this case, I'll type cd pointers
to change directory into pointers.
And I'll type ls, where you
can see, I have pointers.c
and this compiled version of pointers
that I could run if I want to.
Let's go ahead and
open, first, pointers.c.
And we see the very same file--
in this case, encased with some
syntax to help us run this program,
ultimately.
But notice how we have the
same declarations of variables
and initialization and the
same manipulation down below.
And finally what we'll
do is print the results.
So in the end, after running this
program, c, a has the value--
whatever it has, located at
some certain location in memory.
And notice how we're using
that same syntax from before.
We're saying, if we want to
find out where a is located,
let's use ampersand.
So ampersand a says,
what's the address of?
And the format code for a
pointer is simply percent p.
Percent i for integer.
Again, these are all integers here.
So we can use percent i,
percent p or a pointer.
So let's compile pointers.
Let's go down to our terminal
and type Make pointers.
And now I'll clear my terminal and I'll
run dot slash pointers and hit Enter.
And now we'll see the results.
And you might have made up
some addresses as you went,
but we can still see the basic
gist here where a has the value 14
and it's located at some location
memory that ends in, let's say, 53c.
B has a value 25, located at some
other location, but it ends with 538.
So it's in a different location than a.
And finally, c has the value--
well, what value does it have?
It doesn't have an integer,
it just has an actual address.
So in this case, c is a
pointer storing an address.
And of course, a pointer
as another variable
does have a location itself in memory--
in this case, one that ends with 530,
so someplace altogether different
than a and b.
So if you predicted
correctly, congratulations.
You're getting a hang
of your pointer syntax.
If not, not to worry.
Feel free to practice
more with the syntax
and actually learn by
doing as you write programs
that use this syntax here for pointers.
But maybe first let's get a
feel for how this is working.
Well first we had integer
a gets the value 28.
So at some location in
memory, we'll create
this variable called a that gets
the value 28, and so on for b.
So we can give them some random address,
wherever it is that they're assigned.
So a and b have some random address,
but they do have the values 28 and 50.
Now though, let's take a look at c.
Well, C looks a bit different.
It says int star is its type.
So what is int star?
Think to yourself.
It's a pointer to an integer.
So in this case, we
have a pointer called c.
This is going to get not
a, but the address of a.
So wherever a is stored,
c will get that address.
Now c is pointing to, metaphorically,
a, or the value stored at a.
Now we do some manipulation
of these pointers.
So we've set them up initially here,
but now I do some manipulation of them.
We say, OK, let's go to the value
that c is holding and make that 14.
But where, currently, is c pointing?
Well, c, as we just
said, is pointing at a.
C, this pointer called c, to an
integer, has the address of a.
So if we say star c, that means go to
the location of a and change the value
to be 14.
Now we'll update c.
We'll say, c, as a
value, has ampersand b.
So where to c point to now?
C points to b, essentially.
We take the address of
b and store that in c.
And finally, we say, let's follow c to
wherever it's pointing using star c,
and then change the value to be 25.
So at the end result, we should see--
because we've first set a, first set
b, then had c point to a, updated a
to be 14, then had c point
to b, updated b to be 25,
we should, of course, see that a
has a value 14, b has the value 25.
And notice that c has this value that
corresponds to what other variable?
Corresponds to b.
C has the value that
is the location of b.
OK.
So again, feel free to get some more
practice with this, either on your own
or while you work on
the problem set itself.
But these pieces of syntax
will be really useful for you
and great to master as you go
through your programming journey.
Now with that in mind, let's do
something a bit more advanced.
Let's take a look at how we can use
these pointers for actually adding
to files, reading from files and so on.
So let's go back to our slides here.
And let's think about
this idea of file I/O,
where file I/O stands for
file input and file output.
How do we take input from files
and how do we output data to files?
So if we think first
about this idea of a file,
you might have this
kind of common notion
of a file being some place in memory
that has a name, and some maybe text
inside of it, or some other characters
or some other pieces of data.
In this case, we might have
this file called hi.txt.
And inside of hi.txt, well, we just have
the characters, hi, exclamation point.
And now this file is really located
somewhere, of course, in memory.
This file has to have a place, and
let's say it's at 0x456 in memory.
Now, if we want to open this file
in order to read data from it,
we have one way of doing it in C.
For example, we could write this.
We could say file star input gets
this value of fopen, hi.txt, r.
And this is maybe a
lot to take in at once,
so let's break it down as a whole.
First what we're doing is
giving something a name.
We're creating some variable
and calling it input.
OK.
But we also have some
other pieces going on here.
Let's look at this.
We have a type for this variable
we're creating called input.
This is a file pointer,
a pointer to a file.
So it goes to say that maybe this
variable, this pointer called input,
points to some file.
It has the address of
some file inside of it.
Now, if we use fopen here,
it's our very own function
that C gives to us as part
of its standard library.
Well, what we could do is say, I want
to open hi.txt using the read mode.
So the first argument to
fopen, in this case hi.txt
is the file name we want to open.
And when we run this, if we
give a certain file name,
C will look in our current
directory for that file name.
And if it finds it, go ahead and
give us the address of that file.
Now in this case, we have to specify
the mode in which we open this file.
Is it a reading mode or a writing mode?
Reading mode allows us to read
data, to take data from the file,
to really copy it, see what's inside
of that file, but not add data to it.
If we want to do that, we have to
open it in writing mode, which is w.
So we could say hi.txt comma w,
if you wanted to open this file
and add more data to it.
But for now, we're going
to read data from it,
take data copied into our program now.
Now this visual here
looks a bit like this.
We're at the end of running this code.
We have some variable
called input, some pointer
that has the address of our file.
Now it's not quite as simple as this.
There is more going on
underneath the hood.
But for now, we can tell
a bit of a white lie,
that input does have roughly
the address of this file.
In actuality, when we run this
program, this line of code right here,
fopen doesn't give us the
exact address of the file,
it gives us some file structure
that is a bit more complicated.
But the basic idea of this is that
some file has a location memory,
and using fopen to find that location
and have a pointer roughly to that file
that we can use in a special way
as we'll see in just a minute.
Now it's all fine and
good to open our files,
but wouldn't it be good if we
could actually take data from them
and read them into our program?
Read those bytes and put
them inside our program
so we can use them for our own good.
Well, to do that, we first need to
complicate our vision of this file.
Let's take a look at this.
So we have this idea of
a file and some variable,
often called input, that points
roughly towards our file.
This tells us where our
file is and allows us
to access whatever is inside of it.
Now this file is, of course, composed
itself of different bytes of memory.
Where we might have, in this case, many
bytes memory inside of this dot txt
file.
And our goal is to take a peek at those
bytes and see what's inside of them
and put them inside of our own program.
Well, to do that, we'll
often need a place inside
of our program to store these bytes.
And this will often, in our
case, be called a buffer.
So a buffer is a technical
term for some place
we're going to store some data
as we read it from a file.
A buffer might look,
visually, a bit like this,
or it's maybe a sequence of three bytes.
And if a buffer is some sequence
of bytes, back, to back, to back,
or some sequence of
locations memory, back,
to back, to back, what kind
of structure do you think
would be good to use for a
buffer that we've seen before?
What kind of structure would you use?
Buffer might be an array, right, where
we have an array being some locations
memory, back, to back, to back.
A buffer similarly might be an array
of some bytes we read from our file.
Now we have a buffer to store this data
in and a file to read this data from.
It just, reason to say,
OK, we need some tool
to use to actually take
these bytes from our file
and put them now in our buffer.
And thankfully, the C library does
give us this function called fread.
Fread looks a bit like this.
And you can certainly change
the arguments to fread.
But importantly, it takes four distinct
arguments-- four distinct inputs.
The first input that we care about
that makes logical sense to start with
is the file we're reading from.
So this is the file pointer that
we're going to read data from.
Notice how in our prior
visual, we had this input
file pointer, pointing
roughly towards our file.
Well, in this case, we want
fread to read from that location,
so we'll put this in the
fourth argument to fread.
Next in importance is the size
of the blocks to read in bytes.
Notice how our file here is composed
of, in this case, individual bytes.
So we want to read each of those
bytes as a single byte at a time.
So we'll say that this is the
size of the block to read.
The blocks in our file
are a single byte large.
The next question then is, OK, how
many blocks do you want to read?
If we say we have--
the size of our blocks
in our file is one byte,
well, let's read three of them.
So three single byte
blocks from our file.
And where do we put them?
We put them inside of
our buffer, in this case.
So the first argument to fread.
The location we store
the data we're reading.
The second argument, how big
is the block in our file?
How big is a chunk of data in our file?
Third argument, how
many do I want to read?
And finally, for this input,
where are we reading from.
So let's get a visual for
this as we go through.
So first, if we look at
this location to read from,
input, we're telling our file,
here's what we're reading from,
the start hi.txt file,
because we opened it
using it fopen just a little bit ago.
Now we finish the question.
What's the size of blocks to read?
Well, they're a single byte big.
Now how many do we want to read?
We want to read three of them.
So we'll look at three of these here.
And then where do we
want to store these?
Where do we want to read
them and copy them into?
In this case, it's buffer.
So we'll simply take
our data in our file
here and then put them inside of buffer.
And now our file pointer,
previously called input, updates
to the next location in our file.
And as such, we can keep reading, and
reading, and reading from our file
while our file pointer updates.
So it's often good to kind
of see this in practice.
And what we'll do for this
is actually take a look
at how we can test the file as a PDF.
But before we do that, let's take a
look at how we can use a buffer here.
If we want to use our
buffer as an array,
we could, of course, use this bracket
syntax, like buffer bracket zero,
buffer bracket one, and buffer
bracket two, giving us access
to those individual bytes, which
will be important in just a moment.
So for our practice, we'll
create this program called pdf.c.
And the goal of pdf.c is to open a
file given to our program and check,
is that file likely a PDF?
And we can know this because we know
that every PDF, or at least those
of a certain type, a common type,
start with this four byte sequence.
And these bytes correspond
to these four integers--
37, 80, 68, and 70.
So maybe news to you.
Whenever you open a PDF, the
first four bytes in that file
are often going to
represent these integers--
37, 80, 68, and 70.
This is known as a file signature.
It tells a program opening
this file to know hey,
this is pretty sure to be a PDF.
Now let's write this code together.
Let's go to pdf.c over here.
I'll do cd dot dot, get out
of my pointers directory
and I'll clear my terminal.
I'll then go into my new folder
called PDF and cd inside of it.
I'll type ls.
And notice how I have
some test files here.
I have test JPEG and test PDF.
I don't yet, though,
have, in this case, pdf.c.
I'll use these files as tests for my
code, but first I need to create pdf.c.
So I'll do that with code,
in this case PDF, dot c.
Now I have this new file, pdf.c.
And what's the kind
of boilerplate syntax
I should use to start
off my PDF program?
I might want to have an
int main void program--
or a function, some place to
run the main part of my code.
I might also want to simply
import the CS50 library.
I might also want to import
maybe the standard I/O library
to print something out to the user,
tell them if it's a PDF or if it's not.
Now to get started, I first need to
accept some command line arguments
for my program.
I need to ask the user to type in the
name of the file they want to open.
And so what I'll do is I'll check
to see if the user has actually
given me a file name.
Now instead of void here, I probably
want to use int argc and string argv.
This allows my program to
take command line arguments.
And remember that the amount
of arguments I've been given
is stored in argc, and the
actual content of the arguments
is stored in this array, argv.
Now I should check, is argc
equal to the number of command
line arguments I expect?
Now, if I expect one command
line argument, I should check,
is arg not equal to two?
And if it's not I'll say,
printf, this is improper usage.
This is not the way to run my program.
And I'll return 1 to the user, saying,
this is not the right way to do it.
Now why is argc two here, not one?
We expect one argument, really, but
why should I check if argc is two?
Well, keep in mind that when I run this
program, eventually as, in this case,
dot slash pdf, maybe test JPEG
dot JPEG, the first command line
argument, technically, for a program
is going to be dot slash PDF,
and then the second one
is going to be this.
So if I want really one command
an argument to my program here,
I should keep in mind
that this still counts
as some argument given at the terminal.
So I should say if argc is
not equal to two in the end.
Now let me scroll down here.
And once I know that I have some file
name, let me try to open this file.
So let's say open file here.
And how can we do that?
I encourage you to pause the
video, maybe try it on your own.
How could we open whatever file
is given to us from the user?
So let's first keep in
mind the file name, right?
We could perhaps say this-- the
file name, string file name,
is located at argv 1.
Now why argv 1?
What we saw below, when we
eventually run our program with dot
slash PDF test JPEG dot
JPEG or test PDF dot PDF,
well, this will be
what's stored in argv 0,
and this will be what's
stored in argv 1.
So the file name is located at argv 1.
And we need the final name to pass it
into what function to open our file?
Fopen.
So we saw, we could
use fopen like this--
fopen and then the file name.
So we'll say this is our
file name, simply using
this variable we've used before.
And then what mode we
want to open the file in.
Because we're simply
reading this file, seeing
what information is inside
of it, not adding to it,
we can simply open
this file in read mode.
But we need some place to store the
structure we'll get back from fopen--
the file pointer we'll
get back from fopen.
And so for that, let's
go ahead and create one.
We can say, give me a new file pointer.
This one perhaps called PDF.
And now we've created some file
pointer called PDF using fopen.
And actually, because we don't
know if it's going to be a PDF,
let's just call it in this case file.
So we have a file pointer called
file that will take a file name,
find it in our current directory, open
it in read mode, and give it back to us
in terms of this file pointer.
OK.
So we have opened the file.
But as we do, you can
think of some edge cases.
What if, for example, we type in a
file name we actually don't have?
Well, in that case, fopen will return
to us null, as a special term to say,
we don't have that file for you here.
So it's important here to not simply
blindly open the file, but to check,
even.
Is file equal to null.
And if it is, let's
go ahead and return 1.
And we print an error
message to the user.
We could say, in this case
that, no such file found.
And for good measure, why
don't we have some backslash
ends to tidy up our code here.
All right so this is going
to check if file exists.
Now we've opened the file, ideally.
We've checked if it exists.
And presumably, if we get past this
line of code, the file does exist.
So what's the next step?
We want to read from this file, and
ideally, have some place to read into.
So we saw before that it's
common for us to create
what we call a buffer-- some
place to read data from our file
and put it inside our
program in smaller chunks.
It wouldn't be wise, for example,
for us to take the entire program
and put it all--
the entire file and put it
all in our program at once.
Instead, we want to take single
chunks of that file and deal
with those chunks kind
of individually, one
at a time, kind of reading
in smaller pieces of the file
but going through the
entire file over time.
Now to create this buffer-- remember,
a buffer is simply an array.
But in this case, for a PDF, it's
an array of a special kind of byte.
We want the buffer to store the same
type of data that's inside of our file.
And in this case, a PDF stores the
special type called a uint 8 t.
This is a special type of data.
And it might look scary at first, until
we break it down into smaller pieces.
So first, notice some familiar syntax.
Here we have int, right?
So presumably, this is
some kind of integer.
It's a special kind, though.
It's a U int.
U stands for unsigned,
meaning it's only positive.
Remember, that we talk about signed or
unsigned integers, where signed means
it can be positive or negative.
We can have a minus
sign in front or not.
But as unsigned integers, it can
be in this case only positive.
Now we have this 8 here.
It's a uint, unsigned
integer, 8 underscore t.
Well, the 8 here denotes this is only
8 bits-- a single byte for an integer.
It's not a 2 byte integer
or a 4 byte integer.
It's only a single byte.
We can represent up to, in this
case, the number of values we have
with a single byte, unsigned.
Now this underscore t here means
that all that together, this unsigned
integer of 8 bits, is
going to be its own type.
So uint went 8 underscore
t, an unsigned integer
of 8 bits that is its very own type.
Now this is a special kind-- it's
presumably used in more than PDF,
but it's a new one for us today.
So we'll get some practice with this.
To use a uint 8 t, we need to actually
import a different library from the C
library, this one called standard int--
S-T-D dot I-N-T dot H. So we'll
get it from this header file,
standard int dot h, and now we can
use it inside our pdf.c down below.
Now we want a buffer here.
So we want a buffer of uint 8 t's.
And how many integers are we going to
store in this buffer, do you think?
We need four-- the PDF signature
is only four bytes, remember.
Assume I only need four spaces.
So I'll create enough space in an
array for four uint 8 t's that'll
read from our PDF.
And currently this is
empty, but in just a minute,
we'll actually go ahead and try to
read these inside of our buffer.
So now that we have some place to
read in the data from our file,
let's go ahead and try that.
We could say fread.
And remember that the first argument to
fread is the place we're reading into.
So in this case, we'll
read into our buffer.
Now the next two arguments are
the size of blocks in the file,
and how many of those
blocks you want to read.
Now for a PDF, a PDF could consider
it being composed of individual bytes.
So we could say, the size
of the block is one byte.
But how many of these
bytes do you want to read?
Only the first four.
So we could say, take the first four
single byte blocks from this file.
And now where from?
Where is this file reading from?
Well, in this case, it's going to
be from our file pointer from above.
Notice the correspondence between the
file we've opened before and the file
we're reading from down here.
Now fread doesn't necessarily need
to be stored in some variable.
We don't necessarily say, file
pointer, updated file equals fread.
Fread works just on its own.
You can call it.
It'll do the magic of reading
in your bytes from your file,
putting them inside the buffer, and
updating the file pointer to look
at the next four bytes in your file.
Now once we've done
that, we could possibly
take a look at what's inside of
buffer, just for the sake of looking.
Now to iterate through our
buffer, what could we do?
We could write a for loop.
We could say for int i equals 0.
i is less than four, i plus plus.
Now we could look--
let's print out whatever
integer is inside of buffer--
let's put a space after it.
Buffer bracket i.
So now ideally, we've created
some space in our program
to store the first four
bytes from our file.
We've read them from our
file, from our PDF, perhaps.
And now we're going to print them
out, just as a check here to see
what's inside of our buffer.
So I'll go down here, and I'll
run make PDF to compile it and see
if we don't get any errors.
And we'll wait for it to compile.
And it looks like it's all good.
So now I'll type dot slash PDF.
And now we'll give the name
of the file we want to open.
In this case we'll do test
underscore PDF dot PDF.
And let's see.
OK, it looks like inside this
file, in the first four bites
are 37, 80, 68, and 70.
And that does correspond
to what we expect--
37, 80, 68, and 70.
Let's try our, in this case, our JPEG.
But first, notice how I have
this on the same line here.
Why do I do this?
Why don't I say backslash n at
the end to print a new line,
ultimately after I print
out these first four bytes?
Now I'll make PDF again.
I'll do dot slash PDF
test JPEG dot JPEG.
Open this, and now we see the first
four integers inside of this JPEG.
And let's just be sure-- test
a file, it doesn't exist.
Let's do dot PDF, hello.c.
And no such file was found.
Great.
So we seem to be able to
read in data from our file,
put it inside our buffer.
But now I need to check, is this
buffer the same as 37, 80, 68, and 70?
Now I'll leave this up to you
to work on for a minute here.
I encourage you to do that on
your own before coming back.
But maybe pause the video and work
on this together in just a moment.
OK.
So presumably you've
attempted this on your own,
but if you haven't, that's OK.
Let's go ahead and check.
How could we see the
data inside our buffer
and check it against the
signature we're looking for?
Well, it would be handy if we
created our very own signature--
our own array--
that actually has the data
we expect inside of it.
So we could say this.
Let's make a new uint
8 t buffer, this one
called signature, that
stores four values.
But in this case, we'll actually
just give them to the buffer.
We'll say first we're looking for 37.
Then we're looking for 80.
Then we're looking for 68.
And then we're looking
for, in this case, 70.
So this is our file
signature we're looking for.
And as a bit of trivia,
you don't actually
need to include the length of the
buffer or the length of the array
if you have the definition already over
here of four, in this case, integers.
So now we have the buffer that
we're reading from our file
and the signature that has the
data we're actually looking for.
Well, what if we compared buffer
bracket i with signature bracket i,
and see if they're the same?
So I'll do this.
I'll say, as I loop through
my buffer, why don't I ask,
is buffer bracket i the
same as signature bracket i?
And if that's the case,
well, what do I want to do?
Well, I actually really
can't make a conclusion
if I only know that one of buffers
integers is the same as the signatures.
Instead, I should probably
ask, what if it's not the same?
What if as I loop through, it's ever not
the same between buffer and signature?
Well, I could perhaps print to the user,
if I know that one is not the same,
this is likely not a PDF.
So I'll say, likely not a PDF.
And I'll return just a 0
to say everything went OK,
but this is just not a PDF.
Now then, if I get all
the way through this loop,
then I know that I likely have a PDF.
I'll go say, printf, likely a PDF.
And I'll do backslash n up here, too.
And then I'll say return 0.
I don't need this new line anymore.
So notice the logic here.
First we're going to read in
some data into our buffer.
We're going to ask the question,
does the buffer signature match?
Does the better signature match.
We'll loop to buffer, check.
Is every integer and buffer
the same as signature?
If it is, if we never
trigger this condition,
we'll get down here and
print, likely a PDF.
If we ever find it's not the same,
though, we'll print, likely not a PDF,
return 0, and thus ending our program
before we get down to likely a PDF.
OK, so let's run this
program again, I'll
open it up to make PDF dot slash PDF.
I'll do test JPEG dot JPEG.
And we see, likely not a
PDF, which makes sense.
Now let's do dot slash PDF, test PDF
dot PDF, and we see, likely a PDF.
So this file seems to be
working exactly as we intend.
All right.
So this is some of the
magic we can do, now that we
can open files and read data from them.
What we'll take a look
at in just a moment
is what we can do if
we want to keep asking
our program for more and more memory.
Here we're not using
too much memory, we're
only using four bytes
to read in our data
from our file, put it inside our buffer.
But there's more we can do
with memory in this case.
So beyond opening files, let's
take a look at dynamic memory.
And dynamic memory is often seen
the context of using malloc in C.
So malloc, if you recall,
is used for asking
our program for more and more memory.
Importantly, it does it from a special
place that we'll see in just a minute.
But the basic idea is asking for
memory for our program on the fly.
Now for example, let's say we wanted
to create some integer called hours.
Well, we can use malloc here.
We could say int star hours.
Gets the value of running malloc
given the size of an integer.
And there are some stuff to
break down here, so let's do it.
Notice how we have, in this case,
the name of our variable, still.
It's hours.
But it's not an integer right now.
It's an integer pointer.
So malloc, when it runs, always gives
back a pointer to whatever space
it created in memory for us.
So as we run malloc, though, it
needs to know, what size of space
should I give you?
And we can use, in this case,
this function, size of, to say,
give me the size of
whatever type I have.
Size of int, size of char.
If we give that to malloc, it'll
always give us that size in bytes.
So we're asking malloc here for
simply some space for one integer.
Now we get back a
pointer to the integer,
and to then store some
values inside of it,
we need to use that star syntax
we saw a little bit earlier.
What if we wanted not just a
single space for an integer,
but actually maybe an array of integers?
We could ask malloc for that, too.
We could say, instead of size of
integer, give me size of integer times
five, in this case, five
spaces for this integer here.
Now what if you wanted to
actually add in some data?
Well, we could say, as we saw
before, star hours gets 7.
And if you wanted to add in some data
to the right of 7, we could do this.
We could say, maybe, star hours
plus 1 is 9, or stars hour plus 2
is something else.
Notice how we're using some pointer
arithmetic here, or we're saying,
hours plus 1 means go to
the next location memory
after whatever hours is pointing to.
And of course, hours points that first
location in our broader array here.
So we could also, of course, use
same bracket notation we saw before--
like hours bracket 2 for 8, or
hours bracket 3, in this case,
for 7, and so on.
So it kind of begs the question,
what's the point of using malloc
if we can use this very same syntax,
and now we have to do with pointers?
As we saw briefly in lecture,
malloc gives us some memory
from the special place called the Heap.
What we've been using
up until now in CS50
has been the Stack,
where the Stack is what
you use when you use simply a function.
You create some variable
inside your function
that asks for memory from the Stack.
When you use malloc, though,
you get memory from the Heap.
And why would you get
memory from the Heap?
Well, if you want a much
larger data structure,
you might often do that on the Heap
because the Heap is more persistent,
it's quite larger.
You don't really want to
fill up the Stack too much.
You often want to use the Heap for
these really large kind of files
that you might work with.
You might also use
the Heap when you want
to have a data structure that many
functions can operate on-- for example,
a linked list or a hash table.
If you want a single structure that you
can write many functions to operate on,
you'll want to use the Heap
for that, because remember,
a Stack is limited to
the single function call,
but the Heap can be shared
across functions overall.
So this is good, as you'll see,
in the problem set this week
and in coming weeks, you'll be able to
actually share data across functions
when you use malloc and the Heap.
Now if you use malloc, though, there
are still things to be wary of.
And in fact, when we use malloc,
there's often these brand
new errors that we're
now capable of making.
And so let's take a look at
these kinds of errors now.
Often when we use
malloc, we have to make
sure we actually free
every block of memory--
and often, you actually won't remember
do that when you're first beginning.
That's OK.
If you use fopen, you want to make sure
you always close the file that you've
then opened before.
And of course, we want to
be wary of using more memory
than has actually been allocated.
So let's take a look at this.
But before we actually
jump into a new exercise,
let's go back to our previous PDF
one and see if there's something
we could have done a little bit better,
keeping in mind these common memory
errors.
Let's go back over here.
And reading through this file, I might
not see much to improve off the bat,
especially if I'm a beginner here.
But what I can do is
run a special program
that tells me what might be going
wrong, memory-wise in this program.
It seemed to work, but
we could still do better.
So I'll do this-- valgrind of dot PDF.
And I'll type in this
time, test PDF dot PDF.
So if I run my program as I usually
do, but type valgrind in front,
I'll then be able to see what
memory errors, if any, I encounter.
So I hit Enter here.
And now I see--
whoops.
Let me cd into PDF first.
valgrind dot PDF, and
then test PDF dot PDF.
It'll run.
It gave me some slightly cryptic syntax.
But notice how I see this--
leak summary.
If I see a leak summary here
and I see that there are still
some bytes in that leak
summary, well, I've
actually been not necessarily keeping
memory as tidy as I should be.
In this case, it might mean that
perhaps I left some memory on the table
and didn't tell my program to free
that up so other programs could
use this very same memory.
So what did I do wrong?
If I read to this file top to bottom--
keep in mind our common mistakes.
I'll see, well, I didn't use
malloc, but I did open the file.
Did I close it later on?
Let's look through.
I checked the buffer
but I didn't close it.
It's important, before
you end your program,
to make sure you always close
the file that you've opened.
So in this case, I could
close it down here.
Fclose.
And I'll give it the file pointer
I want to close-- in this case,
we called it simply file.
Fclose file.
But this isn't the only
place I should close.
It I should also close it up here.
Keep in mind that if I run
this for loop and ever find
that buffer isn't the same as
signature, I'll print likely not a PDF
and return 0.
If I hadn't closed the file here,
that would be the end of my program
and I wouldn't have
closed the file at all.
So I want to make sure to close
it, at least, in both places.
I could also, perhaps, close it
just after I finished reading--
I could do it up here.
Fclose file there, and that
would avoid duplicating
this in more than one place.
So now let's run this again.
Let's do valgrind dot PDF, test
underscore PDF dot PDF, run it again.
And now we see--
whoops.
Still reachable.
Hm, let's see.
Fclose of file.
Let's try doing what we had before.
So we do fclose down here,
putting it right there.
Fclose down here,
And now let's run this again
and just see if that helps us.
So do Command a there.
Make PDF-- oh, we might not
have recompiled compiled
this, which might make it happen.
So we do dot valgrind dot slash
PDF, test underscore PDF dot PDF.
And now we should see all heap blocks
are free, no leaks are possible.
So whenever you go ahead and
add your fcloses to a file
and you've run valgrind
before, make sure you
recompile it to see the new
results of your new program here.
OK.
So let's go back to a new
exercise-- this one focused
on identifying more kinds of memory
leaks, more errors you're now
capable of making.
So for this one, we'll take a look
at this program called create.
Where you've seen code before in VSCode.
You know how you can type code, maybe
hello.c to open up a new hello.c file.
Similarly, create.c allows you
to open up a new file as well.
So I'll go back to my code base.
I'll do cd dot dot.
And you, too, can download this file.
But I'll do cd create and type
ls, and now I see, in this case--
I'll remove hello.c.
I see create.c, which I'll
open like this-- code create.c.
So the goal of create.c is
to run it a bit like this.
If I type make create to recompile
this, I'll type dot slash create,
and I'll type maybe, hello.c.
And now I type ls again, and I should
see, I have this brand new code.c file.
I can type code hello.c, open it up, and
now I have this blank file for me here.
So create is capable of making whatever
file name I type after I type it.
But as we'll see in just a
minute, there are probably
going to be some errors in here
that we should address first.
So to test if our file has any errors
in it let's run valgrind of dot
slash create, test.c to create this file
test.c, but along the way, figure out,
are there errors we should
consider fixing in this case?
So I'll do valgrind, dot slash
create, test.c, hit Enter.
Valgrind will run.
And notice how I have
error summary down below.
I can see three errors
from three contexts.
I've definitely lost 6 bytes
and I still can reach 472 bytes,
but those bytes were still lost as well.
Or at least they were
leaked from my file.
So I'll give you a minute here to
download this file, read through.
And keep in mind these
three common memory errors.
See if you can figure out
where we've gone wrong here,
and try to fix the file as you go.
Again, remember that you
can always run valgrind
using valgrind dot slash create,
test.c, but always be sure in this case
to recompile your program
before you run valgrind.
We'll come back in one minute
while you all work on this.
All right.
So now that you've had the chance
to identify these memory errors,
let's take a look at them together.
So let's go back to
our valgrind summary,
which I can find by doing
valgrind dot slash create, test.c.
And now I'll look, and I
definitely lost 6 bytes,
and there are still
reachable these 472 bytes,
but we probably want to make sure
we don't leak those in the end.
Let's look at our first error.
Failing to free every block of
memory which we've malloc'd.
So here, let's figure
out where I used malloc.
I seem to have used it maybe on line 16
to create this space for the file name.
Did I ever free it?
It doesn't look like I did.
So I need to make sure I free this
file name after I'm done using it.
At what point am I
done using it, though?
If I scroll down below,
well, I used it for fopen,
but once I do that, I think I
can go ahead and just simply free
that file name.
So I'll run this again.
I'll do make create.
I'll do valgrind dot
slash create test.c.
And now, those 6 bytes that were
before lost are now not lost,
and I am down to two
errors from two contexts.
OK.
Let's see what else I can do.
Well, I want to keep in mind, I need
to fclose every file I've fopened.
Well, I'll look here and see, I
used fopen, but did I use fclose?
I don't seem to have used fclose.
So after I've opened this file,
what should I maybe immediately do?
Well, I should probably
just go ahead and close it.
I'll do fclose in this case, new file.
Now one thing I should also
check while I'm here is this--
fopen, again, isn't guaranteed
to work, as we saw before.
So if it doesn't work, if I can't
open this file for whatever reason,
it's good to check, is this file null?
Is this file pointer a null?
So I'll ask the question
after I open it, is new file--
or if new file is equal
to null, what should I do?
I should printf, could not create
file, backslash n, and then say return
1, for instance.
But down below, I want to make sure that
if I did successfully open this file,
I should go ahead and close it
and then free the file name.
OK, let's do this again.
So we'll do valgrind--
actually do make create.
Then valgrind dot slash
create, and then test.c.
I still see two errors
from two contexts.
But this is at least a little better.
I see all heap blocks were freed.
No leaks are possible.
So there's still something
going wrong here.
I still see two errors
from two contexts.
But I do see I'm no longer
leaking much memory.
So let's take a look at this.
Our next error was using more
memory than we've allocated.
Where might we be doing that?
Well, we malloc'd, in this case, the
size of a character times the file name
length.
But if you think about strings,
strings require more space
than just the characters
we store in them.
What else do they require?
They might require some
place for that null character
at the very end, that
terminating character that says,
this is the end of our string.
So if we went back to that valgrind
output, we might see up above--
let's see.
Invalid write of size 1.
So an invalid write means, we
wrote to some space in memory
we didn't have allocated to us.
We overwrote something we
really shouldn't have done.
But how could I do this?
Well, I could just simply
ask for more memory.
If I know that this is going to store
a string, I should probably in the end
ask for, of course, the number of
characters times the file name length.
But then, let's go
ahead and add 1 to that.
So let's say file name length plus 1
for that null character at the very end.
So now we'll go back down
below and clear the terminal.
Make create, run valgrind
of dot slash create, test.c.
And now, hopefully, fingers crossed, we
do see that all heap blocks were freed,
no leaks are possible, and we have
o errors from 0 context down below.
Now often the best way to avoid
these errors is to really avoid--
to take some preventive measures and
really be judicious or be thoughtful
about your use of malloc, in this case.
So there is probably a better
way to write this same program.
We might not need to even use malloc.
We might not even need to worry
about creating a string that
has space for a null character.
And so I actually encourage you as a
optional additional exercise to figure
out, how would you rewrite
create.c, such that you would
avoid these errors in the first place?
That's always maybe a good first step
for a programmer, is figuring out,
OK, we solved these errors, but
how could we avoid making them even
in the first place?
So I'll leave you with that.
Now this is going to bring us
to the end of our section today.
We've taken a look at pointers.
We've taken a look at
opening files, file
I/O. We've also taken a look at
malloc and common memory errors.
And this should equip
you to go off and do
this week's problem set with
confidence to tackle filter and so on.
And so I hope you enjoy
this week's problem set.
Wonderful to spend time with you.
This was CS50 and we'll
see you next time.