CARTER ZENKE: Well, hello one and
all and welcome to CS50s week eight
section.
My name is Carter Zenke.
I'm the courses
preceptor here on campus.
And the goal of these sections is to
help you bridge the gap between lecture
and this week's problem set.
So together, we'll be diving into
some HTML, some CSS, some JavaScript,
even HTTP.
We'll learn more about
all of those things
and you'll get a chance to
ask your questions for us
to work on the exercises
together and hope
by the end you have all the more comfort
and familiarity with these topics
from this week.
So if you'd like to, feel free
to say a brief hello in the chat.
And what we'll do on the count of
three, so I'll ask you all to unmute
and we'll all say hello together
from all different places
we are around the world.
So on the count of three we'll
unmute and we'll do one two three--
AUDIENCE: (EVERYONE) Hello!
CARTER ZENKE: All right, it's so good
to see your faces and hear your voices.
And this week we'll dive into a
few different topics together.
So again, this is week 8, and in week
8, we touch a lot on web programming.
What does it mean to build websites
and actually create your very own web
pages?
So this week have four different
topics we could discuss.
We have this idea of HTTP, this
idea of HTML, CSS, and JavaScript.
There's a lot of acronyms here,
so we'll try to break down
what each of these acronyms means.
But our goal will be to walk
through each of these kind of step
by step, and by the end,
have modified and created
our very own scoreboard website
all the way from scratch.
So let's start off actually with HTTP.
And could I get maybe in the chat,
what do you think HTTP stands for?
Do you remember from lecture at all?
What do you think HTTP stands for?
What does acronym even mean?
Feel free to say hello
and type in the chat.
So I'm seeing different
answers here and one of them
is Hypertext Transfer Protocol, and that
is going to be the correct answer here.
Hypertext transfer protocol,
it's kind of a mouthful.
So let's try to break it down and
talk first about that hypertext piece.
So what do you think hypertext
means in this context?
This is a hypertext transfer protocol.
What does hypertext mean in this case?
Any ideas?
Feel free to chime in in the chat.
So I'm seeing you say it's more
than text, it involves links,
maybe it's interactive text.
These are all really good ideas.
And hypertext is somewhat
of maybe a dated term now.
Hypertext referred to text that had
links inside of it that would link
to other text or other pages and so on.
And so what does that remind you of?
Perhaps a website or websites
that have these links,
this text has links to
other pages on that site.
So the hypertext part in this
hypertext transfer protocol
has to do with the language
we use or the files we
get to actually view websites with their
links to other text on their pages.
So the transfer protocol part,
though, what do you think that means?
What is a transfer protocol?
If hypertext involves interactive
text, links with text and so on,
what does the transfer
protocol perhaps mean?
So I'm seeing sending
and receiving data.
Maybe some more linking.
Other ideas?
Transfer protocol.
Requesting, I'm seeing.
Managing data from one place to another.
These are all really good ideas.
And the transfer protocol
here, the key word,
transfers, as you all
are saying, transferring
data between different users or
different computers, that is sending
and receiving data.
Maybe we're sending and
receiving this hypertext--
these files we use for our web pages.
And the protocol
involves some common set
of rules we use to
communicate between computers,
so similar to how humans have
languages, computers themselves also
need some rules to follow when
they ask each other for information
or, in this case some hypertext.
So all you need to know
for now is that you end up
using HTTP, hypertext
transfer protocol, when
you go to request a website
from a computer or some server
out there on the internet.
And for example, let's say you go
to our very own web page here using
this URL, cs50.harvard.edu, and in front
of that you prefix it with prefix it
with http colon slash slash, meaning
you want to use the hypertext transfer
protocol to access whatever
files are at cs50harvard.edu.
This is specifying how you want to
ask our servers for some information
that we have on maybe the
course website, for example.
So this is the thing we'll dive into
briefly here-- hypertext transfer
protocol or HTTP.
And the key thing to know
right now is that for HTTP, you
have maybe two computers
a bit like this,
where your computer's on
the right and maybe a server
is on the left hand side.
And you want to request some web page.
So you go to some URL.
And as we saw in lecture,
you might make a request
by sending some data to a server, and
that request is formatted in a way
that the server knows what
to expect because of HTTP.
HTTP has specified how I
should make this request.
And then by convention,
this server responds
with some code that says,
OK, maybe everything went OK.
And by convention, again, 200 tends
to mean that everything went OK
with this request.
So it will give us back some data.
And in this case, it will give
us that page you wanted to see.
So perhaps the course's website over
here that we now have access to.
It gave us that web page because
we asked for it using HTTP,
and it knows how to respond,
again, because of the rules
we defined with HTTP.
So this is what happens
when everything goes right,
but there are maybe some things
that could go wrong, right?
And so let's think about
one maybe error code
you've seen if something is not found.
Have you ever asked for some web
page and found it is not found?
So I'm seeing 404.
And this is some-- again, a
convention in HTTP is to so say,
OK, well, here is some
code we can give you to let
you know that something is not found.
So let's try this again.
And maybe we try to get access to
some page that actually isn't there.
Maybe we have a wrong URL.
So maybe that convention
make this HTTP request.
And the server then responds
by saying, oh, I don't have it.
That's a 404.
I'll instead give you back some
page noting that this is not found
so you know what's going on.
Now there are still other
errors that could happen,
and maybe you'll see this not this
week or maybe not even next week,
but later on as you build
your own websites with Python
and so on, maybe this 500 error code,
which means an internal server error.
So it might have something like this,
where I ask for a different web page.
And maybe at this
point, the server itself
runs into a problem, which means that
somewhere in the computer's programming
language on that server,
an error has happened
and it can't complete the request
I asked for, in which case,
it will give me back
convention this 500 error code
and give me back a page saying that
look, something went wrong in here.
I can't give you what you want.
So all you need to know for
now is that, again, HTTP
is this way of requesting
hypertext, some pages on a website
that you can then view on your computer.
And there are some conventions
we have for the kinds of status
codes we give to back to
you as a computer that
are making the request so you
know what is going on in the end.
Now let's actually build
our own server here.
We can do that in VS coding code
spaces using this command right here.
Http dash server.
And we saw this in lecture.
So what I'll do is go to my
own code space over here.
And I have at my fingertips some
HTML file called scoreboard.html.
And this is on my code space.
But if I wanted to turn my
code space into a server
I could make this request
to, well, I could simply
zoom in a bit here and type http
dash server, and I'll hit Enter.
And now as again we
saw in lecture, I will
see that I have this URL that I
can click on, I'll open this URL.
And now I'm using my VS code, my
code space, as its very own server.
I can now make a request
to it to ask for some files
that it has inside of it.
And here I can see I have
my scoreboard.html file,
so I could click on that
and request that file.
And I do see this text rendered for
me from the HTML now on this web page
here.
So I've made this HTTP request
to my own code space now
and it's giving me back some
file that I've requested here.
So what questions do you have so far?
We'll dive into the HTML, we'll
dive into CSS and so on later on.
But for HTTP, what questions
do you have so far?
What wonderings did you
have from lecture this week?
Right.
So not seeing too many
questions right now.
I'm seeing what does the
plus one do actually.
So we'll get into this in a little bit.
But I hit plus one, notice how I
can keep track of maybe two teams
scores here.
So this is of 80 here.
So we have a scoreboard, we're
keeping track of two teams together.
All right.
So what we'll do is just refresh
this page, reset it to zero.
And we'll go back to our HTML over here.
I can see the request I'm making
on my server at my terminal now.
But let's actually dive into the
HTML that we're going to see.
So I'll maybe stop my server
with Control C. And I'll go ahead
and code scoreboard.html.
So here I see a lot of different
tags, these tags being something
like this and this, and this
right here, called HTML tags.
And it's worth actually taking
a moment to take a break
and think about what are each
of these tags doing for us,
and what is the structure of
this page going to look like?
So let's dive into HTML
now and think about how
it gives some structure to our website.
So go back to our slides over here.
And let's talk about HTML
which stands for what?
What does HTML stand for?
So I'm seeing hypertext,
which is a familiar term now.
Markup language.
So hypertext you're familiar
with, but markup language
is a way of specifying how
we're going to build our pages.
What is the language we use to actually
give structure to our pages here?
So when I think of HTML, you might
often think of something like this.
Some code on the left hand
side is composed of these tags.
We're going to tag is something
like that HTML in braces up above
and that HTML in braces down below.
So notice here, I have an
opening tag on that second line,
that HTML, and a closing
tag on that very last line.
And how would I know it's
a closing tag down below.
Any ideas?
So I'm seeing the slash.
So in HTML, by convention,
we tend to have our closing
tags denoted by this slash over here.
But what are these tags representing?
We have all these tags, what
are they actually representing?
Well, for HTML, we're trying to build
up the structure of our website.
And this very basic HTML
page with no other elements
might look a bit like this
on the right hand side.
So we have some document element
that is encasing everything else.
This is like the highest
element, the very first element,
the very basic one on our page.
And then inside of that,
we have this HTML element
that is denoted by this HTML
tag, opening and closing.
So this open tag and
this closing tag together
constitute this HTML
element that is going
to hold all of our different
elements will build into our site.
So let's say we added
more tags to our code.
Let's say I added two of them
like head, opening and closing,
and body, opening and closing.
So this would look like on
our page something like this.
I would see, as children
of my HTML element,
I now have this head
element right over here.
And now this body element.
And notice how I'm giving
some structure to my page.
Previously, it was
just a single element,
but now I have two different
elements that kind of
correspond or are underneath or
children to this HTML element here.
And now what if I wanted
to add some more tags?
Well, I could maybe add this one--
title, opening and closing.
And then some text down
below, like hello body.
And just be clear, that text,
hello body, is not so much a tag
as it is just some text, whereas
the title and the slash title
inside of those braces there,
the greater than, less than sign,
those there are tags.
So what do you think
is going to happen--
or how is our picture going to
change on the right hand side now?
What do you think we'll see if we try to
render this in our tree-like structure
on the right hand side?
Maybe in the chat,
feel free to chime in.
We have these new tags.
Title.
I have some text, hello body.
So I'm seeing, we're
going to add a child title
to head, which is a good instinct here.
So what we'll see is if I go back
to this visual, underneath head,
we'll now have this child
called the title element, right?
Because again, it's
inside of the head element
because notice how the title tags are
all encased inside of the head tags.
That means title is a child of head.
And now underneath body,
we'll see that the hello body
text shows up inside of our tree.
And to go even further, we
could add some more text here.
We could say maybe as a child of title,
let's go ahead and have this text,
hello title.
So now we see down below hello title.
And this is an example of
what we saw in lecture,
but now just visualize for
us on the right hand side.
So when you think of HTML,
you should often think of it
as designing this tree structure.
And this structure has a name
called the document object
model or the D-O-M, the DOM for short.
And this will help you see the
structure of your web page here.
So what if we made this change now.
What if we said something like this.
We said, OK, I want to put hello body
in a paragraph tag, opening and closing.
What would change now
underneath body, do you think?
What would we see now?
Adding another node or
adding another element.
The paragraph tag will be a child
of bodies is what I'm seeing,
which is correct.
Here we're going to make
a new paragraph element--
keep in mind, the tags are
just the opening and closing
tags on the left hand side,
where we actually type in code.
The element is actually what we see
in the DOM, dominant object model
here now.
So p will be there.
As a child will then have, of
course, hello body underneath.
So now we've kind of made more
children on our page here.
So this is some structure
of a basic, basic web page.
But we have a more complicated
one actually in our code.
So let's now, with this in mind,
dive into our scoreboard.html file.
So if I'll go back to
my code space here.
I can see, well, I have a
few different elements here.
I have some familiar
ones like the HTML tag
up top and the closing
HTML tag down below.
I also have what appears to be a
head tag, which we've seen before,
and a closing head tag.
And inside of my head element,
opening and closing tag here,
I have maybe a title
and some styles defined.
So if we have this here,
we could say, OK, this
is some metadata about our site.
This is some information
that isn't really
wanting to be displayed so much
on the actual web page itself,
but is more going to define
some information about the site,
like what is its title, and what are
the styles we're applying to it here.
And then down below, not as a child
of head but just below the head,
we have the body tag,
opening and closing.
And then we have inside
of here a table, it seems.
So we'll break this down in just
a minute and we'll see a visual
for all of this, because it's
getting to be a lot right now here.
But notice how we have
many different children now
and many different tags in our page.
So let's actually try to visualize this.
We'll go back to our slides here.
And we will think about this.
We'll think about this tree
now for our current page.
So notice how we're seeing
this very same elements now.
We have that document and HTML
elements, we have the head and body.
And in the head, we had our
title element, our style element.
In body we had a table and some
script down at the bottom there.
So let's dive deeper into
the table tag, because that
seems to be what's going to be
more interesting for us here.
So in the table, we
have the table element,
kind of like this
overarching element here.
And inside of it, we
have some tr elements.
And so does anyone know what
the tr is doing for us here?
Why do we have these tr elements?
So yeah, you get table rows.
So how many rows do you
think this table will have?
And we've seen it before,
but based on HTML,
how many rows you think it'll have?
Three rows, right, because there are
three child tr elements for this table.
So we'll have a table with three rows.
And then each of those table
rows has two td elements
as children to that one.
So how many columns do you
think we'll have in this case,
if td stands for table
data, and kind of divides
our row into individual columns, how
many columns will we have overall?
I'm seeing six, which is
maybe slightly correct.
What we're going to have is six cells.
But how many columns?
Two columns, right.
Notice how every row has two columns--
really, every row has two cells.
And if every row has two
cells, we effectively
have two columns in the end.
And inside of each of these cells down
below, we see some text like team one,
team two, 00.
And over here we have plus
one and plus one inside
of a button that we can see on our page.
So let's visualize this in terms of
the tree structure we saw earlier.
What if we change this and we said,
let's visualize this top to bottom.
Well, we have some table
and we had our three rows.
This would look a bit like this,
if we just highlighted these,
and visualize those three
rows to our table now.
And now every row will have
two cells inside of it,
which means that our table
will look a bit like this.
Two cells inside of it.
On the right hand side, we
see two columns, overall.
And then inside of each
of these cells, let's say
we wanted to add some
text or some buttons.
Well, we could do that with
these elements down below.
And these will be inserted
into our new cells
because they are
children of those cells.
So we could say something
like this, where
you now have team one, square
of zero, to the square of zero,
and I have those buttons
that say plus one.
We're going to add a score
to either team in this case.
So what questions are there
on this structure so far?
All we're doing is defining
a basic table layout,
but it's not very pretty yet.
Any questions so far?
So we'll keep going here with HTML.
And our next task will be to try to add
some more elements to our scoreboard.
So the goal here is to add maybe an
h1 element, a p element, maybe a main
and a header element, a ul and an li.
So what we could do is we can
go maybe back to our code space
now and try to add in
some of these elements.
So notice how in my head tag,
my head element up above,
I have some metadata about the site.
I have a title, the styles and so on.
It would really not be good for me to
go ahead and try to add this kind of tag
to my header.
Maybe I say this is a Duke
versus UNC basketball game here.
If you're familiar with
the two collegiate rivals.
Duke versus UNC basketball game.
This would really not be a good
place to put this header here
because it's some content
that I want the user to see.
They would see this content, but because
it's a content I want the user to see,
I should more aptly put this inside my
body tag here, maybe above my table.
Structurally, I want this to show
up first before I show my table.
And then underneath, I can maybe
add this p tag for a paragraph,
to say that I want to tell the
user to click the buttons to add
a point to each team--
to each team, in this case.
And now what I can do
with these elements
added, well, I can go to my terminal
and I could run my server again.
I could say HTTP dash server.
Hit Enter.
Wait for it to load.
And now I'll click on this URL.
And I should see, hopefully, that
I do have this text on my page.
Notice how H1 showed up first.
It's the very first thing in my
body, followed by the p tag--
click the buttons to add
a point to each team.
And finally underneath,
I have my table here.
So with this in mind, we're kind of
building a structure for our site.
Well, let's go ahead and try
to add some other tags, too.
What if we try to add this main tag?
So I'll try this one.
I'll say main.
And what if I added some text like--
well, maybe not add text.
I'll just put this kind of here.
Main.
And just see what if I can
see anything happening.
I'll save my file.
I'll go back over here
and I'll refresh my page.
And I don't seem to see
anything different here.
But why would that happen, do you think?
I do have this new tag called
main, opening and closing.
But why would I not see it on my page?
It's empty, which is fair.
So let me go ahead
and try changing that.
Instead of this, I'll make this
maybe the main part on page.
Let's say I want this tech to
be the main part of the page.
I want to tell the user that they
should click the buttons to add
a point to each team.
OK, I'll refresh the page now.
And it looks slightly different,
like the table moved up,
but it's not really
changing how the text looks.
So what's the point of main?
Does anyone want to hazard
a guess in the chat?
Yes, so I'm seeing some folks talk
about semanticness or sectioning.
And it's actually a good idea.
So here, notice how if I have the p
tag and the h1, I refresh the page,
these show up pretty differently.
I see h1 in huge text and I
see p in much smaller text.
Now main, though, didn't seem
to have much of an effect, here.
And that's because what
main is doing is not
so much visual as it is more semantic.
And by semantic, we mean it's
changing the structure-- or really not
structure.
It's changing the importance of
certain sections of our pages.
So if you look at a
search engine like Google,
Google will look at all of your
HTML files, figure out how to index
or show your site to others.
And if I wanted to help Google figure
out what is the main part of my page,
well, I could use this main tag.
I could simply, maybe, encase this part.
Like let's say not the title, but
really the paragraph here and the table
itself.
That's the main part of my page that I
want Google to really pay attention to.
Well, I could do this.
I could make sure that table
and p are children of main,
thereby making sure
that Google knows, look,
what comes after or is a child to
main is pretty important for my site.
It is the main content that I have.
If I refresh the page
here, nothing happens.
It's all the same.
But now if somebody were to read my
site, look at my HTML like Google,
for example, they would be able to
see that this stuff down below is
a little more important, helping
to section off this content here.
I'm seeing a few questions here.
So do you have any links or websites or
HTML tags or elements that we can use?
So certainly.
If you're looking at other
tags you might want to use
or other elements you could
use, I'd encourage you to simply
maybe Google for some of those.
You could-- I know a
good resource is W3.
You can say W3Schools HTML
tags reference, for example.
And you could-- let me zoom in a bit.
Click on this one right here.
And here we have all the HTML
tags ordered, alphabetically.
So these are all HTML tags you can
use to create elements of your site.
So feel free to look up that on
Google if you'd like to figure out
a reference for all of your tables.
All right.
So again, there's a difference
between these more visual tags
like this h1, and these more semantic
tags, like main, for example.
Other questions here, too, on
these tags, these elements?
A question on whether main helps for
accessibility like screen readers.
It can.
So if you have a screen
reader, something
is trying to read your site for somebody
who's using a computer, often having
these more semantic tags is helpful
because you can tell somebody what
is the main content of your page,
what should the screen reader actually
focus on reading?
Maybe I don't want it to read
everything, like not the title so much.
Maybe I just want it to
read this text down here.
So by delineating this, I
can tell the screen reader
what I want it to focus on as
somebody else looks at my site.
Good question.
I see a question also
on interactive buttons,
how do we make interactive buttons.
We'll get to that in just a
minute using some JavaScript.
But as a sneak peek
down below, we'll see
we have our buttons defined down
here and we have some JavaScript
down below to help those buttons work.
We'll get to that in just a little bit.
So what questions are there
now on HTML tags or elements?
OK, not seeing too many.
What our website looks like
right now is not super pretty.
Like, it just has this big h1,
this paragraph text right in it.
And that's OK, but we could
probably do a little better.
You can really make the site look
a little more clean, a little more
aesthetic and so on.
That's where CSS comes in.
So let's dive into CSS now.
And let's try thinking
about how we could use this.
But first, what does CSS stand for?
What are we going to do with
CSS and what does it stand for?
So a cascading stylesheet, right.
So CSS stands for Cascading Style Sheet.
And now the style sheet probably
is kind of self-explanatory,
meaning that we're going to
apply some styles to our site.
It's a sheet of styles to apply.
But what does the cascading part mean?
Does anyone know?
What is the C in CSS?
So I'm seeing inheritance, nice.
So if we looked at our visual,
for example, of our table,
notice how it kind of
looks a bit like a tree,
and we had this vocabulary of
children of certain elements here.
So button is a child of td.
Well, if I applied
some style to td, well,
that style might also apply to
some of the children of that node.
So it helps to show that this style,
it kind of follows the inheritance
principle would mean that children
the same styles or similar styles
as their parents at least sometimes.
OK.
So let's explore CSS now.
And when we're talking about CSS, we
often talk about this kind of syntax
on the left hand side.
We have our structure
already for us, but now I
want to apply some style to it.
So we can often do this using the
syntax on the left hand side here.
We have a selector to determine
what element in our DOM
or in our website you want to
select, and then what property
do you want to change?
Meaning what kind of style
you want to add, and then
what value should that property have?
So for example, let's
take a look at this.
Let's say I want to select
all the buttons on my page.
I could do it like this.
I could say, select me
all the buttons using just
that plain old button syntax up top.
And change their background color
using this property defined for us
called background dash color to be red.
And now I would see behind
me that my buttons are red.
I could also add some more style
to that very same selector.
I could, again, select all my buttons,
make the background color red,
but also add some border.
So a border is some
property in CSS you can use.
And again, by convention,
we define the border
using this syntax here-- maybe a 4pt
or a 4px, whatever system you're using.
And then dash, to denote that
I want the border to be dash.
We can also do solid if we'd like, too.
So notice how my
buttons have changed now
to be red, and also have this
kind of dash border around them.
And if you're curious about all of
the different properties you can use,
you could look up a similar reference.
So I can go maybe to W3Schools again.
I could search for not a
HTML tag reference, but also
search for a CSS properties reference.
Now I'll go down here, I see
CSS reference from W3 schools.
I'll click on this.
And now I see all of the
CSS properties I could
use to add some styles to my code.
For example, there is accent
color, animation, backdrop filter.
There's so many CSS
properties you can use.
And if you click on any one of
these, like background for example,
you'll be able to see
some examples of how
you might use that CSS property for
certain elements in your web page.
So let's keep going with this
and look at a few different ways
to change some of the
colors on our page.
And maybe one thing we'll run
into is that we really want
these buttons to be different colors.
They're different teams, right?
So how could I change the color
for these buttons, do you think?
Feel free to type in the chat.
How can I make the
buttons a different color?
So I'm seeing different kinds
of selectors or classes or IDs.
So it's good that we have
some vocabulary here already.
And let's focus first on
this vocabulary of an ID.
So an ID in CSS is this idea that I'm
trying to select a particular element
and I've given some
element in my HTML page
a particular ID, some unique
ID I can refer to it with.
So here, let's say I wanted to make the
colors different-- one red, one blue.
Well, I can select different
buttons by their ID.
And if I'm going to select
by ID, I need to use
this hashtag before that selector
to say, I am selecting by ID.
So I can do hashtag,
team one dash button,
give me the selection for
a team one button there.
And hashtag team two dash
button team to give me
a selection for team two button.
And this supposes-- it
presupposes that in our HTML page
that do have some text like this.
That the buttons do have an ID
attribute specified in the HTML.
So on the left hand
side, we have our CSS.
On this side, we have
our IDs and our HTML.
And notice how every button
does have this ID defined for us
where one is team one
button and the other
is team two button, using the
ID equals and some certain text.
So we can select by ID.
We could also do what's called
a class selector so maybe
the ID is good for this.
But I wanted to change
just the header gray,
I could select all the td's using
just that td selector and change
the background color
to be gray, like this.
But that's not quite what I want.
I only wanted the top td's to be
actually a background color of gray.
So I could apply a class.
A class lets me apply
some element or some style
to any elements that
have that same class.
Notice how I'm not using the
hashtag anymore-- that was for IDs.
I'm using the dot for classes, saying
that every element with the class title
should get this style
of defined in here.
So for example, if I look at my
HTML, I must have this defined now.
I should make sure that every element
that I want to apply this style to
has that same class on
the right hand side.
So what questions are there
on these selectors or classes?
I'm seeing one question here.
So what would the perks be of using
classes over IDs and vise versa?
So classes are good
when you want to define
some style across multiple elements.
So let's say I wanted to apply this
to two td's, but not the rest of them.
A class would be great.
But if I wanted to apply a style
to a particular element, only
a single element, an ID
would be useful there.
So classes can apply to multiple
elements, IDs apply to one element.
And a question here, too, can
we use RGB codes in the CSS
instead of using text like red or
blue or gray as I've shown here?
So you absolutely can.
In CSS, you're allowed to define
colors in a variety of ways.
And let me actually try to do
the same thing in my code space.
I'll go back over here.
And let's say I wanted,
well, this button here
to be a dark blue background, and this
one to be like a light blue background.
So I can go up top here and I could
add some CSS in my style page up here.
I have to add this to my style element.
I'll say, let me select the
add one button using its ID.
Hashtag add one.
And then I'll go in and I'll say this.
I'll say that I want the background
color to be, maybe in this case--
I'll look up a different
actual hex code here.
So I'll maybe look up
Duke University blue.
And I'll go to the
colors brand guide here.
I should go down below and I do see Duke
Navy blue, if you all can see it, too,
is this hex code-- hashtag 012169.
I'll copy and paste it.
I'll go back to my scoreboard,
add this element here.
And now if I refresh
the page, I should see--
if it loads, a Navy blue
background in that same color.
But maybe it's going to give
me a minute to load here.
OK, we'll wait for that to load.
But in general, you can use this
kind of syntax here with hex codes,
or you could do something like this.
I could say RGB, and you could also
do some combination of RGB colors.
I could say 128, 255, maybe
0 here to create some color.
I don't need to just say
blue or light blue or so on.
Let me go ahead and see some other ones.
Question about IDs.
Can they only be used once?
So yes.
The definition of an ID is
it can only be used once.
If I go down below here, notice how
this button is labeled add one, right?
I can't then apply this same ID to
this button down here, I'll add to.
I can't do this.
Each one has to have its own unique ID.
Let me look at some
other questions here.
Wouldn't it be better to use a class
like blue button or red button?
A class is great if you know you want
to have multiple red or blue buttons.
If I wanted this to be not the
only button I have, but maybe
multiple buttons that are
blue, a class would be great,
because again, an ID
is a bit of a show--
one element here.
Another question here,
does CSS only work in HTML?
So here we're defining our CSS inside of
our HTML page using the style element,
but we don't have to.
We could define, if we wanted
to, our very own CSS file here.
I could code maybe styles, styles.css.
And I could add--
I could simply just
take all of my styles
here, copy and paste
them over to styles.css.
And now I've separated
those styles away.
I do have to be sure
though that in my HTML,
I have a link element that
links in my styles.css.
And you can look up how to link
in your stylesheet if you'd like,
but here we'll focus for now just
on creating our styles inside
of our HTML page itself.
OK, let's see if this might have loaded.
I'll go back to what I had before.
OK, I'll save that.
I'll go over here, hit refresh.
And now I see that is
a dark blue button.
And maybe I could, just for
consistency, look up UNC blue.
I'll go ahead and over here
look up, UNC blue hex code.
And it seems that it's
hashtag 7BAFD4, by chance.
And I'll go ahead and say
for the add two button,
let's make that background color this.
I'll refresh the page again.
And now I see that that has
that now, UNC blue color here.
So other questions on this CSS?
So one final thing I'd like to
do is maybe try to make sure
that my text is centered.
This is a good use case for a
class, as you all have been saying.
So maybe I want to say multiple elements
in my page, I want to be centered.
So what I could do is I could
make a new class called centered.
And I could say that a
property of this class
is that the text alignment,
text align is centered.
And if I looked up CSS
properties, I would
know that text align line is a way
of aligning some text on the page.
And center, if I give
it that value, will
mean that my text will be centered.
So now I can go to my h1 over
here and apply that class.
I could say that the class
for this is centered,
the same thing I have defined up here.
Notice how I'm not using the
dot-- the dot is just for CSS.
Select any element with this class.
And in my p tag, my p element,
also say, this is centered, too.
And now I can refresh the
page, and hopefully I'll
see my text now centered on that page.
OK.
Other questions here before we move on?
Ah, great question.
Why not just make body centered?
Oh, nice.
So some design questions coming up here.
If I want everything to
be centered in my body,
why don't I just apply it higher up?
I could say body as this class centered.
And I could perhaps take it
off of h1 and take it off of p.
I'll save my file, refresh
it, and see if that works.
It does.
And now I've used fewer
pieces of text on my page.
I've also made it clear
that I want my entire body
to have text that is centered.
A great comment.
OK.
So just to preempt some questions.
One thing we wondered about before
was, how does this button work?
I can click plus one
here and plus one here.
And I see that I'm getting a different
number on the page for each team.
But how could I try to get
a feel for how this works?
Well, if I look at my
page, I'll go down below
and I'll see that I have
this script tag here.
Opening tag for script and
closing tag for script.
And inside of this--
inside of this, I have some
variables and a lot of text over here
that might not make much
sense to us at first.
And this is an example of JavaScript.
So JavaScript is now
embedded in our page.
And this text will run, top to bottom,
whenever our web page is loaded.
So at the time that I refresh this page,
this script runs from top to bottom
and it finishes, likely.
So what I'll do is I'll try
to break this down for you
and see if we can understand a
bit of what JavaScript is doing.
It's a little bit different than you
might expect from a C code or Python
code that you're used to so far.
So we'll go back to
our slides over here.
And we'll try to think about the way
that JavaScript is working for us.
So on our page, we
notice the script tag.
And up top when our page loads, we're
going to run this code top to bottom.
So the very first thing we'll
do is create two new variables,
one called team one and one called
team two, and set them equal to zero.
So I'll say team one over here is going
to be zero, and team two over here
is going to be zero.
So pretty basic stuff.
But next, we actually have
something a little bit different.
Maybe we haven't seen this before.
We have some text like
document, dot, dot, dot some
other things that happen after
it, equals some function,
and that function is defined for us.
So we're saying that some entity,
some attribute, equals some function.
It gets the value of some function.
In JavaScript, the goal is
often to define some events
that the user can do on
the page and then define
what should happen when
the user takes that event.
So a script, in this sense, is mostly
trying to set up something to happen,
something to be triggered
later on, and define
the code we want to have
running when that event happens.
So this is what that code is doing here.
It's kind of metaphorically
doing this for us.
We're trying to set
up some kind of button
over here, that when
that button is pressed,
I want to run some kind of code--
the function we've defined.
And by setting this kind of entity
equal to this function here,
I'm wiring this button
to that piece of code.
Now whenever I trigger this, maybe
when the user clicks on a button,
for example, I will then
run this piece of code.
So this script has set up this
trigger for me, for the user,
to actually run this code later
on when I press that button there.
And the same thing for
what happens afterwards.
So I see document, blah, blah,
equals some function that we define.
And again, what this is doing is saying
that when I press a particular button
or take action, I want to run some
function in response to the user here.
So I'm going to break this
down a little bit more
and actually dive deeper into what
these dot, dot, dots are doing.
So on the code itself we'll
see document.querySelector,
hashtag add one.
This is like our first
step in that code.
And what looks familiar here?
Already.
What have we maybe seen before?
The hashtag and the ID.
OK, so what do you think this is doing?
Just based on the semantics of it,
with the text that we're reading.
Document.querySelector.
It's selecting some element and it's
selecting the element that has this ID.
So document.querySelector is a way of
saying go through my document object
model, go through your HTML elements
and find me that one that has the ID,
add one.
OK, so let's visualize this.
So when I run this piece of code, I
will go through my document object model
and I will try to find that
element that has the ID add one.
I'll start here, keep searching,
keep searching, keep searching,
going down through my tree.
Searching, searching, searching,
until I get to that button that does
have that ID add one.
And now I have selected that button.
I now have it kind of inside of,
quote unquote, my JavaScript code,
and I can add an attribute
to it or change how it works.
And in particular, I'd like
to find some attribute called
the on-click attribute.
So document.querySelector,
hashtag add one.
That gives me that button
with the ID, add one.
And then dot on click is saying
that I want the attribute called
on click of this button to
be equal to this function,
meaning that when the user clicks this
button, I want to run this function,
in this case.
So let's get a visual for this here.
We'll go back to our code.
And we'll see what's going on inside.
So we're kind of familiar with this now.
We're selecting our element
with the ID add one,
saying that when it is clicked,
I want to run this function here.
But what are we doing?
What is this line of code doing?
Team one equals team one plus one.
What is that doing for us?
Incrementing the score, right.
So we'll say team one is currently
zero, but we'll add one to it.
So the first time I
click that button, zero
will become one, then two, then
three, as I click this button.
And then what am I doing here?
We've seen this before.
What am I selecting now?
Some data.
More particularly though,
what am I selecting?
I see hashtag score one.
So I'm selecting the element
with the ID score one.
Well, what is that?
That is this text up here, this table
data that has an zero inside of it,
initially.
But what I could do is
change its inner HTML.
The inner HTML attribute I will
change to be what team one is.
So on my page, I'm literally
kind of going in here.
I'm selecting this element here, getting
its inner HTML, this part, and saying,
that becomes whatever team one is,
which can be as one, or two, or three.
So it changed my HTML
for me more dynamically.
And just to prove the point to you,
what I can do is comment this out.
I could remove this and
remove this down here.
And now notice how if
I refresh the page--
go back over here, refresh the page.
I hit plus one, but I
don't see the change.
The variable itself is
updating in JavaScript,
but it's not actually
updating on my page, right?
So let me try this.
Let me go ahead and uncomment this.
And now I'll show you the page source.
I'll go ahead and do this.
Show you my page source over here, go
into the main part, table, table body.
This second row of tr's.
And now I see that ID
score one, and score two.
Well, I'll click plus one now.
Let me refresh the page again.
Plus one, and I see it changing as I go.
So notice how if I zoom in
maybe just a little bit more
on this right hand side,
I see that number updating
as I go through on both sides.
Now some handy tips as you're
working in JavaScript--
this often won't work as you intend
it to from the very beginning.
So let's say in my code,
I had some syntax error.
I typed plus one and then made
a missing keystroke, like this.
Some random text in my code.
This is maybe kind of obvious to
me, but if I'm running on a page
now, I refresh the page, well,
I don't see things not working.
I mean, I see them not
working, but I don't know why.
I hit plus one here, plus one over here.
But what is wrong?
I don't know.
What I can do is actually
go over to my console.
And this might be named different
things in a different browser.
But in Chrome, it's called console.
And I see my JavaScript console.
And I can see some errors here.
Uncaught Syntax error,
unexpected identifier, awejf.
So that is a clarification or
a hint to me saying that look,
I need to go ahead and go
look at my JavaScript code
again and think of my syntax, which
will allow me to get rid of this
so I can fix that error there.
So not to worry if your code doesn't
work as intended at the very beginning.
It's always helpful to
have some console over here
to help you figure out what
is actually going wrong.
So questions on this JavaScript so far?
Are we feeling OK?
So I'm seeing a good question here.
This question is, what is
the difference between dot
on click, or this on click
attribute, and saying
add event listener for a click.
So there are maybe two
ways I could approach this.
One way is this way as
I've done below here.
I'm saying that I want
to get the add one button
and set its on-click
attribute to be this function.
I could also do this.
I could say, let me get
my button that has the ID,
add one, and then make sure
that it has some event listener.
And event listener, where an event
is some action the user takes.
Maybe they make a click, right?
And then what I could do
is specify the function
I want to run when the user clicks.
And I think the syntax
will be a bit like this.
Function, dah, dah, dah.
And now I can define the function I
want to run when this button is clicked.
And I'll just put dot,
dot, dots here for now.
These are the very same thing.
All this is doing is simply
setting up some function
to run when this button is clicked.
And it just so happens that
a button-- because it's
so common to click
buttons, buttons already
have an attribute, a
built-in attribute called
on click, that allows me to
define a function that they
should run when the button is clicked.
But I could add this event
listener to not just a button
but some table or some text.
If I want something to happen
when I click some text,
I could add this event listener called
click or add this event listener,
listen for a click and then
run some function in the end.
So I hope that helps clarify
the difference-- really,
the lack of a difference between
these two approaches here.
Other questions here?
How do the page update?
Is it from the server or the client?
This is a good question.
So the page always updates
when I request it to update.
So notice how I can hit Refresh
up on my top left hand sidebar,
and you probably can, too.
When I hit Refresh, I then make
another request to the server to say,
give me the latest page
that you see there.
And the server then gives
me that back, that page.
So the update process is both
from the client and the server,
in the sense that myself, the client,
the user, I have to ask for a new page,
and the server then has to give it
back to me through my HTTP protocol.
OK.
So one final touch
that we'll make here is
trying to figure out how we could
determine a team that wins this game.
And ideally, we'd love for
a team to win the game,
maybe when they have a
certain number of points.
And we can maybe alert the user
to say that this team has won.
So let's say we want a team to
win when they get to eight points.
Well, we could do this
in a few different ways.
And in JavaScript, we have this way of
asking a question using that same if
statement from before.
So very familiar to us.
We can go back to our code here.
And maybe we could ask the
question at the very end
and say, if team one is greater
than 10, well, let's go ahead and--
not print, but alert the user
that team one has won, like this.
And we could also ask the
other question saying, OK,
if team two is greater
than 10, what's wrong here?
That's right.
Sorry.
Team two has won.
Like that.
But if I were to run this and I
go to my scoreboard over here,
hit Refresh and go to team one, I can
go way past 10 without getting notified
or alerted.
So what's the problem?
Take a look at my code here.
I do have this conditional.
But why didn't I get alerted?
There is no else, that's true.
So we have to keep in mind that this
script runs top to bottom as soon as I
refresh that page, or I ask for it.
I load the page.
So here I will refresh the page.
And now that script is done running.
I've run from top to bottom.
So what would happen there?
Well, I would see that team
one is zero, team two is zero.
I will set up my event listeners
here, define the functions
I want to run when the
user clicks the button,
and then I'll ask that question,
is team one greater than 10,
is team two greater than 10?
Well, I haven't put this in a loop.
I'm just going to ask that question
at the beginning and only once.
So where would it be more appropriate
for me to ask this question?
I could do a while loop
but I really only need
to ask the question when
I click on a button.
And I can maybe do this if I
said OK, well, let me go ahead
and update the score and
then ask that question.
I'll say if team one is greater
than 10, let's alert the user.
And for consistency, I'll keep my braces
on the same line, like we have up here.
And I'll do the same thing in team two.
Over here.
I'll do this.
So now I'm asking this
question every time
I click the button, because all
this is doing is setting up,
whenever this button is clicked,
run this function, every time.
So I'll go refresh the page here.
I'll hit plus one on team one, ,
plus, plus, plus, again, and again,
and again.
Now we're at 10 points.
But if I get to 11,
well, team one has won.
So I've pressed the button, updated
the score, asked the question,
and now it is true that team
one is greater than 10 points.
And we're saying, what if it's a draw?
Well, we could do this.
We could-- actually,
that's a good question.
Let's hit Refresh here.
Get team one to 10 points,
get team two to 10 points.
And in the end one team does have to
score the point here, so maybe give it
to team two and now team two has won.
But I could also maybe say, oh, team one
gets one more point, now they've won.
So there's probably some
more logic to add here,
but I could leave that
part up to you for now.
Here we're just trying to
figure out if the team has
a certain number of points in the end.
So what questions do you have on this
implementation of JavaScript here?
Which jobs can we do
with the document tag?
Feel free to ask more
specifically, too, if you'd like.
I can answer your question here.
But if we look at this
document tag, I believe
maybe you're referring to this one?
The goal of this one is simply
to say the name of our file,
like the HTML file.
This is going to be an HTML file.
The dock type of this will be HTML.
And just to show our visual again
with a document element above,
go back to my slides over here.
Let me find this, actually.
I think it was up here.
The document we have at the very top.
This is simply, by
convention, all HTML files
do have this kind of document
element at the very top.
And it's a way of starting at the
top of our file and moving down.
So notice how in our JavaScript code--
in our JavaScript code over here, we
started with document.querySelector.
So that's saying start at the document
element, that very top level element,
and go ahead and find me that
element that has the ID, add one.
A question here.
How do you decide the
size of your buttons?
Well, that's a good job for CSS.
So CSS has these properties
like width or height
you could use to determine
the size of your button,
as long as you apply those
styles to your button.
Question here, would a CSS
file have a dock type tag, too?
In fact, it actually wouldn't.
And I think this is, again, just
something that was decided long ago,
there's not so much a reason for it.
If I go to my code
space here and show you
the CSS file we really didn't
use here codestyles.css,
I don't need to have a
dock type tag up here.
All right.
So I'm seeing some other questions here.
And I'm happy to stick
around and answer those.
But for now, let's
actually wrap officially.
This is our entire section.
We've gotten through adding some
HTML elements, styling them with CSS,
and then adding some JavaScript
to make our code interactive.
So we'll probably end
officially here, but thank you
all so much for coming today.
It was wonderful to see you
and we'll see you next time.