CARTER ZENKE: OK, well hello, one
and all, and welcome to CS50s week
9 section, this week where
a lot of it comes together.
My name is Carter Zenke.
I'm the courses
preceptor here on campus.
And the goal of these
sections that we host online
is to help you bridge
the gap between lecture
and this week's problem
you'll be working on.
In this case, you're building our
own web application using Flask.
And so today we'll dive into
these three topics here.
Flask and Jinja, how we can
use forms in our websites,
and how we can work with databases
and build more dynamic applications
overall.
So I thought to kick things
off, we do what we normally
do and maybe on the count of three,
we'll all unmute and say hello,
so a big chorus of hellos
to kick things off.
So on the count of three.
We'll do one, two, three.
AUDIENCE: Hello!
CARTER ZENKE: All right.
It's so good to hear all of
your voices here together.
And again, our goal will be to go
through these three topics right here.
And again, this is
going to be interactive.
So if you have questions about these
three topics as we work through them,
please feel free to message
them in the chat or chime
in when I ask for responses here.
Now we'll dive into Flask and Jinja.
And as we saw in lecture,
Flask and Jinja are these two--
well, Flask is more like
a framework we can use
and Jinja is this templating
library we can use along with Jinja.
But the goal is to build more
dynamic applications than you could
with just HTML, CSS, and JavaScript.
So we saw those three languages--
HTML, CSS, and JavaScript--
in the prior week, week eight.
But we saw some limitations of them.
Maybe if you've worked
on the homepage problem--
you've been doing a lot
of copying and pasting,
or you weren't able to do
everything you wanted to do.
Well, Flask comes in to help
you build something that
is going to be more dynamic for you.
And one of my favorite examples
of this, of a more dynamic website
that Flask can enable us to build
is something like this one right
here, libraryofbabel.info.
And you can actually go to this site.
This site is based on the book,
Library of Babel by Jorge Luis Borges.
And in this book, this
author imagines this library
that has all the possible
stories that have ever
been written, the stories
have been written before us,
ahead of us, currently right
now, because every book contains
these random assortments
of the 26 characters.
This is an infinite
library with infinite books
and contains all the possible
stories that have been written
or could be written.
And we can actually build our
own website along the same,
but let's check out this
one just to be sure.
So you can go to this you URL
right here, libraryofbabel.info.
And I'll do the same
over here on my computer.
I'll go over here.
And you might see a home page
like this, if I zoom in for you.
And you can see we can browse this
library to see what is inside of it.
I'll click browse here.
And maybe I'll choose to go to like
the first section of this library.
I'll go to section zero down here.
I'll click on it.
And I see I'm in this room
with four walls around me.
So maybe I'll click on this wall, wall
one, and I'll see this shelf of books,
right?
And I'll look, maybe just at this
third shelf, just randomly, now.
And I'll go down to, let's
say this book right here.
Let's pick one randomly from the shelf.
And you'll see that I have
this page full of just
lots of random bits of text.
But the idea is, there are so
many books in this library,
full of so many pieces of random
text, that all the stories that could
possibly be made are somewhere in here.
And so if you take my
word for it, we actually
go to the search function
for this website.
I'll go back to the home page
here by going to that slash route.
And I'll go down to
search at this point.
Maybe I'll search in this library.
And I can Enter up to a certain
number of characters here.
Maybe I'll search for this is CS--
and I can't type 50.
I'll say this is computer
science fifty week nine section.
I'll zoom in so you can see it there.
And I want to find out where is this
text in this infinite library of books?
So I'll go down and I'll hit Search.
And I can see down below, it shows
up in a few different places.
I can see the places it shows up
with random characters around it.
So I'll click this one, it
looks like it's on page 61.
I can see it highlighted here.
This is computer science
fifty week nine section--
whoops-- right down in here.
And this is on page
61 of some random book
that we can see the
location of down here.
And we can go back over here.
We can search for other places, too.
Maybe with some other English words.
This is another book that
it's in right over here.
And so we can look at all of
these books and see all the places
that this phrase shows up.
And all this is done just by virtue
of taking in some random text
and figuring out what it might make out
of the randomness that we have here.
So if we think about how this website
is made, let's think about some
of the routes we can
go to-- some of places
we can explore at the
very basics first here.
So if we go back to
our slides over here.
We think of a website
often having these routes
we can go to see different parts of it.
And so if I look at this, you'll notice
that I have this slash at the end.
If I go to libraryofbabel.info
and put a slash at the end,
I'm asking for the
home page of this site.
Give me the very basic
page of this site.
The very initial site I want to see.
But I could also go to, as we saw,
slash-- this is the home page here.
I could also go to slash browse.cgi.
And this is just a name that
the author of this website
kind of made up browser-- browse.cgi
sounded OK for their purposes.
And when I ask for
this route, browse.cgi,
we'll all see something different.
I'll go down here and see I--
OK, I can see some library of books I
can click on and browse in this case.
And because I have all of this, I'm able
to see different parts of the website.
And I ask the server different pieces
to give me back different other pieces
of the site I'm looking for.
We could even, if we wanted
to, add some parameters to it
and look at particular books, if we
wanted to, using something like this,
having parameters and these
dot dot dots at the end here.
Now how is this really working?
You can imagine this website is
full of these HTML pages look a bit
like this, right?
And maybe if you were working
on home page last week,
you could think of it like this.
Or we have maybe trillions of
HTML pages full of different text.
And let's see.
So if I were to request a page
from this server right here,
I can make an HTTP request.
I might say this.
Give me the slash browse.cgi page.
I'll do this.
You're going to get back a
200 code for everything's OK,
and give me back that page over here.
But now, if I wanted to
see the text of this site,
well, I could think
of it a bit like this.
Go over here.
I might see on the right hand
side, well, some text up here on--
sorry, the left hand side and then
some HTML on the right hand side.
And again, if you're working
on a homepage last week,
you might have seen
something like this, where
I could actually try to put in
the random string of text here.
But how many pages would we need
to have all of this kind of text?
If it's all random, it's all a
combinations of these 26 characters,
how many HTML pages would we possibly
need here if we had so many of these?
Feel free to chime in in the chat.
How many would we really need to
have all combinations of these 26
characters?
I'm seeing a lot.
We need a lot of pages,
right, for all of these 26
characters, all combinations of them.
And so if we had
trillions of these pages,
well, that's not very efficient for us.
We could do, instead, probably better,
is we could actually have a single HTML
page and we could just kind of slot in
some random string of text to that page
using something like Python
or Flask, in this case.
So we could do something
like this, where
instead of having millions
and millions of pages that
have all these random strings
of text, we could have one page
and we could use Python to slot
in a single random string for us--
perhaps in this placeholder
right over here.
So let's actually explore
how we could build
our own mini-version
of this website, where
we can generate random
strings of text and see
if we find any interesting, useful
information from that piece of text.
So I'll go to my code space over here.
And I've already set up
this Flask application.
I can zoom in a bit.
And I'll type ls.
And you can see I have
these files down below.
I have app.py, I have helpers.py,
which is a similar file name
you'll see in this week's problem set.
I have history.db, and I
have a templates folder.
And just to refresh our memory,
what do you think will go in app.py?
I mean, what language is that
written in and what do you
think we'll put inside of
it, as we saw in lecture?
Feel free to chime in in the chat.
What will go inside of app.py.
So I'm seeing Python, Flask.
Right, yeah, this is we're
going to write some of our code
that will be written
in Python, and we'll
use the Flask library inside of app.py.
So I can open that up a little bit.
I'll code app.py, and
we'll get you a taste
of what this is doing for us, which
we'll explore in much more depth
later on.
OK, this is our basic Flask app.
Now though, I also have
history.db up here.
And knowing what we know about dot
db files, what kind of file is this?
History.db.
It's a database, right?
So we have some application,
app.py will write our Flask code,
and we also have this
database called history.db.
And inside of templates, what
do you expect we might find?
If I were to cd into
templates to look inside.
HTML, right.
So I could cd templates here.
I'll type ls, list my files.
And I'll see two HTML files,
index.html and layout.html.
So let's get a feel for what
this is doing for us already.
So I'll type ls to see my
application files here.
I'll then type Flask run
to run this application.
This is different from HTTP server.
I want to run this
application using Flask.
So I'll do Flask run, hit Enter.
And now I should see shortly a URL
pop up, or I can open it down below.
And now I should see this very
basic website, Library of Babel
with a search history down below.
Now this is not presently done yet.
For one, there's no text on the screen.
Ideally, you'd want to have some
random string of tax we'd actually
generate every time we
visit this site to see
if we get any meaningful words from it.
So if we look at our
application here, I'll
go ahead and open up a new terminal.
And I will get back to my
library folder and I'll
code app.py to pull up this file.
So here is our very
basic Flask application,
if y'all can see at this text size.
Let me know if you can't.
From lines one through four, what
would you say we're doing here?
If we're going to break this down top to
bottom, what are we doing in lines one
through four?
What's the purpose of these
lines of code, just in general?
Seeing some imports.
Other things you might think, too?
Setting up library
access, yes, definitely.
So here on lines one through four,
we're simply telling our application,
these are the libraries we're
going to use in our program.
Pieces of code somebody
else has written for us.
We'll use these in our application.
Notice how I'm using the CS50 library
here to get something called SQL.
I'm using the Flask library here to
get something called Flask, also,
and also this render template
function, and something called request.
And I also have from helpers
import random strings.
So notice how I had back in my
list of files here, helpers.py.
Well, I could open up helpers.py
here to show you what's inside.
And I do have this function that
I defined called random string.
And if I give it some variable
called len, some argument called len,
I'll then get back a random string
that has that length of characters.
So if I said random string 500, I would
get a string of 500 random characters.
And I made this myself.
But instead of putting it inside
of my app.py, what I did instead,
sort of copy and paste this
into app.py, is I said, well,
I want to keep things separate here.
I'll put this helper function
inside of helpers.py.
Similar to what you'll see this week
with the finance problem set over here.
OK.
And then finally, we're just
importing the random library
so we can get access to
some of its functions.
We'll see those later on in a bit.
Now down below is where we
get a little more interesting.
So here on line six
as we saw in lecture,
we're kind of setting up our
Flask application to run.
You could think of this
piece of code, right here,
capital F, Flask, as being this
template for a Flask application,
that comes with some
built in functionality,
like the ability to say what we want to
do when we visit a route, for example,
on our website.
But here we're saying, let's make
a particular Flask application,
and let's make sure that it
corresponds to this current file--
that's what dunder name
here it's something
for us-- underscore underscore name,
underscore underscore [INAUDIBLE]
dunder name, is going to say build me a
particular Flask app based on this file
right here.
And for the rest of this
file, let's just call it app.
We could call it something else.
We could call it library here.
But notice how we have to
change everything else.
We have to say library.config
or library.route.
So in the end, it's probably
easier to call it app throughout,
this kind of short name we can use
to refer to our own Flask application
we're building from this file.
Now down below, we also have
some connection to our database
as we saw in lecture.
This is saying, give me
some variable called db,
that I can then use to refer to
this database called history.db
that will access using sqlite.
And then down below, let me
just have some configuration
to say that I want my HTML to
auto reload when I change it.
So if I go to an HTML,
make a change, I want
to see that change kind of
automatically in my browser.
And then finally, this little
bit of code down here--
at app.route.
Where have we seen this slash before?
What does it often correspond
to in our applications?
We saw this just a little bit ago.
Yeah, so I'm seeing the
root folder, the home page.
Whenever we ask for the
slash root of an application,
we're often asking for that main
page-- that home page of the site.
And so the hint here is that at
app.route, if I say slash here,
that's going to say,
well, I'm going to define
some function I can run
whenever the user requests
the slash root of my application.
And then down below, notice how I
have this function called index.
I'm going to define, again,
some function I can use to--
function I can use when the
user asks for that slash root,
I will run this function top to
bottom every time they ask for it.
And in this case, it looks
like I'm just returning
the result of this function,
render template index.html.
So I'm giving back the home page,
which is what we saw, again,
when I went to my slash root here.
I then see my home page of my
site that's inside of index.html.
So questions on this syntax so far?
Feel free to ask in the chat.
This is kind of a lot
all at once, but I want
to make sure we get
your questions answered.
OK.
So feel free to keep putting
questions in the chat.
I see one coming in.
Where are the imported libraries
actually imported from?
So presumably, these libraries
are somewhere on your computer.
And in fact, they're probably in some
kind of special folder for Python.
They might be even brought
in from the web a little bit.
I'm actually not quite sure
exactly where they are,
but they are somewhere, right?
And Python is getting
them from someplace.
So I can't answer your
question in particular,
but you could probably look it up
online and figure out where are you
importing these things from.
I can tell you, though,
that for example,
from helpers import
random string, well, that
is being imported right from
this file called helpers.py,
that we see is right next
to our app.py, right here.
And a question-- what is dunder
name doing, dunder name referring
to underscore underscore
name underscore underscore.
That is simply a special
Python variable name that
refers to the name of this file app.
And so this is a way of telling us that,
hey, given this template for our Flask
app that we have, capital F,
Flask here, let's go ahead
and build a particular one that's called
app, and we'll do it from this file
that we're going to call--
well that is presently called app.
So this gives our application access to
all the other kind of files and folders
that matter for our application.
All right.
These are good questions.
So let's keep going on and
figuring out how this corresponds
with our HTML for our program so far.
So I'll go back to my terminal.
And all this time code up index.html.
And why don't I put it--
just for the sake of visualizing
it-- kind of side by side here.
Do this.
Whoops.
Let me move this over here.
There we go.
And now we can see our Python code,
right alongside our HTML code.
And this is helpful because often
when we're working with Flask,
you do want to have some kind of
correspondence between our HTML
and our Python code-- in some
cases, variable names will matter.
And if we're talking about trying
to insert some text to our HTML,
well, it's important to visualize
those things side by side.
So we'll do that from here
on out, assuming you all
can still read the text size here.
So if we visit our
page and I refresh it,
I don't really see any piece of text.
But again, our goal was to
insert this piece of text
so we could actually see it come to life
and we could regenerate some new text
every time we visited the page.
Well, if I wanted to generate just
a random string of characters,
I could do that using my
random string function up here.
So let me try to use that.
I'll go to index function down
here, which, again, is called
whenever I visit that slash root.
I'll put this to the side for now.
I'll come down here and
I'll say, I want to get
a string that is going to get me the
result of, in this case, random string.
And I'll ask for a string of
maybe 1,000 characters, right?
So now if I were to just print
string, I should hopefully
see that I have this random
string of text inside my terminal,
because print here will
print to my terminal.
So open up my terminal.
I'll go back to my server.
And let me go ahead and just
refresh the page over here.
I'll hit slash, go to my
slash root, hit Enter.
And now nothing changes on my HTML.
But if I look inside
of my terminal, I do
see this random piece
of text I generated
right, about 1,000 random characters.
So how could I then get this
string, perhaps, inside of my HTML?
Any ideas from what we
saw from lecture recently?
We have this variable called string.
But how should we get
it inside of our HTML?
So I'm seeing using some
equals, some maybe braces.
And so you're all on the right track.
So notice how here in
our index HTML, we do
have this placeholder
already set up for us.
Let me zoom in on it
on the right hand side.
You can see we have
this placeholder here.
And using what's now
Jinja syntax, we can say,
I want to have a placeholder, some
value I want to write in to my HTML.
And I can denote it with these
curly braces on either side--
double curly braces.
And then the inside
of these braces, I can
say what the name I want to-- the name
of the placeholder I want to call this.
Here I'm just calling it placeholder,
I could also call it string.
I can call it really anything, but
here I'll just call it placeholder.
Now if I wanted to pass in
string to be kind of interpolated
or put inside as HTML, I could do this.
I could say, when I call this
function, render template,
let's go ahead and make sure that
placeholder gets the value of string,
in this case, as somebody in
the chat has already noted.
Placeholder equals string.
So what I'm doing is taking my
Python variable, string, and saying,
let's put it inside of my HTML in the
placeholder that's literally called
placeholder.
And I know that it is
right here because I
can see it in double curly braces using
Jinja syntax on the right hand side.
So now if I go back and refresh
the page, hit Enter here,
I do actually see my
random string of text.
And I can actually do
this again and again.
I'll hit refresh to
see a new random text.
Refresh again and refresh again.
And now I see this piece
of text, over, and over,
and over again, constantly regenerating
every time I call the slash root,
and thus, the index function here.
So what questions do
you have on this so far,
and how we're interpolating or
adding in some of our variables
from Python to our HTML?
Yeah, so one piece we haven't seen yet--
I see a question in the chat--
is about this methods equals GET.
So here, when we define a route of our
application using Flask, we're saying,
here's what the user
can type in, in the URL,
to run this function
down below, and also,
here are the methods they
can use to access this route.
So remember how there
are two HTTP methods--
GET and POST-- where GET
simply involves the user asking
the server for some web page.
If I say get me this page, it's going to
give you back the page I've asked for.
POST on the other hand, is about sending
some data through a form, most likely,
to your server.
And the server then does
something with that data.
So here, because we're just asking--
because the user is just asking
our application for, really,
a random string, we can safely use GET.
But as we'll see later
on in just a moment here,
we'll try to make our
own form and you can
POST data or send data to our server.
So we should use POST in that case, too.
And I see a question, what
is SQLite doing up here?
So notice how, if you
recall from week seven,
SQLite is this database
engine that we use.
And so this line up here,
line eight, db equals SQL,
SQLite colon slash slash
history.db is saying,
let's build a connection to our
database called history.db using SQLite.
And within Python, let's go ahead
and call that connection just db,
in general.
And we can use something like db to
execute to run queries on our database
that we'll see later towards
the end of section here.
All right.
Other questions, too, on this so far?
So let's keep going here.
And maybe one thing we'd
like to do is actually
have more than one variable
inside of our HTML.
So let's say I went up
here and I went down to--
I don't want to call
it Library of Babel.
Maybe I just want to just call it
Library of some name I can pass in.
So to update this, what can I do
to the end of render template?
I have this placeholder called
name, and it's a placeholder
because I have braces brace, brace,
brace, with name on the inside.
So how could I then update this here?
Anyone chime in the chat?
How could I substitute a name in here?
Yeah.
So name equals something.
I can say colon--
or not colon.
A comma, name equals perhaps Carter.
Hope you can see that.
And then I'll go ahead and go
over here refresh the page.
And now I see library of Carter.
So here's one more example of
having multiple different values
you can pass in to our HTML.
I could change this also
to Joel, hit Enter here.
And now-- whoops, let me refresh this.
And now we see a Library of Joel.
So another way of passing
in some data here.
And now often what you will see is
this variable called placeholder.
Or really, this placeholder
called placeholder isn't really
well named, because if you had
to call everything placeholder,
it would get really
messy really quickly.
So we could just call this
also string, in our HTML.
But then what we'd have to
do is go down below here
and say, string equals string, which
is a little confusing if you're
a beginner, because on the
one hand, you're seeing,
OK, string equals string, we know that.
But what this is really saying is
that string on the left hand side
is referring to this
placeholder string in our HTML,
and string on the right
hand side is referring
to this actual Python
variable called string.
So often you'll see these two
names being the same thing,
but they refer to different objects
or different placeholders or variables
in our programs.
So let's go back and call
this maybe not placeholder.
Let's call it maybe a
random string over here.
And I'll do the same
over here, random string,
just so we can keep
a good naming system,
but also try to differentiate the Python
variable from the HTML placeholder.
OK.
So a question that comes up is, how
do we actually get input from the user
now?
So this is all fine and good.
I can go to my URL, I can refresh it.
And I can see-- oops, let
me actually change this.
Library of Babel.
Refresh the page.
And I do see random text over,
and over, and over again.
But what if I wanted the
user to pick out a page,
like they can do in the real
version of this website?
They can go to page 10 or page 410.
They can see the same thing every time.
Well, to get input from the user, we'll
often want to have a form in HTML.
So a form is going to
look a bit like this,
where a form is comprised of this open
form tag and this closing form tag.
And any ideas as to what
often goes inside of a form?
This form is blank.
We don't see anything.
But what goes inside of a form?
Could be a table, some
input, other things, too.
A submit.
What else might go inside of a form?
A button, a label.
Yeah, there are lots of
things you can add to a form.
And to add them to our forms,
we usually put them inside
of these opening and closing tags here.
So form, the opening tag, and
slash form the closing tag.
So what I'll do here is I will
add this input of type text
and this button of type submit.
Now the default type
for input is text, and I
believe the default type
for a button is submit.
But here, we're just spelling
them out deliberately, here.
Where if I were to render this now--
render this HTML on the left hand side,
I might first see this
input box, and that shows up
as this input box on
the right hand side.
Some place I can type some text.
And then, I would also have
this Submit button over here.
It looks a bit like this.
So together, these pieces
are part of my form.
And when I click this
Submit button, what
will happen is my data
will go somewhere--
wherever I tell it to, so long
as I specified the right things.
And now what actually is
missing from this form?
We have our input, we
have button to submit it.
But what are we missing,
perhaps, in the top form tag?
I'm seeing an action.
An action and a method, where if we
have some data, perhaps in our input,
and we click Submit, well,
there's really no place
for that data to go yet.
So we should really specify
where that data is going.
So I might do this.
I might say also, make sure this form
has particular action and a method.
So to get our minds on
what this action is,
notice how we see the slash here again.
So this action is telling us where--
which route we want to
actually send our data to.
Is it the slash route, the slash browse
route, or a different route altogether?
And then the second
one, the request method
is saying, well, how do I
want to make that request?
Should I do it via Post or via GET?
And now what might be one difference
between using Post and using
GET with a form?
Maybe chime in the chat.
What might be one difference if
we used Post versus GET to submit
our data via the form?
So I'm seeing something like--
Post sends data and GET gets it,
which is a true kind of by convention.
We can still send data
through get, though.
One is shown in the URL
and the other is hidden,
which is a more apt
description here, where
we're saying, if I send data via
Post, that won't show up in the URL.
But if I send it via get
it often-- it will show up
in the URL using these URL parameters.
And so Post is good for when we're
kind of sending data to the server,
but we don't want people to see.
Or even when we don't really
care if people see it,
Post might still be
a good method to use.
So let's try building
up our own form here.
Let's go to our HTML and see
how we have a to do here.
That to do is to
implement a search form.
So if I wanted to make
this form, what could I do?
I can go ahead and do form.
And then I need to have some kind
of text input for the page number
the user is inputting.
Let me actually make this over
here and make it a little bigger.
What kind of input element
should I make here?
Any ideas from the chat?
What kind of input element do
I need to get a page number?
I could use a label.
Yeah, so I'm seeing
something a bit like this.
Input and the type should be, in this
case, let's just stick to type text,
assuming the user can type in some text.
We could also, if we wanted
to, make this a number.
But let's stick to text for now.
And down below, we might also
have a button to submit this.
I'll say button, and the type of
this button is a submit button.
And then on the inside I can say
whatever I want the button to say.
I could say submit or
I could say Go to Page.
And now if I refresh my page, I
should see my very own form up above.
And let's just check.
I Can change this to maybe number, here.
Refresh.
And now I can actually have these up
and down arrows for the page number.
Here, though, we'll actually
just stick to text, just
to keep things a little
more simple here.
And now what am I still
missing from this form?
We have our input and our button.
What have I maybe missed out on?
The action.
So I'll say action equals
slash, because I want
to send this data to the slash root.
And the method in this
case will actually be Post.
I want to use a different method.
And notice how in HTML, actually
these methods are lowercase
instead of Get capital or Post capital,
we use post lowercase or get lowercase.
OK.
So now with this form, I can
go over here, refresh the page.
And I'll go to maybe page 10.
I'll hit 10 here.
I'll say, go to page.
But I get method not allowed.
So what have I also not done yet?
I've made my form, it submits via post.
But what have I not
done yet in my Python?
Yeah.
So I need to add this POST method here.
I need to say that in the list of
supported methods, POST is one of them.
And now if I want to do
something different when the user
requests via POST, I could do this.
I could say, if request.method
is POST or equals POST,
do whatever is inside of here.
I'll leave it unimplemented for now,
but there's presumably something
that we might do inside of this.
So if I refresh the page now, I'll
hit Enter, and I can do 10 again,
and 10 again.
And it seems to work for me.
But what we haven't really yet
done is actually gotten the data
from the user in our Python code.
So presumably, the user
is submitting via POST.
And we could confirm this by saying
submitted via POST, printing that out.
I'll open up my terminal.
I'll go over here, submit my form.
And I do see submitted via
POST, so that seems to work.
But what we haven't done has actually
gotten the data from the form itself.
So how could we do that?
If we go back to our
slides here, we might
see that we could actually use this
correspondence between our HTML
and our Python code to get
the values we want to get.
So notice how in addition to a
type, which is now omitted up here
by default. But now we have the
name attribute of our input.
And this one is called page.
We could reference that very
same name in our Python code
to then get the value
that that input holds
at the time the form is submitted.
So I could use request.form.get,
and then say page to get access
to the value of that name--
or that input called name in my HTML.
If I submitted via GET instead of
POST, I could use request.args.get.
So again, POST is request.form.get,
get is request.args.get.
So let's try this out.
Let's go ahead and go back to our HTML.
And let's actually add
a name to our input.
This one I'll call--
this one I'll call page.
And now how should I get that
value inside of my Python code now?
I have this input named page, but how
should I get it in my Python code?
I can use something
like the GET function.
But more specifically, what
kind of line should I write?
So because I'm submitting via
POST, what I should really
do to get access to this data
is I could do request.form.get.
So from this request, from
the form that was submitted,
get me the value of
the input named page.
And why don't I store this
inside some variable called page?
Let me scroll this to the right.
And for good measure, I'll print
page to be sure I have access to it.
Now I'll go to my code here, I'll
refresh the page, hit 10, go to page.
Now I'll look in my
terminal, and I do actually
see I have that page
number being printed out
because I told Flask
to do so on line 17.
I could even make it maybe
page 50-- go to page.
And now I see page 50 down below here.
So I've gotten whatever text is
inside of my input named page.
And this seems to work for now.
But what if we wanted to update this in
some way to actually have some effect?
Well, it doesn't quite
matter for the problems
that this week or anything else really
beyond this particular application.
But if I wanted to have every
page number be set by whatever--
if I wanted every random string
be set by the page number,
I could call this function
called random.seed.
And I've gotten the seed function,
again, from the random library here.
And if I say random.seed
page, well, later
on when I generate my random string,
if I ask for page 10 and page 10 again,
I'll get that same
random string every time,
giving me the illusion
of having different page
numbers in my application.
So for example, I can go to my
application over here, hit Refresh.
I could say page 10.
And I do see some random
string of text over here.
I'll go to page 10 again and
I get that same random string.
I go to page 11 and I get
some new random string.
Go to page 11 again, and I
get that same random string.
So random seed is a way of specifying
how the randomness should work.
As long as I pass in that same number--
10, 11, 20 or so on, I then
get that same random string
later on when I use the
random functions here.
If I don't use POST, though, if
I don't run this piece of code,
well, what I'll do is just
get a truly random string
based on some random seed.
But beforehand, I could set some seed
to account to based on the page to say,
that if I ask for certain
page number, I'll always
get back the same string in the end.
OK.
But what might go wrong with this?
If you look at this form, what are some
bad inputs you could give to this form.
If we're talking about
page numbers, what
are some bad inputs you could give?
Negative nine, letters.
So if I do this, I say, negative nine.
Well, it still seems to work.
But I don't really want it to.
Or if I typed a, a, a, well, that
also worked, but not quite the way
I want it to.
And so how could we do this?
I could actually go back
to my code space here
and I could try to
update this in some way.
So ideally, I want to validate
the user input as I get it.
And maybe I have page here.
But I could ask the question,
before I do anything with page,
is page less than zero?
And if it is, why don't we
return the render template.
Return index HTML now rendered, but at
this point just say some error message
like, type in a positive number.
So now my placeholder called
random string will actually just
be this error message,
type in a positive number.
So now I'll go back over here
and I'll do refresh the page.
And I'll type, let's say,
negative 10, go to page.
Oh, but I got an internal server error.
And if I look at my terminal, I should
see type error less than not supported
between instances of
str and int down below.
So what went wrong do you think?
If we look at this code
on the left hand side.
What went wrong?
Yeah, we forgot to put
page inside of a-- we
forget to convert page to be an integer.
So I forgot to do this.
I forgot to say that if we can,
let's make sure we turn page
from a string to an integer.
So whenever you use request.form.get
or request.args.get,
whether you're working
with numbers or not,
you'll always get your input back
as a string, and it's up to you
to convert it to an integer if
you want it to be an integer.
So here I'll convert page to an integer.
And now I'll try running this.
I'll go back here and I'll say,
slash, to get back to my main page,
and I'll say negative 10.
I'll go to page.
And now I do see, type in a positive
number, which is really good.
I'll do -500, and I see the same thing.
But what is the other kind of input
we could give to this form that
might make it go wrong?
We've seen negative numbers.
What else?
We can give some text.
We'd say, ABC, go to page, and we
get another internal server error.
So something's gone wrong again.
And if we look down in our
terminal, we see a value error--
invalid literal for
int with base 10 ABC.
And this basically means
that I can't convert
the string, ABC, to be an integer.
What does it mean for ABC to be integer?
We don't really know.
So what I should probably do here is
use Python's try and accept syntax
where in Python, often it's
good to simply try something
that you want to do.
Like try to, in this case,
convert page to an integer.
And except, maybe except if
I do see that value error,
let me go ahead and actually
tell the user another error.
And this time I'll tell them,
just enter a number in general.
So again, we'll get the
page number from our form.
We'll then try to convert
page into an integer.
And if we get that error, we can't
convert some text to an integer, what
we'll do is we'll say, I want to tell
the user to enter a number over here.
And then finally, as one final
check, we'll also ask the question,
is page less than zero?
And if it is, we'll tell them to
type in a positive number overall.
So this kind of accesses all the
possible combinations of errors here.
So go back up to our website.
Go to slash.
I'll type, in this case, ABC.
Go to page.
And I see enter a number, which is good.
And then I'll type maybe negative 10.
I'll see enter a positive number.
And now if I type page
10, well, I seem to get
the thing I wanted in the first place.
So questions on this and how
we implemented some of this
getting of data from the form,
but also validating user input,
as you might want to do during
this week's problem set?
OK, seeing-- I'll wait
just one minute or so.
All right.
What happens, though, actually--
maybe there's one more thing
we should take care of--
if I do this.
I could go back over here, put
in nothing, and type go to page.
I see enter number,
it actually works OK.
But we could also--
well, no, I think we're OK here.
Let me know if you find
other errors, though.
Symbols, I saw.
OK, let's try symbols.
I'll type at exclamation point.
Seems to work.
So that seems OK here.
And particularly for
this week's problems set.
We will be getting numbers
and text from the user,
it's often good to really
try to validate the input
to make sure that they're
not being adversarial to you.
They're not trying to give you
some text and mess up your program.
And you're instead making sure
that before you do anything
with their input, you're making
sure it is exactly as you expect.
And if it's not, maybe giving them
some kind of error as we did here.
So let's keep going now.
And one of our final
to-do's was to not just
have the user send some
input to our database,
but also to have some
search history down below.
And ideally, if I search
for page 10, well, I
should see that search
show up at the bottom
of my page in this table down below.
And that's not there yet.
But to do this, we'll probably
need to use some of our SQL
that we learned from a prior week.
And so let's take a look
at how we could use that.
So if we think about databases in our
program, they're going to store data,
long-term for our application.
And if we want it to store
like a search history,
it's a great use case for that,
because we can actually persistently
store search history over time.
So let's take a look at SQL
and how we could do this.
If we look at history.db, at
the beginning of this session,
I ran this function--
I ran this command called
Create table history
with this ID column and this page
column, to give me this table of pages
that I could insert into.
And just to show you, if I go back
to my code space, go over here.
I could go to my new terminal,
type ls, type SQLite3,
history.db to open this up.
And now if I full screen it and
zoom in, if I type dot schema,
I see I've ran that command and
I have this table called history.
I could even select everything from
history, and I see nothing's there.
So I have this kind of empty table
in my database called history.db.
So if I were to insert into this
table, I could do the following.
I can run this SQL command
called INSERT INTO.
And the way this works
is we type the name
of the table, so history, and the
columns you want to insert into,
so page in this case.
So I'll insert page 50 into my table.
Then I might say, OK, let's
insert 100 into my table,
and let's insert 43 into my table as
I go through and make these queries.
But right now, this is all
happening in the SQLite terminal
and not in my Python program.
So how could I run Python or
run SQL but in my Python code?
Any ideas in the chat?
What have we seen so far?
How can I run these same SQL commands
but not in the SQLite terminal,
actually in my Python program now?
Yeah.
I'm seeing db.execute.
So I can type the very same
command, but just inside of Python
using this db.execute command.
So db to execute is a way of trying
to execute SQL commands inside
of our application that
connects to this database
and actually runs them on that database.
So here we can say insert
in history the page 43.
And one kind of handy
thing here is we don't even
need to know the page number originally.
We could just say, insert
some placeholder like this.
I could say, make a question mark for
some value I could insert later on
and then say comma, the name of
the variable I want to insert,
in this case.
So let's actually try this out.
I'll go back to my code.
And let me pull up--
pull up my-- actually, exit from this.
No, I'll keep that up.
Let me go back over here.
I'll code-- oh, cd into
library, and I'll code app.py.
And now I see I'm kind of
back in my view over here.
I want to insert the page number
every time I go to the slash root
and submit the form.
So ideally, when I'm in this post
route, I want to keep track of the pages
that the user has requested.
So once I know that I have a valid
page number right down in here--
let me zoom in a bit--
what could I run to insert this
page number into my database?
I know I can do insert into history
into the pages column, some values.
But what do I want to actually type
here to run it inside of Python?
This is not valid Python code yet.
But how could I make it so?
Yeah, I can use db to execute.
So I can say, db to execute and wrap
this command with that function.
And then to fill in this placeholder
here, this question mark,
I could go ahead and say, I want
to put in page for that right here.
So now if I look at
this entire command, I'm
saying, execute on my database,
which I defined up here--
history.db, using SQLite.
Execute on that database this command.
Insert into history, in the
pages column, this value here.
And what is the value?
What's the value for page?
And we know, page is a page
number the user has submitted.
So let me go back to my
application, refresh the page.
This time, I will type page 10.
I'll go to page.
And if I scroll down,
well, I don't see anything.
And that's because my HTML--
I haven't actually rendered this.
Like I just see search history
but really nothing else over here.
But if I go to my SQLite
connection, My SQLite terminal here
and I type select star
from history, what
do you think I'll see in this case?
Feel free to type in the chat.
What do you think I'll see when I
type select star from history now?
I'll see everything in the database.
And because I submitted this
form with the page number 10,
I should see 10 somewhere.
And I do see it.
I see this has an ID and the page is 10.
And now I can go back and
submit the form again.
I could go back over here.
Let me search for page 50 now.
I'll go to that page and
then I'll go over here.
I'll select everything
from history and now I
see both page 10 and
page 50 in my history.
So I'm adding to my table, not by
being in this terminal down here,
but through my own Python code that
I wrote up above, right in here.
OK.
So questions on this so far?
How we're inserting into our table?
I see a question-- how do we see
the search history in our HTML
which we'll get to in just a second.
But questions on inserting or
this db to execute for now?
All right.
So let's keep going then.
And our last step is really to try to
show this search history in our HTML.
And we'll need a bit more
advanced syntax, at least
with Jinja on the right hand side here.
But for now, let's figure out,
how could I get access to the data
from my database inside
of Python, and then
use Python to pass
that data into my HTML?
So we're going a few
different places here.
We're asking our database, what rows
do you have, putting those in Python,
and then telling Python to send
that data to our HTML page.
So maybe down here
when I visit this page,
let's say I've finished making a
request, either via POST or GET.
And now I've generated a string.
But I also want to figure out,
what is inside of my database?
Well, I could do db.execute.
And as we saw before, how could I
get everything from my history table?
What kind of SQL command could I use?
Yeah, star.
Select star from history, right?
And let me actually add the
semi-colon up here, just to be sure.
And now that I've done this,
well, I selected everything,
but I also need a place to store
this data so I can use it in Python.
And it happens to be that
db to execute returns to you
a list of all the rows as dictionaries.
So for example, I could
say rows equals db.execute.
And I'll get back a list where every
row is a dictionary that has the column
names as its attributes or its keys.
So just to show you--
I could print rows down
here, just to my terminal.
And now I'll go to Library of Babel.
I'll hit slash now.
I still don't see anything
in my search history
down below, because I
haven't made that part yet.
But if I go to my
terminal, open that up.
Let me go back over here to my server.
I see that I ran this command,
select star from history,
and it gave me this
list of dictionaries.
So see, I have one dictionary
that has ID and page as keys.
And the ID is one, the page is 10.
I have this next dictionary where
the ID is two and the page is 50.
That's another row in my table.
And together, this is an
entire list-- a list of rows.
So what could I do with this?
How could I render this in my HTML?
Well, as we saw maybe a
little bit briefly in lecture,
I could try to pass in
this variable-- rows--
to my HTML, and render it there.
So I could say, maybe I have this
placeholder called history in my HTML.
And I'll make sure that that placeholder
is filled with the values of rows.
And let me go over
here to my index.html.
Now, open this part up.
And maybe in my table body, well, I
could just place history like this.
I'll make this placeholder
for history and I'll
put the value of rows
right in there in my table.
So I'll go back to Library of Babel and
I will hit slash to refresh the page.
And well I don't quite
see what I expected.
This is not an ideal format.
I've kind of literally interpolated
or copy pasted the value of rows
into my HTML, but it looks kind of
wonky and not how I want it to look.
So there's a better way to do this.
And actually, in Jinja, instead of
just pasting an entire variable,
we could iterate over a
variable but in our HTML.
And now Jinja has the special
syntax we can use to use for loops,
so what we have in Python.
So I could say this.
I could say percent-- or brace
percent and then closing brace--
closing percent and then brace.
Let's say for maybe row in history.
And then end for down here.
So now I've made this
for loop in my HTML
where history is the
list I'm iterating over
and row is what I want
to call everything--
every individual thing I'm
iterating over on a given iteration.
So now I can say, I want
to, inside of this table,
make myself a new table row for
every row that I have in history.
And then inside that table
row, I want to have some data.
Again, this tr is our table row tag
and this td is our table data tag.
And now what should go inside here?
Well, maybe I could actually have this
placeholder that is equivalent to row
and I could borrow some Python
syntax here, row bracket page.
So what do you think
we'll see in this case?
Any ideas in the chat if we do this?
We're iterating over our history
list, a list of rows from our table.
We're going to call
every iteration, row.
And then we'll say,
row, get me the key--
give me the value corresponding
to the key called page.
So again, here is our entire
list, down below here.
On the first iteration, this will be
row, and we'll get the page value--
so 10.
On the next iteration, this
will be row, and then we'll
get the page value, or 50.
So let's refresh the page
and see what happens now.
I'll go over here--
oops.
Here.
Slash.
And now, I do see my search history,
kind of as I intended it to be.
And if I even go up here and type going
to page 100, I'll go to that page,
scroll down, and I see
that added to my history.
I could go to 100 again.
I see that same random
string like we saw before,
and now I can see my
search history down below.
So all of this, this
kind of syntax here,
is just a way to print
our list of dictionaries
a little more prettily,
a little more in line
with what we expect to see in our HTML.
OK.
So what questions are there on this?
On how we passed in some list
of dictionaries to our code
and iterated over it
to make a table here?
Same question.
Showing the back end to the front end
is not insecure, how do we hide that?
So the key thing to remember
here is that this app.py
is kind of like what we call our
back end-- something the user never
really sees.
And even our HTML page over here
is somewhat back end, in the sense
that if I were to render this--
let me look over here.
If I were to render
template, index.html,
well, I would actually see not
this code for row and history
and for row, bracket, page, I'd
actually generate this HTML file
and then show it to the user.
And so if I go to my HTML file
over here and scroll down,
notice how I don't actually
see any of the Jinja syntax,
I just see the resulting
pieces of it here.
So I don't see for or the
dictionary or anything like that.
I just see the result of it here.
And so that is secure
enough for us, as we're
showing our web page to the user on the
front end, what they can see up front
here.
Question-- how do we get the key values?
So notice in our HTML.
We said row with the key of page,
but how do we know it was page?
Well, if I go to my SQL prompt
over here, select star from history
as you did before.
I have this row called page.
So it's just in the way we made our
table we had this column called page
on a row, a column called page here.
OK.
Other questions here?
While we're waiting for
questions to come in,
this week will be a lot of
doing exactly what we did today,
of trying to insert some
data from Python into HTML,
trying to render dictionaries,
lists of dictionaries
and so on, and even using
some of our helper functions
that we saw before here.
I hope you go off and work on
this problem set with some of what
you learned during this section.
We'll probably officially
conclude here, but I'm
happy to be around to answer
any questions that you all have.
Thank you very much for coming
and I hope to see you next time.