CARTER ZENKE: OK, hello, everyone.
It is so good to see you here.
My name is Carter Zenke.
I'm the course preceptor here on campus.
This is our week six section for CS50.
We'll dive into Python.
So in lecture, we saw
a few different topics
and we have those same
topics on the board today.
Some including strings, this
new dot notation for Python,
loops, dictionaries, libraries, and
how we read and write from files.
So we'll touch a bit on each of these
different topics during this section.
And we'll spend a bit more time on
things like loops and dictionaries
and file writing and file
reading to help prepare you
for this week's problem set.
So that's all those topics this
week, but we'll try to dive
into a few of them in particular.
So let's actually start off
with this idea of these strings.
So we saw strings in
C. And these strings
are actually still here in Python.
And there are all kinds of interesting
things you can really do with strings.
So one of them might be taking
in some information from a book.
So maybe you've read Goodnight Moon.
And if you have, you know
it's this children's book
that has lots of simple text
that is involved with it.
And maybe the book starts off like this.
It says, in the great
green room, and maybe we're
interested in seeing what a
computer does with this text.
So one thing we can now do
with Python is have more access
to all these different kinds of
libraries and things we can use.
Actually use AI and such.
And so maybe we give this piece of text
to this AI called DALL-E with OpenAI.
And we get back maybe this kind of
image here in the great green room
that DALL-E generated just
from seeing this piece of text.
And we could also do it
with the next phrase.
We could say, there was a
telephone and a red balloon,
and we'll get back some text--
or some images a bit like this.
This telephone here, this red balloon
generated by the AI, again, here.
Now, all of this-- this fancy
AI, this image innovation,
comes down to just giving
text to a computer.
And so let's think about how we do
that in Python here as compared to C.
So we saw in C we had
this top level code here,
char *text gets this get_string function
whenever we prompt the user for there.
And then, in Python, we had this
text gets the value of input.
And so take a moment here,
maybe pause the video
and think, what are the differences
you see between the top level
code and the bottom level coding?
The top and C and the
bottom one in Python.
So maybe you notice that,
in Python, we no longer
have to say the type of the
variable we're working with.
So down below, we're still
working with strings,
as we are in the top piece of code.
But notice how, in Python, we just get
to say the variable name, like just
text, right?
Not string text, not
char *text, just text.
And so C is what we call a
statically typed language.
We have to declare the type
before we use a given variable.
Like text has to declare
it as a string or a char *.
Whereas, in Python, which is
a dynamically typed language,
we don't have to do that.
We can say, Python, please
infer for me the data type
that we're talking about here.
Saying text gets
whatever input gives us.
And because we know this input
function always gives us a string,
well text, of course,
is going to be a string.
OK, so it's one difference between C
and Python in getting these variables
and getting these strings.
But how would we actually
compare them perhaps?
So in C, we had this top code.
And in Python, we now
have this bottom code.
And so take a moment to
yourself, maybe pause the video
and think, what differences
do you notice here
between the top and the bottom?
And so maybe you've
seen that, in the top,
we actually are
comparing text with hello
using a different kind of function.
We're saying, let's use str compare
to look at text and look at hello
and check the return
value of that and see
if it's 0, where 0 indicates
that these are the same.
Well, in Python, we don't
have to do any of that.
No special functions involved here.
All we get to say is, if
text is equal to hello,
if this text is hello, let's
do something that's indented.
And maybe you notice as well that,
in the top, in our if statement,
we have to have these curly braces.
And the code that gets run
if this condition is true
is inside those curly braces.
Whereas, in Python down below, we see
that we have this if text equals hello.
Then, we actually do the
code that's indented.
So no longer do we need
these curly braces here.
We can only rely on
code that is indented.
And so while you may be able to throw
out the braces and the semicolons,
you can also make sure you have
to have your code indented.
That's what can matter more in Python
versus these curly braces up top.
So comparing strings works a little
differently in Python, but let's
take a look at how we
actually get access
to individual characters of a string.
Because remember that
strings are just collections
of characters or strings of characters.
And to see individual
characters in Python,
we can actually do the same thing we
did in C. We have the same bracket
syntax, like text [i] to get
access to a particular character
inside our piece of text.
And this also works for lists.
So let's say we had a list in
Python similar to an array in C.
We could try to actually have these
curly brace-- these brackets here
that get us access to an individual
element inside of our list.
So some differences in strings here.
But mostly, we can actually
use some familiar syntax
with these accessing
individual characters here.
Now, strings are a little more
powerful than just comparing
them or getting them in your program
or even getting individual characters.
And in fact, in C, we
have-- not in C. In Python--
sorry-- we have access to
these individual functions
or the individual methods that belong
to this type called str in Python,
more long we call the string.
So here we have this dot
notation that we can introduce.
So let's say we're trying to
give this string to our program.
Well, we could have some code a
bit like this like we saw before.
We could say that text equals input.
And maybe our text looks like
this on the right hand side.
And if you pause the
video or asked yourself,
what looks a little odd
about this text on the right?
What is a little messy about it?
And so maybe you've noticed
that, in general, we
have some spaces before the text
and some places after the text.
And ideally, those shouldn't be there.
That's going to be a remnant of
the user typing in some information
and they typed it in wrong.
We want to get rid of that.
Well, luckily, in Python, we
actually have these methods
we can use to get rid of
that whitespace on either end
to strip that whitespace off.
And this method is
actually called dot strip.
So we can say text.strip.
And if you run this
line of code now, we'll
see that those white spaces on
either end, actually, go away.
So here is what we had before.
It's a piece of messy text with
white space on either side.
But running text.strip,
well, we've got rid of that.
Now, we just have, in
the great green room,
the actual characters
inside of our string.
OK, and that's actually pretty good.
But what if we had some
other kinds of input?
Let's say we had maybe
miscapitalized letters.
Like IN, all caps, thE with E
capitalized, and ROom with RO
capitalized.
Well, how could we make sure
this is all standardized?
Well, we could use another
method that belongs
to strings, this one called lower.
We could say text.lower.
And that then gives us this
same string, but in lowercase.
And similarly, maybe we want
to actually capitalize this
because it's a sentence.
We could actually do
that very same thing.
We could say text.capitalize to
make sure that the I in this string
is capitalized and the
rest is here lowercased.
So all of these are what
we call methods that
really belong to this idea of the
string-- this data type called
the string in Python.
Some Python developers long ago
decided that because these functions,
like lower or capitalize or split
and so on-- or not split, but strip,
belong to this thing called a string.
They're so integral to what
it means to be a string,
we actually have to include them inside
this string data type, so to speak.
So if we keep going here, we
can actually think of other ways
to use these methods.
But first, let's actually dive
into how they work, why they exist,
and where they are.
Compare what kinds of methods
you want to use in your own code.
So again, these strings, or more
succinctly called strs in Python, S-T-R
for short, actually you have a
variety of methods you can figure out
in the Python documentation.
So if you go to docs.python.org,
you'll see something like this.
And if you scroll down
to the str section,
you'll see string methods inside.
You get to find all the methods you
could call on your strings in Python.
We have capitalized down here and
some others if we scroll down.
But notice how we have
access to this dot notation.
It's not capitalize, and then, give
the string as input to capitalize.
It's actually str.capitalize
or string.lower.
And so why does this come up in Python?
Well, if we actually bring it back
to what we saw in C with our structs,
we might get some intuition here.
So in C, we had this idea of a struct
called a candidate, for example,
in an earlier problem set.
And a candidate looks a bit like
this, just a single person over here.
And remember how this candidate
had different attributes,
like they had a name, or they
had maybe a number of votes.
And this candidate was
some data type we had
constructed to have these attributes.
It had a name and some number of votes.
And to get access to those, well, we did
this very same thing of candidate.votes
to get access to votes.
And then, candidate.name
to get access to name.
So in Python, this str data
type now is somewhat similar,
but you can think of it
as more of a toolkit.
It's a data type that
has some tools inside
you can use on the string you're
talking about in this case.
So we could say str.capitalize.
And there's a tool
inside of this str type
we can use-- this function we can
use, or more particularly this method,
we can use on this str data type.
And similarly, we could even
have str.lower, this other tool
inside of our toolbox for strs
we can use to actually make
the str do what we want it to do.
So very similar in spirit to this idea
of attributes for our structs in C
where structure often maybe defined
as our own data types, similarly,
in Python, we have our
own data type called
a str that now has not
just attributes, but also
functions that can belong to it and
that can operate on its own self.
So that's all for dot syntax.
And take a look at the Python all
the functions you can use here.
But let's actually take
a look at loops in Python
and how strings come in with loops.
So if we remember from lecture,
we see that there are maybe
the same kinds of loops impact.
We have the while loop, the for loop,
but they look a little different.
And then, one big example
of this difference
is Python's four blank in blank syntax.
And we'll see this very often in Python
because it's so convenient to use.
So let's say, for example, I
have some piece of text, again,
in the great green room
on the right hand side.
And I want to loop through
this piece of text.
Well, I could do that much more
simply than I really could in C. All I
have to do is say for C in text.
Maybe we want to print
out every character.
And so what we'll do is make
a new variable called C.
And it'll actually loop through all the
characters inside of this string called
text and make sure that on each
iteration C updates as we go through.
So for example, let's
say I run this code.
I would see that C gets that very
first character in text, like the I.
On the next iteration, C will get
that next character called n, and then
the space, and then the t, and
then the h, and then the e.
And this will keep going and going and
going all the way through our string.
Now, we could call C
anything we want to call it.
We could call it z.
We could call it s.
We could call it character,
just like a long variable name.
We could even call it
zebra if we wanted to.
But the main thing here is
that Python takes this string
and infers that when it sees this loop
called for blank in whatever string
you have, it's going to take
every individual character,
assign it some name as you loop through,
and make sure that each time that name
refers to a particular
element inside of your string
where the element is now,
in this case, a character.
Now, this is actually-- this
works beyond simply strings.
We also have this kind
of syntax for lists.
And so let's say we want to
turn this piece of text, which
is all one string, into really
a list of different strings
where each string is a word.
Well, we could have a different
kind of method for a string.
This one called .split.
So here we have, again, our
text on the right hand side.
And let's make this new variable
called words that will get our text
but split up now individual words.
And when you call .split onto a piece
of text, it's going to automatically,
or by default, look for spaces in that
string and give you back substrings
that are smaller strings that
are between those spaces.
So for example, if we were to run
text.split here, what we'll get
is now a list of individual words.
So see how this changes from one long
string into multiple individual words
and are part of this Python list.
And as a thought question here,
how do we know this is a list?
Take a look at the syntax
on the right hand side.
Let me show it back to you again.
How do we know this is a list?
Well, you might have thought that it's
because of the brackets on either side.
We see these square brackets, and
that in Python denotes a list.
But we also see these commas in between
our words or their individual strings.
So we say in, which is a string, comma,
though, which is a string, comma.
Those are all inside
these square brackets.
So that denotes to us a Python
list, which is similar in spirit
to a C array, but it's much
more flexible overall for us.
OK, so now, we split our words into--
split our text into individual
words, let's actually
see how we can loop through
these words as a whole.
So if we then use our for blank in blank
syntax with a list as that second blank
there, we could say, for word in words.
Let's print out the word.
And what this will do for us visually
is say, on this first iteration,
word will get the value in.
And on the second iteration,
word will get the value the.
And on the third, it will get
the value great and so on.
And so you might be able to guess, well,
on the fourth iteration, what will word
get?
It will get green.
And on the fifth iteration,
what will word get?
It will get room, right?
It will get room at the very end.
So we see that word is going through
and getting these individual words
inside of our list.
Well, why is that?
Why is it the actual words
now inside of our list
as opposed to the characters
inside of our string?
Well, what matters here
is the kind of data type
you are asking Python to iterate over.
So this for/in syntax
is helpful if you want
to have some kind of loop going
through every element of a--
what we call iterable, where an
iterable means you can iterate over it.
It has some elements you
can go over individually.
If you have a list, what
Python will do is go over
every element inside that list.
So in this case, our strings are
the elements of our list, right?
But if we have just a single string,
like in or the or great or the string
as a whole, in the great
green room, well, Python
will decide to go through
every individual character.
Because in this case, the characters are
that subpiece, that subelement inside
of our longer string, in this case.
So I encourage you to
actually go out and check
what Python does in
these different cases
to actually see how this changes as you
change what you iterate over in Python.
So our first exercise together
will be to actually take
a look at this piece
of code that will have
us look at a variety different
loops and figure out which
one is going to print out which thing.
So let's look back at our code here.
I'll go over to my code space and
I'll go ahead and sign in over here.
I'll let you get your code space up too.
So we have our code space loaded.
So let's actually go ahead
and pull up our piece of code
that we'll take a look at it together.
So we'll open up text.py.
And I'll zoom in a bit on it for you.
Now, the goal for this
exercise-- so take
a look at each of these loops
in Python and figure out
what they're going to do for us.
So notice at the very top, we
have the same text from before,
in the great green room.
And we split it up by word.
So we're saying let's split up our
text and make this list called words.
But we have different loops down here
to actually loop through those words
and print out those words out
in a variety of different ways.
So let's look at round one here.
What might we see in?
And feel free to pause the video
and write it out for yourself.
What might we see in this round one?
So we might see, as we saw before,
every individual word being printed.
So we might see first in,
and then the, and then
great, and then green, and then room.
These are going to be on new
lines because, if we know,
print at the very end always includes
that new line for us automatically.
If we wanted to change that, let's
say, print these all on the same line,
like in the great green room
on that same line, well,
we could change the ending
character of this print statement.
We could do this.
We could say end equals blank.
Or end equals, in this case,
it's going to be a space.
So what'll happen here is Python will
print out end, that very first word,
add a space at the end, and then,
print out that next word going
and going and going through.
So up to you, but we can
maybe just leave this
as printing out the individual
words on single lines.
Let's take a look at round two now.
And feel free to pause the
video and ask yourself,
what might get printed out here?
So if we look through this,
we have for word in words.
It's the very same loop we had before.
We're getting access to every
individual word in our list of words.
So first in, then the, then
great, then green, then room.
But now, we have for c in word.
And so recall, when we have a list we're
looping over, like in this first loop,
we're getting access to
the elements of that list.
But word now is simply
an individual string.
So what are we printing out here?
Probably the individual characters
inside of that particular word.
So if we loop through this, we
might see first I and then n.
And then, would we see
the space or would we not?
Maybe take a guess?
In this case, we actually
wouldn't see the space.
And that's because we've split
our words into a list of words.
And then, I actually try to
print this out for you to see.
I'll go ahead and copy this and I'll
open up a new one called list.py.
I'll paste this here.
I'll print words.
Let's go ahead and run this.
Python of list.py.
Well, we see now in
the great green room.
Notice how there aren't
any spaces inside
of these individual strings
that are inside of our list.
So if we go back here and we loop
through the individual characters,
first in this word, which is I and
n, well, there are no spaces there.
And if we loop through
this next word like,
T-H-E, there are no
spaces there, either.
So we'll say T-H-E and
so on and so forth.
You can keep going like this.
We're printing out every individual
character except for the spaces,
in this case.
OK, let's look at now our third round
where we have for word in words.
Same thing we saw before.
But now, if g--
this character g is in
the word, what will we do?
Print the word.
So take a guess as to what you might see
in this loop, keeping in mind that this
is our text, in the great green room.
What would we see here?
So you might see only the
words that have g in them.
And in Python, it's just this
easy to ask if some string is
part of another string.
That's because we're
asking if g, this string,
will be inside this smaller
string, this word right here.
So let's go ahead and say I,
it doesn't have any g's in it.
The, no g's.
Great has a g at the beginning,
so maybe we print that.
And green does too, but room does not.
So we probably-- it would be safe
to say that we would see great here
and we would see green printed out
to the screen on these new lines.
And now, we have perhaps
some new syntax here.
For word, in words, [2:] .
And maybe you're not
familiar with that, but feel
free to take a guess as to what
you might think will happen here.
Maybe pause the video.
And if we take a look at this, well,
let's go back to our list.py file
and try to get a grasp on what
this is really doing for us.
So we see words [2:] .
And this is somewhat familiar to us.
We've seen words [2] before.
What this will do if I run
it as Python of list.py.
Well, that will give
us just great, right?
It will give us the
second indexed element
where this is 0, 1, and 2 in our list.
Just point that out.
But what if we wanted not just that
element, but that one in all the rest
after it?
Well, Python comes with
this fancy feature.
We can say a colon here to say,
get me that word at index 2
and all the rest, right?
So I could do this.
I could say Python of list.py
and see great, green, and room.
Now, I've sliced my list into
these smaller piece here.
That only includes great
and green and room.
That's the technical term for it.
Slicing.
We're slicing a list using
this colon syntax here.
Now, I could even add an end state.
Let's say I don't want room.
I only want great and green.
Well, I could modify my slice like this.
I could say start at index 2, in
this case, that's great, again,
we're 0 index.
0, 1, and 2.
And then, go up to, but not
including, that last index here.
And that last index is 4.
Again, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4.
So we'll go here.
2:4 Python list.py.
Now, I see great and green.
This worked because the very first
number we put in is inclusive.
We're going to get this index back.
So we're going to get this
value here, this string here.
And we're also going to get 3--
index 3.
But we won't get index 4.
This is exclusive.
The very first number is inclusive,
the last number is exclusive.
So to get just, for example,
great, we could also do this.
But that's not really necessary, right?
We only really need 2, 4
to get great and green.
Or if we wanted to, just 2: to get
all the rest of them in this list, OK?
So now that we've seen that, what
do you think will happen here?
Well, it will probably print out every
individual word that is in this list
only after the second index.
So we'll probably see great--
we'll see great and green
and we'll see room overall.
OK, last one here.
We have for word in words,
print Goodnight Moon.
Now, what do you think you will see
here if you were to pause the video?
And maybe you've noticed
that, for a Python loop,
we have this idea of going through
every element we have in our list.
A lot of Python for loops
are really built on lists.
So if we have for word
in words, well, our list,
again, is the same one in list.py
if I print out just words now.
In the great green room.
Well, this will actually iterate
over every element in that list.
We'll say, OK, first in, then the,
then great, then green, then room.
And it doesn't matter-- if we're
not doing anything with word,
we're just looping that many times.
So we're going to loop, in
this case, five times and print
out Goodnight Moon.
But it seems a little
odd to do it that way.
And actually, I think I might
have a syntax error here.
I don't think we need this
parentheses here for word in words.
If we did this, well, why
do we have but call it word?
We're not really using word at all.
So we could just say underscore, meaning
that, look, this name doesn't matter.
It could be anything.
It could be z, it could be f, it could
be zebra, whatever we want it to be.
But we're not going to
use this variable name,
SO let's just call it underscore just
to signify that this file name doesn't
quite matter.
All we're interested in
doing is looping through it.
It doesn't change the
output of this for loop.
It doesn't change anything
about how it runs.
It just changes the variable name.
So it signifies we don't really
care what the name is, in this case.
So I'll change it back
to for word in words.
Let's go ahead and run
this piece of code.
We'll run Python of text.py.
And now we'll see, in round
five, five Goodnight Moons.
So let's keep scrolling up again.
Round one, we did see,
in the great green room.
Round two, we see all the individual
characters in the great green room.
Round three, we just
see great and green.
Round four, we see great green room.
And of course, in round
five, as we saw before,
we do see five instances
of Goodnight Moon.
OK, so that covers a
lot of Python loops.
And in general, if you're going
to use this kind of Python syntax,
I think you'll find it really handy.
But it just takes some practice to
get to know what each of these loops
is doing and how they work with
different data types, in this case.
So let's keep going here.
And let's take a look at
this new Python data type.
This one called dictionary.
And dictionaries are really important
in Python, very easy to use,
and often very useful for us, as you'll
see in the problem set this week.
So a dictionary.
Well, if we think of a dictionary,
it's this piece of paper, so to speak.
We might have some idea of
hosting some keys and some values.
Maybe words and their definitions,
like a real dictionary has.
So here we have, for example,
maybe a dictionary of authors.
So maybe Goodnight Moon
is one of our keys.
And the value associated with
that key is Margaret Wise Brown.
Or Corduroy, that's our
key, the book title,
is now associated with the value
Don Freeman, that author there.
And Curious George
associated with H.A. Ray,
where we have Curious George as
a key and H.A. Ray has the value.
So what this gives us is
this ability to look up,
like in a dictionary, the actual author
of some piece of text given the title.
So we see, again, Goodnight
Moon is example of a key here
and Margaret Wise Brown
example of a value.
So in this dictionary, authors, I could
ask for a title-- like a book title.
I could say, give me a book title
and I'll say, Goodnight Moon.
And the dictionary will
actually giving back
the value associated with that
key, like Margaret Wise Brown.
Now, this example here is a
collection of multiple objects
in the same dictionary.
Have multiple books here
all in that same dictionary.
We have Goodnight Moon, we have
Corduroy, we have Curious George.
But we can also have a single
dictionary for a single object.
We could also have, for example,
a single book dictionary.
And this dictionary has a
title key and an author key,
the two things that make it a book.
It has a title and an author.
Well, the title of this
book is Goodnight Moon
and the author is Margaret Wise Brown.
So I could simply ask this dictionary
for the title of the book by saying,
give me the value--
the key title.
I'm going to give you Goodnight Moon.
I could also ask for
the author of this book
by asking for the value
associated with the key author,
and I get back Margaret
Wise Brown, in this case.
OK, so let's see an example
of this in actual syntax.
This is a pretty good
theoretical overview,
but let's think about it in syntax form.
Here I have a new
dictionary, book equals dict.
And what this is doing
for me is saying that,
give me an empty dictionary,
nothing in it yet, and call it book.
So on the right hand side, I'll see this
dictionary, a blank slate called book.
Now, let's I want to add in a key and
a value that's associated with it.
So I can do this.
I can say, make sure you
add this key called title
and give it the value Corduroy.
So this bracket notation is back.
But now, to add a key to the
dictionary, we're going to use that.
So we're going to say book ["title"] to
insert a new key called title and give
it the value Corduroy.
And we can also do it for the author.
We could say book ["author"]
is Don Freeman, in this case.
So we're to say that, in this case,
this book's author is Don Freeman.
Now, if I want to get back some value
from my dictionary, I could do this.
I could say, book, bracket,
title, and print it out.
And what would I get in this case?
What do you think?
I might get Corduroy.
I would see Corduroy printed
out to the screen down below.
That's because saying
book ["title"] is saying,
look for the value associated with this
key called title inside this dictionary
that we're calling book, right?
OK, now though, what if I
asked for the key Corduroy?
What do you think would happen?
Well, if we look at our dictionary,
do we have a key in Corduroy?
It doesn't look like we do.
We only have a key for
title and a key for author.
Corduroy is a value, but
it's not really a key, right?
It's associated with this key
title, but it isn't a key itself.
So if we did this, we
get what Python calls
a key error where a key
error is simply we're
trying to access some key in our
dictionary that doesn't exist.
They'll tell us that this key
is not part of dictionary.
You can't look up the value for a
key that doesn't exist, in this case.
OK, so that gives us access
to these dictionaries.
We're going to make them in code.
But what if we wanted to do
something a little more advanced?
This is a single book, but
what if we had multiple books?
Well, we could maybe shorten
our syntax a little bit here.
We could say that if I want a new book,
let's just define it all in one breath.
Here we have a new dictionary
denoted by these curly braces now.
Not square brackets, but curly braces.
And we have the key, like title and
the value, like the Goodnight Moon,
and the key author in the
value Margaret Wise Brown.
To give you the full picture here
it looks like-- a bit like this.
But again, this is only one book.
So how could I actually get
multiple books to actually represent
multiple books in our code?
Well, we could keep this
same style of dictionary
where we have a
dictionary for every book
and it has the two
keys, title and author.
We could also make a list of
them-- a list of dictionaries.
So let's take a look
at this we could see--
OK, here I have this list.
And how do you know it's a list if
you take a look at this piece of code?
Well, we see those square
brackets on either end.
Again, the square
brackets that are there
at the beginning and
square brackets at the end.
And we also see we have
some commas in the middle,
just to highlight that here.
This is a list.
But inside of this list,
instead of individual strings,
for example, as we saw earlier,
we now have full dictionaries.
We have this dictionary for Goodnight
Moon, this dictionary for Corduroy,
and this dictionary for Curious George.
So this is helpful for us because we can
represent all kinds of different things
using dictionaries, but make
sure we have multiple of them
by keeping a list of these
very same dictionaries.
So let's get some practice here.
Let's go to books.py.
And inside of books.py,
we'll actually make
sure we can prompt the user for
a title of book and an author.
And we'll add that to our bookshelf,
which is a list of books, in this case.
So let's go back over here.
And let's close out some
old files and maybe we'll
go ahead and code up books.py.
So notice how we have part
of our code imprinted for us.
We have this list of
books that is empty.
And this is a list, again, because
it's simply two empty square braces.
Nothing inside this list, but
there could be eventually.
And now, we have this for
loop for i in range 3.
We saw range in lecture, which simply
gives us a list from 0 all the way up
to 2, in this case.
We can do 0, 1, 2, loop three times.
And inside this loop, we'll actually
make sure we have our new dictionary
and we add it to our list of books.
And finally, at the very
end, we'll print out
our bookshelf, our list
of books, in this case.
So if we wanted to start here,
well, I can go back to my syntax
as we saw before.
If I go back here and I see--
if I want to make a new dictionary,
I just need to ask for a blank dict.
So I'll go back over here and I'll say
give, me a new dictionary called book,
in this case.
And maybe I want to add
a key to this dictionary.
So think to yourself, what
is the syntax for that?
And it looks a bit like this.
We could say, OK, I want
to have a title here.
The key to this
dictionary will be title.
And I'll say, make sure that the
title is whatever the user inputs.
And I'll ask them for a title.
And similarly, I could also say, OK,
let's add an author to this book.
And I'll say, the input for that will
be asking the user for an author.
So now, we have this blank dictionary.
We've asked the user
to give us a new key
for the-- a new value for
the key title, and similarly,
a new value for the key author.
We've made these keys and given
them some value from the user.
All right, we have our book.
We could even print it
out if we wanted to.
You can print book down here.
Let's run Python of books.py.
We'll say let's get, in this case,
Goodnight Moon by Margaret Wise Brown.
And we see that, down below here, we do
have that dictionary being printed out.
And it's dictionary because we see it
has these curly braces on either end
and it has these keys
associated with these values.
So let's actually end our program here.
What we can do is try to
add this book to our list.
And if you are not familiar
with this yet, that's OK.
We can actually go ahead and say
books.append to add to our list.
So currently, our list is empty.
But we could use this method associated
with a list called append to actually
insert this book into our list.
Books.append and individual book.
So let's try this.
Let's actually go ahead
and down books.py.
We'll do Python of books.py.
Let's go ahead and add Goodnight Moon.
This one written by, let's say, CS50.
We could also add Corduroy.
And maybe, [INAUDIBLE] CS52.
And maybe we could add--
oh, I don't know, we
can add Curious George,
and that one is also written by CS50.
So now we see down below--
if I go full screen--
we have this list of dictionaries.
So what we saw before.
We have the brackets starting
our list on either end.
The commas separate our dictionaries.
And on the inside, we have this
dictionary, this dictionary,
and this dictionary down below here.
So now, we have some individual
books on our bookshelf.
And now, what can we do?
We could maybe decide to
print out just the titles.
I can go back through my books.
I could say for book in books,
looping through my list of books,
print out the book's title like this.
So now, instead of
printing the entire list,
I could print out just the titles.
I could do this.
I could say Python of books.py.
I'll say Goodnight Moon by CS50.
I'll say Corduroy by CS50.
And I will say, in this
case, Curious George by CS50.
And now, I see Goodnight Moon,
Corduroy, and Curious George.
So helpful because we're able
to structure our data inside
of a dictionary and put that
inside of our list here.
OK, so what if we wanted
to make sure the user
couldn't type in a really awkward title.
Like let's say, if I
do this again, I might
type in space, space, Goodnight Moon.
And that isn't quite what I want, right?
That isn't really good on me as
a user to give this kind of data,
but it's also not
going to the programmer
to assume that these are going to
give me exactly what I want here.
So instead of just accepting
user input, I actually
could go through and try to
sanitize it a little bit.
Make sure to clean it up.
So I actually have it in the
format I want it to be in.
I could instead say, OK,
whenever I get this input,
I want to afterwards
strip the white space.
And I also want to--
and we capitalize it.
So what this is doing here is
stringing this dot notation together.
So here I have input, which
took me back a string.
And remember, strings have access
to these methods, like dot strip
and dot capitalize.
So first, we're going to get some
input from the user, some string.
We're going to strip it using this.
And then, we're to run
capitalize on it like this.
So let's try that again.
Let's do, in this case, print out
just the title right after we get it.
We'll print out book title.
And let's go ahead and do this.
We'd say Python of books.py.
We'll say Goodnight Moon.
And it's a little better, right?
We capitalized the G in
Goodnight Moon and we made sure
that everything else is in lowercase.
And there's no white space in
front of anything we added here.
OK, so just some handy syntax
for cleaning up user input
and making sure that you
can make sure your data
is formatted correctly in
your own programs here.
OK, so now that we have some
dictionaries and this ability
to represent data in
this way, we can think
of getting a little more
advanced with our programs.
If I go back to our
slides, we might think
of not just getting this shelf
of books that the user types in,
but really using some
data in our programs.
And we'll see this in action
during the problem set this week.
How do we get data and use it inside of
our programs, especially using Python.
Well, you can think of these
libraries and these modules,
where a library is some code
somebody else has written.
And in Python, we more specifically we
call this often a individual module.
And so, in this example,
we'll actually see
a CSV module to work with data
that's inside of a CSV file.
But what is a CSC file?
So on your computer, maybe you have
Excel or Google Sheets or something
like that.
And you could store data in
different rows and different columns.
So notice how here I have a
title column and an author column
and individual rows for every book.
So I see Goodnight Moon with Margaret
Wise Brown, Corduroy with Don Freeman,
all the way down for these 15 or so
books that I have in my data set.
So this is what it looks like
in Google Sheets or Excel.
But under the hood, in the
actual computer's file,
you'll see something looks a bit like
this with title,author Goodnight Moon,
Margaret Wise Brown, and
Corduroy, Don Freeman.
So a CSV stands for
Comma Separated Values,
where notice how every
individual row is a single book
except for that first
one, which is the row--
is the column titles.
And for every row we have,
we have multiple columns
separated by these columns.
So Goodnight Moon is
a title of this book
and Margaret Wise Brown is the author
of this book that's on the same row
right here.
And similarly, Winnie the Pooh is
the title of this book and A.A.
Milne is title of this book--
is the author of this
book on that same row.
OK, so to read in these
kinds of files, we
might want to use a specialized
system that understands
how this data is formatted, right?
It would be a lot of work for you
to go through and parse every comma.
To figure out, OK, if
there's a comma here,
I need to put this piece of data in
that dictionary or this dictionary.
Let's not do that.
Let's actually rely on somebody else
who's done that work for us here.
So in Python, there is this
CSV library, or CSV module,
that has various methods or
functions given inside of it
that can help us read CSV files.
So here, if you go to the Python
documentation, docs.python.org,
and you look at this
CSV module, you'll be
able to see all the kinds
of information on what
is defined inside the CSV module and
what you get as part of that module.
Now, how would I use this in my code?
We saw this in lecture.
I could simply write import
csv, similar to hashtag
includes DNIO or hashtag includes CS50.
Here, I'm simply
including, or importing,
the CSV library that contains
all this functionality I
saw in the documentation.
So we can think visually of this.
It's a bit like getting
a big box of stuff.
We have this big box of code we can
use in our program now called CSV.
This is giving us a big box of code.
And inside of that are some
individual functions we could use.
We could use maybe DictReader,
DictWriter, reader, or writer.
All this is defined
inside of the CSV library.
But how do we know from
this big box of stuff
what we actually want
to use in our program?
So if we just import the entire
module, this entire big box of stuff,
well, to be more specific, what we want
to use, we have to use that dot syntax.
We could say something like this.
csv.DictReader, for example,
to read our CSV as this
collection of dictionaries.
We could say csv.DictReader
saying, go to that big box of stuff
in the CSV module and give me
the DictReader part of it--
the DictReader function, right?
We could also do csv.reader to
get the reader aspect and so on.
So this dot syntax is
coming back, but now, it's
enabling us to access
individual parts of our module.
But let's say we don't want the entirety
of this entire big box of CSV module.
We don't want everything in here.
Well, we could do this also.
We could say, instead of import CSV
as a whole, well, we could just say,
give me from the CSV library
the DictReader portion.
I could do this.
I could simply use now from
here on out just DictReader.
So from CSV, from this big box
of stuff, import just DictReader.
And then, I can simply use DictReader
without qualifying where it comes from
or what module it's part of
just using DictReader now.
Now, in general, we might prefer
to actually do this the other way,
to use it this way.
And why do you think that might be?
Think to yourself for a moment.
Well, it's often handy
to do it this way.
Because we do it this
way, we actually are
able to make sure we
don't collide our name.
So maybe my own program
has this function
called reader, by chance, right?
Here, if I say csv.reader, that
differentiates this reader function
from my own reader function.
So it's helpful if you're actually
defining your own function that
might collide names with the functions
you get from other modules in Python.
But you can, of course, do it this way.
If you'd like, and you're
very certain don't have
any function called DictReader here.
OK, so let's see some of the differences
between using these various functions
inside of this CSV library.
So we saw here before we had DictReader,
DictWriter, reader, and writer.
But what are the
difference between these,
and why would we even
use one versus another?
So to do that, let's actually dive
into reading files and maybe writing
to them.
So let's actually go back to our code
space now and think about this CSV.
We have books.csv.
and it's same thing we saw before.
We have title, author
as our column names,
and we have the title and the author
on individual rows separated by commas.
So if I want to read these,
I'll say, code reads.py.
I now have this list of books
and I've imported the CSV library
so I can read books from this CSV and
add them to my shelf, so to speak.
So to open a file in Python, well,
there's a few different ways to do it.
I could simply just call open.
I could say open books.csv.
But if I do that, I later have to
do something with the file here.
I'll say it like, file equals open.
And then, I have to close it.
I could say close file like this.
Or is it fclose?
Pretty sure it's close.
But you can double check me on that.
But we actually don't
have to-- we actually
have to worry about this at all
if we just say let's not just open
it like this.
Let's actually open it
within a certain context.
Only open it for a little bit.
And once we're done with that file,
go ahead and close it afterwards.
We can say with open this file and
let's call it something, like file,
in this case.
So we're going to open books.csv
and call it file with open this file
as file.
Let's do the following code indented.
So while we're indented
here, our file will be open.
We can do all kinds of things with it.
But once we unindent, we go back
out, our file will be closed.
We can't do anything more with it here.
So this takes care of
running close on our file
or figuring out when to
open it versus close it.
Python handles all of that now for
us using this with syntax here.
OK, so let's see this
in a little more depth.
We saw with open.
This whatever filing we have as file.
You can change file here.
We can also call this
maybe even books_file.
Doesn't have to be just file.
But here, we'll call it file.
We can then read it in
a few different ways.
And one way, it doesn't
even use the CSV module.
We could do this.
Text equals file.read where .read is
some method associated with a file that
lets us read in all the data that's
part of it and store it inside some
variables.
So here, let's do the same.
Let's say, text equals file.read.
And this is not using the CSV library.
We don't even need this right now.
We could simply say, Python of reads.py.
And we've maybe read our file.
It's hard to tell, so let's go
ahead and maybe print out the text.
And our Python of reads.py.
And now we see, in our terminal,
well, all the same text we had before.
Title, author.
Goodnight Moon, Margaret Wise Brown.
All of that is in our terminal now.
But this isn't very useful, right?
If we wanted to actually read in
some data, store it in our bookshelf,
well, that isn't going to help us
add to our list of books, right?
All of these books are
still jumbled together.
We don't really want that.
We want to actually
differentiate them and have
dictionaries for every book in our CSV.
So that's where this function of-- this
method called a DictReader comes in.
We can actually use the CSV module to
define a special way to read our file.
And we can then use it like this.
We could say, give us a
new file reader, this one
is special from the
csv.DictReader function.
And let's actually use that to
go through every individual row
in our file and do
something for those rows.
So it's best shown by example here.
If we go back to our code, let's
not just read all the text.
Let's go ahead and get a
special reader for our file.
Let's say I want a file reader.
And I'm going to make sure this is the
DictReader inside of the CSV module.
Well, if I read the documentation,
I know that DictReader needs access
to a certain file to read.
So I'll give it my file here
that I've opened, book.csv.
And DictReader will give
us back some special data
structure that we'll call file reader.
And we can use this in
our code as follows.
I have to loop over it
similar to a list in Python.
And I can do that with for syntax.
I could say for whatever in file reader.
And let's maybe call
this-- because we know
we're looking at books--
let's call this book.
For book in file reader.
And now let's just print out
book to see what we get here.
So I want it to just
say Python of reads.py.
And now, I see individual
books as dictionaries.
So DictReader has done
a lot of stuff for us.
It said, well, I know
that from your CSV file,
you have these columns
called title and author.
And I also know that
every individual row
is going to be some
particular element that you're
interested in where maybe this
column corresponds to title
and this column corresponds to author.
So what I'll do is I'll
give you each of those rows
as a dictionary with the keys
that are your column names
and the values that are whatever is
inside every individual row right here.
Notice how we have, in this
case, title as the key.
Goodnight Moon is the value.
Author is the key and Margaret
Wise Brown is the value.
And it's the very same thing
all the way through our CSV.
Now, print it out in our terminal
in individual dictionaries.
So if we've printed these out, adding
them to our list is pretty simple.
We can just say books.append
an individual book.
And now, if we clear our terminal
and are in Python or reads.py,
well, we don't see anything
because I didn't print it out.
So do print books down below here.
And now, we see all of our
books inside of our list.
And this is helpful because,
again, we could just print out
individual books or book titles.
I could say for book in books.
Let me go ahead and
print out the book title.
And I should see--
instead of all of my
information on all my books,
like we saw earlier with our just .read
method, I can say Python of read.py.
Now, I see just the titles formatted
very nicely for myself here.
So if we go back, this is how we're
going to actually read CSV files.
There's other ways too, like csv.reader.
But this isn't going to
quite be as useful for us
because let's take a look at this.
If we say csv.reader, let's go ahead and
save for row in file reader, print row.
Let's see what we get instead.
Python reads.py.
Well, we get just a list.
And notice how it's actually included
the column names in a single list.
So reader gives us back every
row of our file as a list.
But this isn't quite
as handy because I have
to know that, for example, if I want
to print out the book title, well,
that's going to be a row where my
titles are in the very first index.
So I'll say row [0] to get the titles.
Python reads.py.
And I get title
Goodnight Moon, Corduroy.
That works, but it's not
quite as clean as being
able to name the actual
attributes of my book that I want.
And that's where DictReader comes in.
By reading our rows as
dictionaries, we get access
to those individual keys we can
use throughout our code here.
So for book and file
reader, I can instead
print, in this case, the book's title.
Oops, the book title.
Python reads.py.
And now, I see all of this.
And DictReader also
knows, if you're curious,
not to print out the actual first row
because it assumes that these are going
to be the key names,
unlike reader, which
does not make that same assumption, OK?
So having done this tour of
these libraries and these modules
and how to read in
different pieces of data,
this is really going to
give you a lot of tools
to use on this week's problem set.
You'll be actually working with
these very similar files, CSV,
so even just textual files.
And as you go through, food to keep in
mind all what we learned right here.
How to open a file, how to read
it in using DictReader, and so on.
And as you go off into this week,
feel free to use all this stuff
from the section.
Thank you all for coming today.
Wonderful to see you.
We'll see you next week.