BRIAN YU: In the check function,
your job is to take a word
and check to see if the word
is in the dictionary or not.
The check function will
take a char star or a string
representing the word as
its input, and the output
will be a Boolean
variable, true or false.
So what does your check
function need to do?
Well, your function should return true
if the word is in your dictionary.
And it should return false otherwise.
And importantly, your check
function should be case insensitive.
It shouldn't matter if some
of the characters in the word
are uppercase or lowercase.
Your spell checker should still be able
to detect whether or not the word is
in the dictionary regardless of case.
So what are you going to need to do?
Well, the first step is
going to be to take the word
and hash the word using the hash
function that you implemented earlier
in order to obtain a hash value.
Then, you'll access the
linked list at that hash value
at that particular index in your
hash table, which, again, is just
an array of those
individual linked lists.
Once you've access that
individual linked list,
you know that if the word
is in the dictionary,
it's going to be in that list.
And if the word is not in that list,
then it's not in the dictionary.
So you can traverse that linked
list, looking at one node
at a time looking for
the word in question
and using the strcasecmp function,
which is similar to strcmp, which
compares to strings, but strcasecmp will
compare two strings case insensitively.
So it won't matter whether the word
is uppercase or lowercase for example
in order to find the word.
If you're able to successfully find the
word, your function will return true.
And otherwise, your
function will return false.
How do you traverse
a linked list though?
Well, let's take a look at an example.
Here, let's imagine that
head is a variable that
is a pointer to the first element in
the linked list, in this case, the word
bat, which is inside
of a node that points
to a node that has the word book,
which points to banana, for example.
How might I traverse that linked list?
Well, you could imagine that I
could set up a variable called
cursor, for example, which initially
is a pointer to the first element
in the linked list.
And I might check, is that
the word that I'm looking for?
And if it's not the word I'm looking
for, then what I'd like to do
is take the cursor and move it to
the next node in the linked list.
Well, where's the next node stored?
It's stored inside of the
next field inside of the node
that I'm currently looking at.
So if I were to use syntax like
cursor equals cursor arrow next,
that would mean take cursor and set it
equal to whatever cursor's next pointer
is currently pointing to.
So that would move cursor to the
next node in the linked list.
And I could check this node to see if
this is the correct word, again, using
the strcasecmp function to compare
two strings to see case insensitively
whether they contain the
same characters or not.
If that's not right, then I
might repeat the process setting
cursor equal to cursor arrow next
to move the cursor to the next node.
If I ever find the word in question,
I'll go ahead and return true.
But when do I stop?
You might imagine that this is
happening in some sort of loop.
And eventually, I'll reach the end of
the linked list, where, at some point,
I'll set cursor equal
to cursor arrow next.
And at the end of the linked
list, what we'll have is null.
So if we move forward cursor
equals cursor arrow next
and eventually cursor
becomes null, that means
we've reached the end of
the linked list and the word
wasn't found, which means the
word isn't in our dictionary
and our function should at
this point return false.
So as a brief recap, how are we
going to traverse this linked list?
You'll start with some cursor set to the
first node inside of your linked list.
And then you'll keep
moving the cursor, setting
it equal to cursor arrow next over
and over again checking each word
as you go until you get to null.
If you find the word
along the way, then that
means the word is in the dictionary and
you can return true from this function.
And otherwise, if you
reach the end of the list,
then the word is not in the
dictionary and you can return false.
As a result, your check function
will be able to take any word
and determine whether or not
it's inside of your dictionary.