BRIAN YU: The last step to
completing your spell checker is
to implement the unload function,
which is responsible for freeing up
any memory that you've allocated in the
process of running your spell checker.
What does this mean?
Well, remember that
anytime you dynamically
allocate memory using malloc,
it's also your responsibility
to call free on that memory,
to free up that memory
and give it back to the computer.
So what is your unload
function going to do?
Well, your unload function is
going to call free on any memory
that you've allocated using
malloc and return true
if it's able to do so successfully.
How are you going to do that?
Well, remember again that
your hash table is really
just an array of
individual linked lists.
Each of those linked
lists contains nodes
that you have allocated memory
for, likely using malloc.
So you'll need to free
each one of those nodes.
So you might imagine iterating
over your hash table,
going over each of those
individual linked lists,
and calling free on all of the
nodes inside of those linked lists.
But how do you free all of
the nodes in the linked list?
Let's take a look at an example.
Here again is a linked list
where we have a variable called
head, which is going to be a pointer to
the first element in the linked list.
In this case, a node that
has the word bat in it,
which has a next pointer that points
to book, which has a next pointer that
points to banana, in this case.
And let's imagine how we
might free up these nodes
that we've allocated using malloc.
You might imagine again that we could
have a variable called cursor which
is set equal to this node here.
It's a pointer to this node bat.
If I wanted to free this
node which I originally
allocated memory for using malloc.
I could use syntax like this--
free(cursor): to say, take what
cursor is pointing to, this node,
and go ahead and free up that memory.
But if I did that, what
you'll notice is now suddenly
I've freed up that memory,
which means I've also freed up
the memory that was allocated for
the next pointer that gave me access
to book, and banana, and all
of the remaining elements
inside of this linked list.
So you'll want to be careful.
If you free up some memory
before you're done using it,
you might lose access to the rest
of the nodes in the linked list
that you also need to free.
So what's the solution here?
We probably need some
other variable to help
us keep track of where we
are in this linked list
and to make sure that we
don't lose track of any nodes.
Let's go ahead and try this again.
Here, in addition to a variable
called cursor, which is currently
looking at the very first node
inside of this linked list,
I'll create another
variable called temp,
which is going to be equal to cursor.
They're both pointing to the same node.
In other words, they both contain
the address of this first node
inside of the linked list.
Now what I'd like to do
is free this temp pointer,
which is pointing to this first node.
But I want to make
sure that I don't lose
track of the rest of the linked list.
So what I can first do is say something
like cursor equals cursor arrow next
to say, go ahead and move the cursor
to the next element in the linked list
before we free the first element.
Now cursor is pointing to the
second element in the linked list.
So if I run a line of
code like free temp,
I can free up the bat node
without worrying about losing
the rest of the linked list.
Cursor is still pointing to it.
And now I can repeat the same process.
Go ahead and set temp to be
the same thing that cursor is.
Have temp point to book as well.
Then, to make sure we don't
lose the rest of the list,
go ahead and move cursor.
And then we can free up
the space that is allocated
to what temp is currently pointing to.
Free up that node and
repeat the process.
Have temp be set to the
same thing cursor is set to.
Move the cursor forward.
And then free up temp.
And eventually, once you get through
this entire process, what you'll find
is that cursor is pointing to null.
In other words, you've reached
the end of the linked list.
And at that point, that will
tell you that you've freed up
all of the nodes inside
of that linked list
and you're done freeing up all
the memory that was originally
allocated for those nodes.
If you repeat that process for
every one of the linked lists
that's inside of your
hash table, the result
will be that you've freed
up all of the memory that
was allocated for your hash table.
My name is Brian, and this was Speller.