BRIAN: In credit, your task is going
to be to take a credit card number
and determine whether that number
is an American Express credit card
number, a MasterCard number, a Visa
number or maybe, something else
entirely.
How are you going to do this?
Well, credit card numbers
follow particular patterns.
American Express card numbers, for
example, are generally 15 digits,
and start with the digits 3, 4 or 3, 7.
MasterCard numbers will
usually have 16 digits,
and often start with
51, 52, 53, 54, or 55.
Of course, there are other MasterCard
numbers that don't necessarily
follow this pattern, but for
the purposes of this problem,
we're just going to look at this
subset of MasterCard numbers.
And finally, Visa numbers
are 13 or 16 digits,
and will start with the digit 4.
But not every sequence of 13
digits that starts with the digit 4
is, necessarily, a Visa card number.
Every valid credit card number
also satisfies a checksum,
a relationship between the
digits of that credit card number
that determine whether that
particular sequence of numbers
is a valid credit card number or not.
How does this checksum algorithm work?
Well, it works as follows.
We first, multiply every other digit
of the credit card number by 2,
starting with the second to last digit.
Then we add those products'
digits together to get a number,
and we add that number to
the sum of all the digits
that we didn't multiply by 2.
If we take that final result,
and the last digit is zero,
then the credit card number is valid.
And if it's not, then it's invalid.
Let's take a look at an example
to see this algorithm in practice.
Here's an example of
a credit card number.
The first thing we're going to
do is take every other digit,
starting with the second to last digit.
So we're looking at the 1, the 0, the 0,
the 0, the 0, the 6, the 0, and the 4.
And we're going to take each of
those digits and multiply them by 2.
The next step is going to be to add all
of these individual digits together.
So 8 plus 0 plus 1 plus 2, because
those are the digits in 12,
plus 0 plus 0 plus 0 plus 0 plus 2,
that's going to give us the sum 13.
We're going to take 13 and add
that to all of the other digits
that we didn't multiply by 2.
So 13 plus 0 plus 3 plus 0 plus
0 plus 0 plus 0 plus 0 plus 4,
that result is going to
give us the number 20.
This is our final result.
The last digit is 0,
so this credit card number
satisfies the checksum.
It could be a valid credit card number.
So one of your tasks in
this problem is going to be,
given the credit card number, figure
out if it satisfies the checksum or not.
And to do that, you're going
to need to take a big number
and get at the individual
digits of the number.
But how do we get the
digits of the number?
Let's take a big number,
like this credit card number,
and consider how would we get the last
digit of this credit card number, which
in this case is the number 4?
Well, notice that if you take any
big number, and take the remainder.
When you divide it by 10, what
you get is the rightmost digit.
If we take this big number, divide
it by 10, and take the remainder,
the remainder is 4, the last digit.
And in code, we have the modulo
operator that gets us the remainder
when we divide it by something.
So if we take this big
number, and take it modulo 10,
that will give us the remainder,
when we take this number
and divide it by 10,
which in this case is 4.
So this gives us a way
of taking a big number
and figuring out what the last digit is.
And I'll leave it up
to you to figure out
how to adapt this to get the second to
last digit, or the third to last digit,
for example.
What do you need to do
in this problem, then?
Well, you'll first want
to prompt the user to type
in their input, a credit card number.
Then, you'll want to calculate
the checksum to figure out
if it could be a valid
credit card or not,
based on if that checksum has a
final digit that is or isn't a 0.
After you do that, you'll want to
check the credit card's length, as well
as the starting digits, to figure out if
it matches the pattern for an American
Express card or a Visa or a MasterCard.
And if it matches the
checksum and also matches
the card length and
starting digit requirements,
then your program should print
out Amex for an American Express
card, MasterCard for MasterCard,
Visa for a Visa card,
and if it doesn't
satisfy any of the three,
your program should print out invalid.
After you do that, you should
be able to test your program
on some sample valid and
invalid credit card numbers,
and make sure that you
get the right result.
My name is Brian, and this was credit.