[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right, one last time.
This is CS50, and we realize this
has been a bit of a fire hose
over the past-- thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
We realize this has been
a bit of a fire hose.
Indeed, recall that we
began the class in week 0,
months ago with this
here MIT hack, wherein
a fire hose was connected
to a fire hydrant,
in turn connected to a water fountain.
And it really spoke to
just how much information
we predicted would be sort of flowing
at you over the past few months.
If you are feeling all these
weeks later that it never actually
got easy, and with pset 1 to
pset 2, pset 3 on to pset 9,
you never quite felt like
you got your footing,
realize that it's kind of by design
because every time you did get your--
every time you did get
your footing, our goal
was to ratchet things
up a little bit more
so that you feel like
you're still getting
something out of that final week.
And indeed, that final
week is now behind us.
All that remains ahead of
us is the final project.
And what we thought we'd do today is
recap a little bit of where we began
and where you hopefully now are.
Take a look at the
world of cybersecurity,
because it's a scary place out
there, but hopefully you're
all the more equipped
now with a mental model
and vocabulary to evaluate threats in
the real world, and as educated people,
make decisions, be it in
industry, be it in government,
be it in your own personal
or professional lives.
And we hope ultimately,
too, that you've walked away
with a very practical
skill, including how
to program in C, how
to program in Python,
how to program in SQL, how
to program in JavaScript
in the context, for instance, of
even more HTML, CSS, and the like.
But most importantly, we hope
that you've really walked away
with an understanding of how to program.
Like, you're not going to have CS50 by
your side or even the duck by your side
forever.
You're going to have really, that
foundation that hopefully you'll
walk out of here today having
accumulated over the past few months.
And even though the world's
languages are going to change,
new technologies are going
to exist tomorrow, hopefully,
you'll find that a
lot of the foundations
over the past several months
really do stay with you
and allow you to bootstrap
to a new understanding,
even if you never take
another CS course again.
Ultimately, we claim that this
was all about solving problems.
And hopefully, we've kind of cleaned
up your thinking a little bit,
given you more tools in your toolkit
to think and evaluate and solve
problems more methodically, not only in
code, but just algorithmically as well.
And keep this mind too.
If you're still feeling like, oh, I
never really quite got your footing--
my footing, think back to how hard Mario
might have felt some three months ago.
But what ultimately matters in
this course is indeed, not so much
where you end up relative
to your classmates,
but where you end up relative
to yourself when you began.
So here we are, and
consider that there delta.
And if you don't believe me, like,
literally go back this weekend
or sometime soon, try
implementing Mario in C. And I do
dare say it's going to come
a little more readily to you.
Even if you need to Google
something, ask the duck something,
ask ChatGPT something just to
remember some stupid syntactic detail,
the ideas hopefully are
with you now for some time.
So that there hack is actually
fully documented here in MIT.
Our friends down the
road have a tradition
of doing such things every year.
One year, one of my favorites
was they turned the dome of MIT
into a recreation of R2-D2.
So there's a rich history of going
to great lengths to prank each other,
or even us here Harvard folks
akin to the Harvard Yale video
we took a look at last time.
And this duck has really become
a defining characteristic
of late of CS50, so much so that last
year, the CS50 Hackathon, we invited
the duck along.
It posed, as it is here, for
photographs with your classmates past.
And then around like, 4:00 AM, it
disappeared, and the duck went missing.
And we were about to head off
to IHOP, our friends from Yale.
Your former classmates
had just kind of packed up
and started driving back to New haven.
And I'm ashamed to say our first
thought was that Yale took it.
And we texted our TA friends on the
shuttle buses, 4:30 AM asking, hey,
did you take our duck because we kind
of need it next week for the CS50 fair?
And I'm ashamed to say that we thought
so, but it was not in fact, them.
It was this guy instead, down the road.
Because a few hours later after I
think, no sleep on much of our part,
we got the equivalent of a ransom email.
"Hi, David, it's your friend, bbd.
I hope you're well and not too
worried after I left so abruptly
yesterday night after such a successful
Hackathon and semester so far.
I just needed to unwind a bit and take
a trip to new places and fresh air.
Don't worry though, I will
return safe, sound, healthy, home
once I am more relaxed.
As of right now, I'm just spending
some few days with our tech friends
up Massachusetts Avenue.
They gave me a hand on moving tonight.
For some reason, I could never find my
feet, and they've been amazing hosts.
I will see you soon and I will miss
you and Harvard specially our students.
Sincerely yours, CS50 bbd."
So almost a perfect hack.
They didn't quite get the
DDB detail quite right.
But after this, they proceeded to make
a scavenger hunt of sorts of clues here.
This here is Hundredville.
And so in Hundredville, they handed
out flyers to students at MIT,
inviting folks to write a Python
program to solve a mystery.
"The CS50 duck has been stolen.
The town of Hundredville
has been called on you
to solve the mystery
of the-- authorities
believe that the thief stole the
duck and then shortly thereafter took
a walk out of town.
Your goal is to identify who the thief
is, what school the thief escaped to,
and who the thief's accomplice
is who helped them escape.
This took place on December 2, 2022,
and took place at the CS50 Hackathon."
In the days to come, we proceeded to
receive a series of ransom postcards
as the duck traveled, not only to MIT
to Professor John Guttag 6.100B class,
which is a rough equivalent
of CS50 down the road.
Pictured there our CS50 duck
with some tape on its torso.
But then the duck took,
apparently, a ride,
either in actuality or with
Photoshop, not only there,
took a tour of the Charles
River in front of Harvard,
the Charles in front of Boston.
It went all the way over to Yale.
We then received this
postcard from Princeton
all the way over from Stanford.
Duck took a flight according
to this photo here,
and then saw a bit of the world as well.
So eventually, we received a
follow-up email saying, "Hi, David.
I intend to arrive for the fair
between 8:37 AM and 9:47 AM.
It would be easier for my MIT hacker
friends to bring me to the right
location if there's someone waiting
there with a sign that says 'Duck'."
I'm not sure if we actually stood
there with a sign holding duck,
but it turns out they came
actually earlier in the morning
to escape detection altogether.
The duck found its home and
everyone lived happily ever after.
And here the duck is again today.
But our props to our
friends down the road at MIT
for returning the duck safely and
for going to such crazy lengths
to put us in the annals
of MIT's Hacks Gallery.
In fact, in exchange for this,
we sent them a little package.
And without telling you what
it is, you can read more
about this here hack that's
now been immortalized
on hacks.mit.edu at this URL here.
So maybe round of
applause for our friends
down the road for having
pulled that off a year ago.
[APPLAUSE]
So before we dive into
some of today's material,
I wanted to give you a sense
of what lies ahead as well.
So this year's CS50 Hackathon
is an annual tradition,
whereby students here at Harvard
and our friends from Yale who
will take buses in the
other direction to join us
in about a week's time for an epic
all-nighter, starting roughly at 7:00
PM ending roughly at 7:00
AM will be punctuated
by multiple meals, first meal-- first
dinner around 9:00 PM, second dinner
around 1:00 AM.
And those of you who
still have the energy
and are still awake around 5:00
AM, we'll hop in a shuttle bus
and head down to IHOP, the
larger one down the road,
not the one in the square, and have
a little bit of breakfast together.
The evening typically
begins a little bit
like this with a lot of
energy, the focus of which
is entirely on final projects.
The staff will be
present, but the intent
is not to be 12 hours of office hours.
Indeed, the staff will be working
on their own projects or psets,
final projects, and the like, but
to guide you toward and point you
in the direction of solutions
to new problems you have.
And we do think that the duck, and
in turn, AI, CS50.ai and other tools
you'll now be able to use, including
the actual ChatGPT, the actual GitHub
Copilot, or other AI tools
which are now reasonable to use
at this point in the semester
as you off board from CS50
and enter the real world.
Should be an opportunity for you to
take your newfound knowledge of software
out for a spin and build something
of your very own, something
that even maybe the TFs and myself
have never dabbled in before,
but with all of this now
software support by your side.
This here is our very own CS50 shuttles
that will take us then to IHOP.
And then a week after
that is the epic CS50
fair, which will be an opportunity
to showcase what it is you'll
pull off over the next few
weeks to students, faculty,
and staff across campus.
More details to come, but you'll
bring over your laptop or phone
to a large space on campus.
We'll invite all of your friends,
even family if they're around.
And the goal will be simply
to have chats like this
and present your final
project to passersby.
There'll be a bit of an
incentive model, whereby
anyone who chats you
up about their project,
you can give a little sticker to.
And that will enter them into
a raffle for fabulous prizes
to grease the wheels of
conversations as well.
And you'll see faculty from
across campus join us as well.
But ultimately, you walk out of that
event with this here CS50 shirt,
one like it, so you too, can proudly
proclaim that you indeed took CS50.
So all that and more to come, resting
on finally, those final projects.
But how to get there.
So here are some general advice
that's not necessarily going
to be applicable to all final projects.
But as we exit CS50 and
enter the real world,
here are some tips on what you
might read, what you might download,
sort of starting points so that
in answer to the FAQ, what now?
So for instance, if
you would like to begin
to experience on your own Mac or PC
more of the programming environment
that we provided to you, sort of turnkey
style in the cloud using cs50.dev,
you can actually install command line
tools on your own laptop, desktop,
or the like.
For instance, Apple has their own.
Windows has their own.
So you can open a terminal
window on your own computer
and execute much of the same commands
that you've been doing in Linux
this whole term.
Learning Git, so Git is
version control software.
And it's very, very popular in industry.
And it's a mechanism for saving
multiple versions of your files.
Now, this is something you
might be familiar with if still,
even using file names in the real
world, like on your Mac or PC--
maybe this is resume
version 1, resume version 2,
resume Monday night version, resume
Tuesday, or whatever the case may be.
If you're using Google documents,
this happens automatically nowadays.
But with code, it can happen
automatically, but also
more methodically using this here tool.
And Git is a very popular tool for
collaborating with others as well.
And you've actually
been secretly using it
underneath the hood for
a lot of CS50's tools.
But we've abstracted
away some of the details.
But Brian, via this video and
any number of other references,
can peel back that abstraction and
show you how to use it more manually.
You don't need to use cs50.dev
anymore but you are welcome to.
You can instead install VS
Code onto your own Mac or PC.
If you go to this first URL
here, it's a free download.
It's actually open source.
So you can even poke around and
see how it, itself is built.
And at CS50's own
documentation, we have some tips
for making it look like CS50's
environment even if longer term,
you want to cut the cord entirely.
What can you now do?
Well, many of you for
your final projects
will typically tackle websites, sort
of building on the ideas of problem
set 9, CS50 finance and the like,
or just generally something dynamic.
But if you instead want to host a
portfolio, like just your resume, just
projects you've worked on and
the like, a static websites
can be hosted for free
via various services.
A popular one is this URL
here, called GitHub pages.
There's another service that
offers a free tier called
Netlify that can allow you to host
your own projects statically for free.
But when it comes to more dynamic
hosting, you have many more options.
And these are just some
of the most popular.
The first three are some of
the biggest cloud providers
nowadays, whether it's Amazon or
Microsoft Azure or Google services.
If you go to this fourth URL here,
this is GitHub's education pack,
they essentially broker with
lots of different companies
to give students,
specifically, discounts on
or free access to a lot of tools.
So you might want to sign up
for that while you're eligible.
And then lastly, here are two
other popular third-party, but not
free services, but
that are very commonly
used when you want to host
actual web applications.
So maybe it's Flask, maybe it's
something else, but something
that involves some input and output.
Questions meanwhile-- so there's
just lots of communities.
If you want to keep an eye
on what's happening in tech,
these are just some of
the popular options.
And undoubtedly, if you
have some techie friends,
they'll have suggestions as well.
But you might find some of
these destinations of interest.
Of course increasingly, will you just
ask questions of software itself,
AI, whether it's ChatGPT,
GitHub Copilot, or the like.
And then classes, we're clearly a little
biased here with what's on the screen.
So these aren't college classes per
se, but freely available OpenCourseWare
courses that CS50's team
has put together over time.
And in a nutshell as you can infer
from the suffix of each of these URLs,
if you want to learn
more about Python, CS50
has got a free, open online
class for that, or SQL, thanks
to Carter, web and AI stuff, thanks to
Brian, a games class, thanks to Colton,
cybersecurity, which will
extend where we leave off today.
And then if you're
more interested, not so
much in coding and going
more deeply into software,
but want to take a step higher level and
focus more on intersections of computer
science with business
or law or technology,
those two are freely
available, if you're
looking for something to do over January
the summer or just to dabble over time.
And there's innumerable
other free resources
from other folks on the
internet as well certainly too.
All right, so a few
invitations and thank yous.
So one, after today, after we dive
into and out of cybersecurity,
please do stay in touch via any
of CS50's online communities.
As we start to recruit next year's
team for teaching fellows, teaching
assistants, course assistants,
we'll be in touch via email
for those opportunities as well.
And now some thanks for the group before
we then dive into here today's topic.
So one, allow me to thank
our hosts here for giving us
access to such a wonderful, privileged
space to just hold classes in,
the whole team for Memorial Hall.
Our thanks too, to ESS, which is the
team that makes everything sound so
good in spaces like this with music,
mics, and the like, our friends,
of course, Wesley down the road
at Changsho, where we went most
every other Friday this semester.
If you've never actually been,
or if you're hearing this online,
please join our friends at Changsho
show on Mass Ave down the road
any time you might like.
And then especially, CS50's
team-- there's quite a few humans
operating cameras in the room, both
here and way in back, as well as online.
My thanks.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you to them for making
this look and sound so good.
And what you don't see is
when I do actually screw up,
even if we don't fix it in
real time, they very kindly
help us go back in time, fix things,
so that your successors have hopefully,
an even improved version as well.
And then as well, CS50's
own Sophie Anderson,
who is the daughter of one
of CS50's teaching fellows
who lives all the way over in
New Zealand, who has wonderfully
brought the CS50 duck to
life in this animated form.
thanks to Sophie, this duck is now
everywhere, including most recently,
on some T-shirts too.
But of course, we have this
massive support structure
in the form of the team.
This is some of our past
team members, but who
wonderfully via Zoom you'll
recall in week seven,
showed us how TCP/IP works by
passing those envelopes up,
down, left, and right.
I commented at the time,
disclaim, that it actually took us
quite a bit of effort to do that.
And so I thought I would share
as a representative thanks
of our whole teaching team, whether
it's Carter and Julia and Ozan and Cody
and all of C50's team members
in Cambridge in New Hey,
thought I'd give you a look behind
the scenes at how things go indeed,
behind the scenes that
you don't necessarily see.
So let me switch over here and hit play.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[INAUDIBLE]
[INAUDIBLE] Buffering.
OK.
Josh?
Nice.
Helen?
Oh.
[CHUCKLING]
[INAUDIBLE] Moni-- no, oh, wait.
That was amazing, Josh.
Sophie.
Amazing.
That was perfect.
Moni.
[LAUGHTER] I think I--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
- Over to you, [INAUDIBLE].
Guy.
That was amazing.
Thank you all.
- So good.
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: All right,
these outtakes aside,
my thanks to the whole teaching team
for making this whole class possible.
[APPLAUSE]
So cybersecurity, this
refers to the process
of keeping secure our systems,
our data, our accounts, and.
More and it's something that's going
to be increasingly important, as it
already is, just because of the
sheer omnipresence of technology
on our desks, on our laps,
in our pockets, and beyond.
So exactly what is it?
And how can we, as students of computer
science over the past many weeks,
think about things a little more
methodically, a little more carefully,
and maybe even put some numbers to the
intuition that I think a lot of you
probably have when it comes to deciding,
is something secure or is it not?
So first of all, what does it
mean for something to be secure?
How might you as citizens of the
world now answer that question?
What does it mean to be secure?
AUDIENCE: Resistant to attack.
DAVID MALAN: OK, so resistant to
attack, I like that formulation.
Other thoughts on what
it means to be secure?
What does it mean?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: You control
who has access to it.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so you control
who has access to something.
And there's these techniques known
as authentication, like logging in,
authorization, deciding
whether or not that person,
once authenticated, should
have access to things.
And, of course, you
and I are very commonly
in the habit of using fairly
primitive mechanisms still.
Although, we'll touch
today on some technologies
that we'll see all the more of in the
weeks and months and years to come.
But you and I are
pretty much in the habit
of relying on passwords for
most everything still today.
And so we thought we'd begin
with exactly this topic
to consider just how secure or
insecure is this mechanism and why
and see if we can't
evaluate it a little more
methodically so that we can make
more than intuitive arguments,
but quantitative compelling
arguments as well.
So unfortunately we humans are
not so good at choosing passwords.
And every year, accounts
are hacked into.
Maybe yours, maybe your friends,
maybe your family members
have experienced this already.
And this unfortunately happens
to so many people online.
But, fortunately, there
are security researchers
in the world that take a look at
attacks once they have happened,
particularly when data from attacks,
databases, are posted online
or on the so-called dark web
or the like and downloaded
by others for malicious purposes,
they can also conversely provide us
with some insights as to
the behavior of us humans
that might give us some insights
as to when and why things
are getting attacked successfully.
So as of last year, here, for
instance, according to one measure
are the top 10 most popular, a.k.a.
worst passwords-- at least
according to the data
that security researchers
have been able to glean--
by attacks that have already happened.
So the number one password as of last
year, according to systems compromised,
was 123456.
The second most, admin.
The third most, 12345678.
And thereafter, 123456789, 1234, 12345,
password, 123, Aa123456, and then
1234567890.
So you can actually infer--
sort of goofy as some of these are--
you can actually infer certain policies
from these, right?
The fact that we're taking such
little effort to choose our password
seems to correlate really
with probably, what's
the minimum length of a
password required for systems?
And you can see that
at worst, some systems
require only three digit passwords.
And maybe they might require
six or eight or nine or even 10.
But you can kind of infer corporate or
policies from these passwords alone.
If you keep going through the list,
there's some funnier ones even down
the list that are
nonetheless enlightening.
So, for instance, lower on the
list is Iloveyou, no spaces.
Sort of adorable, maybe
it's meaningful to you.
But if you can think of
it, so can an adversary,
so can some hacker, so much so that
it's this popular on these lists.
Qwertyuiop, it's not quite English, but
its derivative of English keyboards.
Anyone?
Yeah, so this is, if you look
at a US English keyboard,
it's just the top row
of keys if you just
hit them all together left or right
to choose your, therefore, password.
And then this one,
"password," which has an at
sign for the A and a zero for the O,
which I guess I'm guessing some of you
do similar tricks.
But this is the thing too, if you
think like you're being clever,
well, there's a lot
of other adversaries,
there's a lot of adversaries out there
who are just as good at being clever.
So even heuristics like this
that in the past, to be fair,
you might have been taught
to do because it confuses
adversaries' or hackers' attempts,
unfortunately, if you know to do it,
so does the adversary.
And so your accounts aren't necessarily
any more secure as a result.
So what are some of our
takeaways from this?
Well, one, if you have these lists
of passwords, all too possible
are, for instance, dictionary attacks.
Like we literally have
published on the internet--
and there's a citation in the
slides if you're curious--
of these most popular
passwords in the world.
So what's a smart adversary going to do
when trying to get into your account?
They're not necessarily going
to try all possible passwords
or try your birthday
or things like that.
They're just going to start with
this top 10 list, this top 100 list.
And odds are, statistically,
in a room this big,
they're probably going to get into
at least one person's account.
But let's consider maybe a little more
academically what we can do about this.
And let's start with something
simple like the simplest, the most
omnipresent device we might
all have now is some kind
of mobile device like a phone.
Generally speaking, Apple
and Google and others
are requiring of us
that we at least have
a passcode or at least
you're prompted to set it up
even if you therefore opt out of it.
But most of us probably have a
passcode, be it numeric or alphabetic
or something else.
So what might we take away from that?
Well, suppose that you
do the bare minimum.
And the default for years
has generally been having
at least four digits in your passcode.
Well, what does that mean?
Well, how secure is that?
How quickly might it be hacked?
And, in fact, Carter, would
you mind joining me up here?
Perhaps we can actually decide
together how best to proceed here.
If you want to flip over
to your other screen there,
we're going to ask everyone to go to--
I'll pull it up here-- this URL
here if you haven't already.
And this is going to pull
up a polling website that's
going to allow you in a moment to
answer some multiple choice questions.
This is the same URL as earlier
if you already logged in.
And in just a moment, we're
going to ask you a question.
And I think, can we show the
question before we do this?
Here's the first question
from Carter here.
How long might it take to crack--
that is, figure out-- a four-digit
passcode on someone's phone,
for instance?
How long might it take to
crack a four-digit passcode?
Why don't we go ahead and flip
over to see who is typing in what.
And we'll see what the
scores are already.
All right, and it looks like
most of you think a few seconds.
Some of you think a few minutes,
a few hours, a few days.
So I'd say most of you are about
to be very unpleasantly surprised.
In fact, the winner here is
indeed going to be a few seconds,
but perhaps even faster than that.
So, in fact, let me
go ahead and do this.
Thank you to Carter.
Let me flip over and
let me introduce you
to, unfortunately, what's a very real
world problem known as a brute force
attack.
As the word kind of
conjures, if you think
to-- back to yesteryear when there
was some kind of battering ram trying
to brute force their
way into a castle door,
it just meant trying to hammer
the heck out of a system.
A castle, in that case, to
get into the destination.
Digitally though, this might
mean being a little more clever.
We all know how to write code in a
bunch of different languages now.
You could maybe open up a text editor,
write a Python program to try all
possible four-digit codes from 0000 to
9999 in order to figure out exactly,
how long does it actually take?
So let's first consider this.
Let me ask the next question.
How many four-digit passcodes are there?
Carter, if you wouldn't mind
joining me and maybe just staying up
with me here to run our second
question at this same URL.
How many four-digit passcodes
are there in the world?
On your phone or laptop, you
should now see the second question.
And the answers include 4, 40, 9,999,
10,000, or it's OK to be unsure.
Let's go ahead and flip
over to the results.
And it looks like most
of you think 10,000.
And, indeed, that is the case.
Because if I kind of led you with 0000
to 9999, that's 10,000 possibilities.
So that is, in fact, a lot.
But most of you thought it'd take maybe
a few seconds to actually brute force
your way into that.
Let's consider how we might measure
how long that actually takes.
So thank you.
So in the world of a
four-digit passcode-- and they
are, indeed, digits,
decimal digits from 0 to 9--
another way to think about it is there's
10 possibilities for the first digit,
10 for the next, 10 to the 10.
So that really gives us 10 times
itself four times or 10,000 in total.
But how long does that actually take?
Well, let me go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead and open
up on my Mac here, not even--
not even Codespaces or cs50.dev today.
I'm going to open up VS Code itself.
So before class, I went ahead and
installed VS Code on my own Mac here.
It looks almost the same as
Codespaces, though the windows
might look a little different
and the menus as well.
And I've gone ahead here and
begun a file called crack.py.
To crack something
means to break into it,
to figure out in this case
what the passcode actually is.
Well, how might I write some code to
try all 10,000 possible passcodes?
And, heck, even though
this isn't quite going
to be like hacking
into my actual phone, I
bet I could find a USB or a lightning
cable, connect the two devices,
and maybe send all of these passcodes
to my device trying to brute force
my way in.
And that's indeed how a hacker
might go about doing this
if the manufacturer doesn't
protect against that.
So here's some code.
Let me go ahead and do this.
From string, import digits.
This isn't strictly necessary.
But in Python, there is a
string library from which
you can get all of the
decimal digits just so I don't
have to manually type out 0 through 9.
But that's just a minor optimization.
But there's another
library called itertools,
tools related to iteration, doing
things in like a looping fashion, where
I can import a cross product
function, a function that's
going to allow me to combine
like all numbers with all numbers
again and again and again for
the length of the passcode.
Now I can do a simple
Python for loop like this.
For each passcode in the cross product
of those 10 digits repeated four times.
In other words, this is just
a programmatic Pythonic way
to implement the idea of combining
all 10 digits with itself
four times in a loop in this fashion.
And just so we can visualize
this, let's just go ahead
and print out the passcode.
But if I did have a lightning cable
or a USB cable, I wouldn't print it.
I would maybe send it through
the cable to the device
to try to get through
the passcode screen.
So we can revisit now
the question of how long
might it take to get into this device.
Well, let's just try this.
Python of crack.py.
And assume, again, it's
connected via cable.
So we'll see how long this program takes
to run and break into this here phone.
Done.
So that's all it took
for 10,000 iterations.
And this is on a Mac that's not
even the fastest one out there.
You could imagine
doing this even faster.
So that's actually not necessarily
all the best for our security.
So what could we do
instead of 10 digits?
Well, most of you have probably
upgraded a lot of your passwords
to maybe being alphabetical instead.
So what if I instead were to ask
the question-- and Carter, if you
want to rejoin me here in a second--
what if I instead were to consider
maybe four-letter passcodes?
So now we have A through Z four times.
And maybe we'll throw into
the mix uppercase and--
well, let's just keep it four letters.
Let's just go ahead and do
maybe uppercase and lowercase,
so 52 possibilities.
This is going to give us 52
times 52 times 52 times 52.
And anyone want to
ballpark the math here,
how many possible four-letter
passcodes are there, roughly?
7 million, yeah, so roughly 7 million,
which is way bigger than 10,000.
So, oh, I spoiled this, didn't I?
Can you flip over?
So how many four-letter
passcodes are there?
It seems that most of you, 93% of
you, in fact, got the answer right.
Those of you who are
changing your answer-- there
we go, no, definitely not that.
So, anyhow, I screwed up.
Order of operations matters in computing
and, indeed, including lectures.
So 7 million, so the
segue I wanted to make
is, OK, how long does that
actually take to implement in code?
Well, let me just tweak
our code here a little bit.
Let me go ahead and go back into
the VS Code on my Mac in which I
had the same code as before.
So let me shrink my terminal window,
go back to the code from which I began.
And let's just actually
make a simple change.
Let me go ahead and simply change digits
to something called ASCII letters.
And this too is just a
time saving technique.
So I don't have to type out A through
Z and uppercase and lowercase like 52
total times.
And so I'm going to change
digits to ASCII letters.
And we'll get a quantitative
sense of how long this takes.
So Python of crack.py,
here's how long it takes
to go through 7 million possibilities.
All right, clearly slower because we
haven't seen the end of the list yet.
And you can see we're going through
all of the lowercase letters here.
We're about to hit Z. But now we're
going through the uppercase letters.
So it looks like the answer this time
is going to be a few seconds, indeed.
But definitely less than a
minute would seem, at least
on this particular computer.
So odds are if I'm
the adversary and I've
plugged this phone into
someone's device-- maybe
I'm not here in a lecture,
but in Starbucks or an airport
or anywhere where I have physical
opportunity to grab that device
and plug a cable in-- it's not going
to take long to hack into that device
either.
So what might be better than just
digits and letters from the real world?
So add in some punctuation,
which like almost every website
requires that we do.
Well, if we want to add punctuation
into the mix, if I can get this segue
correct so that we can now
ask Carter one last time,
how many four-character passcodes
are possible where a character is
an uppercase or lowercase letter or a
decimal digit or a punctuation symbol?
If you go to your
device now, you'll see--
if we want to flip over to the screen--
these possibilities.
There's a million, maybe, a
billion, a trillion, a quadrillion,
or a quintillion when it comes
to a-- oh, wrong question.
Wow, we're new here, OK.
OK, we're going to escalate things here.
How many eight-character
passcodes are possible?
We're going to make things more
secure, even though I said four.
We're now making it
more secure to eight.
All right, you want to
flip over to the chart?
All right, so it looks
like most of you are now
erring on the side of
quintillion or quadrillion.
1% of you still said million, even
though there's definitely more
than there were a moment ago.
But that's OK.
So quadrillion-- quintillion
is still winning.
And I think if we go and
reveal this, with the math,
you should be doing is
94 to the 4th power.
Because there's 26 plus 26
plus 10 plus some more digits,
some punctuation digits
in there as well.
So it's actually, oh, this is
the other example, isn't it?
This is embarrassing.
All right, we had a good run
in the past nine weeks instead.
All right, so if you were curious as to
how many four-character passwords are
possible, it's 78 million.
But that's not the question at hand.
The question at hand was, how many
eight character passcodes are there?
And in this case, the
math you would be doing
is 94 to the 8th power,
which is a really big number.
And, in fact, it's
this number here, which
is roughly 6 quadrillion possibilities.
Now, I could go about actually
doing this in code here.
So let me actually,
for a final flourish,
let me open up VS Code
one last time here.
And in VS Code, I'm going to go
ahead and shrink my terminal window,
go back into the code, and I'm going to
import not just ASCII letters, not just
digits, but punctuation
as well, which is
going to give me like
32 punctuation symbols
from a typical US English keyboard.
And I'm going to go ahead and just
concatenate them all together in one
big list by using the
plus operator in Python
to plus in both digits and punctuation.
And I'm going to change the 4 to an 8.
So this now, it's what
four actual lines of code
is, all it takes for an
adversary to whip up some code,
find a cable as step two,
and hack into a phone that
even has eight-character passcodes.
Let me enlarge in my
terminal window here, run
for a final time Python of crack.py.
And this I'll actually
leave running for some time.
Because you can get already sort of
a palpable feel of how much slower it
is-- because these characters
clearly haven't moved--
how long it's going to take.
We might actually do--
need to do a bit more math.
Because doing just four-digit
passcodes was super fast.
Doing four-letter passcodes was
slower, but still under a minute.
We'll see maybe in time how
long this actually runs for.
But this clearly seems to be better,
at least for some definition of better.
But it should hopefully not be
that easy to hack into a system.
What does your own device probably do to
defend against that brute force attack?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Gives you a
limited number of tries.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so it gives
you a limited number of tries.
So odds are, at least once in your
life, you've somehow locked yourself out
of a device, typically after typing
your passcode more than 10 times
or 10 attempts or maybe it's your
siblings or your roommate's phone
that you realize this is a feature of
iPhones and Android devices as well.
But here's a screenshot
of what an iPhone might
do if you do try to input the wrong
passcode maybe 10 or so times.
Notice that it's really telling
you to try again in one minute.
So this isn't fundamentally
changing what the adversary can do.
The adversary can absolutely use those
same four lines of code with a cable
and try to hack into your device.
But what has this just done?
It's significantly increased
the cost to the adversary,
where the cost might be measured
in sheer number amount of time--
like minutes, seconds,
hours, days, or beyond.
Maybe it's increased the
cost in the sense of risk.
Why?
Because if this were like
a movie incarnation of this
and the adversary has just
plugged into the phone
and is kind of creepily looking
around until you come back,
it's going to take way too long for
them to safely get away with that,
assuming your passcode
is not 123456, it's
somewhere in the middle of
that massive search space.
So this just kind of fundamentally
raises the bar to the adversary.
And that's one of the biggest
takeaways of cybersecurity in general.
It's completely naive to think
in terms of absolute security
or to even say a sentence like
"my website is secure" or even
"my home is physically secure."
Why?
Well, for a couple of reasons,
like, one, an adversary
with enough time, energy,
motivation, or resources
can surely get into most any system
and can surely get into most any home.
But the other thing to
consider, unfortunately,
that if we're the good people in
this story and the adversaries
are the bad people, you and
I rather have to be perfect.
In the physical world, we have
to lock every door, every window.
Because if we mess up just one
spot, the adversary can get in.
And so where there's
sort of this imbalance.
The adversary just has
to find the window that's
ajar to get into your physical home.
The adversary just needs
to find one user who's
got a really bad password to
somehow get into that system.
And so cybersecurity is hard.
And so what we'll see
today really are techniques
that can let you create a gauntlet
of defenses-- so not just one,
but maybe two, maybe three.
And even if the adversary gets in,
another tenant of cybersecurity
is at least, let's have
mechanisms in place that detect
the adversary, some kind of
monitoring, automatic emails.
You can increasingly see this
already in the real world.
If you log into your Instagram
account from a different city or state
suddenly because maybe
you're traveling, you
will-- if you've opted into
settings like these-- often
get a notification or
an email saying, hey,
you seems to have logged in from
Palo Alto rather than Cambridge.
Is this, in fact, you?
So even though we might not be
able to keep the adversary out,
let's at least minimize the
window of opportunity or damage
by letting humans like us know
that something's been compromised.
Of course, there is a downside here.
And this is another
theme of cybersecurity.
Every time you improve something,
you've got to pay a price.
There's going to be a tradeoff.
And we've seen this with time and space
and money and other such resources
when it comes to
designing systems already.
What's the downside of this mechanism?
Why is this perhaps a bad thing
or what's the downside to you,
the good person in the story?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, if you've
just forgotten your passcode,
it's going to be more
difficult for you to log in.
Or maybe you just really need
to get into your phone now
and you don't really
want to wait a minute.
And if you, worse, if you
keep trying, sometimes it'll
change to two minutes,
five minutes, one hour.
It'll increase exponentially.
Why?
Because Apple and Google figure
that, they don't necessarily
know what the right cutoff is.
Maybe it's 10, maybe it's
fewer, maybe it's more.
But at some point, it
is much more likely
that this is a hacker trying to get in
than it is for getting your passcode.
But in the corporate world,
it can be even worse.
There's a feature that lets phones
essentially self-destruct whereby
rather than just waiting
you wait a minute,
it will wipe the device,
more dramatically.
The presumption being that, no, no, no,
no, no, if this is a corporate phone,
let's lock it down further
so that it is an adversary,
the data is gone after
10 failed attempts.
But there's other mechanisms as well.
In addition to logging
into phones via passcodes,
there's also websites
like Gmail, for instance.
And it's very common, therefore,
to log in to websites like these.
And odds are,
statistically, a lot of you
are in the habit of reusing passwords.
Like, no, don't nod if you are.
We have cameras everywhere.
But maybe you're in the
habit of reusing it.
Why?
Because it's hard to remember
really big long cryptic passwords.
So mathematically, there's
surely an advantage there.
Why?
Because it just makes it so much
harder, more time-consuming,
more risky for an adversary to get in.
But the other tradeoff is
like, my God, I just can't even
remember most of my
passwords as a result
unless I reuse the one good password
I thought of and memorized already
or maybe I write it down on
a post-it note on my monitor,
as all too often happens
in corporate workplaces.
Or maybe you're being clever
and in your top right drawer,
you've got a printout
of all of your accounts.
Well, if you do, like ha-ha,
so do a lot of other people.
Or maybe it's a little
more secure than that,
but there are sociological side effects
of these technological policies that
really until recent years
were maybe underappreciated.
The academics, the IT administrators
were mandating policies
that you and I as human users were
not necessarily behaving properly
in the face of.
So nowadays, there are things
called password managers.
And a password manager is just
a piece of software on Macs,
on PCs, on phones that manage
your passwords for you.
What this means
specifically is when you go
to a website for the very
first time, you, the human,
don't need to choose
your password anymore.
You instead click a button or
use some keyboard shortcut.
And the software generates a really
long cryptic password for you
that's not even eight characters.
It might be 16 or 32 characters, can
be even bigger than that, but with lots
of randomness.
Definitely not going to be on
that top 10 or that top 100 list.
The software thereafter
remembers that password
for you and even your username, whether
it's your email address or something
else.
And it saves it onto your Mac or your
phone or your PC's disk or hard drive.
The next time you visit that
same website, what you can do
is via menu or, better yet, a keyboard
shortcut, log into the website
without even remembering or
even knowing your password.
I mean, to this day, I'll
tell you, I don't even
know anymore 99% of my own passwords.
Rather, I rely on software like
this to do the heavy lifting for me.
But there's an obvious
downside here, which
might be what if you're doing this?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Right, so what if
they find out the one password
that's protecting this software?
Because unstated by me up until now
is that this password manager itself
has a primary password that protects all
of those other eggs in the one basket,
so to speak.
And my one primary password
for my own password manager,
it is really long and hard to guess.
And the odds that
anyone's going to guess
are just so low that I'm
comfortable with that
being the one really difficult thing
that I've committed to my memory.
But the problem is if someone does
figure it out nonetheless somehow
or, worse, I forget what it is.
Now, I've not lost access to one
account, but all of my accounts.
Now, that might be too
high of a price to pay.
But, again, if you're in the habit
of choosing easy passwords like being
on that top 10 list, reusing
passwords, it's probably a net
positive to incur this single
risk versus the many risks you're
incurring across the board
with all of these other sites.
As for what you can use,
increasingly our operating systems
come with support for this, be it in the
Apple world, Google, Microsoft world,
or the like.
There's third party software
you can pay for and download.
But even then, I would beware.
And I would ask friends
whose opinion you trust or do
some googling for reviews and the like.
All too often in the software
world have password managers
been determined to be buggy themselves.
I mean, you've seen in weeks of CS50
how easy it is to introduce bugs.
And even the best of programmers
still introduce bugs to software.
So you're also trusting that the
companies making this password
management software
is really good at it.
And that's not always the case.
So beware there too.
But we'll also focus today
on some of the fundamentals
that these companies can be using
to better protect your data as well.
But there's another mechanism, which
odds are you're in the habit of using.
Two-factor authentication,
like most of us
probably have to use this
for some of your accounts--
your Harvard account, your Yale account,
maybe your bank accounts, or the like.
So what is two-factor
authentication in a nutshell?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, you
get a second factor
that you have to provide to
the website or application
to prove that it's you
like a text to your phone
or maybe it's an actual application that
gets push notifications or the like.
Maybe in the corporate
world, it's actually
a tiny little device with a screen on
it that's on your keychain or the like.
Maybe it's actually a USB dongle that
you have to plug into your work laptop.
In short, it's some second factor.
And by factor, I mean
something technical.
It's not just a second password,
which would be one factor.
It's a second fundamentally
different factor.
So generally speaking in the world of
two-factor authentication or 2FA or MFA
is the generalization as
multi-factor authentication,
you have not just a password,
which is something you know,
the second factor is
usually something you have--
whether it's your phone or that
application or the keychain.
It might also be biometrics like
your fingerprints, your retinas,
or something else physically about you.
But it's something that significantly
decreases the probability
that some adversary is going
to get into that account.
Why?
Because right now, if you've
only got a username and password,
your adversaries are literally
every human in the world
with an internet connection, arguably.
But as soon as you
introduce 2FA, now it's
only people on campus or, more
narrowly, only the people in Starbucks
at that moment who might
physically have access
to your person and your
second factor, in this case.
More technically, what those
technologies do is they send you
a one-time passcode, which is further
secure because once it's used,
there's hopefully some database
that remembers that it has been used
and cannot be used again.
So an adversary can't like
sniff the airwaves and replay
that passcode the next
time they, indeed, expire,
which adds some additional defense.
And you might type it into a
phone or maybe a web app that
looks a little something like this.
So passwords thus far, some defenses,
therefore, any questions on this
here mechanism?
No?
All right, well, let's consider this.
Odds are, with some frequency, you
forget these passwords, especially
if you're not using a password manager.
And so you go to Gmail
and you actually have
to click a link like
this, Forgot Password.
And then it typically
emails you to initiate
a process of resetting that password.
But if you can recall, has anyone
ever clicked a link like that
and then got an email with
your password in the email?
Maybe if you ever see
this in the wild, that
is to say in the real world, that
is horrible, horrible design.
Why?
Because well-designed websites,
not unlike CS50 Finance,
which had a users table, should
not be storing username-- rather,
should not be storing passwords
in the clear, as it actually is.
It should somehow be
obfuscated so that even
if your database from CS50
Finance or Google's database
is hacked and compromised
and sold on the web,
it should not be as simple
as doing like select star
from Account semicolon to see
what your actual passwords are.
And the mechanism that
well-designed websites use
is actually a primitive back
from like week 5 when we
talked about hashing and hash tables.
This time, we're using it for
slightly different purposes.
So in the world of passwords, on the
server side, there's often a database
or maybe, more simply, a text
file somewhere on the server
that just associates
usernames with passwords.
So to keep things simple, if there's
at least two users like Alice and Bob,
Alice's password is maybe apple.
Bob's password is maybe banana, just
to keep the mnemonics kind of simple.
If though that were
the case on the server
and that server is compromised,
whoever the hacker now
has access to every username and
every password, which in and of itself
might not be a huge deal because maybe
the server administrators can just
disable all of the accounts, make
everyone change their password,
and move on.
But there's also this attack
known as password stuffing, which
is a weirdly technical term, which
means when you compromise one database,
you know what?
Take advantage of the
naivety of a lot of us users.
Try the compromised Apple
password, the banana
password not on the compromised
website, but other websites
that you and I might have
access to, the presumption
being that some of us
in this room are using
the same passwords in multiple places.
So it's bad if your password
is compromised on one server
because, by transitivity, so can all
of your other accounts be compromised.
So in the world of hashing,
this was the picture
we drew some time ago, we can apply
this same logic whereby, mathematically,
a hash function is like some
function F and the input is X
and the output or the
range is F of X. That
was sort of the fancy way
of describing mathematically
hashing as a process weeks ago.
But here, at a simpler level,
the input to this process
is going to be your actual password.
The output is going to be a
hash value, which in week 5
was something simple
generally like a number--
1 or 2 or 3 based on the first letter.
That's not going to be quite
as naive an approach as we
take in the password world.
It's going to look a
little more cryptic.
So Apple weeks ago might have just
been 1, banana might have been 3.
But now let me propose that in the
world of real world system design, what
the database people
should actually store
is not apple, but rather
this cryptic value.
And you can think of this as sort
of random, but it's not random.
Because it is the result of an
algorithm, some mathematical function
that someone implemented and
smart people evaluated and said,
yes, this seems to be
secure, secure in the sense
that this hash function
is meant to be one way.
So this is not encryption, a
la Caesar Cipher from weeks
ago whereby you could just add 1 to
encrypt and subtract 1 to decrypt.
This is one way in the
sense that given this value,
it should be pretty much impossible
mathematically to reverse the process
and figure out that the user's
password was originally apple.
Meanwhile banana, back in week 5 for
simplicity, for hashing into a table,
we might have had a simple
output of 2, since B
is the second letter of
the English alphabet.
But now the hash value of banana, thanks
to a fancier mathematical function,
is actually going to be
something more cryptic like this.
And so what the server really does is
store not apple and banana, but rather
those two seemingly cryptic values.
And then when the human,
be it Alice or Bob,
logs in to a web form with their actual
username and password, like Alice,
apple, Bob, banana, the
website no longer even
knows that Alice's password is
apple and that Bob's is banana.
But that's OK.
Because so long as the
server uses the same code
as it was using when these
folks registered for accounts,
Alice can type in apple, hit Enter,
send it via HTTP to the server.
The server can run that same
hash function on A-P-P-L-E.
And if the value matches, it can
conclude with high probability, yes,
this is in fact, the original Alice
or this, in fact, is the original Bob.
So the server never saves the password,
but it does use the same hash function
to compare those same hash values again
and again whenever these folks log in
again and again.
So, in reality, here's a simple
one-way hash for both Alice's
and Bob's passwords in the real world.
It's even longer, this
is to say, than what I
used as shorter examples a moment ago.
But there is a corner case here.
Suppose that an adversary is
smart and has some free time
and isn't necessarily interested
in getting into someone's account
right now, but wants
to do a bit of prework
to decrease the future cost of
getting into someone's account.
There is a technical term
known as a rainbow table,
which is essentially like a dictionary
in the Python sense or the SQL sense,
whereby in advance an adversary could
just try hashing all of the fruits
of the world or, really, all of the
English words of the world or, rather,
all possible four-digit, four-character,
eight-character passcodes in advance
and just store them in two columns--
the password, like 0000
or apple or banana,
and then just store in
advance the hash values.
So the adversary could effectively
reverse engineer the hash
by just looking at a hash, comparing it
against its massive database of hashes,
and figuring out what password
originally correspond to that.
Why then is this still relatively safe?
Rainbow tables are concerning.
But they don't defeat
passwords altogether.
Why might that be?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, so
the adversary might not
know exactly what hash
function the company is using.
Generally speaking, you would not
want to necessarily keep that private.
That would be considered
security through obscurity.
And all it takes is like one bad
actor to tell the adversary what
hash function is being used.
And then that would put
your security more at risk.
So generally in the
security world, openness
when it comes to the
algorithms in process
is generally considered best practice.
And the reality is, there's a few
popular hash functions out there
that any company should be using.
And so it's not really
keeping a secret anyway.
But other thoughts?
Why is this rainbow
table not such a concern?
AUDIENCE: It takes a lot
longer for the [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: It takes a lot
longer for the adversary
to access that information
because this table could get long.
And even more along those lines--
anyone want to push a little harder?
This doesn't necessarily put
all of our passwords at risk.
It easily puts our
four-digit passcodes at risk.
Why?
Because this table, this dictionary
would have, what, 10,000 rows?
And we've seen that you can
search that kind of like that
or even regenerate all
of the possible values.
But once you get to
eight-character passcodes,
I said it was 4
quadrillion possibilities.
That's a crazy big dictionary
in Python or crazy big list
of some sort in Python.
That's just way more RAM or memory than
a typical adversary is going to have.
Now, maybe if it's a particularly
resourced adversary like a government,
a state more generally, maybe
they do have supercomputers
that can fit that much information.
But, fine, then use a
16-character passcode
and make it an unpronounceable
long search space
that's way bigger than 4 quadrillion.
So it's a threat, but only if you're
on that horrible top 10 list or top 100
or short passcode list that
we've discussed thus far.
So here's though a related threat
that's just worth knowing about.
What's problematic here?
If we introduce two more
users, Carol and Charlie,
and just for the semantics of it,
whose password happened to be cherry.
What if they both happened to have
the same password and this database
is compromised?
Some hacker gets in.
And just to be clear, we wouldn't be
storing apple, banana, cherry, cherry.
We'd still be storing, according
to this story, these hashes.
But why is this still concerning?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
If you figure out just one of
them, now you've got the other.
And this is, in some sense,
just leaking information, right?
I don't maybe at a glance what I
could do with this information.
But if Carol and Charlie have
the same password, you know what?
I bet they have the same password
on other systems as well.
You're leaking information that
just does no good for anyone.
So how can we avoid that?
Well, we probably don't want to
force Carol or Charlie to change
their password, especially
when they're registering.
You definitely don't want to say, sorry,
someone's already using that password,
you can't use it as well.
Because that too would leak information.
But there's this technique
in computing known as salting
whereby we can do this instead.
If cherry we in this scheme hashes
to a value like this, you know what?
Let's go ahead and sprinkle a
little bit of salt into the process.
And it's sort of a metaphorical salt
whereby this hash function now takes
two inputs, not just the password,
but some other value known as a salt.
And the salt can be generally something
super short like two characters even,
or something longer.
And the idea is that this
salt, much like a recipe,
should of perturb the
output a little bit,
make it taste a little bit
differently, if you will.
And so concretely, if we take the word
cherry and then when Carol registers,
for instance, we randomly choose a
salt of 50, 5-0, so two characters,
the hash value now--
because there's two inputs--
might now be this value.
But if for Charlie, we still have
cherry, but we change the 50,
we might see this instead.
Notice that for this
first example, Carol, 50,
the salt is preserved in the hash
value, just so you know what it was
and you can sprinkle the same amount
of salt, so to speak, next time.
But that's the whole hash
value for Carol in this case.
But if Charlie also has a password
of cherry, but we change the salt to,
say, 49 arbitrarily, that
whole hash value changed.
And so now in my hash database, I'm
going to see different salts there,
different values, which is going
to effectively cover up the fact
that Carol and Charlie
have the same password.
Now, if we have so many users
that we run out of salts,
that still might leak some information.
But that's kind of a we can kick down
the road and probabilistically not
going to happen if you require passwords
of sufficiently long length, most
likely.
So any questions on
salting, which to be clear,
is just a mechanism for
decreasing the probability
that an adversary is
going to glean information
that you might not want them to have?
So what does this mean concretely?
When you get an email from a
website saying "click this link
to reset your password," it's not
the website, if well designed,
is being difficult or shy and
not telling you your password,
the web administrators just do
not know, ideally, your password.
So what are they doing?
They're probably sending you
a link, similar in spirit
to a one-time password, there's
some random unique string in there
that's unique to you.
They've stored that in their database.
So as soon as you click on that
link, they check their database
and be like, oh, wait a minute, I know
I set this link a minute ago to David.
Let me just trust now-- because
probabilistically there's no way
someone guessed this
URL within 60 seconds--
let's trust that whatever he wants
to type in as his new password
should be associated with that
Malan account in the database.
But if, conversely, you ever get an
email saying your password is 123456
or whatever it is, it is clearly
not being hashed, let alone salted,
on the server.
And that is not a website to do
anything particularly sensitive with.
All right, so what more can we do?
Well, let's pick up where we left off
in week two on the art of cryptography,
this art, the science of scrambling
information, but in a reversible way.
So whereas hashing, as we've described
it here, is really tends to be one-way,
whereby you should not be able to
reverse the process unless you cheat
and make a massive table
of all of the inputs
and all of the outputs,
which isn't really so much
reversing as it is just looking it up.
Cryptography, like in
week 2, can actually
be a solution to a lot of
problems, not just sending messages
across a crowded room.
We, weeks ago, really focused
on this type of cryptography
whereby you've got some
plain text message.
You've got a key, like a secret
number 1 or 13 or something else.
The cipher, which might be a rotational
cipher or a substitution cipher,
some algorithm, and then
ciphertext was the term
of art for describing
the scrambled version.
That should look like random
zeros and ones or letters
of the alphabet or the like.
This though was reversible,
whereby you could just
input the ciphertext with the key
and get back out the plain text.
Maybe you have to change a positive
number to a negative number.
But the key is really the same.
Be it plus 1 minus 1 or plus 13
minus 13, the process was symmetric.
And, indeed, what we
talked about in week two
was an example of something called
secret key cryptography, where
there's, indeed, one secret
between two parties, a.k.a.
symmetric cryptography.
Because encryption is pretty much
the same as decryption, but maybe
you change the sign on the key itself.
But this is not necessarily all we want.
Because here's that general process.
Here's the letter A.
Here's the key of 1.
We outputed in week 2 a value
of B. That's not necessarily
the solution to all of our problems.
Why?
Well, if two people want to communicate
securely, they need some shared secret.
So, for instance, if I wanted to
send a secret message to Rongxin
in the back of the room
here, he and I have better
agreed upon a secret in advance.
Otherwise, how can I possibly send
a message, encrypt it in a way
that he can reverse?
I mean, I could be like,
(WHISPERING) let's use a key of 1.
(SPEAKING NORMALLY) But
obviously, anyone in the middle
has just now heard that.
So we might as well not
communicate securely at all.
So there's this kind of
chicken-and-the-egg problem,
not just contrived here in lecture.
But the first time I want to
buy something on amazon.com
with my credit card, I would like
my credit card to be encrypted,
scrambled somehow.
But I don't know anyone personally
at amazon.com, let alone someone
that I've prearranged some secret
for my Mac and their servers.
So it seems that we fundamentally
can't use symmetric cryptography
all of the time, unless we have some
other mechanism for securely generating
that key, which we don't have as
the common case in the world today.
Thankfully, mathematicians
years ago came up
with something known as
asymmetric cryptography, which
does not require that you use the
same secret in both directions.
This is otherwise known as
public key cryptography.
And it works essentially as follows.
When you want to take some
plaintext message and encrypt it,
you use the recipient's public key.
So if Rongxin is my colleague
in back and he has a public key,
it is public by definition.
He can literally shout
for the whole room
to hear what his public key
is, which effectively is just
some big, seemingly random number.
But there's some mathematical
significance of it.
And I can write that down.
Heck, you can all write it down if you
too want to send him secure messages.
And out of those two inputs, we
get one output, the ciphertext,
that I can then hand off to people in
the room in those virtual envelopes.
And it doesn't matter if all of
you have heard his public key.
Because you can perhaps
guess where this is going.
How would Rongxin reverse this process?
He's not going to use one public key.
He's going to use, not surprisingly,
a corresponding private key.
And so in asymmetric cryptography
or public key cryptography,
you really have a key pair, a
public key and a private key.
And for our mathematical
purposes today, let
me just stipulate that there's
some fancy math involved, such
that when you choose that
key or, really, those keys,
there's a mathematical
relationship between them.
And knowing one does not really give
you any information about the other.
Why?
Because these numbers are so darn
big it would take adversaries more
time than we all have on Earth
to figure out via brute force
what the corresponding private key is.
The math is that good.
And even as computers
get faster, we just
keep using bigger and bigger
keys, more and more bits
to make the math even
harder for adversaries.
So when Rongxin receives that
message, he uses his private key,
takes the ciphertext I
sent him through the room,
and gets back out the plaintext.
So this is exactly how
HTTPS works effectively
to securely establish a channel
between me and Amazon.com, gmail.com.
Any website starting with https://
uses public key cryptography to come up
with, initially, a secret.
And in practice, it turns
out, mathematically,
it's faster to use secret key crypto.
So very often, people
will use asymmetric crypto
to generate a big shared key and then
use the faster algorithms thereafter.
But it does solve
asymmetric cryptography,
that chicken-and-the-egg problem, by
giving us all public keys and private
keys.
If you've heard of RSA, Diffie-Hellman,
elliptic curve cryptography,
there's different algorithms
for this that you can actually
study in higher level,
more theoretical classes.
But there's a bunch of different ways
mathematically to solve this problem.
But those are the primitives involved.
And how many of you have
heard of now passkeys, which
is kind of only just catching
on in recent months, literally.
If I had to make any
prediction this semester,
odds are, you're going to see
these in more and more places.
And in fact, the next time you register
for a website or log into a website,
look for a link, a button that
maybe doesn't say passkeys, per se.
It's often called passwordless login.
But it's really referring
to the same thing.
Passkeys are essentially a newish
feature of operating systems,
be it Mac OS or Windows or Linux
or the OS running on your phone,
that doesn't require that you choose
a username and password anymore.
Rather, when you visit a
website for the very first time,
your device will generate a
public and private key pair.
Your device will then send
to the website for what
you're registering your public key
so that it has one of the values,
but you keep your private
key, indeed, private.
And using the same mathematical
process that I alluded to earlier,
you can therefore log into
that website in the future
by proving mathematically that
you are, in fact, the owner
of the corresponding private key.
So, in essence, if we
use a picture like this,
when you proceed to log in to
that website again-- and, again,
that website has stored
your public key--
it essentially uses something
known as digital signatures--
you're familiar with this term,
you've heard it in the wild--
whereby the website will
send you a challenge message,
like some random number
or string of text.
It's just some random value.
If you then effectively encrypt it with
your private key or run both of those
through a particular algorithm,
you'll get back a signature.
And that signature can be verified by
the website by using your public key.
So digital signatures are kind
of an application of cryptography
but in the reverse direction.
In the world of encryption,
you use someone's public key
to send a message encrypted.
And they use their
private key to decrypt it.
In the world of signatures,
or really passkeys,
you reverse the process, whereby you use
your private key to effectively encrypt
some random challenge you've been sent.
And the website, the third
party, can use your public key
to verify, OK, mathematically,
that response came from David.
Because I have his public key on file.
So what's the upside of this?
We just get out of the business
of passwords and password managers
more generally.
You do have to trust and
protect your devices, be it
your phone or your laptop
or desktop all the more.
And that's going to open
another possible threat.
But this is a way to chip away
at what is becoming the reality
that you and I probably have dozens,
hundreds of usernames and passwords
that's probably not
sustainable long-term.
And, indeed, we read to often about
hacks in the wild as a result.
Questions then on
cryptography or passkeys?
All right, just a few more building
blocks to equip you for the real world
before we sort of maybe do a final
check for understanding of sorts.
So when it comes to encryption, we
can solve other problems as well.
And in this too is a feature you
should increasingly be seeking out.
So end-to-end encryption refers
to a stronger use of encryption
than most websites are
actually in the habit of using.
Case in point, if you're using
HTTPS to send an email to Gmail,
that's good because no one
between you and Gmail servers
presumably can see the message
because it's encrypted.
It just looks like
random zeros and ones.
So it's effectively secure
from people on the internet.
The emails are not secure from
like nosy employees at Google
who do have access to those servers.
Now, maybe through corporate policy,
they shouldn't or physically don't.
But, theoretically,
there's someone at Google
who could look at all of your
email if they were so inclined.
Hopefully it's just not
a long list of people.
But end-to-end encryption
ensures that if you're
sending a message from A to B, even if
it's going through C in the middle--
be it Google or Microsoft or
someone else-- end-to-end encryption
means that you're encrypting it between
A and B. And so even C in the middle
has no idea what's going on.
This is not true of services
like Gmail or Outlook.
This is true of services
like iMessage or WhatsApp
or Signal or Telegram or other
services where if you poke around, also
you'll see literally mention
of end-to-end encryption.
It's a feature that's becoming
a little more commonplace,
but something you should seek out when
you don't necessarily trust or want
to trust the machine in
the middle, the point
C between A and B. So, indeed,
when sending messages on phones
and even video
conferencing nowadays too.
And here's something where
sometimes you kind of have to dig.
Most of us are familiar
with Zoom certainly by now.
And if we go into Zoom
settings, which I did
this morning to take this screenshot,
this is what it looks like as of now.
Here's the menu of options
for creating a new meeting.
And toward the bottom
here-- it's a little small--
you'll notice that you have
two options for encryption.
And funny, enough the one
that's typically selected
by default, unless you opt in to the
other one, is enhanced encryption.
Brilliant marketing, right?
Who doesn't want enhanced encryption.
It is weaker than this encryption
though, which is end-to-end encryption.
End-to-end encryption
means that when you're
having a video conference
with one or more people,
not even Zoom can see or hear
what you're talking about.
Enhanced encryption
means no one between you
and Zoom can hear or see
what you're talking about.
So end-to-end ensures that it's A
to B, and if Zoom is C In the story,
even Zoom can't see what you're doing.
Now, there are some downsides.
And there's some little fine print here.
When you enable end-to-end encryption
on a cloud-based service like Zoom,
you can't use cloud recordings anymore.
Why?
Well, if Zoom by
definition mathematically
can't see or hear your meeting, how
are they going to record it for you?
It's just random zeros and ones.
You can still record it
locally on your Mac or PC,
but end-to-end encryption
ensures that you
don't have to worry about prying eyes--
be it a company, be it a government,
a state more generally.
And so societally, you'll start to
see this discussed probably even
more than it already is when it comes
to personal liberties and freedom
among citizens of countries
and states because
of the implications for actual
privacy that these primitives
that we've been discussing and
that you even explored in week 2,
albeit weakly, with these ciphers
we used in the real world.
But encryption has one other use
that's worth knowing about too and yet
another feature to turn on.
So when it comes to deleting files,
odds are, most everyone in the room
knows on a Mac or PC that when you drag
a file to the trashcan or the recycle
bin, it doesn't actually go
away unless you right click
or Control click or go to the
appropriate menu and empty the trash.
But did anyone know that even when
you empty the trash or recycle bin,
the file also doesn't really go away.
Your operating system typically
just forgets where it is.
But the zeros and ones that compose
the file or files you tried to delete
are still there for the
pickings, especially
if someone gets physical or
virtual access to your system.
So, for instance, here is a
whole bunch of ones and zeros.
Maybe it's representing
something on my hard drive.
And suppose that I want
to go ahead and delete
a file that comprises these
zeros and ones, these bits here.
Well, when your operating
system deletes the file,
even if you click on Empty
Trash or Empty Recycle Bin,
it essentially just forgets about those
bits, but doesn't actually change them.
Only once you create a new
file or download something else
do some of those zeros and ones
end up getting overwritten.
And per the yellow remnants here, the
implication of this contrived example
is that even at this point
in time you can still recover
like half of the file, it would seem.
So maybe the juicy part
with a credit card number
or a message that you really wanted
to delete or the like, there's
still remnants on the
computer's hard drive here.
So what's the alternative?
Well, if you really
want to be thorough, you
could delete files and then download
the biggest possible movies you
can to really fill up your hard drive.
Because, probabilistically,
you would end up
overwriting all of those
zeros and ones eventually.
But that's not really
a tenable solution.
It would just take
too much time and it's
fraught with possible simple mistakes.
So what should we do
instead, well, maybe we
should securely delete information.
And securely delete would
mean when you actually
empty the recycle bin or the trash
can, what happens to the original zeros
and ones is that you take them
and you change all of them
to zeros or all of them to ones or
all of them to random zeros and ones.
Why?
So that you can still
reuse those bits now,
but there's no remnants even
on the computer's hard drive
that they were once there.
But even now, this is not fully robust.
Why?
It turns out that because of today's
electronics and solid state devices,
there might still be remnants of files
on them because these hard drives,
these storage devices
nowadays are smart enough
that if they realize that
parts of them are failing,
they might prevent you from
changing data in certain corners.
So if you think of your memory as
like a big rectangle, some of the bits
might get blocked off
to you just over time.
So there might still be remnants there.
So if you really are worried about a
sibling, an employer, or a government
like finding data on that system,
there might actually still be remnants.
Now, you can go extreme
and just physically
destroy the device, which
should be pretty effective.
But that's going to get pretty expensive
over time when you want to delete data.
Or, again, we can use encryption
as the solution to this problem.
So, again, encryption is
increasingly in the real world
an amazing tool for your toolkit because
it can be deployed in different ways.
So, in this case, full disk
encryption is something
you can enable in Windows or Mac OS.
Nowadays, it's typically
enabled by default on iOS
and you can opt in as
well on other platforms.
In the world of full disk encryption,
instead of storing any of your files
as a plain text, like in
their original raw format,
you essentially randomize
everything on the disk instead.
You rely on the user's
password or some unique string
that they know when you
log into your Mac or PC
to essentially scramble the
entire contents of the hard drive.
And it's not quite as simple as that.
Typically, there's a
much larger key that's
used that in turn is protected
by your actual password.
But, in this case, this means that if
someone steals your laptop while you're
not paying attention in Starbucks or
the airport or even your dorm room,
even if they open the lid
and don't have your password,
they're not going to be able
to access any of the data
because it's just going to
look like zeros and ones.
Even if they remove the
hard drive from your device,
plug it into another device, they're
only going to see zeros and ones.
Now, if you walk away from your
laptop at Starbucks with the lid open
and you're logged in, there
is a window of opportunity.
Because the data has got to be decrypted
when you care about it and when
you're using it.
So here too is another
example of best practice.
You should minimally be
closing the lid of your laptop,
making sure it's logging you out
or at least locking the screen,
so that someone can't just
walk off with your device
and have access to
your logged in account.
But full disk encryption essentially
decreases the probability
that an adversary is
going to be successful.
In the world of Macs,
it's called FileVault.
It's in your System Preferences.
Windows, it's called BitLocker.
There's third party solutions too.
Here too, we have to trust
that Microsoft and Apple don't
screw up and write buggy code.
But generally speaking, turning
on features like these things
are good for you.
Except what's maybe an obvious
downside of doing this?
What's that?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, if
you forget your password.
There's no mathematician
in the world who
is probably going to be able
to recover your data for you.
So there too, it's
maybe a hefty tradeoff.
But hopefully you have
enough defenses in place,
be it your-- a good
password, a password manager,
maybe even printing out your primary
password on a sheet of paper,
but locking it in a box or bringing
it home so that no one near you
actually has physical access, you can
at least mitigate some of these risks.
You'll read about, though,
in the real world even this,
which is like an adversarial
use of full disk encryption.
Sometimes when hackers
get into systems, this
has happened literally with hospital
systems, municipal government systems,
and the like.
If they hack into them, they don't just
delete the data or just create havoc,
they will proactively encrypt
the server's hard drive
with some random key that
only the hacker knows.
They will then demand that
the hospital or the town
pay them, often in Bitcoin
or some cryptocurrency
to decrease the probability
of being caught,
and they'll only turn over that key to
decrypt the data if someone actually
pays up.
So here too, there's sort of a dark
side of these mathematical principles.
So there too, it's always a trade off
between good people and perhaps bad.
Well, maybe before we
wrap and before we serve
some cake in the transept, Carter,
can you join me one last time?
But, first, before I turn things over
to me and Carter, here's your problem
set 10, a sort of unofficial homework.
One, among your takeaways
for today, you should
start using a password manager or
even these fancier passkeys, at least
for your most sensitive accounts.
So anything medical, financial,
particularly personal,
like this is a very concrete
takeaway and action item.
I wouldn't sit down and try to
change all of your accounts over.
Because knowing humans, You're not going
to get through the whole to-do list.
So maybe do it the next time
you log into that account,
turn on some of these features
or add it to a password manager
or at least start with
the most important.
Two, turning on
two-factor authentication
beyond where you have to at
places like Harvard and Yale,
but certainly bank accounts,
privates, anything medical, personal,
or the like.
And then lastly, where you can,
turning on end-to-end encryption.
Being careful with it,
you don't want to go
and during lecture, hopefully no one
clicked the turn on FileVault button
while we're in class.
Because closing your laptop lid
while things are being encrypted
is generally bad practice.
See us after though if you
did do that a moment ago.
So here's just then three
actionable takeaways.
But we thought we'd conclude by taking
a few final minutes for a CS50 quiz
show of sorts, a final check for
understanding using some questions
we come up with ourselves, but
also some of the review questions
that you all kindly contributed as
part of the most recent problem set.
So some of these questions
come from you yourselves.
And let me go ahead and turn things over
to Carter here to help run the show.
We will invite you at this point
to take out that same device
as you had earlier.
This is the same URL as before.
But if you closed the tab,
you can reopen it here.
To make things a little fun--
because we still have some cookies
left-- could we get three
final CS50 volunteers?
OK, one hand is already up.
How about two hands there?
And how about three hands?
Over here.
All right, yes, sure, a round of
applause for our final volunteers.
Come on up.
[APPLAUSE]
On the line are some
delicious Oreo cookies.
If the three of you would
like to come over and take
any of these seats in the middle,
you will be our human players,
but we'll invite everyone
in the group to play too.
Do you want to take a mic and
introduce yourself to the world?
AUDIENCE: Sure.
Hi, I'm Dani.
I'm a first year in WIG C. And I'm
planning on studying economics.
DAVID MALAN: Nice, welcome.
AUDIENCE: Hi, I'm Rochelle.
I'm from the best state, Ohio.
DAVID MALAN: [INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: And I'm a freshman in Greeno.
I'm planning on concentrating in CS.
DAVID MALAN: Nice, welcome.
And?
AUDIENCE: My name is Jackson.
I'm from Indiana.
I live in Thayer.
I'm a first year.
And I'm studying linguistics and
Germanic languages and literatures.
DAVID MALAN: Welcome as well.
So, if our volunteers
could have a seat, you're
going to want to be able to
see this screen or that one.
So you can move your
chairs if you would like.
Carter is going to kindly cue up the
software, which hopefully everyone
has on their phones as well.
And I should have mentioned, do
you have your phone with you?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Do you have
your phone with you?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, do you
have your phone over there?
OK, what's your name again?
AUDIENCE: Rochelle.
DAVID MALAN: OK, Rochelle
will be right back,
if you want to go grab your phones.
And in the meantime, we're
going to go ahead and-- thank
you so much-- we're going to go
ahead and cue up the screens here
for the CS50 quiz show.
It's about 20 questions in
total, the first few of which
are going to focus on
cybersecurity to see how well we
can check our current understanding.
The rest will be questions written by
you in the days leading up to today.
All right, Carter, let's go ahead
and reveal the first question.
And note that you can win up to
1,000 points this time per question.
It's not just about
being right or wrong.
And you get more points the
faster you buzz in as well.
So we'll see who's on the top based
on all of the guest user names.
All right, here we go,
Carter, question one,
what is the best way
to create a password?
Substitute letters with
numbers or punctuation signs,
ensure it's at least
eight characters long,
have a password manager
generated for you,
or include both lowercase
and uppercase letters?
All right, let's see
what the results are.
Almost everyone said have a password
manager generate it for you.
90% of you said that's the case.
And, indeed, that one is correct.
Nicely done.
Let's go ahead and see the
random usernames you've chosen.
So this looks like it's
web_hexidecimalidentifier to keep
things anonymous.
So if you are OAF9E,
nicely done, but there's
a whole lot of ties up at the top.
All right, and I see-- well,
just to keep things interesting,
you had 792 points.
You had--
AUDIENCE: 917.
DAVID MALAN: 917 points, 917 points.
So it's a close race here.
Number two, what is a downside
of two-factor authentication?
You might lose access
to the second factor.
Your account becomes too secure.
You can be notified someone else
is trying to access your account.
You can pick any
authentication you like.
Hopefully, you can reload.
You might have missed that one.
And the number one answer was might
lose access to the second factor.
Indeed, 93% of you got that.
And we're up to 1,375
points, 792 points, and--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, and forced reload.
So, yes, you tried reloading the page
and hopefully it'll click back in.
All right, Carter, number 3.
We have, what would you see if you
tried to read an encrypted disk?
You would see a random
sequence of zeros and ones,
scrambled words from
the user's documents,
all of the user's
information, or all one's?
About 10 seconds remain.
Is it working for you now?
OK.
All right, three seconds.
And the ranked answers are a
random sequence of zeros and ones.
91% of you indeed got that right.
Let's see who's winning
on the guest screen.
Web user a28c3, nicely done.
But it's still a close tie among
three of you anonymous participants.
Number four, which type of
encryption is most secure--
enhanced encryption, end-to-end
encryption, full scale encryption,
advanced encryption?
About five seconds.
And most popular response is the
correct one, end-to-end encryption
with 92% of you.
Nice.
We're up to 2,375, 3,792, and 2,917.
And good job to these three
folks in the front of our list.
All right, Carter, number 5,
the last on cybersecurity.
When would it make sense to store
your password on a sticky note
by your computer?
When it's too complicated
to remember, when
you need to access your account quickly,
when you share your account with family
members, never.
Oh.
And the most popular response was
never, which is indeed correct.
And only 79% of you
think that right now.
It is never OK to store it on a
post-it note on your computer.
You should minimally be using today's
password manager for that same process.
All right, two of you, a28c3 and
c9a23 are still atop the list.
We have 3,000-plus
points, 3,000-plus points,
and probably about the same as well.
All right, now we move on to
the user-generated content
that you all from Harvard
and Yale generated for us.
Number 6, what is the variable
type that stores true/false values?
Boolean, string, integer, or double?
About 10 seconds to come up with this.
We saw these in different
languages, these types.
But the idea was the same.
And in two seconds,
we'll see that the answer
is Boolean with 96% response rate.
All right, what else do we have here?
It's still a two-way tie at the top.
All right, next question,
Carter, is number 7.
What placeholder would
you use when trying
to print a float in C, a float in C?
Seven seconds.
I'll defer to the visual syntax
on the screen for this one.
And the most popular and
correct answer is, indeed, %f.
We never saw %fl and we
definitely didn't see %float.
Two of you, though,
are still in the lead.
Nicely done, whoever you are.
All right, next question, what does I++
do in C++ where I is an integer value?
Note, for the record, we did
not teach C++ in this course,
but this question is from you.
I will admit it's the same
as in C, which we did teach.
Decrements the integer, deletes the
integer, increments the integer by one,
or reassigns the integer to zero?
The most popular answer
and correct answer
is increments the integer by one.
It definitely doesn't decrement, so.
All right, two responses
still atop the list.
And here we have 6,000-plus,
6,000, and 6,000.
So it's getting closer.
Using a hash table to
retrieve data is useful
because it theoretically achieves a
search time of O of n, O of n log n,
O of log n, or O of 1?
Five seconds to make your decision.
Getting a little harder.
And let's see the results.
O of 1, only 30% of you got the correct
answer from a very core week 5 topic.
That is the theoretical
hope of a hash table.
In practice, though, to be fair, it
can devolve, as we saw, into O of n.
We didn't really see those other two
answers in the context of hash tables
specifically.
All right, wow, a28c3
is in the lead now.
Let's take a look at
number 10, halfway there.
What is the first
program we made in CS50?
This should be fast.
All right, Greet, Meow,
DNA, Hello, world?
One second.
And it was, indeed, Hello,
world, Hello, world.
All right, still in the
lead with 10,000 points.
And now let's move on
to the second half.
Question 11, when malloc is used
to allocate memory in a C program,
that memory is allocated in
the pile, heap, bin, or stack?
Very creative set of answers.
Five seconds.
All right, and the
results have heap at 43%.
Malloc was from the heap at the top.
The stack is where function calls go.
It's getting a little
more worrisome here.
But that's OK.
Still in the lead with perfect
score, it seems, 11,000 points.
Next up is number 12.
Which data structure allows you to
change its size dynamically and store
values in different
areas of the memory--
an array, a queue, a
linked list, or a stack?
Change its size dynamically
and store different values
in different areas of the memory.
And the answer from the group is a
linked list at 62%, which is correct.
An array, as we defined
it, cannot be resized.
You can create a new array,
copy everything over.
I'm starting to think maybe we
shouldn't end the class on this note.
But that's OK.
We'll move on.
12,000 points for the lead.
And number 13, what does CSS
stand for in web development--
computer style sheets, cascading
style sheets, creative style systems,
colorful sheets styles?
And most popular answer is correct
with 81%, cascading style sheets.
On the top 10 list here at 1,300
points, still a perfect score,
and our three human volunteers
are doing well here too.
14, how to represent a
decimal number 5 in binary.
All right, here we go.
I'll let you read these.
All rights, fingers crossed, decimal
number 5 in binary is, indeed, 101.
Because that's a 4 plus 0
plus 1 gives us a decimal 5.
All right, next question, and amazing
a28c3, whoever you are out there,
nicely done.
Who is the CS50 mascot--
cat, duck, robot dog
Spot, Oscar the Grouch?
All of whom have appeared in some form.
This one will be a little looser with
answers, but looks like duck and cat
were both the most popular.
Duck has kind of become the
mascot, suffice it to say.
Cat is kind of everywhere
on CS50 social media.
So we'll accept cat as well.
We love Spot, but has only
made that one appearance.
15,000.
Final few questions, what is the output
of printf quote, unquote, "1" plus
quote, unquote, "2?"
It will return an
error, twelve, 3, or 12?
English and digits respectively there.
Six seconds.
All right, one second.
And 12 with 74% is correct.
Because it's not quite
12, it is more rather
1, 2 because those are two strings that
got concatenated would not actually
be an error in that case.
It's just not what you expect.
All right, it's getting a little
harder, but still someone's
got a perfect score.
What does LIFO stand for?
Lost In First Order, Last In First
Out, Let Inside Fall Outside,
Long Indentation For Organization?
Good one.
Last In First Out, and we discussed
this in the context of a stack.
Because as you pile things
on top of the stack,
the last one in is the first one out.
All right, nicely
done, this player here.
Three questions to go.
On average, how early did
you submit the weekly pset?
A couple of days early, no rush, the
morning of, a couple of hours early,
but was not too nervous,
11:59:59, I live on the edge.
Again, user-generated content.
And the most popular answer--
[LAUGHTER] Carter and I
conferred before class
and we autocratically
decreed that this is
the only right answer
and the only one we
will accept here, though we
appreciate the others as well.
Wow, all right, did you take
this class for the CS50 shirt?
Yes, no, maybe, I'm not telling you?
So that is this here shirt, which
you'll get at the CS50 fair.
One second.
And, yes, no, maybe, I'm not telling
you, this time, we'll accept all four
of those, which brings us to our
final question, at which point
we'll reveal the scores
of all of our participants
and see if we can get the
number one score online.
What is the phrase that David
says at the end of each lecture?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
DAVID MALAN: All right,
before we actually
say what the right answer
is, though we can show it,
Carter, we'll see that there is 98%--
I've never said this at the end
here, but 98% answers there.
Let's go ahead and
look at the top chart.
Do we know who web_a28c3 is?
Oh my goodness, come on down.
And among our friends here, can
you pull up each of your scores
if you're able to see?
And among our human volunteers,
16,792, 17,292, 16,958.
So we have our human winner as well.
So without further ado, allow
me to thank our volunteers.
Thanks so much to CS50 staff.
We're about to give out some
cookies and, if you want,
some stress balls here.
Cake is now served.
And this was CS50.
[CHEERING]
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
[MUSIC PLAYING]