BRIAN YU: Let's analyze some DNA.
In this problem, your task is going
to be to take a sequence of DNA
and determine which person
it most likely belongs to.
Recall that a sequence of DNA is really
just a sequence of nucleotide bases
where there are four different
nucleotide bases that
are abbreviated T, C, A, and G. If
you put enough of these in sequence,
you end up with a human's DNA sequence.
And interestingly, if you look
at a human's DNA sequence,
you'll often find places in the DNA
where certain parts of the DNA repeat.
Take a look at the
sequence AGAT for example.
You'll notice that in this
DNA sequence, it appears here.
And then it repeats right after it
here and here and here and here.
And it repeats five times
consecutively in a row.
This isn't a coincidence.
It's something called
a short tandem repeat--
a sequence of DNA that
repeats consecutively
in particular locations in human DNA.
The short tandem repeats, also called
STRs, vary a lot in the population.
In particular, different
people have each STR
repeated different numbers of times.
So what are the key observations here?
Well, for any STR, people in a
population vary in how many times
that particular STR
repeats consecutively.
You might have a particular
STR repeated 25 times.
I might have it repeated 28 times.
Someone else might have it repeated
some different number of times.
And matching STR counts can be used to,
therefore, identify who a sample of DNA
belongs to.
If we take a sample of DNA and
count up for each of the STRs--
how many times do they
repeat consecutively
and it matches some existing
piece of DNA in a DNA database,
for example, then it's pretty
likely that those two pieces of DNA
came from the same person.
And in fact, the very DNA sequence
that we were looking at earlier, AGAT,
is actually one of the STRs that the
FBI uses in its own DNA database.
Your task in this problem is going
to be to do something similar.
We're going to give you a DNA
database of your very own, formatted
as a CSV file where each row is
going to correspond to a person.
And each column is going to
correspond to a particular STR,
a particular sequence of DNA that
repeats some number of times.
We can take this CSV file, or
comma separated value file,
and format it as a table in order
to read it a little more easily.
And the way to interpret
this is that Alice
has the DNA sequence AGAT repeated
28 times consecutively somewhere
in her DNA.
She also has the sequence AATG repeated
42 times consecutively somewhere
in her DNA.
And she has the TATC sequence repeated
14 times elsewhere in her DNA.
Bob has the same thing
with different numbers.
And Charlie has the same STRs
with different numbers as well.
What we're going to
give you in this problem
is we're going to give you a CSV
file representing all of this data,
and we're also going to give you
a DNA sequence formatted as a text
file called sequence.txt, for example.
And your task is going to
be to take this DNA sequence
and figure out whether or
not it matches all of the STR
counts for any person in the
DNA database that we give you.
What does this actually mean?
Well, it means that
your program will first
need to open the CSV
file and the DNA sequence
and read the contents into
memory in your Python program.
Next up, for each of
the STRs, you're going
to compute the longest run of
consecutive repeats of that STR
in the DNA sequence you've been given.
Once you've calculated
the number of times
that each STR repeats
consecutively, you're
going to compare those counts
against every row in the CSV file
to look for a match.
If you find a match, you'll
print out their name.
And if there's no match,
you'll just print out
no match to indicate that there was no
match for anyone in your DNA database.
So let's go through these steps one at
a time, starting with opening the files.
When you open the CSV file,
one thing you'll notice
is that the very first row of the
CSV file has name as the first column
and every subsequent column is going to
be an actual DNA sequence representing
the STRs that you should be counting.
Every other row of the CSV
file is going to correspond
to a person, where the first column
is going to be that person's name.
And all of the remaining columns are
going to represent the number of times
that the STR repeats consecutively
in that person's DNA.
So a couple of hints for doing this--
one thing to note is
that Python has a CSV
module, a module designed with functions
that will help you to read CSV files.
In particular, you might want to
take a look at reader and DictReader
to read a CSV file as a sequence of
lists or a sequence of dictionaries,
respectively.
You'll also note that Python has
a sys module-- short for system--
which will give you access
to sys.argv for the command
line arguments of the program where
the first command line argument, other
than the program's name, is going to
be the DNA database formatted as a CSV
file.
And the second argument
is going to be the DNA
sequence so you're actually going
to read and do some calculations on.
Another hint-- once you've opened
up a file by calling open and then
passing in the file name in parentheses,
you can read its contents using f.read
if f is the name of
the file, for example.
Once you've opened up all
of the files, the next step
is going to be to compute
the individual STR accounts.
In other words, how many times do they
repeat consecutively in a person's DNA?
Well, let's take a look at
this DNA sequence for example
and look at the STR AGAT.
You'll notice that it
appears once here, AGAT.
It also appears once here, AGAT.
And here it repeats twice in sequence--
AGAT and then AGAT after that.
And you could imagine doing this for
every position within the DNA sequence,
computing at that particular
place in the sequence
how many times does AGAT repeat
starting from that position.
Once you've computed
all of those values,
you could imagine taking whichever
of those values is the biggest
and that's going to be the
longest run of consecutive STRs
that you're going to find for
this particular DNA sequence.
So what does this actually
mean algorithmically?
Well, it means for each
position in the DNA sequence,
you'll want to compute how
many times the STR repeats
starting at that position.
How do you do that?
Well, for every position, you can keep
checking successive substrings-- first,
checking to see whether the STR matches
once, then to see if it matches twice,
then three times, so on and so forth
until it doesn't repeat anymore.
And at the end, you'll
just want to keep track
of what is the maximal number of
times that this particular STR
repeats consecutively.
In order to do this, you
might find the len function
in Python helpful, which will
give you the length of a string s
or any other sequence for that matter.
And you can also take a string and get
a substring of it by using s[i:j] which
takes the string s and will return the
substring with all the characters from
character i up to but not
including character j.
And that might be helpful if
you've got a long sequence of DNA
and you want to find out whether
a particular subsequence of it
matches some expected result.
Once you've computed
all of these STR counts,
the last step is to compare it
against the data in the CSV file
that we've given you.
How are you going to do that?
Well, you'll want to save the STR counts
in some sort of data structure, maybe
a list, maybe a dictionary,
maybe something else,
whatever makes most sense to you.
And then for each row
in the data, you'll
want to check if each of
the STR accounts matches.
And if each of the STR accounts
matches for a particular person,
then the DNA is a match and you
should print out that person's name.
Otherwise, you should
just print out no match.
In order to do this, you
might want to remember
that int is a function
that you can actually
call in Python that takes a string
and turns it into the integer
version of that string.
So if you took the string "2"
for example in quotation marks
and passed it into the int function,
what you'd get back is the integer 2.
And remember that to confirm a
match for a particular person,
you'll need to check every column of the
CSV file other than the first column,
because the first column just
stores the person's name.
So once you've opened up the CSV file
and the DNA sequence into memory,
calculated all the STR counts,
and then compared those counts
against each row in your
CSV file, you should then
have the ability to
take a sequence of DNA
and figure out most likely
who that DNA belongs to.
My name is Brian and this was DNA.