BRIAN YU: In Fiftyville,
your task is going
to be to use SQL to solve a mystery.
In the town of Fiftyville,
you've been told
that the CS50 duck has
been stolen, and it's
going to be your job to
figure out what happened.
Here's the information
that we'll give to you.
What you know is that, first,
the theft took place on July 28,
and second, that the theft took
place on Chamberlain Street.
But beyond those two pieces of
information, you don't know much else.
And in particular, your task is
going to be to identify three things.
Your goal is to determine,
first, who the thief is,
second, where the thief escaped to.
You believe the thief
probably escaped out
of town to a different
city other than Fiftyville,
and your goal is to figure
out where they went.
And third, you're supposed to identify
who the thief's accomplice was
who helped them escape out of town.
How are you going to figure
out all of this information?
Well, you've been provided
with a database, fiftyville.db,
which is a SQLite database that contains
a number of tables with data collected
from around the town.
And what you're going to
do is query that database
in order to access information
in order to try and figure out
who the thief actually is.
In order to do that,
on the command line,
you can run sqlite3 followed by
fiftyville.db, the name of the database
file that you'd like to
open and query, to start
running queries on that database.
After you run this
command in the terminal,
you'll be presented with
the SQLite prompt, where
you'll see the word "sqlite"
followed by a greater than sign.
And it's here that you can
start running your SQL queries,
like your SELECT queries, for example.
But before you do that,
you'll probably want
to know what the structure
of the data in this database
is, for example, what the tables are
and what columns those tables have.
To find out that information, one
command you might want to run first is
.tables, which is a command in
SQLite that will list for you all
of the tables that are
inside of this database.
If you type .tables at the
sqlite prompt and press Return,
you'll be presented with
something that looks like this,
a listing of all of the tables that are
inside of this database, and therefore,
all of the types of data
you might have access to.
Taking a glance at the
tables you see here,
you'll see that we have information
about airports and bank accounts
and crime scene reports and flights
and interviews, for example.
And in particular, the
crime scene reports
one looks potentially interesting.
Especially since all
we know at the outset
is that there's been some crime that
took place on some day in some place,
the crime scene reports
table might offer us
some additional information
that can help us
along the way to solving this mystery.
But .tables will just tell you what
the names of all of the tables are,
but won't tell you, for example, what
columns those tables have or what
the types of those columns actually are.
So if we want to see the
database schema for a table,
in other words, what columns make it
up, we can use a command like this.
I can run a .schema, followed by
the name of a table, for example,
.schema crime scene reports sine the
crime scene reports table was a table
that looked interesting when I was
looking at that full listing of all
of the tables.
If I press Enter now, what
I'll be presented with
is the CREATE TABLE command that was
used in order to create the crime scene
reports table.
And what we'll notice here is that
there are some interesting fields
that I might find useful.
For example, there are columns
in this table that correspond
to the date on which a crime happened.
There's a street column that
corresponds to what street
the crime scene report was taken on.
And there's a description field, just
some text describing what happened.
And in particular, for this
crime, one place to start
might be trying to figure
out what the description is
for the crime in question.
And for the crime in question,
we know what day it took place,
for example, a month and a day.
And we also know on what
street it took place.
So in order to query the crime scene
reports table for this information,
I can look at what columns the
table has and run a SQL query that
looks something like this, for example.
SELECT description, that's the column
that I'm interested in, FROM crime
scene reports, that's the
table that I'm querying from,
WHERE a particular condition is true.
And in this case, the
condition is that the date
is the date on which the crime
took place and the street
is the street where I know that
the crime took place as well.
By executing this query
within SQLite, I'll
be presented with the description
from the crime scene reports table
for this particular crime.
As you work through
solving this mystery,
you'll probably find
that you'll need to look
at some other tables other than
just the crime scene reports table.
And recall that if you ever need
to remember what all of the tables
in the database are, you can run .tables
at the sqlite prompt to see a listing
of all of the tables that
you might want to access.
A few suggestions as you
go about your process
of trying to solve this mystery.
First, explore the table
schemas by running .schema,
followed by the name of a table,
to better understand what data is
available to you and how those
tables connect to one another.
Oftentimes, one column
of one table might
correspond to another
column of another table,
and getting a sense for how those
tables interact with each other
is going to be a helpful
way of making sure
that you know how to get access to
the data that you're looking for.
Additionally, you might find
it helpful to run queries
across multiple different
tables if you're
trying to access information
that might be stored
across two or more different tables.
In order to do that, there
are multiple strategies
you could try to approach
the problem with.
But one approach would be to
nest queries within each other.
And another approach is to use JOIN
to join multiple tables together
in order to access data across
multiple columns that might
be found in multiple different tables.
And as you go about
the process of trying
to figure out who the thief
actually is, where they escaped to,
and who their accomplice is, it might be
helpful to maintain a list of suspects,
people that you believe
might be the thief.
And you might narrow down
that suspect list over time
as you discover more evidence
and look through these tables
to find even more
information to help you
along the way to trying
to solve this mystery.
Ultimately, you should be keeping
track of all of the queries
that you run inside of your log file.
And you can use this file as well as a
place to add comments, to take notes,
and to describe your thought process
as you go through the process of trying
to solve this mystery.
Ultimately, after looking through these
tables and running these SQL queries,
you should be able to identify who
the thief is, where they left to,
and who their accomplice was, and
ultimately solve this mystery.
My name is Brian, and
this was Fiftyville.