Next up is sepia.
In the sepia function,
your task is going
to be to implement a filter
that takes a bitmap image
and converts it to
sepia, giving everything
a reddish brown old-time feel to it.
How are you going to do that?
Well, you're going to take each pixel
and convert it to its sepia equivalent.
So what does that look like?
If we take this green
pixel, for example, it
has a sepia equivalent wear the red
value is 183, the green value is 163,
and the blue value is 127.
But where did these
numbers actually come from?
Well, it turns out that
there's a sepia formula--
an algorithm that you can use that
takes the original red, green,
and blue values and determines what
the new red, green, and blue values
should be in the sepia
version of that pixel.
And the algorithm looks like this.
We compute the amount of red in
the sepia version of the pixel
by taking the original amount of
red and multiplying it by 0.393,
taking the original amount of
green and multiplying it by 0.769,
and taking the original amount of
blue and multiplying it by 0.189.
And there are similar
formulas for calculating
how much green should be
in the resulting pixel
and how much blue should
be in the resulting pixel.
So given a pixel like our
green pixel from before,
if we take the original color
values-- the original amount of red,
the original amount of green,
and the original amount of blue--
then we can compute what
the new values should
be just by plugging in all
of those original values
into the formula to calculate
how much red, green, and blue
there should be in the sepia
version of the same pixel.
Of course, when you run
this formula, you'll
probably notice that the output you
get is not going to be an integer.
And recall that every channel
value-- red, green, and blue--
needs to be an integer value.
So what you'll likely want
to do is be sure to round
that number to the nearest
whole number to make sure
that it is actually an integer.
What other corner cases
might you run into, though?
Well, imagine this pixel, where
the original red value is 200,
the original green value is 240,
and the original blue value is 190.
When you run through this
formula, applying the formula
to calculate how much
red, green, and blue
there should be in the sepia pixel,
what you get is a red value of 299.07,
a green value of 266.36,
and a blue value of 207.45.
Of course, we'll want to
round these as we did before.
But there is still a problem.
Remember that each of red, green, and
blue not only need to be integer values
but they also need to be
values in a valid range,
representable by eight bits of memory.
In other words, the
minimum value is zero.
And the maximum value is 255.
But in this case, you'll notice that the
red and green values both exceed 255.
The red value is to 299 and
the green value is to 266.
So in this case, if we ever get
channel values that exceed 255,
we'll want to make sure to cap them
at 255, setting those values to 255,
to make sure that we can still represent
that color value using only eight bits.
So what does this algorithm
actually look like?
Well, for each pixel in
our two-dimensional array
of pixels that represents
our image, we're
going to calculate each new color
value using the sepia formula,
using the original amounts of
red, green, and blue to figure out
what the new amounts of red,
green, and blue should be.
But in particular,
we'll want to make sure
that the result we get for each channel
value is an integer between 0 and 255,
inclusive.
Once you've written the sepia
function, you should be able to test it
by running your filter
program by calling ./filer,
passing in the -s command
line argument, s for sepia,
specifying what the input file is
and what file you'd like to produce
as output.
And if all goes well, you should
see your original image converted
to the sepia version of the same image.
My name is Brian.
And this was sepia.