BRIAN YU: The first filter you're
going to implement is grayscale.
The grayscale filter
should take a color photo
and convert it into grayscale,
turning it into black and white.
But how exactly are
you going to do that?
Well, let's take a look at a
pixel, which as you'll recall,
has a red value, a green
value, and a blue value.
If all of those values are zero,
the pixel shows up as black.
And remember that if all of the
values are the maximum of 255,
then the pixel shows up as white.
The interesting thing to
note, though, is as long
as the red, green, and blue values
are the same, what you'll get
is a different shade of gray.
If the red, green, and blue
values are the same small value,
you'll get a darker shade
of gray, something closer
to the black end of the spectrum.
And if the red, green, and
blue values are all the same
but are a higher value, then
you'll get a lighter shade of gray,
something closer to the
white end of the spectrum.
So your task in grayscale is
really just, for each pixel,
to make sure that the red, green,
and blue values are all the same.
But what value are you
going to set them to?
Well, you might imagine
that for a lighter color,
you probably want a lighter
shade of gray to represent it.
And for a darker color, you
probably want a darker shade of gray
to represent that.
So if we have a color that looks
a little something like this,
you probably want a
lighter shade of gray
to represent it by setting the
red, green, and blue values
all to a relatively high value.
But if we have a color
that's a little bit darker,
then you probably want
a darker shade of gray,
where the red, green, and blue
values are all a little bit lower.
And one thing that we can do is just
take the red, green, and blue values
and calculate the average pixel value
for any of these individual channels
and use that as the new value
for red, green, and blue.
What does this look like in practice?
Well, let's take this shade of green,
for example, where the red value is
equal to 50, the green value is equal to
190, and the blue value is equal to 90.
If we take these three channel values
and take the average of the three,
the average is 110.
So for our new pixel that we're
going to convert to grayscale,
we're going to take the red value, set
it equal to 110, take the green value,
set it equal to 110, and take the blue
value and set it equal to 110 as well.
The result is a shade of gray that
approximately matches the brightness
or darkness of the original pixel.
Of course, it's possible that
depending on the original color
values, the average value you
get might not be a whole number.
In this case, the average is 109.67.
Remember that each of
red, green, and blue
need to be integer values
in the range from 0 to 255.
So if the average value
is not an integer,
you'll want to make sure to
round it to the nearest integer
in order to determine what the
new value actually should be.
So that's how to take one pixel
and convert it to grayscale.
But how are you going to
do it for the entire image?
Well, you could imagine looping
through the image one row at a time,
starting with the first row, then going
to the next row, so on and so forth,
and converting each row to grayscale.
Where for each row, you'd iterate one
more time, using yet another loop,
starting with the first pixel in the
row, then the second pixel in the row,
so on and so forth.
And for each pixel, what
you'll likely want to do
is calculate what the
average pixel value
is by taking the red channel
value, the green channel
value, and the blue channel value
and averaging them together.
Then, once you've
calculated the average,
you can set each of the color values--
each of red, green, and blue--
to whatever that average value is--
of course, making sure to round
it to the nearest integer.
After you've implemented
the grayscale function,
you should be able to
try the filter program.
After you make the filter
program, you can run ./filter,
passing in -g as a
command line argument,
indicating that you'd like to
apply the grayscale filter,
passing in an input file as infile.bmp
or whatever the file name happens
to be, and then specifying the name
of the new file you'd like to produce
as output--
outfile.bmp, for example.
If you do that and pass
it an input file in color,
if you've implemented the
grayscale function successfully,
after you run the program,
you open up the out file,
you should see the same photo,
but converted to grayscale.
My name is Brian.
And this was grayscale.