[MUSIC PLAYING]
[AUDIENCE EXCLAIMING]
[APPLAUSE]
SPOT: Hello, world.
This is CS50, Harvard
University's introduction
to the intellectual
enterprises of computer science
and the art of programming.
Woof, woof.
[LAUGHTER]
I'm sorry, Dave.
[PINK, "WHAT ABOUT US"] What about us?
What about us?
La-da-da-da-da-da-da.
We are searchlights.
We can see in the dark.
We are rockets pointed up at the stars.
We are billions of beautiful hearts.
And you sold us down the river too far.
What about us?
What about all the times you
said you had the answers?
What about us?
What about all the
broken happy ever-afters?
What about us?
What about all the plans
that ended in disaster?
What about love?
What about trust?
What about us?
La-da-da-da-da-da-da.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
So--
[APPLAUSE, CHEERING]
This is CS50, Harvard
University's introduction
to the intellectual
enterprises of computer science
and the art of programming.
And this is Spot.
And our thanks to our
friends at 3D Cowboys
for bringing him by class today.
Perhaps a round of applause for
our special Professor [INAUDIBLE]..
[APPLAUSE]
My name is David Malan.
And I actually took this class,
CS50, myself, some years ago.
But I almost didn't.
And I didn't because when I
got to campus, as a first-year,
I really gravitated toward
things already familiar, things
with which I was already comfortable,
specifically, government.
And I came in here thinking I was going
to major or concentrate in government.
And it was only once I got to
sophomore year, fall semester,
that some friends of mine were
coming to this class called
CS50 that was very much to
beware at the time, in that it
was an unfamiliar field to so
many of us, myself included.
But I got up the nerve to go over the
threshold, sit in on the first class,
just shop it, so to speak.
And I was hooked.
I found that homework was,
for the first time, fun.
And this was after having enrolled
only because the professor let
me enroll pass/fail or [INAUDIBLE]
because I didn't really
think I could even cut it.
But fast forward to five
Mondays later in the semester,
I actually switched to a
letter grade, deciding,
wow, this is actually something for me.
And I say this because
computer science, what
I didn't realize about
it at the time, really
is this very general purpose way of
thinking and way of solving problems.
And even if this is the
only CS class you ever take,
even if this is the only formal
training you have in programming
as a practical skill, it's
just so darn applicable
to so many other fields-- the
arts, humanities, social sciences,
natural sciences, and beyond, and
certainly within the STEM fields,
themselves.
That said, it's going to often
feel a little something like this.
This is from our friends at MIT, down
the road, which is one of their hacks
whereby they connected a fire
hydrant to a drinking fountain,
with a little sign up there that says,
"GETTING AN EDUCATION FROM MIT IS LIKE
DRINKING FROM A FIRE HOSE,"
which is to say that it's
going to feel, quite
often, in this class,
too, that there's just
a lot of information.
And you can't possibly
absorb it all, but realize
that's to be expected, especially
in an introductory class.
The whole point is for so much of it to
feel new, but with practice, with time,
with years, even, looking
back, will you get all the more
comfortable with the material.
But you're not meant to feel
comfortable along the way.
And so let me encourage
you, invite you, expect
you to get comfortable feeling
uncomfortable along the way,
whether you have or have not prior
computer science or programming
experience.
Now, back in my day, the class'
syllabus was a little bit different.
And, really, when I and all of
my classmates exited the class,
we would say to friends
that we learned how
to program in C, which is a language
that we, ourselves, will still
learn in this class.
But that was it for languages.
But nowadays, as you'll
see, we'll explore not just
this older language called
C, but a more modern language
called Python that's very much in vogue
for data science, and web applications,
and much more.
But we'll also introduce
you, along the way,
to another language called S-Q-L or SQL,
which is specifically for databases.
And SQL is a different type
of programming language
that's just going to give you
different ways of solving problems,
different building blocks with which
to express problems you want to solve.
We'll introduce you, toward
the end of the semester,
yet another language,
JavaScript, often used
with markup languages called HTML
and CSS, with which maybe you
have some experience if
you've made websites.
But we'll do this because so many of
today's actual real-world software
is web-based.
Or it's phone-based,
mobile-based, but even then,
it's using these same
languages, like JavaScript.
And so by the end of
CS50, in particular,
you won't know how to program
in X, or Y, or Z, per se.
But, period, you'll
learn how to program.
And, indeed, among the
goals of this class
is to equip you with enough of a set
of concepts, enough practical skills
and experience that after CS50, again,
if you never take another CS class,
you can teach yourself new languages.
And you won't feel--
you won't have been reliant
on a class to, indeed,
introduce you to each
and one of those ideas.
And what are we going to
do, then, in this class?
And, really, what are we
going to start doing today?
Well, we're going to learn
how to solve problems.
And that's really what
computer science is all about.
We'll, very specifically,
today, knock off a few to-dos.
We'll learn how to represent
simple things, like numbers.
We'll learn how to represent letters
of an alphabet, like English.
We'll learn how to represent
colors-- red, green, blue,
and everything in between.
We'll learn how to represent,
more interestingly,
full-fledged images that you might
see on the web or your phone.
We'll talk about representing
videos and even audio files.
So, by the end of today,
alone, you will exit here
with a newfound mental
model for how you can
represent all of today's media and
multimedia that we take for granted
and use most every day.
But we'll also focus
today, ultimately, on how
to write algorithms, like
step-by-step instructions for solving
some problem, specifically,
implementing algorithms with code.
And that's what we'll find.
An algorithm is just
something you can express
in English or any human language,
but code is a translation of that
to, presumably, the 0's and
1's that you've probably heard
is all that computers ultimately speak.
And if you're feeling like
that's a lot for today,
if you're feeling like that's
a lot for the whole semester,
realize and take comfort in
knowing that -thirds of you
have never taken a CS course before.
So even if you think, like
I did all those years ago,
that, surely, my friends, the
kids I didn't even in the class,
must know more than I,
have been programming
since they were six years old.
That's just not the case.
You're in very much good company.
And within the class will
you find different tracks,
by way of the homework
assignments, called "problem sets,"
by way of the sections or recitations.
There will be different
tracks for those of you
less comfortable, more
comfortable, somewhere in between.
And if you really don't
know why you are here today,
we'll even have sections for those
least comfortable, where you just
don't necessarily feel ready to dive
into CS or maybe STEM, more generally.
But we'll get you there by way of
the course's support structure.
And it's very much
grounded in this mindset.
What ultimately matters in
this class is not so much
where you end up relative
to your classmates,
but where you end up relative
to yourself, when you began.
So whether you have or have not
prior programming or CSS experience,
it's not going to matter when
it comes to evaluation, when
it comes to the output, be it a grade,
or a satisfactory mark, or the like.
It's going to depend on,
really, where you are today,
in this, what we call week zero, versus
the very end of the semester, when
you will have built something grand,
of your very own, in software.
But CS50 is also
characterized, fairly uniquely,
by its community, its culture.
And along the way, you'll
see that your experience
is punctuated by a lot of social
and academic events alike.
CS50 lunches, most every Friday,
we'll gather at a nearby restaurant
called Changsho where we'll
have Chinese lunch together.
And as many of you as
might want to attend
that week will be able to join us,
sit down, and chat casually with me,
the course's teaching staff, friends
of ours, alumni from industry, as well.
CS50 Puzzle Day, coming up this
weekend, will be an opportunity,
even if you have no prior CS
experience, just to solve problems,
not jigsaw puzzles, but
puzzles in the logical sense.
We'll hand you a packet of puzzles--
logic problems, or
riddles, or the like--
that you, as teams, can solve together.
And at the very end,
we'll walk you through.
And along the way, there'll be not only
these puzzles, but pizza, and prizes,
and so much more, as well.
Towards the end of the semester,
we'll have a CS50 Hackathon whereby
we'll get together around 7:00 PM,
at the start of reading period,
and we'll finish up around
7:00 AM the next morning.
And it will be this
opportunity to really bond
with your classmates, your project
partners, if you work in a team,
on your very own final
project, which is meant
to be a capstone of the course,
something you build, yourselves,
that we don't hand you
a specification for.
But it's your final offboarding,
so that when you exit CS50,
you don't need CS50 anymore.
You don't need me.
You don't need your TF.
You can actually write code
and solve problems on your own.
So this picture here is one of our past
photos from earlier in the evening.
Things get a little quieter
as we then, around 5:00 AM,
drive anyone who's still awake
and energetic to a nearby IHOP
for pancakes, around then.
But here is how most of the evenings
tend to end for at least some
of your classmates prior.
But at the very end of the class
is the so-called CS50 Fair,
an exhibition of all of your final
projects for friends, faculty,
students, and staff
across campus, whereby
you'll be invited to a space like this.
Bring your laptop.
Bring your phone, whatever it
is you have built and created.
And we'll just show it off
for a bit of the afternoon,
complete with music, and
friends from industry,
and candy, and all what makes
gathering together at term's end fond.
And you'll wear,
ultimately, very proudly,
we hope, your very own "I took CS50,"
stating, very matter of factly,
what I did some years ago; that, indeed,
this was a course I, myself, took.
So, today, let's focus, then, on
computer science, like what is it.
Well, it's really the
study of information.
But, really, it's, more
specifically, about solving problems,
using certain ideas and techniques, all
of which you'll exit the course with.
So, as such, problem
solving is a goal that we'll
approach by way of something
called "computational thinking."
So computational thinking, you can
oversimplistically think about it
as thinking like a computer.
But it's really the application of
ideas that we'll dive into today
and we'll finish some
weeks from now, that you
can apply to problems from this field or
most any other, but in a computational,
that is, a very methodical,
very careful way.
And that's what CS really did for
me and does for a lot of people.
It helps clean up your
thought processes.
Even if you go off into the real
world and do nothing in tech,
you have an ability,
after classes like this,
to express yourself a
little more correctly, more
precisely and, generally,
having better command
of your own ideas and your language.
So what's problem solving?
Let me propose that this is it.
This is as simple as we can make
today's goals and the semester's goals.
Problems to be solved look like this.
You've got some input,
the problem to be solved.
You've got a goal being the output,
like the solution there, too.
And then somewhere in the
middle is the secret sauce,
where we'll spend the next
several weeks figuring out how
we can convert these inputs to outputs.
But before we can do
that, we all just have
to agree on how to represent
these inputs and outputs,
whether it's with English or,
really, any type of language.
But, as I spoiled earlier, you
probably came in here already
with a general sense that,
yeah, computers somehow
only speak or know 0's and 1's,
the so-called binary system.
But that's just one way of
representing information.
Even simpler than binary is unary.
So if you've ever, at this age or any
prior age, counted on your fingers,
this is unary notation, whereby
each of your digits, your fingers
literally represent some
piece of information;
taking attendance, like 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
But on your one human hand, how high
can you count in this unary notation?
AUDIENCE: Five.
DAVID J. MALAN: Five, I'm hearing five.
Six, I heard one six.
But I'm going to go further and say
the answer, if you're clever about it,
is actually--
AUDIENCE: 40?
DAVID J. MALAN: Not quite 40.
You overbid, but--
AUDIENCE: 31.
DAVID J. MALAN: 31 is as
high as I can actually count.
And that's because if I
actually-- and if you're thinking
this is weirdly painful
now, it will be, but this
is my hand representing the number 0.
Normally, in unary, this is 1,
2, 3, 4, 5, of course, obviously.
But what if I take into
account the order in which I'm
putting my fingers up and down?
So maybe this is still 0.
Maybe this is still 1.
But maybe this is now 2, where it's
just the single second finger up,
not two of them, total.
Maybe this is now 3.
Maybe this is now-- often offensive,
with just the middle finger up.
This is now [LAUGHS] 5.
This is now 6.
This is now 7.
And my hand just hurts too much if
I try to count higher than seven.
But, theoretically, because each
of my fingers can be down or up
and I've got five of them, that's
actually 32 possible permutations,
up and down.
But wait a minute.
We said, 31, but if you start at 0.
You have to subtract 1 from
the biggest possible value.
So this is to say you and I have been
using unary because it's just simple,
and it gets the job done.
But if we just think about
representation a little more cleverly,
we can do exactly what computers do,
using not what mathematicians call
"base-1," where the finger is either
there or it's not, but base-2.
And in base-2, we just need
two digits at our disposal.
And we could call these digits 1
and 2, A and B, black or white.
We just need two words to describe
two pieces of information.
Computers keep it simple.
And just like we humans start
counting 0, 1, 2, 3 on up,
computers use 0 and 1, and that's it.
But that's by convention.
But why do they do that?
Well, it turns out, when you use
base-2, otherwise known as binary, well,
it just maps really
readily to the real world.
Because, at the end of
the day, what do we all
do, if you've got a laptop,
or a phone, or any device?
You plug it into the wall because
it needs electricity at some point.
And what if you have electricity or not?
Well, there's your two possible values.
Either it's there, or it's not.
And because computers
are electrical devices,
this is why binary is just useful.
It's nice and simple.
Either electricity is
there, or it's not.
So when you plug this
device in and you've
got all these electrons
or whatever flowing, maybe
if we just hang on to
some of that electricity,
we can represent what we'll call a 1.
And maybe if we let it dissipate
or go away, that's a 0.
So on and off maps very readily
to this idea of just 0's and 1's.
And if you've ever thought of
this, now, as binary digits--
"bi" implying 2, 0 and 1-- well,
if you've ever heard this term now,
"bit," it just means binary digit.
A single bit is just a 0 or 1.
But we could have called
these things anything we want.
Now how does this map to
be clear to the real world?
Well, we can't see the tiny little
switches inside of our Macs,
PCs, and our phones that are
actually turning the electricity on
or off, storing electricity or not.
But they're called transistors.
They've got millions of
them in today's hardware.
And they're just on or off,
like a switch or a light bulb.
So, for instance, if
there's no electricity,
the switch is off, we would
call this, by convention, a 0.
If, though, you throw the switch and it
actually turns on, we would call this--
AUDIENCE: On.
DAVID J. MALAN: --an "on," exactly, a 1.
We could have reversed it.
But this is just the way the
world decided to standardize.
And that's it.
So you've either got something
on or off, a 1 or a 0.
And this, then, is this thing we
know now as a binary digit or a bit.
So once we've got these
values, what about how--
how can we go about,
perhaps, representing things?
Well, you know what?
It turns out we've got a lot
of light bulbs right here.
Let me grab-- thanks.
Excuse me, spot.
Let me grab the little music stand here.
Let me borrow a couple
of these bulbs and see
if we can't make clearer than my
hand, alone, what's going on here.
So I'm going to go ahead
and grab two of these.
And I'll just put them here.
And I can turn these
things on or off now.
So if I've got two bits, two switches,
two transistors, if you will, well,
if I go ahead and turn on this one,
I'm representing what number in binary,
perhaps?
AUDIENCE: 1.
DAVID J. MALAN: So just 1.
Now, if I'm using unary, I would
turn this one on and be done with it.
And that's 2, but not in binary.
Binary, it's the permutations, which
ones are on and off, that matters.
So what, now, am I
representing here, perhaps?
AUDIENCE: 2.
DAVID J. MALAN: 2.
So this is when I put my
single pointer finger up.
But then when I did
this, in my human hand,
this was like representing the number 3.
How do I represent the number 4.
Yeah, I need another light bulb, so
I need more hardware, so to speak.
So if I turn--
if I leave this one-- if I turn this
one on, this one off, this one off,
now I have the number 4.
And someone tell me,
saying the words "on"
and "on" and "on," or
"on," or "off," or "on,"
using combinations of
"on," "off" and-- "on"
and "off," how do I represent
5, from your left to your right?
How about over here?
AUDIENCE: On, off, on.
DAVID J. MALAN: "On, off, on," I heard.
And that's exactly right.
And how do I represent, maybe, 6?
Over here?
AUDIENCE: Off, on, on.
DAVID J. MALAN: Off, on, on, not quite.
From left to right?
AUDIENCE: Off-- the other way.
DAVID J. MALAN: The--
[LAUGHS] OK, so from right to left.
So I think we leave this one on.
This one, I'm going to claim,
represents, now, 6 and 7.
AUDIENCE: On, off.
DAVID J. MALAN: I'm just going to--
it's actually going to be "on, on, on."
Now, if you're wondering, where
are these people coming up
with these combinations,
there's actually a system here.
It's actually hard for
me to do it backwards.
But it turns out there's actually a
system that's not all that unfamiliar.
In fact, let me propose this.
Let me propose that we
consider what you and I all
learned in grade school, which was
something like the base-10 system, 10
meaning that you use 10
different digits, not two, 10.
So 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, that's
the base-10 system, otherwise known
as decimal, "dec" implying 10.
So that's what you and I use every day.
Well, let's think about how we
represent numbers in decimal,
in the normal human way.
Well, here is a number.
It's what number, of course?
AUDIENCE: 123.
DAVID J. MALAN: 123.
So we all just have an
intuition for that, obviously.
But it's not necessarily 123.
You're just assigning meaning to
the positions of these digits.
This is really the pattern 1-2-3.
But you immediately jump,
mathematically, to 123, but why?
Well, odds are, in grade school, you
learned that the rightmost digit is
the ones place or the ones column.
This is the tens place
or the tens column.
This is the hundreds place.
And so why is this relevant?
Well, this is like doing
100 times 1 plus 10 times
2 plus 1 times 3 or, if we multiply
that out, 100 plus 20 plus 3,
ergo, the number, now, that we
just take for granted is 123.
But that's in base-10, the
so-called decimal system,
whereby each of these digits
is in a different column.
And those columns are, again,
ones place, tens, hundreds.
If we keep going, thousand,
ten thousand, and so forth.
But where did these come from?
Well, here's the base.
If you remember exponents
and all of that,
this is just 10 to the 0, 10 to
the 1, 10 to the 2, ad infinitum.
And so, now, what if we just changed
the base from 10, 0 through 9,
to just two digits, 0 and 1?
Well, now the math is
fundamentally the same.
But it's 2 to the 0, 2
to the 1, 2 to the 2,
which gives us the ones place,
twos place, and fours place.
Now, why is this relevant?
If you've got three light bulbs or
three bits that are off, off, off,
what have I done?
4 times 0 plus 2 times 0 plus 1
times 0 is, obviously, the number
you and I know, in decimal, as 0.
This, though, represents the
number you and I know as--
AUDIENCE: 1
DAVID J. MALAN: This represents--
AUDIENCE: 2.
DAVID J. MALAN: --3, 4.
And just to be clear, this is why, when
I grabbed the additional light bulb,
we claimed that this now was 4.
Because we had "on, off,
off," "on, off, off."
This now is 5.
This now is 6.
This now is 7.
And if I wanted to count higher, what
would the pattern of 0's and 1's be
for the number 8?
AUDIENCE: 1, 0--
DAVID J. MALAN: 1, 0, 0, 0.
So we just need more
hardware, more bits.
So it wasn't arbitrary,
even if it was non-obvious,
what I was actually doing with
turning these light bulbs on and off.
Now, it turns out here we are talking
about how to represent information,
like numbers, but we could also
use bits, 0's and 1's, light bulbs
to represent instructions, as well.
Because, at the end of the
day, that's all computers do.
They process data, information
of some sort, whether it's files,
or numbers, or images,
or videos, or the like.
And you do things with those files.
You open them.
You print them.
You edit them and the like.
So there's this notion of instructions,
what the computer can actually do.
And I bet we could come up with
some pattern of 0's and 1's
or, equivalently, light bulbs
that tell even Spot what to do.
Maybe, go up, or down,
or left, or right.
And it could certainly do this
autonomously by using various sensors.
We need to keep things safe today.
We're using Wi-Fi in sending
Spot these very instructions.
But what's happening, wirelessly,
with our friend Andrew, here, is,
essentially, he's sending Spot
instructions just encoded, wirelessly,
somehow, as patterns of 0's and 1's.
And the folks at Boston Dynamics,
who built this robot, programmed
Spot to recognize certain
patterns as meaning "up,"
a certain pattern as meaning
"down," "left," "right,"
and any number of other things.
So, in fact, Spot, come on
over here, if you could.
Come on, Spot.
[FOOTSTEPS]
OK.
So Spot, for instance, may
very well have a pattern
of 0's and 1's that represents shake.
Shake, Spot.
So he could do that and any number
of other movements, as well.
And maybe, especially with sensors here
and also a little human help over here,
for today, what if we went
ahead and did something-- maybe
ask Spot some questions?
So let's go ahead, and
we'll start simple.
Spot, here we have some
bits, "off, off, on."
Spot, what [LAUGHS]-- OK.
Spot, what is this
representing, "off, off, on"?
[SPOT TAPS STAGE]
Correct?
I think so.
Very horse-like, OK.
Thank you.
All right, so a round of
applause for Spot here.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
So, Spot, what if we [LAUGHS] turn--
OK.
We'll turn that one off here.
How about if we turn this one on?
So it's "off, on, off."
Spot, what's this number?
[SPOT TAPPING STAGE]
Is that correct?
Nice.
OK.
[APPLAUSE]
[LAUGHS] How about one final flourish?
How about, Spot, instead
of "off, on, off,"
let's go ahead and do "off, on, on"?
So think, in your mind's eye,
what the answer should be.
All right, Spot, "off, on, on."
[SPOT LANDING ON THE STAGE]
OK.
And a round of applause
for, Spot, as well.
[LAUGHS]
[APPLAUSE]
So this is to say, no matter how--
thank you, Spot.
No matter how fancy today's
hardware or software is,
it really just boils
down to representing
information and instructions.
And computers, and phones,
and the like really are just
operating on those same
pieces of information,
whether implemented in 0's and 1's
or with, really, anything else.
All right.
So, where can we take this, once
we have this agreed-upon system
for representing [LAUGHS] information?
Well, it turns out that using three
bits, three 0's and 1's, at a time,
isn't actually all that useful.
And you and I, even in conversation,
don't often say the word "bit."
We say the word "byte."
And what is a byte, if familiar?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: It's eight bits.
DAVID J. MALAN: So it's just eight bits.
It's just a more useful unit of measure.
And it happens to be a
power of 2, 2 to the third,
which just makes math work out cleanly.
But it's just a convention, to have
more interesting units of measure
than individual bits.
So a byte is eight bits.
So, for instance, this represents,
using eight bits, eight light bulbs,
the number you and I know is 0.
And this byte of all 1 bits--
now you've got to do some quick math--
represents what number, instead?
So it's all 1's; eight of them, total.
How about over here, on the end?
AUDIENCE: 255.
DAVID J. MALAN: So it's, indeed, 255.
Now, that's not the
kind of math that you
need to do in your head for a
class like this, but you could.
This is the ones place, twos,
fours, eight, 16, 32, 64, 128.
And because they're all 1, you just have
to add up all of those columns' values.
And you get 255.
But a little mental trick, too,
is that, if you've got eight bits
and each of them can be two
possible values, 0 or 1,
that's like 2 possibilities here times
2 times 2 times 2 times 2, eight times.
So that's 2 to the eighth, so that
is maybe a little easier to do.
That's 256.
Or easier, in the sense that you get
used to seeing these numbers in CS.
That's 256.
But wait a minute.
How do I reconcile this with your 255?
Because you start at 0.
So you lose one on the high end because
we started counting and representing
the number, like 0.
All right.
Questions on how we've represented
just numbers or, for instance,
instructions to Spot, thus far?
Any questions on binary,
unary, or the like?
No?
All right, so seeing none,
let's let things escalate a bit.
So how do you represent letters
because, obviously, this
makes our devices more
useful, whether it's
in English or any other human language.
How could we go about representing
the letter A, for instance?
If, at the end of the
day, all our computers,
all our phones have access to is
electricity; or, equivalently,
switches; or, metaphorically,
tiny little light bulbs
inside of them that can
be on and off-- that's it.
There's no more building
blocks to give you.
How could we represent
something like the letter A?
Yeah, how about here?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: You could assign a number.
DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
So we could just assign
every letter a number.
And we could do this super simply.
Maybe 0 is A, and 1
is B. Or maybe 1 is A,
and 2 is B. It doesn't really matter,
so long as we all agree and we all
use the same types of computers,
in some sense, ultimately.
Well, for various reasons, the
humans that designed this system,
they went with the number 65.
So, nowadays, anytime your computer
is showing you the capital letter
A on the screen, underneath
the hood, so to speak,
it's actually storing a pattern of 0's
and 1's that represents the number 65.
And it tends to use seven bits
or, typically, eight bits, total,
even if it doesn't need
all of those bits in total.
So how do we get there?
Well, here, for instance,
is that same pattern.
Here is that pattern of
bits that represents 65.
And why?
Well, quick check here.
This is the ones place, twos,
fours, eights, 16, 32, 64's place.
OK, so 64 plus 1 gives me 65.
So that is to say here's how a computer,
using some light switches, so to speak,
would represent the number 65.
And our Macs, our PCs, our
phones just all know this.
So whenever they see that in
their memory, so to speak,
they show a capital
letter A on the screen.
So that's it.
That's the system known as
ASCII, the American Standard
Code for Information Interchange.
And the A is actually operative there
because we're only talking, thus far,
about English letters in our alphabet.
And, in fact, I claimed, a
moment ago, that we only use
seven, maybe eight bits to
represent letters of an alphabet.
So, just to come back to
you, if I may, how many
possible letters of the
alphabet could-- how
many possible letters of any alphabet
could we represent with eight bits?
AUDIENCE: 256.
DAVID J. MALAN: 256, the
numbers 0 through 255.
Now, that's more than enough
for English because we've
got A through Z, uppercase,
lowercase, a bunch of numbers,
a bunch of punctuation symbols.
But in a lot of languages, with accented
characters, a lot of Asian characters,
this is not nearly enough
memory or bits with which
to represent all of
those possible values.
So we need to do a
little better than ASCII,
but we can build on top of
what they did years ago.
So here is a chart of ASCII codes.
It's just a bunch of columns showing
us the mapping between letters
and numbers.
So, for instance, up here is the
capital letter A, 65; capital B, 66;
capital C, 67; dot, dot, dot.
72 is H. 73 is I and so forth.
There's some weird things over
here, like special symbols,
that we'll learn about over time.
But there's a mapping
between every English letter
of the alphabet and some
number, just as you'd propose,
both for uppercase and lowercase.
So, for instance, if we highlight
just a few of these for now
and I say that I've just received
a text message or an email that,
underneath the hood, so to
speak, if I have the ability
to look at what switches are on and
off, I received this message here.
Well, first-- and this is not what
CS is about, but just fun fact.
Does anyone know what number
this would represent in decimal,
if this is the binary pattern,
like ones place, twos place?
AUDIENCE: 72?
DAVID J. MALAN: 72 is correct.
And again, not, intellectually,
all that interesting
and this is not the kind of math
that we spend all day as CS--
a computer scientist doing.
But it's just following the
same darn pattern, which
is to say it might look
cryptic, but, conceptually,
intellectually, it ultimately
is exactly as we did before.
So, yes, I'll spoil
the rest of the math.
It's 72, 73, 33.
Now, anyone remember, in your mind's
eye, what message we just spelled?
AUDIENCE: Hi.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
so it is, in fact, "Hi!"
Though, no one really
said that excitedly.
What's the 33, if you noticed?
AUDIENCE: Exclamation point.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, so
a lot of people noticed.
Yes, it's an exclamation point.
And that's, indeed,
noticeable right here.
33 is the exclamation point.
And that's just something,
eventually, that might sink in.
But, for the most part, if
you remember capital A is 65,
you can figure out at least 25 other
answers to these kinds of questions
because they're all
contiguous like that.
So there's the exclamation point.
But at the end of the day, we might
just have this mapping known as ASCII.
And it's how our phones, and
computers, and devices, more
generally, actually store information.
So we thought we'd make--
maybe take a little
pressure off of me here.
And could we maybe flip things around?
How about we try applying
this newfound knowledge--
if it's, indeed, new to you-- with seven
volunteers, seven bits, if we could?
OK.
I saw your hand first.
Come on down.
Maybe your hand, there.
OK, three, come on down over here.
How about four and five?
Yep, come on down.
Yep, in the black shirt, yep.
How about let me go farther back?
How about in the green, over there?
And how about you, seven, over here?
All right.
Come on down.
[CHATTER]
So a round of applause
for our brave volunteers.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
So if you'd like to stand, roughly,
side by side, here in the middle
of the stage.
First of all, thank you.
Let's see.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, perfect.
OK.
And let's go all the way
over to this place, here.
If you would like to introduce
yourself to the class.
RACHEL RICHEY: I'm Rachel Richey.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
And what year?
Anything about you?
RACHEL RICHEY: Oh, first
year, concentrating in CS.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
Welcome to the stage.
Next.
SPEAKER: Hi.
I'm [? Kang. ?] Also a
first-year concentrating in CS.
SPEAKER: Hello.
My name is [? Lam. ?] I'm a [INAUDIBLE]
student from education department.
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
OK.
Next.
JORDAN MITTLER: Hi.
I'm Jordan Mittler, concentrating
in economics and maybe some CS.
SPEAKER: So, hi.
I'm [? Natalia. ?] First
year, and I want to do CS.
SPEAKER: Hi.
I'm [? Khadija. ?] I'm a
first-year, and I want to do CS.
DAVID J. MALAN: [LAUGHS].
SPEAKER: Hello.
I'm [? Caleb. ?] And, once again,
first year, concentrating in CS.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
Wonderful.
A pattern, yes.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
So, if you haven't guessed
already, each of these volunteers
is going to represent a bit, from
left to right, or right to left,
in this case.
So let's see.
If you want to represent--
how about the twos place?
How about the fours place, the eighths
place, 16ths place, 32's, 64, and 128?
Although, wait a-- I think I screwed up.
We needed one-- eighth volunteer.
I think you know-- well, I think--
[CLEARS THROAT] Spot?
OK.
Come on over.
If you guys could step forward a
little bit, and then scooch this way,
just to give Spot some room.
[FOOTSTEPS]
So Spot will represent the ones place.
Now, what our volunteers have on
the back of their sheets of paper
are little instructions.
We're going to spell out a three-letter
word in English by using three bytes,
from left to right, because
now we have eight volunteers.
I'm going to propose that you
raise your hand, if you're
supposed to represent a 1.
Or you just stand there,
without raising your hand,
if you're meant to represent a 0.
And what we'll have the
audience do is do the quick math
to figure out-- one, two, three--
each letter, what number is it.
What letter is it?
And we'll see what word that
we have finally spelled.
All right.
So, in round one--
you have instructions on your back
of your sheet that will tell you to--
what your number is.
If you're 0, stand there.
If you're a 1, raise your hand.
[PAPER RUSTLING]
What number do these guys
seem to be representing?
AUDIENCE: 68.
DAVID J. MALAN: 66, I think.
64 plus 2, so 66, which is the letter--
AUDIENCE: B.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, so,
B. OK, so, B. All right.
Hands down.
Second letter is going
to be spelled how?
[SPOT LANDS ON THE STAGE]
AUDIENCE: Whoa.
DAVID J. MALAN: [LAUGHS] All right.
What are we spelling now?
[INDISTINCT CHATTER]
I think-- psst, yep, OK.
Yeah, I think you're one.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
Now what number are we spelling?
AUDIENCE: 79
DAVID J. MALAN: 79, I
heard, which is the letter?
AUDIENCE: O.
DAVID J. MALAN: O. OK.
So hands down.
Thank you, Spot.
One final flourish.
So we've spelled B-O--
third letter, go ahead.
[SPOT LANDS ON THE STAGE]
What number, now, is this?
AUDIENCE: 87.
DAVID J. MALAN: I heard it here, 80--
AUDIENCE: Seven.
DAVID J. MALAN: --seven, which is?
AUDIENCE: W.
DAVID J. MALAN: W, which,
of course, spells "bow."
So if our volunteers could
take a bow, Spot included.
[APPLAUSE]
So this will make more
sense in week one,
when we have an assignment involving
a certain someone from the Nintendo
World.
But we have a lovely parting
gift for each of you.
SPEAKER: Thank you.
[LAUGHS]
DAVID J. MALAN: Thank
you for volunteering.
SPEAKER: Thanks.
DAVID J. MALAN: You might need to
share it with the folks next to you.
[CHATTER]
Oop, here we go.
There we go.
Thank you--
SPEAKER: Thank you.
RACHEL RICHEY: Thank you.
DAVID J. MALAN: --so much.
One more round of applause, if
we could, for our volunteers.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Did you lose something?
OK.
All right.
So, [LAUGHS] Spot's had it.
So let's see, then,
if we've solved, now,
the problem of representing
English letters of the alphabet,
being able to spell out words like
"bow," B-O-W. What if we actually do
have accented characters?
What if we do have other glyphs
that we want to represent?
Well, here, of course, is a standard
US English keyboard, which a lot of you
might have.
But there's also characters
that you can type much more
easily if you have a foreign
keyboard, relative to the US,
or with certain keystrokes on
your own Mac, PC, and phone.
But, nowadays, too, there's
this menu that, probably, you've
used in the past hour or two
to actually send some emoji.
An emoji, even though
they look like pictures
and they actually are
pictures on the screen,
they're, technically, just characters,
characters of an emoji alphabet
that happened to use a certain
pattern of 0's and 1's to represent
each of these faces, each of these
people, and places, and things.
And it turns out that one of
the reasons that we have just
so many [LAUGHS] such characters
nowadays is because we now
use Unicode instead of ASCII.
So Unicode is a superset,
so to speak, of ASCII,
which is to say that we, humans,
realized, some time ago, that just
using eight bits to represent
letters of the alphabet
certainly isn't very good
when we want to represent
other, non-English languages.
So Unicode doesn't just use eight bits.
It sometimes uses 16 bits per character,
sometimes 24 bits per character,
and sometimes even 32
bits per character.
Now, why those numbers?
That's just one byte, two bytes,
three bytes, or four bytes.
And that gives us--
does anyone know?
That gives us the ability
to represent as many as 4
billion possible characters.
Because if the longest one is
32 bits, that's 2 to the 32,
which, if you do out the math,
trust me, is roughly 4 billion.
So that's a lot of characters.
And we've got a lot of
room, then, for these emoji.
But it's not just about having
fun, pictorially, on the screen.
Unicode's mission really is to represent
and to preserve all human languages
digitally, both past,
present, and future.
So it is really about capturing
the entirety of human knowledge,
as we've expressed it
in language, but also
giving this newfound ability that's been
used centuries ago, too-- in writings,
on walls, and the like--
pictograms via which
we can still communicate,
even independently
of our own human language.
So we'll reduce it, today, to
just patterns of 0's and 1's, but
the problem being solved is much greater
and well-beyond CS, itself, there.
So here is a pattern
of 0's and 1's using
Unicode, so more than eight bits, that
represents a very popular emoji, which
might be a bit of a hint.
This is the most popular emoji,
as of last year, at least,
statistically, internationally.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
DAVID J. MALAN: Does this help?
It's, roughly, this number here.
No?
It's this one here.
So this is the most popular emoji,
by most measures, as of last year.
But it doesn't always look like this.
Those of you who have a Mac or an
iPhone recognize this symbol, perhaps,
immediately.
Those of you with Android
devices or other platforms
might notice that it's the same idea,
but it's a little bit different.
And this is because, too,
emojis, at the end of the day,
just represent character, but
those characters can be drawn,
can be painted in different ways.
And reasonable people
will interpret differently
this emoji, whose official name
is "face with tears of joy."
And, indeed, Google interprets
it a little differently
from Apple, versus Microsoft, versus
Meta, versus other companies, as well.
So you can almost think of
those different companies
as having different fonts for emoji.
And that really starts to connect things
to the world of text and characters.
So, just so you've seen it.
More on this, another time.
It turns out that emoji and,
really, characters, in general,
we don't use binary 0's
and 1's to represent them
because no one, myself included,
is going to recognize what's what.
It's just too much math.
It's not interesting.
And even decimal numbers--
that was 4 billion or some--
I don't remember which number is which.
So we represent things
a little more compactly.
And this, too, admittedly,
still looks cryptic,
but this is a Unicode code point that
uses another system, mathematically,
called base-16 or hexadecimal.
More on that, another time.
But it's just a way of representing
numbers even more succinctly,
writing less on the screen,
because you're using not just 0
through 9, as in decimal.
But you're using A through
F, as well, so a few letters
of the English alphabet come into play.
But, for now, that's
just a little easier
to remember, too, for people who
care, that that is the number that
represents "face with tears of joy."
But what if we want a customized emoji?
And this, increasingly, is the case.
Here, for instance,
are the five skin tones
that phones, and laptops, and
desktops, nowadays, support.
It's based on something called the
"Fitzpatrick scale," which essentially
categorizes human skin tone
into six or, in this case, five
different categories,
from lighter to darker.
But this suggests that, wow,
if we want to represent people
with five different skin tones,
like this, that could significantly
increase how many unique
patterns of 0's and 1's we
need for every possible face.
But if we think about it from
an engineering perspective,
we can actually just think of skin
tone as modifying some default
color, for better or for worse.
And yellow is the de facto
default, Simpson style.
But to modify it to look more genuinely
human-like, from lighter to darker,
well, maybe we just use
the same pattern of bits
to represent a human thumb, for
instance, thumbs up or thumbs down.
And we just, then, modify that character
to be displayed with a different skin
tone.
So, for instance, here,
then, is the "thumbs up"
that you might use on various platforms.
And let me just stipulate that
this is the Unicode code point.
That is the number that
Macs, PCs, and phones
use underneath the hood to represent
the default yellow "thumbs up."
But if you want to give
it a medium skin tone,
you still use that same number,
that same pattern of 0's and 1's,
or switches, underneath the hood.
But you use a few more switches
that the computer or phone
will interpret as, "Oh, you don't
want to see the default in yellow
because of this second number that's
in the computer's memory somewhere.
You want me to adjust it to
be the medium skin tone or any
of the other values, instead."
So that's the engineering
solution to this problem
of just trying to represent
different ranges of emoji here.
Well, what about something like this?
There's a lot more
combinatorics, nowadays,
on your keyboard for
relationships, for instance.
So here is a "couple with heart" here.
So the couple, here, of course,
is represented with, apparently,
this number here.
But that's it.
But if you want to be more
specific-- like man and woman,
or man-man, woman-woman--
it's the same idea,
but we just need to express
ourselves a little-- with a little
more information.
So, for instance, the way the
Unicode folks came up with,
years ago, to represent, for instance,
a woman with a heart and a man,
from left to right, would
be using these values.
So things just escalated
quickly, but only
in the sense that we're using more
bits, more 0's and 1's, to represent,
more expressively, this
particular combination.
So this happens to be
the number in Unicode
that represents the woman at left.
This is the number that
represents the man at right.
And this is the pair of
numbers that represents
the heart in the middle, sometimes red,
sometimes pink, displayed here as pink.
But if we want to change the
combination, for instance, to be,
say, woman--
if we want to change the
combination to be woman-woman,
notice that, now, the left and
the rightmost numbers match.
Or if we flip it back to man-man,
it's just using different numbers
on the tail end again.
And meanwhile, if I rewind, there's
these two identical values here.
These are called zero-width
joiners or ZWNJ characters.
It just is a special number
that humans reserve to say,
glue the emoji at the left to the
emoji on the right and so forth.
So it connects ideas in this way.
So there's actually a
lot of emojis, nowadays,
that are a combination
of different things.
"Heart on fire" is one
that's, technically,
the combination of a heart
emoji, the fire emoji,
joined together,
numerically, in this way.
So computer scientists who
come up with these things
are just reducing things
to representations.
All we have at our
disposal are 0's and 1's.
So we all just need
to agree, ultimately--
whether we're Google, Microsoft, or the
like-- how we're going to standardize
these kinds of things as information.
Questions, then, on how characters
are represented in a computer,
be it English or any other language?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: How is the plus a number?
DAVID J. MALAN: How is the what?
AUDIENCE: The plus, the U+.
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, the U+
is just a convention, really.
So U+ represents a
special Unicode character,
which is a U with a plus in the middle.
And this is just the
convention for saying,
hey, everyone, here comes a number
that represents a Unicode code point.
The U and the 1 have no-- sorry.
The U and the plus have no
mathematical significance.
It's just a visual clue to folks.
Other questions on
representing text in this way?
All right.
So what about colors?
We've already started
looking at pictures.
Well, how are those pictures, be it
emojis or anything else, represented?
One of the most common
ways is just with RGB--
red, green, and blue.
It turns out that if we just
keep track of how much red should
be on the screen, and how much green,
and how much blue, combined together,
that gives us every
color of the rainbow,
from white to black and
everything in between.
So how do we represent an amount
of red, and green, and blue?
Well, frankly, just with
three different numbers.
And this is how computers
typically represent colors.
Every one of the dots on your
computer screen or your phone screen
is called a pixel.
And every single dot underneath the hood
has three numbers associated with it,
so three numbers, three numbers,
three numbers for every little dot.
And those three numbers, together,
say how much red, green, and blue
should the device
display at that location.
So, for instance, if you
had a dot on your screen
that said, "use this much red, this
much green this much blue," because each
of these numbers, I'll tell
you, are one byte or eight bits,
which means the total
possible values is 0 to 255--
let me just ballpark that the 72,
it feels like a medium amount of red
because it's in between 0 and 255.
73 is a medium amount of green, and
33 of blue is just a little bit.
So if you combine a medium amount of
red, green, and a little bit of blue,
anyone want to guess what
color of the rainbow this is?
AUDIENCE: Brown.
DAVID J. MALAN: Sorry?
DAVID J. MALAN: Brown?
So, close.
It's a little more
yellow than it is brown.
But if we combine them, it looks
a little something like this.
This is just CS trivia,
not something that even
I would be able to eyeball, unless I
came up with that particular example.
But wait a minute.
We've seen these numbers before.
72, 73, 33 represented what--
AUDIENCE: Hi!
DAVID J. MALAN: --a few minutes ago?
So it meant "Hi!" but here I
am, claiming, no, no, no, no,
that means yellow.
How do you reconcile this?
Well, at the end of the
day, this is all we have,
0's and 1's, whether you
think of them as numbers,
or letters, or even colors now.
But it depends on the context.
So if you've received a
text message or an email,
odds are the pattern of 0's
and 1's that the computer
is showing you are going to be
interpreted as text because that's
the whole point of a
text message or an email.
If, though, you opened up MacOS's
or iOS's or Windows's or Android's
calculator app, the same
pattern of 0's and 1's might
be interpreted as numbers for some
addition, or subtraction, or whatever.
If you open the same pattern
of 0's and 1's in Photoshop,
like a graphics program, they're going
to be interpreted, in that context,
as colors.
So context matters.
And, indeed, as soon
as next week, when you
start writing code in
that language called C,
the onus will be on you, the programmer,
to tell the computer, interpret
the following sequence of bits as a
number, or a letter, or something else.
And you won't have to even worry
about what the 0's and 1's are,
but you need to give the computer
a hint as to what type of file
or piece of data you're representing.
So that gives us bits.
And you can actually see these
dots, these pixels on the screen.
Let me zoom in, zoom in.
And here we have it, just with this
emoji, which, at the end of the day,
is a picture that someone at
Apple, in this case, drew.
And you can see-- if you really
zoom in, or take your phone or TV
and really put it close to your
face, you'll see all of these dots,
depending on the hardware.
And each of these
dots, these squares, is
storing 24 bits or three bytes,
24 bits, 24 bits, 24 bits.
And that's whey, dot,
dot, dot, if you've
got a photograph, for instance,
that's three megabytes, which
is 3 million bytes, well, odds are
there's 1 million pixels therein
because you're using
three bytes per pixel
to represent each of those colors.
That's a bit of an
oversimplification, but that's
why images and photos are getting
bigger and bigger nowadays.
Because we're throwing even
more pixels into the file.
Music--
[MUSIC PLAYING]
--how could you represent
music, digitally,
using just 0's and 1's,
or numbers, really?
Any instinct, whether a musician or not?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: The notes could
be represented by a number.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so we can
just represent notes by a number.
So A is some number, and B. And maybe
sharp or flat is some other number.
But note might not be
quite enough for some--
yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Ah, OK.
So one note-- one number to
represent the note, itself,
the sound or the pitch; one other
number to represent the duration.
In the context of piano, how long
is the human holding the key down?
And maybe I can think of
a third, the loudness.
How hard has the person
played that note?
So, minimally, with
three numbers, you could
imagine representing music, as well.
And, indeed, that's very
well might be what computers
are doing when you listen to sound.
What about video?
How could you represent videos, as well?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Through many images.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, many images.
So if you've ever produced a film
or looked at some of the fine print,
30 frames per second, FPS,
or 29 frames per second
is just how many pictures
are flying across the screen.
But that's really all a
video file is on a computer,
lots of pictures moving so quickly in
front of us that you and I, our brains,
interpolate that as being actual motion.
And, in fact, from
yesteryear, motion pictures,
it's like pictures that are
giving the illusion of motion,
even though there's only 30 or so
of them flying across the screen.
So we have a way, now, to
represent information, both as
input and output, whether it's numbers,
letters, images, anything else.
Let's now focus on what's
inside of that black box,
so to speak, wherein we have
algorithms, step-by-step instructions
for solving some problem.
Now, what do I mean by "algorithms"
or "step-by-step instructions"?
Well, maybe, if we were
to turn this into code--
and that's how we'll connect
the dots, ultimately, today.
Code is just the implementation,
in computers, of algorithms.
An algorithm can be something
we do in the physical world.
Code is how we implement that exact
same idea, in the context of a computer,
instead.
And here, for instance, is a very
common application inside of a computer,
for your context.
This is the iOS version of the icon.
And, typically, if you
click on that icon,
you'll see something like
all of your contacts here,
typically, alphabetical,
by first name or last name.
And your phone or your computer lets
you often search for someone's name
at the very top.
And it will autocomplete, and
it'll be pretty darn fast.
But it'll be pretty darn fast
because the programmers who
implemented that application are
looking for someone quickly for you.
Now, I can do this old school style,
whereby we have one of these things
from yesteryear, an actual phone book.
So, in a physical phone book like
this, you might have 1,000 pages.
And on every page are a bunch
of names and a bunch of numbers.
And as I flip through this, I
could look for someone specific.
So suppose I want to call John Harvard,
who's-- the first name, of course,
starts with a J. Well, I
could just turn, page by page,
looking for John Harvard.
And if he's not there, I
keep turning and turning.
So this is an algorithm.
I'm stepping through the phone
book, one page at a time.
Is it correct, this algorithm,
assuming I'm looking down?
So, yeah.
I mean, it's stupidly
slow because why am
I wasting my time with the A's,
and the B's, and the so forth?
I could probably take
bigger bites out of it.
But it is correct.
And that's going to be one of the goals
of writing code, is to, of course,
solve the problem you
care about correctly.
So correctness goes without
saying, or else what's
the point of writing the code
or solving-- or implementing
the algorithm?
All right.
Well, let me at least speed things up.
So, instead of one page at a
time, so, two, four, six, eight--
no, ignore that-- 10,
12, 14, 16, and so forth.
It's a little hard to do,
physically, but it sounded faster.
It was twice as fast,
theoretically, but is it correct?
AUDIENCE: No.
DAVID J. MALAN: So, no.
Why?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, you might [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, I might miss
John Harvard because, just by accident,
he might get sandwiched
between two pages.
But do I have to throw the
algorithm out altogether?
Probably not.
Once I reach the K section,
which is past the J section,
I could double back at least one
page, at least, [PATS TELEPHONE BOOK]
and just make sure I didn't
blow past him completely.
So that is twice as fast,
because I'm going two pages
at a time, plus one extra step.
So it's still an improvement.
So the first algorithm,
worst case, if it's
not John, but someone
whose name starts with Z,
that might take me a full 1,000 steps.
The second algorithm is
just 500 steps because I'm
going two pages at a time plus
one, in case I have to double back,
but that's in the worst case.
But most of us in the-- in yesteryear,
and what Apple, and Google, and others
are actually doing is, in
software or here, physically,
we're typically going,
roughly, to the middle.
Especially if there's no cheat
sheet on the side, like A through Z,
I'm just going to go
to, roughly, the middle.
And, oh, here I am, not
surprisingly, in the M section.
But what do I now know.
If this is the M section,
where is John Harvard?
So, clearly, to the
left, alphabetically.
And so here is where we can take a
much bigger bite out of the problem.
We can really divide
and conquer this problem
by tearing [TEARS BOOK] the problem
in half, throwing half of it
away, 500 pages away, leaving
me with a smaller problem,
half as big, that I can
really just now repeat.
So I go, roughly, here, and
now I'm in the E section.
So I went a little too far back.
But what do I now know?
If this is the E pages, where's John?
AUDIENCE: To the right.
DAVID J. MALAN: So
now he's to the right.
So I can-- again, hopefully,
he's not on that page.
I can tear the problem in half
again, throw that 250 pages away.
And now I've gone from
1,000 to 500 to 250 pages.
Now I'm moving because the first
algorithm was one page at a time,
second was two.
This is hundreds of pages at a time.
And if I go, roughly, again,
to the middle; roughly,
to the middle; roughly, to
the middle, hopefully, I'll
find John Harvard on one final page.
Can only do this once,
but one final page.
So that invites the
question, I would think,
if the phone book does
have 1,000 or so pages,
how many times can I divide the problem
in half to get down to one last page?
So it's, roughly, 10.
And the quick math is 1,000 goes to
500 to 250 to 125 to 67 something.
So we have to deal with
rounding issues, eventually.
But assuming we work out the math,
it's, roughly, 10 page tears.
And that's crazy faster than 1,000
pages and still faster than 500 pages.
So it's fundamentally better.
And, indeed, if I finally get to that
final page, in the software world,
you'd see something like this,
John Harvard and his number,
which you're welcome to call or text.
But that's how we now have our answer,
much like the single page there.
But let's consider just how
efficient that actually is.
So here's a very rough, broad--
with broad strokes, a chart.
So here's an xy plot.
So here, on the horizontal, is
going to be the size of the problem.
And, by that, I mean, how many
pages are we trying to go through?
This would be zero pages.
This would be a lot of pages.
How much time does it
take to solve the problem?
How long does it take to find
John Harvard or anyone else?
This means no time.
This means a lot of time.
So what's the relationship
among these algorithms?
Well, the first one is
actually just a straight line.
If there's n pages in
the phone book, well, I
claim that it's a
one-to-one relationship.
Because if Verizon or the phone
company adds another page next year,
that just means I might have
one more step next year,
as well, to find John
Harvard or anyone else.
But the second algorithm,
it's also a straight line,
but it's lower, even though
it might not look obvious.
And what do I mean by that?
Well, let me just draw
some temporary lines.
If this is how many pages
are in the phone book-- dot,
dot, dot-- notice that it takes
this much time, on the red line,
to solve the problem.
But if I, instead, use
the second algorithm,
it takes me half as much time.
So, even though they're
both straight lines,
one is strictly lower than the
other, which means it's faster.
It's better.
But the third algorithm is a
fundamentally different shape,
and it looks a little
something like this.
And it looks like it's going to
flatten, flatten, flatten out,
but it never does.
It just rises ever so slowly.
And what this means is that if
maybe Cambridge and Allston, here
in Massachusetts, merge next year,
so we go from 1,000 page phone book
to a 2,000 page phone book, that
means, if we're here this year,
we're over here next year.
It's not all that much higher.
But it would be much higher if we
were using the first two algorithms.
Why?
It'd be an extra 1,000 steps to
find someone in that combined phone
book or maybe another 500 steps.
But, to be clear, if we're using
my third and final algorithm,
how many more steps will
it take me next year,
when Cambridge and Allston merge
into one 2,000-page phone book?
Just one more step, no big deal.
It's one more page tear.
And this is what we mean,
ultimately, about not just writing
code or implementing algorithms
that are correct, but, now,
that are well-designed or
efficient, specifically.
And this is what makes someone
a better programmer, perhaps,
than someone else, or a better
problem-solver than someone else,
is acquiring, over time, these skills.
So that, sure, you could solve
the problem quickly and dirtily,
so to speak, but if you're
going to have a lot of data
eventually, be it in your phone book
or maybe your Google website index,
if you're searching
the web, you're going
to want to try to think about how to
design algorithms that look like this.
Mathematically, this
is called a logarithm.
And it's log base 2 because I'm halving,
halving, halving, again and again.
But, for now, just know that it's a
fundamentally faster and different
shape.
So, among our goals in CS50,
ultimately, is not just
to write and solve problems correctly,
but, ultimately, ever more efficiently,
as well.
Any questions, then, on these
ideas of efficiency and design?
Any questions here?
Yeah, in back?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: A good question.
Just to repeat it, can a graph like this
capture the accuracy of the algorithm?
Short answer, no.
For instance, if I drew
a straight line that
is super low on this graph, which
would imply that the algorithm takes
the same amount of time, no
matter how many pages there are,
my algorithm might actually be to
just pull a random page from the phone
book, one step, and say, here it is.
But that's not necessarily
going to be accurate,
unless I get really, really lucky.
So the graph really only
speaks to efficiency
and the design of the algorithm,
not the correctness of it.
To analyze the correctness, you need
to use another mechanism altogether,
namely, logic.
Other questions now, on
efficiency, in this way?
No?
All right.
So, with that in mind, let's begin to
translate this to some actual code.
And, in fact, before we look at,
today, one actual programming language,
albeit a graphical one, let's
consider something called pseudocode.
So pseudocode has no formal meaning.
Generally, you write it in English or
whatever your own human language is.
But you write your thoughts down
tersely, succinct, but precisely.
You try to really convey your
thoughts, not with a wave of the hand,
metaphorically, but
step by step, precisely.
So what do I mean by this?
Here might be some
representative pseudocode
via which I describe that third
and final algorithm in a way
that I could hand it to you and
you could do the same at home.
Or I could hand it to someone at Google,
and they could implement it in Android.
Or I could hand it to someone at Apple,
and they could implement it in iOS.
So, step one, I claimed,
was "Pick up phone book."
Step two was "Open to the
middle of the phone book."
Step three, "Look at
the page," as I did.
And now things get a
little more interesting.
Step four, "If person is on
page," I have to make a decision.
Presumably, what should I do if John
Harvard is on the page I'm looking at?
So stop and probably make the call, or
email, or whatever the goal might be.
And so I'm going to actually indent
this, visually, by a few spaces,
just to make clear that you should only
do line five if the answer to line four
is yes.
Otherwise, you don't bother.
The next thing I'm going to do, line
six, is consider another possibility.
"If the person I'm
looking for is earlier
in the book," what do I want to do?
Well, I could write--
I could describe this
in a bunch of ways.
I'm going to do this
tersely, as follows.
"Open to the middle of
the left half of the book,
so it's open to the middle
of the left half of the book.
And then, what am I going to do?
Well, I've just divided the
problem into something smaller.
But it's fundamentally the same problem.
It's just a fewer number of pages.
So I'm just going to go back
to line three and do it again
because the problem is just getting
smaller and smaller, presumably.
Else, if the person I'm looking
for is later in the book,
open to the middle of the
right half of the book,
and, also, "Go back to line 3."
But there's a fourth
possibility and its failure
to realize, sometimes, that there's
other possible outcomes that
make computers crash, or spinning
beach balls, or the like,
if a programmer doesn't
anticipate some situation.
What's the fourth possible situation,
when looking for John Harvard?
AUDIENCE: If they're not in the book.
DAVID J. MALAN: If they're
not in the book, at all.
And, indeed, I might get to the very
last page and John Harvard's not even
on that one.
I'd better handle that and say, else,
as a catchall, just quit altogether.
And, truly, often, in
your Macs, PCs, phones,
when they freeze, or, again,
spinning beach ball, or the like,
and just weird things
happen, that's just
because some human made a dumb mistake.
And they didn't realize that you could
somehow get your phone or your laptop
into a configuration that
they didn't anticipate.
So we're going to try
to handle that here.
Now this is just one way
of writing pseudocode.
There's no one way to do this.
All of us in this room could come up
with slightly different pseudocode.
But I think you'll find
characteristic are certain building
blocks in all of our answers.
Here, in yellow, are
what, as of today, we're
going to start calling
"functions," technically speaking.
These are like actions or verbs that
literally, in this case, tell me
what to do.
Next, we're going to have
these things, conditionals,
forks in the road, so to speak, that
take me down this path or another,
metaphorically.
So I do this thing or something else.
But how do I decide if I want
to go this way, or this way,
or this way, or this way?
I need to ask a question.
And in programming,
we'll typically use what
are called Boolean expressions,
named after a mathematician, Boole.
And a Boolean expression is
essentially just a question
with a yes/no answer, a true or
false answer, a 1 or 0 answer.
It doesn't matter how you think about
it, but it's got two possible answers.
And so you can think of these as
being expressions with question marks,
even though I didn't draw such.
Person on page, person earlier
in book, person later in book,
those are Boolean expressions.
And they tell me whether I should go
down one fork in the road or another.
And, lastly, there's this, "Go back
to line 3," in two different places.
That represents what we call a
"loop," some kind of cycle that's
doing something again and again.
Now these are just a few
building blocks here--
functions, conditionals,
Boolean expressions, loops.
But you'll find that
they're characteristic of so
many different languages, one of which
we'll look at today, another of which
we'll look at next week.
And those include, indeed, C, and
Python, and other languages still.
And so this is why we
focus on these basics
and fundamentals in these
early days because we're
going to see them again and again.
So even if you feel like that
fire hose is hitting you sometime,
we'll give you, today,
ultimately, more visuals
by which you can hang onto, so as
to actually write code, ultimately,
in different languages and
solve all sorts of problems.
Now, we'd be remiss in not bringing
up what's behind characters like Spot,
and ChatGPT, and other software,
artificial intelligence.
And it turns out, to
get to the point of AI,
we're actually going to need
more building blocks than just
functions, and loops, and conditionals.
It's not going to be quite that simple.
But this has been a lot, so far.
Let's go ahead, here, and
take a five-minute break.
And when we resume, we'll
take a look not only at AI,
but also a specific
language called Scratch.
So no cake, just yet, but
we'll come back in five.
Before we dive back in, I just
wanted to call out a special guest
that we have here today,
beyond Spot, someone
who's come from even farther away.
And, in fact, if any of you have taken
CS50x, the OpenCourseWare version
of the class, or dabbled in
it over the past few years
in some of CS50's online
social communities,
you might have had
your questions answered
by a certain human from New Zealand.
And she's come all this way, today,
to spend this lecture with us.
This is CS50's own Brenda Anderson.
If you might come up for
acknowledgment from all of us here.
[APPLAUSE]
It's not much, but just a
little token of our thanks.
Brenda has helped, truly,
thousands of students online
for the past many years.
And, in fact, her own
daughter has been the artist
behind the duck that's about to loom
large in CS50 this year and beyond.
So, thank you to Brenda.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
So it's hard to escape a discussion
of artificial intelligence, nowadays,
but we thought we'd use
this as an opportunity
to connect some of these dots.
Because, indeed, over the
course of the semester,
we'll be-- not only be talking
about artificial intelligence or AI,
but really using it all
the more constructively
to help you solve problems,
help you get unblocked
when you hit a wall, cognitively or
syntactically, when writing code.
And, indeed, it's no accident
that we have this duck here,
looming large, which is really
the embodiment of the sort of AI
that you'll experience within
CS50, itself, this year.
So let's talk about the
so-called chatbots that
inspired some of those
headlines with which we began
class, that weren't quite on the nose.
So the class will still
be taught by us humans,
but helped by this CS50
duck, a chatbot of sorts.
Now what do I mean by this?
Well, it turns out that, when it
comes to implementing something
like an artificial
intelligence, we don't quite
have all of the building blocks yet,
certainly after just today's week zero,
to implement something like that.
But I think we can skate in
that direction, intellectually.
So, for instance, if we were to take a
stab at implementing our own chatbot--
some interactive text-based
program that talks to us,
and answers questions,
and the like-- we could
try borrowing some of today's ideas
already, those functions, conditionals,
loops, and more.
And I could write something like this.
If I am writing code or
pseudocode for a chatbot,
I could program the chatbot
to do something like this.
If the student says,
hello, to the chatbot,
then the chatbot should
say, hello, back.
Else, if the student says,
goodbye, well, the chatbot
should say, goodbye, back.
Else, if the student asks how you are,
the chat bot should say that it's well.
But things get a little
harder when you start
asking more interesting
questions, like, else,
if the student asks why 111
in binary is 7 in decimal.
Now, you could imagine that
we just have a conditional,
with this Boolean expression, that
programs the chatbot to just give you
the answer and explain, in an English
sentence, why that, in fact, is.
But what if you, the student, asks why
110 is 6 in decimal or why 010 is 2?
I mean, you can just imagine the
explosion in the amount of code
that we would have to write to just
anticipate every darn question that you
might ask about today and every
other class, not to mention all
of the knowledge in the universe.
So, surely, there are other
ways to implement algorithms
that allow something
like a chatbot or AI,
more generally, to be fed input,
still, like all of the internet, all
of the worldwide web, all of the
pages and textual content therein,
but to let it just figure out
how to answer our questions based
on those kinds of inputs, assuming
the inputs, themselves, are accurate.
So "large language models"
is a term you might
have heard bandied about over
the past several months, or LLMs.
And a large language model really
is an implementation, in software,
of code that actually takes, as
input, lots and lots of language--
like the text of lots and lots of web
pages, dictionaries, encyclopedias,
Wikipedias, and the like--
and infers, from the patterns of
English words or any human language,
what a typical human might
actually say when asked a question.
And some of these
questions are easy, right?
Probably, on the internet, alone, not
to mention everyday life, if someone
extends their hand and says, "Hi.
How are you," odds are, with 90%
probability, you're going to say,
"Good.
Thanks.
How are you?"
So I bet we could write
software that just
infers what it should say,
probabilistically, statistically, based
on those kinds of patterns online.
And that's, indeed, where
the world is starting
to go, when it comes to
the most sophisticated
of algorithms, where
you and I, the humans,
we don't try to anticipate
every possible input.
Rather, we give it a
more general purpose
input, like all human knowledge, and
ideally just let it figure things out.
Now, we're not quite there, yet.
And odds are you've heard of
hallucinations or just mistakes
that these large language models make.
But their inputs are imperfect.
And sometimes there's a
bit of randomness sprinkled
in because you don't want the thing
to always say the exact same thing.
Even you and I might say, "Eh, I'm
not that great today" 10% of the time.
So you need to perturb
the output in some way.
But within CS50 and within this
world of large language models,
we do have these tools like
ChatGPT, and Bing, chat, and others.
And we'll stipulate that,
for CS50's purposes,
the direction we're going
this year is that this
is what's in the
syllabus, dot, dot, dot;
that it will not be allowed,
it will be considered
not reasonable to use AI-based
software, other than CS50's own.
So the goal here is
not to simply take away
tools that are clearly inevitable,
in my view, and clearly helpful
and productivity savers.
But we'd like there to be some
guardrails, intellectually, on just how
helpful these chatbots are.
Because as you've probably
seen, if you ask it a question,
these chatbots are already
pretty good at not just helping
you finish your current
thought, but it'll
hand you your second and your third
thought and do the assignment for you.
But I think, through
prompting, so to speak,
we'll be able to coax
some of our own tools,
being computer scientists,
ourself, in a direction
that you actually find to be the
right balance, akin to having
a good tutor by your side 24/7,
who doesn't just hand you answers,
but, indeed, tries to
lead you to the same.
So you actually get something
out of the experience,
and, ideally, three-plus
months from now,
those training wheels can come off, too.
And you're able to
still stand on your own.
So it will be reasonable to use
CS50's own AI-based software which
will actually take the form of a CS50
duck, which is actually available now--
and we'll use it throughout the term--
at CS50.ai, a web-based application
that's quite similar
to ChatGPT, but that
has the personality of a CS50 teaching
fellow or TF, or teaching assistant,
TA, that also happens to
think of itself as a duck.
And for reasons we'll get to
in a couple of weeks time,
but rubber ducks, in particular,
are a thing in programming.
But more on that, before long,
as you can even see from the one
there on my desk.
With that said, too, well, I'm
going to call out CS50's own Brenda
Anderson, whose daughter,
Sophie, kindly not only created
the first incarnation, digitally,
of this duck, but also,
most recently, once it actually
did more than quack a random number
of times in response
to questions, has now
been virtually brought to life, too.
So, all that and more, over the coming
weeks, but you'll find, ultimately,
that the goal is to really bring to life
the availability of an AI-based tutor
that you have access
to, a friend in your--
next to you, that will help guide
you through a lot of the course's
challenges along the way.
And we actually rolled
it out this past summer,
already, with some of your predecessors,
through the Harvard Summer School.
One student wrote, at
summer's end, that this duck
"felt like having a personal tutor--
I love how AI bots will answer questions
without ego and without judgment
generally entertaining even
the stupidest of questions
without treating them
like they're stupid.
It has, as one could expect,
an inhuman level of patience."
So there's actually something really
there because as many teachers
as there are in CS50--
myself, the course's preceptors,
teaching fellows, teaching assistants,
and course assistants--
there's only so many of us.
And we're only awake so
many hours of the day.
And I think you'll find, too, that
we're on the cusp of something
pretty remarkable, in
the coming years, where
it's going to get a lot more
enabling, now, to learn material
not only within the confines of a class,
but on your own, ultimately, as well.
And as one other student put it, at
summer's end, with respect to the duck,
"Love love loved the duck.
We're friends now."
So that, too, awaits.
But, first, we're going to
need to start with the basics.
And we started today by
talking about binary.
And darn it, here it is again.
So we can't actually get to the point
of using, or solving, or implementing AI
until we understand this.
And odds are most of you won't know, at
a glance, what this piece of software
does.
But these are the 0's and
1's that represent, perhaps,
the first program that any programmer
writes, which is now a clue to some
of you who have dabbled in code before.
What does this pattern of 0's and
1's tell a typical computer to do?
Might someone guess?
AUDIENCE: "Hello, world."
DAVID J. MALAN: It's going to
have it say, "hello, world,"
which is one of the very
first programmer-- programs
that most any programmer writes.
Should you be able to
recognize these 0's and 1's?
Do I recognize these 0's and 1's?
No, not at all.
I just happen to know
that they are the same.
And that was a leading question.
But they are representing data
and instructions, ultimately,
data like H-E-L-L-O, comma,
W-O-R-L-D and an instruction like,
"Print that data to the screen."
As for what these patterns
of 0's and 1's are,
this is not something that a computer
scientist or programmer worries about.
We just stipulate that, OK, someone,
somewhere knows how to do this.
And it's probably someone
like Intel, who makes
the hardware inside of the computers.
But you and I, starting
now, already, in week zero,
can start to view
binary more abstractly.
We don't care about the 0's and 1's.
We only care that you
can use 0's and 1's
to represent more useful
quantities, like numbers,
and letters, colors, and more.
So this, next week, is going
to be the code we actually
start writing at a keyboard.
And this is that language called C. It's
the same language I, myself, learned
years ago, when taking CS50, when
all we learned at the time was C.
But this, too, has
some crypticness to it.
And if you've never programmed before,
you can probably wrap your mind around,
OK, I'm guessing the "printf"
prints out the "hello, world."
But what's with the semicolon,
the quotes, the backslash,
and the curly braces, the #include,
and all of this stupid syntax?
A lot of this, in the beginning of
any class, is really a distraction.
It is not intellectually interesting.
But it's the stupid kind of stuff
that's going to trip you up quite often.
And so, today, what
we'll do is focus not
on syntax, characters on
the keyboard, but ideas
because what really
matters in this program
is that "printf" is a function
here for our purposes.
And that function is to display
information on the screen.
Everything else, as
we'll soon see, has value
and will be understood by you, before
long, but for now, it's a distraction.
Let's focus on those building blocks.
When it comes time to write
code, though, for the curious,
especially if you've
programmed before, we'll
use a very popular free
and open-source tool
called Visual Studio Code, or VS Code.
We'll use a cloud-based version of
it that we pre-install everything
you need in the cloud
for you so you don't
have to deal with headaches like
getting your Mac or PC to work.
You'll use instead this
URL, cs50.dev, but more
on that in next week, week one.
For now, we'll use another
cloud-based editor called Scratch.
And odds are some number
of you use this probably
as early as like middle
school or the like.
And that was fine to create
your own animations, games,
interactive art, or the like.
But we'll use it today for just a bit.
And we'll use it in the
course's first homework,
AKA problem set 0, to explore
now some of these same ideas.
And among the goals today
for the remainder of today
is not to focus so much on
Scratch and the particulars
because this is not a
language that you're
going to use often but to give you
very visual representations of ideas
so that when things do escalate
next week to C, to the more cryptic,
it's the same ideas just typed out
instead of dragged and dropped.
So by that, I mean this.
I'm going to go ahead and share in just
a moment the user interface of Scratch.
But what's nice about
Scratch is that this
is how we're going to implement
that same program today.
These are two blocks or
puzzle pieces on the screen,
and they've been interconnected to
tell the computer to say "hello, world"
on the screen.
The user interface
that we're about to use
will look generally something like this.
It's a web-based editor
that you can also
download it locally to use offline.
And you'll see that at the left here
are a whole bunch of puzzle pieces
or blocks.
They're categorized by
color, and the blue ones
tend to relate to motion, for instance.
The purple ones represent looks.
The pink one represents sounds.
The yellow one represents events.
More on that soon.
The orange ones represent
control, and then
there's operators, variables, my
blocks, and even some extensions
we can install as well.
So it just categorizes things
visually and colorfully so that you
can find what you're looking for.
But we're going to use these
puzzle pieces to drag and drop them
onto this area here.
And we're going to connect them
when we want them to do something.
What can they do?
Well, by default, Scratch comes
with this cat here, otherwise known
as a sprite, which is a character
in a game or in a graphics context.
And this cat lives in this
two-dimensional world in which
the cat can go up, down, left, right.
And you can actually
change the cat's costume
to be a dog, a bird, or anything else.
It really is more of an idea than it
is a specific animal in this case.
But the world that Scratch lives in
looks a little something like this.
It's like a Cartesian plane with
x-coordinates and y-coordinates.
And the numbers don't so
much matter fundamentally,
except that when you want the
cat or any character to go up,
down, left, or right
by some amount, it's
useful to know, for instance, that 0, 0
is the middle, 0 comma 0 for x comma y.
All the way up is a y value of 180.
All the way down is -180.
All the way to the left is -240.
All the way to the right is 240.
And generally, you're not going
to have to worry about numbers.
You're going to use these relatively--
go right, go left, go up, or down.
But that's just the world that
Scratch itself lives in here.
So let's go about using Scratch here.
I'm going to change over
to my cloud-based editor
here, where I've gone
to scratch.mit.edu.
And I've clicked Create in
order to create a project.
And that gives me this
blank canvas here.
And I'm going to do these somewhat
quickly because I kind of know
what I'm looking for.
But part of the process with problem
set zero is going to be clicking,
and dragging, and sort
of scrolling around
to see what building blocks exist.
But I know under Events
there's this puzzle piece here
when green flag clicked.
Why is that germane?
Well, if I zoom out, and go back to
Scratch's world at the right here,
notice that above
Scratch's world there's
a green flag, which is going to
mean go, and a red stop sign, which,
of course, is going to mean stop.
So if I drag this puzzle piece
anywhere into the middle,
it's just going to plop where I put it.
But what that means semantically is
when someone clicks that green flag,
I want Scratch the cat
to do this other thing.
Well, what do I want it to do?
Well, let me go under Looks.
And looks here in purple have
some puzzle pieces like this.
Well, I can say hello for
some number of seconds,
or I can just go ahead and say hello.
So let's do that.
I'm going to drag this say block.
And notice that as soon
as I get close enough,
it's going to magnetically
want to connect.
So I can let go, and they
snap together automatically
because they're the right shape.
I don't have to say
hello, exclamation point.
I can change it to the more
canonical, hello comma world.
So anything in this
white oval is editable
that you can change as just text there.
If I now zoom out, let me go
ahead and click the green flag.
And voila-- this should be
my first program in Scratch.
Hello, world.
Without any of the
distractions of syntax
or weird characters on the screen,
it's just done what I want it to do.
All right.
Let me go ahead and click Stop there.
And let me make it a
little more connected
to what we've discussed thus far.
So this puzzle piece
here, say hello, world,
represents what type of building
block using the vocabulary of today?
So it's a function.
So these purple blocks are
functions, say, hello, world.
And let me give you another
piece of terminology.
These white ovals that
take textual input--
in general, those are called
parameters or arguments.
And they customize the
behavior of a function.
So a parameter or an
argument customizes,
modifies the default behavior of a
function, like in this case, say.
Similarly, in the C code from
earlier that we'll see next week,
the printf function took a quoted phrase
like, hello, world, similarly as input.
But more on that in the future.
So how does this connect to the
mental model we presented earlier?
Well, here's problem-solving as I
described it earlier, inputs to outputs
with algorithms or code in the middle.
Well, what we've got here really is an
input of, hello, world, the white oval.
The function or algorithm that it's
going into as input is the say block.
And what is the output of using
this say block, the say function?
It's the visual effect of having the
cat have the little speech bubble appear
above its head, saying, hello, world.
So everything we do, in
fact, can be mapped back
to that very simple idea
of inputs and outputs.
Well, let's make it a little
more interesting, though.
It's a little boring to just
say "hello, world" all the time.
Let me go ahead and drag this away.
And if you just drag it to the left and
let go, it gets automatically deleted.
Let me go under Sensing
in light blue here.
And you'll see there's a
bunch of blocks, one of which
is an ask block, an ask function,
which is going to prompt
the human, me, for some input.
So let me go ahead and drag that
over here, and it snaps together.
I could change the question,
but I'm OK with that question.
We'll use what's your name.
But notice that this block,
ask, is a little special.
It is not just going to display
like a speech bubble on the screen.
It's actually going to
return a value, and this is
another term of art today and onward.
A return value is some value that can
be handed back to you conceptually
from a function so that you
can do something with it.
It's as though the ask function
asks someone for their name,
writes it down on a piece of paper,
and hands you the piece of paper.
You can do anything now that
you want with that name.
And here is how you access the
name in this special block called
answer, which, again, will
start calling a return value.
So if I want to say "hello" to someone
specific, I'm going to do this.
Let me zoom out.
Let me go back to Looks,
and let me go back to Say.
And I'm going to change the say
block here to "hello, comma."
Then I'm going to zoom out.
Well, I need two inputs, I think.
So I'm going to grab another say
block, and I'm going to put it below.
And I could just type
"David," but this is
going to defeat the whole point
of asking me for the name.
And it will only work for me.
So I don't want to do that.
So let me go back to Sensing, and
notice the shape is important here.
Even if it's not quite the
same size, the shape matters.
And I can actually drag this and
change the input of this say function
to be whatever that return
value is, that piece of paper
that has the person's name on it.
And it grows to fill,
but now we have a program
that I think when I click the green
flag-- watch-- is going to prompt me.
What's your name?
And now I have room to type down here.
So I'm going to type D-A-V-I-D.
I'm going to hit Enter,
and it should say "hello, Dave."
Wait.
Hmm.
Huh.
Maybe it was-- didn't work.
D-A-V-I-D. Here we go.
Hello, David.
Hmm.
It's missing the hello, but I'm quite
sure we have a hello right there.
So what explains this bug or mistake?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
So they overlap.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
Put another way, my Mac,
my PC, it's just so darn
fast that it did exactly
what it was supposed to.
But it said "hello, David" so fast that
we didn't even see, we being the human,
the slowest part of the
puzzle, see the actual hello.
So there's a few different
ways to fix this, as you know.
We could have it say "hello"
for some number of seconds.
So I could kind of do that.
So let me do this.
I can decouple these by just
dragging and letting it go
so that they're magnetically far apart.
Let me go ahead and drag this
one, say hello for two seconds.
I'm going to change the grammar
here to be hello comma again.
I'm going to go ahead
and disconnect these two.
I'm going to throw away the old
one that I don't want to use.
And I'm going to reconnect
this so that now--
OK.
It's going to say hello for two
seconds and then my name, hopefully.
So let me click Stop and Start.
D-A-V-I-D. Enter.
OK.
So it's better, but it's
kind of poorly implemented.
Like, come on.
I just wanted to say hello comma David.
Why is that hard?
Well, maybe we can actually
combine these a little differently.
And let me propose this.
Let me actually get rid
of these blocks again.
And let me go ahead
and just say one thing.
But can I somehow combine this to say
hello comma David all in one breath?
Well, it turns out if
I go under Operators,
I know from having played with this
before that there's this puzzle
piece down here called join.
It's an oval.
It's a little big, but,
again, it will grow to fill.
And by default, it wants to join
two words, "apple" and "banana."
But those are just placeholders.
So let me go ahead and drag
this over the default hello.
Let me change "apple" to hello
comma space and then banana.
Let me go back to Sensing.
Let me grab answer and
drag and drop that.
So now notice that I'm
kind of layering my ideas.
And put another way, the
output of this join block
is presumably going to
join two things together,
apple and banana or hello comma David.
And then the output of join is
going to become the input to say.
So aesthetically, it just looks better.
It's still correct,
but it's just better.
So if I type "David," and
hit Enter, hello, David.
This is what a normal
program would presumably
do, not show you part of the phrase
and then the rest of the phrase.
Like, it's just better in this way.
So let's connect this now to this same
puzzle piece and this methodology.
So here's that same puzzle piece, ask.
How do we fit it into this input
and output flow with algorithms?
Well, the input to that puzzle piece
is something like, what's your name,
question mark.
Then the algorithm or the
code implementation thereof
is this ask block and wait so the human
has a moment to type their response in.
The output of that function
recall is a return value.
You don't see anything on the screen by
default because we've not used say yet,
but we get this return value.
And let me scooch everything
over now so that we can now
join those inputs together.
So here's this puzzle piece.
Let me go ahead and propose that
the inputs now to the join block
are two arguments or two parameters,
so to speak, hello and answer.
They go into that join puzzle
piece, whose purpose in life
is to return one joined version thereof.
Let me slide this all
over logically now so
that now that output becomes
the input to the say block
and now is why the cat has the
speech bubble saying all at once,
hello comma David.
So what we've done here is
kind of composed the output
and from one function
into the input of another.
And you can think of this in
a couple of different ways,
left to right, as I
did there, or kind of
like stacking these things
on top of one another.
But at the end of the
day, even as programming
gets more and more powerful for us,
it's just inputs and outputs, inputs
and outputs.
And thankfully, with built-in
functionality from our friends
at MIT who designed Scratch, I can
even do something playful like this.
I can go to that Extensions
button at the bottom.
And there's a lot of fancy things I
can add here, like text-to-speech.
So let me go ahead and
choose text-to-speech.
And let me go ahead here and
change the say block in purple.
Let me get rid of the say
block, and let me borrow this.
Let me get the speak block like this.
And now let me drag and drop this oval.
It's going to grow to fill.
And I think it's just about to
be a little more interesting.
Let me click Play now, and
hopefully this isn't too loud.
D-A-V-I-D. Enter.
SPEAKER: Hello, David.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
That's a low bar.
[CHUCKLES] Let me go ahead
and set the voice too.
And you might now remember
how we began class, where
we had a robotic, computerized voice.
Well, we didn't use Scratch at the time,
but we could change this in Scratch
alone to be a little different.
So D-A-V-I-D.
SPEAKER: Hello, David.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
Little creepy, but we can
play all day long with that.
But the point is that
these functions are just
now doing something a little different.
But it's just these inputs and outputs.
Well, let's make the
cat more like a cat.
Let me go ahead and throw away
all of this asking question stuff.
Let me go up to Sound,
and let me go ahead
and drag the play sound meow until done.
And here too it comes with meow.
You can add your own sounds as well.
But I'm just going to use the
default meow and here too.
Hopefully, this won't be too loud.
Let's make the cat
meow by clicking Play.
[MEOWING]
OK.
It's a little piercing, but it's cute.
And if I want the cat to meow twice,
I could just play the game twice.
[MEOWING]
All right.
But it would be nice to just get it
to meow automatically two, or three,
or more times.
So you know what I could do?
I could just drag a second one of these.
Actually, you know what?
I could even just right-click or
Control-click and duplicate them.
But I'll just keep
dragging and dropping.
There's different ways
to solve problems.
And now let me click Play.
[MEOWING]
OK.
Cat does not sound particularly happy.
So we could go under--
how about Control?
We could wait one second.
Now, there's no room, but it will
sort of expand to give room for me.
So let me try this.
And now it's going to wait
one second in between meows.
[MEOWING]
OK.
Let me stipulate that is correct.
If my goal is to get the cat to meow
three times, it meowed three times.
But per our discussion earlier of
algorithms and the design thereof,
this is not the best design.
[MEOWING]
OK?
[LAUGHTER]
Thank you for playing along at home.
Yeah.
In what sense is this
arguably not well-designed?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: You repeated yourself.
DAVID J. MALAN: I repeated myself,
which actually in programming
tends not to be a good thing.
Now, it was easy.
I almost resorted to copy-paste,
which saves me time upfront.
But just imagine a contrived scenario.
Now, what if I want it to wait
like two seconds in between?
All right.
It's not that big a deal.
I change it here, and I change it here.
But what if the program
is meant to meow 10 times?
Then I have to change it here, and
here, and here, and here, and here.
And eventually I'm going to screw up.
Humans are fallible.
I'm going to overlook one of them.
One time, it's going to be one second.
Another is going to be two, and
just stupid things will happen.
You're setting yourself up for
failure if you design things poorly.
And so I would propose that we
use another type of building block
to solve this instead.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So we could use a loop and
just write minimal code
but to accomplish even
more functionality.
So let me throw away
most of these blocks.
And let's go and grab this repeat
block, which we haven't used yet,
but it's right there.
And as the name
suggests, this will allow
me to repeat something
some number of times.
Let me put these two
puzzle pieces inside.
It'll grow to fill.
Let me reconnect it to the green flag.
I'll change the default 10 to a 3.
And now--
[MEOWING]
It's just sort of better because if
now you want it to meow more times,
you change it one place.
If you want it to slow down,
you change it in one place.
There's no room for error.
And that's generally a good thing.
But this is silly.
Like, Scratch comes with a cat.
Why didn't MIT give us a
puzzle piece called "meow?"
Like, why am I implementing
the idea of meowing myself?
Like, that took me what?
1, 2, 3, 4 puzzle pieces.
Why isn't there just one
puzzle piece that meows for me?
This too we can do in code, be it in
Scratch, or C, or other languages too.
I'm going to go down to
these pink my blocks here,
where I can create my own puzzle piece.
And I'm going to call
this literally "meow."
And I'm going to go
ahead and just click OK.
And notice that it's given me
this new type of start connector.
It's a start puzzle piece
that nothing goes above it.
But you can put anything
you want below it.
And I'm going to go
ahead and cheat here.
I'm just going to grab my
existing code, so to speak.
This is code I'm writing, even
though it's puzzle pieces.
And now let me just claim,
and I'll move this aside.
Here is now an implementation
of my own function,
my own block called "meow,"
whose purpose in life
is to meow until done
and then wait one second.
But what's powerful now is notice at
top left, now that I've made the block,
I can use it any number of times.
So I can grab this meow block, drag
it over here, and you know what?
Now that "meow" exists as an
idea, I can abstract that away.
And I'm just going to arbitrarily
drag it way to the bottom.
I'm not deleting it.
I'm just putting it out
of sight, out of mind so
that we can focus now on this idea.
And I claim that this
implementation of meowing
is sort of better because it's
more compact, it does what it says,
and I don't care about the
implementation details of "meow."
So this idea of abstraction, something
we're going to use frequently.
To abstract something
away is to simplify.
Don't think about the underlying
implementation details.
Just care about what it
does or what it's called.
Someone has to care about
the implementation details,
like me 30 seconds ago.
But here on out, I don't need to care.
And so in fact, you and I
are using the abstraction
that is Scratch because I don't know how
to put a speech bubble on the screen.
I don't know how to
create that sound, meow.
MIT did that, and they
abstracted those pieces
of functionality away already
for us by just giving us
these puzzle pieces we see here.
So the code will work the exact same.
[MEOWING]
But it's sort of better
designed now because now I've
abstracted away the idea of meowing.
But I bet I can improve this further.
Can I get rid of the
repeat block altogether?
And let me just tell the meow
block how many times to meow.
Well, let me go down to the bottom and
look at the implementation details.
I'm going to right-click
or Control-click on this,
and I'm going to edit it.
So I'm going to make a change.
And I didn't do this before, but I'm
going to call it "meow," as before.
I'm going to add an input.
And just so I know what
it says what it does,
I'm going to add the word "times" here.
And I'm going to change
this placeholder to n.
n for "number" is the
go-to placeholder any time
we want to talk about a number in CS.
So now notice the puzzle piece
looks a little different.
It takes an argument
or a parameter called
n, which represents the number of
times you want the thing to meow.
Now, that doesn't do that yet.
So let me go back to my other code.
Let me just decouple these temporarily.
I'm going to move my loop into
my implementation of meowing.
But I don't want to hard code, that is
literally write the number 3 anymore.
I'm going to grab this
oval and put it there.
So now I've generalized the function.
So now it will meow any number of
times, 0 on up, by executing that loop
and now more powerfully.
Out of sight, out of mind.
Notice that my code just
became so darn simple.
Like, my function is called "meow."
It meows some number of times.
All I have to do is type a
number there, and it just works.
And I don't care any more about
those lower-level, so to speak,
implementation details.
So here, no surprise.
If I type in the number 3,
zoom out, and hit Play--
[MEOWING]
--it still works just fine.
So any questions on what
we've just done here?
It's still just meowing, but
that's besides the point.
It's this creation of our own
functions, this modularity,
this abstraction that's going to be
the idea that keeps coming back to us.
No?
All right.
So let's make this a
little more cat-like.
Let me throw away all of this code.
And let me go ahead--
oops-- let me throw away this code
first and then the rest of this code.
And let me go ahead and give
myself another green flag block.
And let me go ahead, and let's
create a cat that allows us to pet it
by moving my cursor over the cat.
And maybe it likes that, so
it'll meow when I do that.
So let me go under Control, and
let me grab this if conditional,
which we talked about as
a building block earlier.
Let me go to Sensing, and
we haven't used this before.
But here is a weird
sort of diagonal shape
that says touching mouse
pointer question mark.
So that's a Boolean expression.
So I'm going to drag that, and
it's definitely the wrong size.
But it is the right shape,
so it will grow to fill.
And the question I want to ask is if
the cat is touching the mouse pointer,
then go ahead and meow happily.
So let me grab the meow
sound, put it in there.
And so I think when I click the
green flag to start the program,
and now I let the mouse pointer
touch the cat, we should hear--
huh.
Doesn't seem to be working.
There's a bug or a mistake
in this program too.
What did I do wrong?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: You didn't specify
the sprite [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID J. MALAN: I don't need to
specify the sprite explicitly
because a detail I
didn't discuss earlier.
In the bottom right
of the screen, notice
that the cat is already selected.
So this code relates to that cat.
So your instinct is good if
we had two or more sprites,
but I just have one,
so I'm covered there.
Other thoughts.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: It only checks once.
DAVID J. MALAN: It only checks?
AUDIENCE: Once.
DAVID J. MALAN: Once.
So I click the green flag.
The computer did what I told it to do.
The mouse pointer was not
touching the cat at that moment
because it was touching the green flag.
So, of course, it didn't meow.
So what maybe is the fix here?
What puzzle piece can we add?
AUDIENCE: After the green
flag is [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
OK.
Interesting solution.
So let me go ahead, and under Control
let me grab a-- wait one second.
I'm going to change the 1 to 5, and
now I'm going to click the green flag.
So here we go.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
Damn it.
[MEOWING]
OK.
That was yours, not mine.
[LAUGHTER]
It didn't work.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Sorry?
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, maybe forever.
So your approach would work, but
it's very much a hack, if you will.
Like, I would have to time it perfectly
so that the mouse pointer is touching
it, or, conversely, I have
to drag it there and just
leave it there for five seconds.
And that's a little weird because
you don't just touch a cat
and then five seconds
later it meows at you.
Like, presumably, we want
it to be more interactive.
So I like this idea of a loop.
Right?
Why don't we just tell the cat
to forever listen for the cursor
as by using not repeat but forever?
Let me move this in here.
So now the cat's going to be told when
the green flag is clicked just forever,
if touching, if touching, if touching.
Oh, meow when actually touched.
So now if I zoom out and hit
Play, nothing's happening.
I don't have to wait
any number of seconds.
But when I do touch the cat--
[MEOWING]
[APPLAUSE]
[CHUCKLES] Fan section here.
Thank you.
[MEOWING]
So now it's actually working quite well.
So there we have sort of a logical bug.
But it does make sense if
you think about what it was
you told the computer to actually do.
Well, let's make things
even more interesting
by using one of these extensions.
In this bottom left corner, this is
how I got to text-to-speech earlier.
Let me go to Video
Sensing over here too.
And I can actually-- there we go--
literally, the video has come on.
Let me go ahead and do this.
Get rid of this code, and
let me step out of the frame.
When video motion is greater than--
well, this is CS50, so
let's just type in 50,
which is just a measure of motion.
Let me go and play sound meow.
OK.
And let me stop and restart.
All right.
So there's the cat.
[MEOWING]
OK.
It worked.
The cat's a little insensitive.
[MEOWING]
There we go.
Actually, you know what?
Maybe it's just-- let me
put-- let's change it.
20.
Oh, my God.
Oh, that's OK.
[MEOWING]
There we go.
All right.
So now it's a little more sensitive
to the petting by using the camera.
Now, this is kind of a weird example.
And if I just start moving
around crazily, like,
it's just going to meow incessantly,
which was what was happening--
[MEOWING]
Stop.
[LAUGHTER]
OK.
When in doubt, this is
when you reload the page.
[LAUGHTER]
All right.
So now we're back to
where we wanted to be.
But where can we now use these
kinds of building blocks?
Like, we were doing such
tiny little programs.
But even that we could turn
into a whole game, I bet.
Could we get like one
volunteer to come on up?
One volunteer?
Everyone's looking down.
OK.
On the end here.
Come on down.
Yeah.
All right.
Round of applause for our
one brave volunteer here.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
These Super Mario cookies
are on the line for you,
depending on how this goes.
So I'm going to have you come over here.
And in advance on Scratch's website,
we have some pre-made games,
one of them written by one of your
predecessors, a former student,
that they implemented this
sort of "Whac-A-Mole" game.
So what you're about to see
is the camera turn on on you.
And you're going to see four moles
above, below, left, and right.
And using only your head--
up, down, left, right--
the goal is to whack a mole
to get a point every time your
head touches one of these sprites.
So you're about to see things get
very interesting very quickly.
But using these building
blocks, just those simple
blocks but have four sprites, not
four cats but four moles in this case.
We can actually turn
these into actual games.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So here we go.
Click Beginner.
OK.
And we just need you to
center your head first.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[INDISTINCT CHATTER]
[CHUCKLES]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Nice.
Ten seconds.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Nice.
Two seconds.
AUDIENCE: [LAUGHS]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
A round of applause.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
You want to introduce yourself?
AUDIENCE: Hi, everybody.
My name is [? Vanilla. ?]
I'm a first year,
and I'm going to be majoring in
computer science and economics.
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice to meet you.
Here we go.
Thank you.
AUDIENCE: Nice to meet you.
[APPLAUSE, CHEERING]
DAVID J. MALAN: So we won't look
at the code for that actual game.
It was written by one
of your predecessors.
And you can see it
online if you're curious.
But you can think about now with
our functions, conditionals,
Boolean expressions, loops how you could
kind of compose that kind of program.
So odds are there was a loop that
was just constantly listening
for that kind of
connectivity, or it was one
of those extensions that
was waiting for motion to go
touch one of those sprites.
Notice that there's
these numbers up here.
And we haven't talked about this yet.
But just like in math, where you
can have variables x, y, and z,
in programming, you can create
variables using other puzzle pieces
in Scratch that just keep track
of how many seconds are left,
that keeps track of how many times
her head hit one of the moles.
And so you can implement the mechanics
of games using very simple building
blocks.
But how do you go about
building something
that's more interesting
and interactive like that?
Let me go ahead and
bring up, for instance,
one of the very first
things I wrote years ago
when I was in graduate school
and Scratch had just come out.
I was taking a class at MIT's Media Lab.
And they invited us to beta test-- that
is, try out the software before it then
became part of the world.
And the game I made was this one here.
Let me find the right
version of "Oscartime."
So "Oscartime" is a game that took
me tens of hours probably in the end.
It was a little bit addictive, but
let me go ahead and full-screen it.
And I won't play the whole game.
But it looked a little
something like this.
OSCAR: (SINGS) Oh, I love--
DAVID J. MALAN: Where trash
is falling from the sky.
And I can click on it and drag it.
And notice as I get close,
the lid opens up like this.
And if I let it keep falling, it
goes in, and Oscar gives me a point.
And I can do this again.
OSCAR: If you really want
to see something trashy--
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
Here comes something else.
OSCAR: I have here a sneaker that--
DAVID J. MALAN: So now
there's two pieces of trash.
OSCAR: It's all full of
holes, and the laces are--
DAVID J. MALAN: And it just keeps
going, and going, and going.
And if we can lower the volume for just
a moment, we'll let more trash fall.
But to your comment earlier
about one sprite or more
sprites, that's what we're seeing here.
Even though our examples thus far
are just one cat, one or two puzzle
pieces, or a few puzzle pieces.
Here is, I claim, a sprite.
Here is another sprite.
And by toggling among them in
that bottom right-hand corner,
I can just associate different puzzle
pieces with each of these sprites.
Now, I didn't start off by
implementing this whole game.
And in just a moment, if we can
raise the volume a little bit,
we'll see even more trash is falling.
So this is what--
I hate this song now, like 10 plus
hours listening to this song on loop
just to get the timing right.
But it brings to life all
of these different sprites.
And if you play it again and again,
it's always a little bit different
because I'm using some randomness.
So this newspaper doesn't
always fall from there.
Sometimes it's here.
And so here, again, we have
mechanics of a game where
things are being perturbed a
little, randomized a little bit
to keep things more interesting.
And let me go ahead.
OSCAR: (SINGS) I love trash.
DAVID J. MALAN: There we go.
How. about raise a little volume?
One more piece of trash.
So a clock.
It just goes on forever,
this kind of game.
But let's go ahead and consider.
Let me close that.
Let me go ahead and consider.
How I went about implementing
that from the get-go.
So I will stipulate--
let me open a few of these versions
here-- that the very first thing I did
was pretty much just
implement the stage.
Right?
I was kind of procrastinating,
so I poked around.
I found the Sesame Street lamppost,
and I dragged it into the world.
And done.
Version one is done.
It didn't do anything, but at least
I had the world sort of laid out.
That is to say I took a
baby step toward my goal.
Then I started thinking
about, all right,
how do I bring the trash to life, even
if it doesn't do much of anything else?
And so I created another sprite
by clicking the appropriate button
in that bottom right-hand corner.
And I thought about, well, what
do I want this trash to do?
I want it to just kind
of fall from the sky.
And so what I did here
was the following.
If I go to this trash piece
here or-- actually, sorry.
Out of order.
What I actually did first was I
didn't even have the trash fall.
If I play this game, the trash
just stays there in the air.
But I can do this.
I can drag it, and as before,
as I touch the other sprite,
I get the trash can lid to go up.
So how do I do that?
Well, let me click on Oscar
down there, my first sprite.
And here are the puzzle pieces
via which I implemented this idea.
I changed Oscar's
costume, his appearance,
to be just number one, which was one of
the images I imported into the program.
And then I forever did this.
If Oscar is touching
the mouse pointer, then
change Oscar's costume to number
two, otherwise change it back to one.
So it's super simple animation.
I'm just toggling between lid
up, lid down, lid up, lid down,
but it kind of feels interactive.
And if I wanted to
really make this pretty,
I could have 30 different costumes where
the lid is ever so slightly higher.
Then it would look even more
like a movie or fluid motion.
But this was enough to
get the job done, which
is to say I didn't try to implement
all of "Oscartime" together.
I just took a second
baby step toward my goal.
And then my next version
of "Oscartime" might
have looked a little something
like this, where now the trash--
there's more going on here.
Let's look at two of
these blocks of code.
The first thing I did was I
enabled drag mode to draggable,
and I had to Google to figure
this out because otherwise it
didn't let me drag the trash
while playing the game.
But once I figured that
out, I tell the trash
to go to a random
x-coordinate between 0 and 240
from left to right and
then the y location 180
because I always want the
trash falling from the sky.
And then what do I do?
I told the trash to forever change its
y-coordinate, its vertical coordinate,
by negative 1, negative
1, negative 1, one pixel
at a time, which creates the
illusion of it falling from the sky.
But I needed to do one other
thing, and let me scroll up.
Each of your sprites can have
multiple programs, multiple scripts,
so to speak, that are not
attached to one another.
They will happen in parallel for you.
The second one is saying this.
Forever if the trash is touching
Oscar, what should it do?
Go to a completely different x
and y location at the very top.
Why?
Well, as soon as I drag
the trash over the Oscar,
I want it to disappear as
though it's going into the can.
And I then want it to reappear
at the top so more trash falls.
So I just thought about
what would it mean
for the trash to go into the trash can.
Well, who cares?
What really matters to the
human user is that it just
disappears and teleports elsewhere.
And so that's the idea
I implemented here.
So if you can reduce intuitive ideas to
just basic building blocks like this,
you can start to make things
much more interactive.
And lastly, if I look
at this version here,
you'll see that we've combined these.
And so indeed, if I actually
go ahead and play this now,
not only is it falling.
I can let it fall right on top
of Oscar and watch it disappear.
But notice Oscar doesn't pop out yet
because that was the fourth version
and then the fifth version.
And then I added the annoying
music and so forth but sort of
composed this program
step by step by step
so as to accomplish my larger goal.
And this is going to be true
of all of the code you write,
be it in Scratch, or C, or Python, or
in the like, trying to come up with--
or rather, trying to reduce your ideas,
your grand vision to just baby steps,
building blocks so that
you start with version one,
and maybe you submit version 10 or 20.
But you don't try to implement
version 10 or 20 at the get-go.
You take those incremental steps.
All right.
How about one other?
Well, let me propose this.
Let me go ahead and open
three games that represent one
that your predecessors also implemented,
which looks a little something
like this in version zero.
Suppose I wanted to
implement a game that
simply has these kinds of mechanics.
I'm touching my arrow keys on my
keyboard-- up, down, left, and right.
And I'm moving the Harvard logo.
Let me zoom in a bit.
So if I hit the up arrow,
the Harvard shield goes up.
If I hit the down arrow,
the shield goes down.
If I go all the way to
the left, it goes left
until it hits the wall and
same thing on the right.
So this is like the beginnings
of a game or a beginning
of a maze, something like that.
Well, how might I implement this?
Well, let me look inside this one.
And there's a lot going on, but,
again, I sort of took simple steps.
Notice that I've got three sprites--
a left wall, which is
just a straight line,
the right wall, which
is a straight line.
And just intuitively, why did
I implement those as sprites?
Why do they need to exist
as entities themselves?
Yeah, in front.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
I want it to interact with the shield.
So I need to be able to ask
that Boolean expression, like,
not touching mouse pointer but
touching shield, for instance,
a different type of yes/no question.
And so what is the code for
the shield actually doing?
Well, there's a lot of duplication, and
let me focus on the abstraction first.
Notice that I've got this
one green flag clicked.
I want the shield to go
dead center, 0 comma 0,
and then forever listen for the human's
keyboard, and feel for the wall.
So I decided to implement my
own pink puzzle pieces that
implement the two separate ideas.
One, just listen for the
keyboard-- up, down, left,
right-- and then do something.
And then feel for walls is
this idea of whenever I go up,
down, left, or right,
if I touch a wall, I
need to stop doing whatever the
keystrokes are telling me to do.
So now if we dive into those
implementation details, listen and feel
are abstractions, custom puzzle pieces.
Let's look at the
implementation details.
Well, here's the keyboard.
If the key arrow up is
pressed, change y by 1.
If key down arrow is pressed,
change y by negative 1.
And you can probably
see where this is going.
Right arrow is x by 1.
Left arrow is x by
negative 1, and that's
sort of all that's involved
with up, down, left, right.
But wait a minute.
Why is there no loop in this
listen for keyboard puzzle piece?
I needed a loop last time
so it constantly works.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
I put the loop in my
main part of my program
up top so something is telling me
to keep listening again and again.
So it's got to be somewhere,
but it doesn't have
to be in the actual implementation.
And lastly, how about
this feel for walls?
Well, if touching left wall, which is
just another sprite, change x by 1.
So that is to say if I'm
touching the left wall,
I want to bounce it
back the other direction
and same thing on the right wall.
If I'm touching the right
wall, I want to bounce it
back to the left, which effectively
means that even if the human's hitting
the key, it's like
fighting with this code,
but it's never going to go through
the wall based on that math.
It's going to stop it right there.
All right.
Let's add something else to the mix.
Suppose I want the game to change
to be a little something like this,
where Yale is some kind of block
in between me and the exit.
So some dramatic race here.
OK.
I just got by, but the
Yale logo doesn't seem
to be doing all that
much except bouncing.
So I'm guessing there's a loop, maybe
a conditional checking for those walls
too.
So let's go ahead and
zoom out, see inside.
Let's not worry about Harvard
because it's pretty much the same.
Let's look at the Yale puzzle pieces.
And sure enough, go to the middle.
0 comma zero.
Point in direction 90, so
point horizontally on the grid.
And then if touching left
wall or touching right wall--
I'm kind of cheating this time, but
cleverly, just spin around and do 180
so you effectively bounce off the wall.
This just tightened up my code.
I don't need to do the
negative 1 or the plus 1.
I just say bounce in this
form of code, otherwise just
constantly move one step.
Now, if this is a game where Yale
is supposed to be better and faster,
well, let's change the 1 to 5.
Move 5 pixels at a time.
Let's move it 10 back and forth.
Let's maybe 100.
Uh-oh.
So what just happened?
That is a bug, which we can
avoid by just not doing that.
But why did it break out of the wall?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
At first it was [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
Because I'm doing 100
steps at a time, I'm
never actually touching the
other sprite because I'm
sort of stepping way over it.
So there's never a moment where
they're actually touching.
So previously, I was just getting
lucky by doing fewer steps because it's
gradually going over
the wall, which gives me
just enough time to detect as much.
So I would have to kind
of tinker, and he'll
handle this a little bit differently.
So it's a bug if it's too fast.
But at least if I keep
it slow and reasonable
the math actually does work out, so
long as it starts again in the middle.
Well, let's do one final flourish here,
whereby let's bring MIT into the mix.
Right?
They're super smart, so
maybe they can kind of
track us and follow wherever I'm going.
So how might this work?
All right.
So nothing happens yet because we
haven't finished composing the game.
And notice here--
OK.
Now MIT is struggling.
It's kind of twitching there because
it's going just above, and below,
and then above, and below.
So we could fix that too if we want.
But that's just a function of
my math, one pixel at a time.
Let me open up this one, see
inside, and click on MIT.
And it doesn't take much
to implement MIT, it seems.
So go to random position, forever
point towards the Harvard logo outline,
AKA the shield, and then move one step.
So if I wanted to make MIT even smarter,
even faster, what do I change here?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
Change one step to two steps to double
their speed or five steps, 10 steps,
or 100 steps.
And the game is going
to be over like that.
But that's all it takes to now
make these kinds of elements.
So if you are a game player
on your phone, or consoles,
or computer, or whatever, if
you think about almost any game,
you can probably now start to
think about how they implemented
those mechanics because it's just being
reduced to functions, conditionals,
loops, variables, and
the like in this case.
So let's go ahead here and
have maybe one final volunteer.
We've got one more bag of Oreos here.
OK.
That was super fast.
Do you want to come on up?
All right.
Brave volunteer.
Come on up.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
Let me find the full-fledged version
of this that one of your predecessors
made.
And let me get the right one.
OK.
Here we go.
We'll see some instructions on
the screen in just a moment.
And when we hit Play, you'll see that
the mechanics are all combined now
into one full-fledged game.
But first, an introduction.
It's on.
SAM: Hi, everyone.
I'm Sam.
I live in [INAUDIBLE].
I'm a freshman, and I'm from Nepal.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
Welcome to the stage.
[APPLAUSE]
SAM: Thank you.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
So here we go.
Yep.
Go ahead and click the green flag.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[MC HAMMER, "U CAN'T TOUCH THIS"]
You can't touch this.
DAVID J. MALAN: You see the
grid is just bigger this time.
(SINGING) You can't touch this.
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
Now there's that Yale element.
(SINGING) You can't touch this.
My, my, my my music hits me so hard.
Makes me say, oh, my Lord.
Thank you for blessing me with a
mind to rhyme and two hyped feet.
It feels good when you know you're down,
a super dope homeboy from the Oaktown.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
Third Yale.
All started at slightly
different positions.
(SINGING) I told you, homeboy.
You can't touch this.
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
All right.
There's MIT.
(SINGING) And ya know
you can't touch this.
[CHEERING, APPLAUSE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh.
(SINGING) You can't touch this.
Yo.
Let me bust the funky lyrics.
DAVID J. MALAN: Gotta go fast.
Oh.
No.
[CHUCKLES]
(SINGING) Cold on a
mission, so fall on back.
Let them know that you're too much,
and this is a beat they can't touch.
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
[EXCLAIMING]
(SINGING) You can't touch this.
DAVID J. MALAN: No more
walls but two MITs.
(SINGING) Yo, sound the bell.
School's in, sucker.
DAVID J. MALAN: Princeton now.
(SINGING) Give me a song or rhythm.
Making them sweat, that's
what I'm giving them.
Now, they know you talk about
the Hammer when you're talkin'
'bout a show that's hyped and tight.
Singers are sweatin', so pass
them a wipe or a tape to learn.
DAVID J. MALAN: Second to last level.
(SINGING) The chart's legit.
Either work hard, or
you might as well quit.
That's word because you
know you can't touch this.
You can't touch this.
Break it down.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
Clear.
There we go.
Nice.
Oh, oh.
Oh.
Few more lives.
(SINGING) Stop.
Hammer time.
DAVID J. MALAN: Here we go.
There we go.
[EXCLAIMING]
All right.
Couple more tries.
Yes!
Oh, no.
(SINGING) This is it for a winner.
Dance to this, and
you're gonna get thinner.
Now move, slide your rump.
DAVID J. MALAN: Starts
getting stressful.
(SINGING) Just for a minute,
let's all do the bump.
Bump, bump, bump.
Yeah.
You can't touch this.
Look, man.
You'll probably get hyped, boy.
DAVID J. MALAN: One more try.
(SINGING) You can't touch this.
Ring the bell.
School's back in.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
A round of applause, nonetheless.
[APPLAUSE]
Nicely done.
Thank you.
So as you might have
noticed if your eyes started
to wander to the light
bulbs here, there's
actually 64 of these light bulbs.
And I'm wondering if you divide 64
by 8, that's 8 bytes of light bulbs.
And we now have some
Unicode in our vocabulary.
So might very well be
the case that we've
been spelling something out on the
stage here for you all of this time.
But before we adjourn for cake
to be served in the Transept,
allow me to introduce some
of CS50's human friends,
the Harvard Krokodiloes
and the Radcliffe Pitches,
to give us this exciting
ending, "This is CS50."
[APPLAUSE, CHEERING]
[HARMONICA NOTE]
[VOCALIZING]
SPEAKER: (SINGING) There's a
certain someone who I'm indebted to.
And since the old [? BNC ?] has
50, I have this friend for you.
A two, three, four.
[VOCALIZING]
Oh, rubber ducky, you're the one.
You make [INAUDIBLE] so much fun.
Rubber ducky, I'm awfully fond of you.
[SCATTING] Rubber ducky, you make me
smile, and you help my code compile.
Rubber ducky, you're
my very best friend.
It's true.
When I'm at a standstill, your
debugging abilities stun me.
When I'm at the end of my rope, you
just snap, and my code's up and running.
Rubber ducky, you're so fine,
and I'm lucky that you're mine.
Rubber ducky, you're
my very best friend.
It's true.
You're my best friend.
Rubber ducky, I'm awfully fond of you.
[CHEERING, APPLAUSE]
SPEAKER: Good afternoon, CS50.
We are the Harvard Krokodiloes,
Harvard's oldest a cappella group,
founded way back in 1946 at the
historic Hasty Pudding Club.
We'd love to make a big
thank you to CS50 staff
and to David Malan for having us
perform here at Sanders Theater.
And you enjoyed this performance,
please come audition for us
this weekend at Farkas Hall.
[CHEERING, APPLAUSE]
SPEAKER: Hello, everyone.
We are some of the Radcliffe
Pitches, and we are also
hosting auditions this weekend.
You can find more information at
our Instagram, @radcliffepitches.
Now, let me tell you a little
bit about just about a year ago
today, when I was sitting in your very
seats on my first day of CS50 lecture.
And this is just about
how I was feeling.
[HARMONICA NOTE]
[VOCALIZING]
(SINGING) It's the first day of
class, and I'm brand new to code.
Is this for me?
So many people around.
Can I get through the workload?
But it's my dream.
I tend to stick to English, not science.
But my [INAUDIBLE] friends
told me to try this.
Hey, dancing robot dog, you kind of
look like you have your life together,
I guess.
I really need some advice.
(ALL SINGING) We know
you're feeling unsure,
but this is really the right call.
In CS50, you'll meet new
friends, get free food.
You'll be all set for this fall in CS50.
You have a thousand
TAs who will help you.
You'll get cupcakes,
duckies, Chinese food.
And you can always take
this class and set aside.
SPEAKER: This is CS50.
Fist bump.
[LAUGHTER]
[APPLAUSE, CHEERING]
DAVID J. MALAN: Thank you to the Kroks.
Thank you to the Pitches.
Cake is now served.
Come on up to say hi if
you'd like or meet Spot.
See you next time.
[APPLAUSE, CHEERING]
[MUSIC PLAYING]