[INTRIGUING MUSIC]
DAVID MALAN: All right, so this is CS50.
And this is week 1,
zero index, so to speak.
And it's not every day that you can
say that you've learned a new language,
but today is that day.
Today, we explore a more traditional
and older language called C.
And rest assured that even if what
you're about to see-- no pun intended--
looks very cryptic, very
unusual, particularly if you're
among those less comfortable,
cling to the ideas from last week,
week zero, wherein we talked about
some of those fundamentals of functions
and loops and conditionals, all
of which are coming back today.
Indeed, whereas last week,
and with problem set 0,
we focused on learning how
to program with Scratch,
which, again, you might have played
with as a younger student days back.
Today, we focus on C instead.
But along the way, we're going
to focus, as always, frankly,
on learning how to solve problems.
But among the goals for today and
really on an entire class like this
is just to give you week after week
all the more tools for your toolkit,
so to speak, via which
to do exactly that.
So for instance today, we'll learn
how to solve problems all the more
so with functions, as per last week.
We'll do the same with variables.
We'll do the same with conditionals,
with loops, and with more.
But we'll also learn at
the end of today's class
really how not to solve problems.
It turns out as powerful as Macs,
PCs, cell phones are nowadays,
there's actually certain things
that they can't do very well
and information they
can't represent very well.
And that actually leads to a lot
of real-world problems, both past
and surely future.
So more on what we're not going to
be able to do with programming before
long.
But beyond that, let's come
back to this picture here.
So this was the very first
program that I wrote,
that you wrote presumably in some form.
And all it does is say "Hello, world."
But as promised, today, this puzzle
piece, or these puzzle pieces together,
are going to very quickly
start to look more like this.
And I've deliberately color coded it
in a way so that the text on the screen
now kind of resembles the puzzle piece.
So if I go back, notice that we had
this, when green flag clicked puzzle
piece, mostly in yellow with the
green flag, that sort of kicks off
the whole process once
you actually click
the button at top right of
Scratch's user interface.
And then there's the purple block
which actually is the verb, the action,
the function that does something.
So if I bring us back over to
what we're about to see today,
there's going to be some boilerplate,
so to speak, some orange text here
on the screen that for now you
just type and take for granted,
like you need to write
your code like that.
But more interesting is
going to be the purple.
And we're going to see today
that the function previously
called "say" in Scratch is now called
"printf" in this language called C.
But in white here, you'll see
similar text to our white oval
last week, whereby that's where
user input, like your input
as the programmer, can actually go.
So there's a lot of distraction.
And honestly, it's these
kinds of things that
tend to distract and get
frustrating early on when
learning to code for the first time.
But the ideas, most importantly,
are going to be the same.
So how are we going to
go about using this.
Well, it turns out,
like last week, you're
going to start writing
something called source code.
So code as we know it, quote,
unquote, is more technically called
"source code."
That's what you and I as
humans actually write.
And indeed it might look a little
something like we just saw.
But unfortunately, computers
only speak this, binary--
zeros and ones-- more properly known
as machine code, in other words,
those same patterns of zeros and
ones last week, someone guessed,
print out "hello, world" on the
screen because one of those patterns
is an H. Another pattern is an E,
an L, and L, and an O, and so forth.
And then other patterns of those zeros
and ones are commands or instructions
to the computer that literally say, show
H-E-L-L-O comma "world" on the screen.
But machine code would
not be nearly as much fun
to write if it were
indeed in zeros and ones.
Entirely for us, ideally,
you and I are going
to write source code, which conceptually
is sort of up here, high level.
But we're going to need a program to
convert it to the lower-level machine
code so that we don't spend our lives
actually having to read and write
zeros and ones, which back in
the day, kind of in yesteryear,
you kind of did with
things called punch cards
and holes on physical sheets of paper.
We're beyond that because after
years and years of innovation,
folks have given us
higher-level languages instead.
So here's what we're
going to need to do today.
If at the end of the day you
and I are writing source code
but we want machine code as
output, we need something
in the middle that's going to convert
that source code to machine code.
You and I are not going
to have to learn or talk
about really any more zeros and ones.
And the type of program we're going to
start using today and introduce you to
is called a compiler.
So a compiler is a program that
translates one language to another.
And it can be any two languages.
But today, and often, we'll talk
about it in the context of source code
to machine code.
So this is Apple or Google or
Microsoft or folks from other companies
or even volunteers who have written
software that do this conversion.
You and I are essentially going
to download a free compiler
and use it to actually get our
computer to understand the source
code that you and I write in
these higher-level languages.
So where are we going to do that?
Well, we could actually
give you instructions
and you could download the
appropriate free open-source software
onto your own Mac or PC.
The reality is that creates so many
technical support headaches because we
all have slightly different computers.
We all have slightly different
versions of Windows or macOS or Linux
or other operating systems.
And that, too, tends to be a distraction
at the beginning of any course
like this or learning programming.
So we're going to use the cloud instead.
We're going to use a URL of
the form https://cs50.dev.
And what this will do for you is
put inside of your browser window
absolutely everything you need for the
course, but it's going to use software,
software called Visual Studio
code, otherwise known as VS Code,
that's actually free itself.
It's very popular in industry.
It's what "real"
programmers use every day.
But it's a cloud-based version thereof.
And so everything will just
work for you out of the box.
But toward the end of
CS50, the goal is going
to be to get you off of
CS50's infrastructure,
to get you to download this freely
available software onto your own Mac
or PC if you so choose so that
those training wheels, so to speak,
can come off.
And then even if you never
take another class again,
you don't need any class's
infrastructure moving forward.
You'll have everything you want
and need on your own Mac or PC.
But for now, it'll
save us a bit of time.
So in just a bit, I'm going to go
to that URL myself on my computer.
And I and you will see
a user interface that
looks a little something like this.
The colors might be different
based on your settings.
Fonts might be different, and so forth.
But in general, it consists
of a few different regions.
So over here at the top is where we
are going to start writing code today.
So it's a tabbed interface like
any number of programs nowadays.
And this is that same C
code we saw a moment ago.
So this is where, in a moment,
I'm going to start to type it.
Over here at the bottom is
what we're going to call
a terminal window, or a console.
And the terminal window is where
we're going to type commands
for compiling our code,
for running our code.
And we'll see today a contrast
between a graphical-user interface,
or GUI, which has menus
and icons and things
you click and are very familiar with,
versus a command-line interface,
or CLI.
And so we're using
both of these together.
And command-line interface just means,
down here, you only use your keyboard.
You can click, click, click
if you want with your mouse.
It's not going to generally do much
because a command-line interface takes
commands at the keyboard.
So in a weird sense, it's
going to feel like taking
a step backwards from the Macs, the PCs,
the iPhones, and Android phones we all
have, which are very graphical.
But it turns out, once you become a
"computer" person or a programmer,
you can be a lot more productive,
a lot more efficient, I dare say,
by learning to harness
the command-line interface
and using both types of interfaces
for what each is good at.
So more on that in just a bit.
Over here at left, you're going to see
soon a folder interface like Mac OS
or Windows where any of the files
or folders we create in CS50
are going to end up, as well.
So it gives you the best of both worlds.
You can point and click on the left,
or you can type commands at the bottom,
as we'll soon see.
And then along here is the
so-called activity bar,
where there's just VS Code-specific
features but also CS50-specific
features.
And if you're in your
own version of CS50.dev,
you click through in
the dot dot dot menu
or zoom out so you can see everything.
You'll see CS50's own rubber
duck, virtually speaking,
that will be there throughout
the course to answer
any and all of your questions, as well.
So more on that soon, too.
So here's the code that I
propose that we write first,
just like we wrote our very first
Scratch program to say "hello, world."
So let's go ahead and do exactly this.
I'm going to switch over
to this screen here,
where I've already logged
into CS50.dev on my computer.
And just to keep the focus on the
code, I've hidden the activity bar.
I've hidden the File
Explorer, so to speak.
So you're seeing here the area
where all of my tabs are about to go
and the terminal window, where all
of my commands are going to go.
But I've just simplified
the UI to keep our focus
on the interesting parts for now.
So how do I go about actually writing
and compiling and running some code?
Well, the teaser is going
to be these three steps.
One of these is a command
called, aptly, Code.
And Code is just going to let
me to open or create a new file,
like a file called "hello.c."
Make is going to be, for
now, my compiler that
allows me to make the program, that
is convert source code into machine
code, so from C to zeros and ones.
And then weirdly, but
we'll soon see why,
./hello is going to be the
command to run my actual code,
so the textual equivalent of like
double-clicking on a Mac or a PC icon
or tapping an icon on your phone.
So that's it.
These three commands are going to allow
me to write, to compile, and to run
code ultimately.
So let's go ahead and do that.
I'm back in my VS Code interface.
I'm going to go ahead
and run "code hello.c."
And notice a couple of details here.
So one, there's this weird dollar sign,
which has nothing to do with currency,
but it's just a common convention
in the programming world
to represent your prompt.
So if a TF, if I ever
say, go to your prompt,
we really mean, go to
your terminal window.
Go to the dollar sign.
And the dollar sign is
where you type the command.
Sometimes it's a different symbol,
but a dollar sign is conventional.
Now that I've typed
"code" space "hello.c,"
I'm going to go ahead and hit Enter.
And maybe not
surprisingly, this gives me
a brand new tab, a new file
if you will, called "hello.c."
And just like Word documents have their
own file extension, like DOC, DOCX,
and Excel files have .XLSX and PDFs have
.PDF and GIFs have .GIF and so forth,
so do C files have a file
extension by convention that is .C.
Now, a couple of minor points.
Notice that, by convention,
I'm almost always
going to name my files in lowercase.
By convention, I'm never going
to use spaces in my file names.
And my file extension, too,
is going to be lowercase.
Long story short, accidentally
hitting the spacebar
or using file names
with spaces just tends
to make life harder when you're
in a command-line environment.
So just beware silly,
stupid things like that.
So all lowercase, no spaces for now.
So my cursor is literally
blinking because the program
wants me to write some code.
I'm going to do this from memory.
It'll take you presumably some
time to acquire the same instincts.
But I'm going to go ahead and
type this first line here,
pronounced "include standard io.h"--
more on that soon--
int main(void), with some
parentheses thrown in.
Notice what's about to happen
here is a little interesting.
In the code I want to
type, I want what we'll
call curly braces, the
sort of squiggles that you
don't use often in English,
at least, but are there
on your keyboard somewhere.
But notice what VS Code does, and
a lot of programming environments,
is it finishes part of my thought.
So I'm only going to
type a left curly brace,
but notice I actually get two of them.
And if I hit Enter, notice that not
only does it scooch one down a bit,
it also indents my cursor because,
just like with pseudocode last week,
whenever you're doing something
logically that should only
happen if the thing above
it happens, similarly
is indentation going to be a
thing when we actually write code.
So VS Code and programs
like it just try to save us
keystrokes so I don't have to
waste time hitting the spacebar
or hitting Tab or wasting
my human time like that.
All right, so with that
said, I'm going to go ahead
and type the last of
these lines, "printf,"
where the F is going to mean
"formatted," and then a parentheses.
And notice it gave me two.
It gave me the second one for free.
Sometimes it will get confused.
And you can certainly override
this, delete it, and start over.
And now, unlike Scratch,
in C, It turns out
I'm going to need to use
double quotes anytime
I'm using an English word or phrase
or any human language for that matter.
"Hello" comma "world."
And then at the very end of my line,
much like English uses periods,
I'm going to use a semicolon in C.
So that's a lot of talking,
but it's not much coding.
It's technically six lines of code.
But honestly, the only interesting
one intellectually, as we'll soon see,
is really line 5.
Like, that is the equivalent
of that, say, block.
Now here's where I'll
cross my fingers, hoping
that I didn't make any
typographical errors.
It's going to automatically save for me.
And I'm going to go back to my
terminal window where now I'm
going to do that second
command, "make" space "hello."
Common mistake-- you do not
say "make hello.c," because you
already made that file.
You say "make hello," which is the name
of the program that in this case I do
want to create.
And Make is smart.
It's going to look in my folder.
And if it sees a file
called "hello.c," it's
going to convert that
source code to machine code
and save the results in a simpler
shorter-named file just called
"hello," like an icon on your desktop.
Now, hopefully nothing will happen.
And that is a good thing,
quite paradoxically.
If you do anything wrong when
programming, odds are you're
going to see one or many more
lines of error sort of yelling
at you that you made a mistake.
Seeing nothing happen
is actually a good sign.
So the last command, to run my
code, recall our three steps here.
We've written code to create the file,
Make to compile the file from source
code to machine code.
So lastly is "./hello."
So this now is the equivalent of
my double-clicking on a Mac or PC
or single tapping on a phone.
Enter.
[SIGHS] So close!
All right, it's pretty good.
I got the H-E-L-L-O comma space "world."
But there's something a
little stupid about my output.
What might rub some of you
aesthetically the wrong way?
Yeah?
STUDENT: The dollar sign.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so the dollar
sign looks like I was like, "hello,
world" dollar sign in my output.
But no, that's just kind of a remnant of
my prompt starting with a dollar sign.
And this is a little nitpicky,
but this just doesn't feel right,
doesn't look right.
It's not quite correct.
So how can I go about fixing this?
Well, here's where, at
least initially, it's
going to take some introduction to
just new syntax in C to fix this.
The simplest instinct
might be to do this.
Well, let me just hit Enter like that.
But this should soon,
if not already, rub you
the wrong way because
in general, we're going
to see that programming
in C and in Python
and other languages
tends to be line-based.
Like, you should really start and
finish your thought on one line.
So if you're in the habit
of hitting Enter like this
and finishing your
thought on the next line,
generally programming
languages don't like that.
So this is, in fact, not
going to do what we expect.
And just to show you as
much, I'm going to do this.
Let me go back to my
terminal window here.
I'm going to rerun "make hello"
after making that change.
Enter.
And there we have it, like the
first of our erroneous outputs.
And it's yelling at me.
It's missing a terminating character.
And there's some red in here, some
green, drawing my attention to it.
Sometimes these error messages
will be straightforward.
Sometimes you're going to rack your
brain a bit to figure them out.
But for now I've kind of spoiled it.
Obviously Enter is not
the right solution.
So let me clear my terminal
window just to hide that error.
Let me delete this.
And let me propose now that
I add this incantation here.
So backslash n, it turns
out, is going to be
the sort of magical way of
ensuring that you actually get
a new line at the end of your output.
So let me go ahead now and rerun "make
hello," because I've changed my code.
I need to now reconvert, recompile
the source code to new machine.
"./hello."
And now, there is the canonical
"hello, world" program
that I hoped to write
in the first place.
So for now, don't worry
about the include.
Don't worry about the standard io.
Don't worry about int or main
or void or the curly braces.
Focus primarily on line 5 here.
And over the course of
today and next week,
we'll start to tease
apart the other characters
that, for now, you should
take at face value.
Questions, though, on any of
the steps we've just done?
Yeah?
STUDENT: Why is the backslash
n inside the apostrophes?
DAVID MALAN: Sure, why is the backslash
n inside of the quotation marks,
if you will?
So short answer is that's
just where it needs
to be because inside of the quotes
is the input that you want printf
to output to the screen.
So if you want printf, this
function, to output a new line,
it must be included in the
quoted text that you give it.
STUDENT: So the backslash n [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Backslash n is a special pattern
that "printf no" means, OK, I should
move the cursor to the next line.
Good question.
Other questions on any of these steps?
Yeah?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: A good question.
So what if you actually
want to print backslash n?
Things get a little tricky there.
Let me go ahead and
propose that we do this.
So it turns out-- and this is
often the case in programming--
when you want a literal
character to appear,
you actually put another
backslash in front of it.
But this is not going to
be something we do often.
But there is in fact a solution to that.
But let me propose that
beyond that now we compare it
against what we've actually done.
So here is the first Scratch program
we wrote with the green flag there.
Here, recall, is the mental
model that I proposed
we have for almost everything
we do whereby functions are just
an implementation, say, in code of
algorithms, step-by-step instructions
for solving problems.
The inputs to functions,
recall from last week,
are called arguments, or in
some contexts parameters.
And sometimes functions
can have side effects.
Like last time with Scratch,
there was the speech bubble
that magically appeared
next to the cat's mouth
as a sort of side effect
of using the Say block.
So just like this then, we
had the white oval as input.
The Say block was the
function last week.
And then we had this here, side effect.
Well, how do we compare
these things left to right?
Well, here's the Say block at left.
Let's compare now to
the C code at right.
Notice a couple of things to
adapt from Scratch to C. Print
is almost the name of the function.
It is technically "printf," for
reasons we'll eventually see.
Notice the parentheses in C are kind
of evocative of the oval in Scratch.
And that's probably why MIT chose
an oval, because a lot of languages
use parentheses in this way.
You still write "hello, world" just
as we did last week in Scratch.
But per our demo thus far, you
do need the double quotes--
and double quotes, not single quotes--
double quotes on the left and right.
And in order to get that new
line, you need the backslash n.
And one more thing is missing.
Yeah?
STUDENT: Semicolon.
DAVID MALAN: The semicolon
to finish your thought.
So all of these sort
of stupid things now
that honestly you will forget initially
if you've never programmed before,
but you'll soon-- within
days, within weeks--
develop the muscle memory where
all of that stuff just jumps off,
jumps off the page right at you.
All right, so this backslash
n is generally known,
just so you know, as an escape sequence.
And so backslash n allows us
to specify a character that
might otherwise be hard to type.
But let's tease apart some of the other
things atop that function already.
So include stdio.h.
It turns out that in C, a
lot of the functionality that
comes with the language is
tucked away in separate files.
So if you want to use certain functions,
you have to tell the compiler,
hey, I want to do some
standard input and output.
Like, I want to print
some things on the screen.
And that's because, for
now, you can think of printf
as living in this file, stdio.h.
That's a bit of a white lie for now.
But in stdio.h is essentially
a declaration for printf
that will teach the compiler how
to print things to the screen.
So "hash include" here
simply tells the compiler
before it does anything else
essentially go ahead and find
on the local hard drive
a file called stdio.h
and copy/paste it there so
I know now about printf.
So this thing, this .h file, is what
we'll technically call a header file.
And if you've ever heard
this word, especially
if you have programmed before,
it represents essentially what
we'll start calling a library.
So a library in the world
of programming is just code
that someone else
wrote that you can use.
It's usually free and
open source, which means
you can literally see the
code that someone else wrote,
or sometimes you pay for it.
Sometimes it's closed source,
which maybe Microsoft wrote it.
They won't show you the code, but they
will let you use the zeros and ones.
So libraries are super
useful because honestly
even I don't really
know how printf works.
I've taken for granted for 25
years that if I use printf,
stuff prints on the screen.
But someone smarter than
me had to actually write
the code in C that figures out how to
get the H, the E, the L-L-O, and so
forth onto the Mac screen, the PC
screen, the phone screen, or somewhere
else.
So libraries allow us to stand
on each other's shoulders
and so that someone else
can do the hard work,
and we can now solve problems
that are more interesting to us,
not the basic commodity stuff that
everyone might want in their code.
So again, library is code
that someone else wrote.
A header file in C is
just a file ending in ".h"
that gives you access to the same.
And so for instance, if you
to learn more about these,
there are, what are called in the
world of programming, manual pages.
And these are textual files,
like a documentation of sorts,
via which you can just
learn how a function works
or how you can use its
inputs or arguments.
The reality is they're written
for folks who aren't in CS50.
They're written for folks who
aren't just learning how to program.
They're written for and by folks
who have been programming for years.
And so frankly, they're a
little hard to understand.
And so CS50 has its own version
thereof at this URL, manual.cs50.io,
where you'll see not only the official
documentation for C, the language,
but also staff-written
simplifications in layperson's terms
what all of the various popular
functions are, what their inputs,
and what their outputs are.
So for instance, under stdio.h, you
can actually go to that website.
You can go to a URL like this,
where stdio.h is in there.
And you can actually see
the documentation therefore.
So let me go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead
in my browser here,
I'm going to go to manual.cs50.io.
And let me go ahead here
and select those functions
that are frequently used in CS50.
And under stdio.h, you'll
see a bunch of functions,
only one of which we've even
discussed called printf.
I'm going to click on printf there.
And you'll see an interface
that at first glance
might be a little
overwhelming, but it's going
to start to look more and more familiar.
So first of all, you'll see that if
you want to use printf under Synopsis,
you need to include this header file.
Like, you literally copy and paste
that line into your own code.
You'll also see this, which
for now is a bit arcane,
but this is kind of a hint as to what
the function is going to look like.
But more on that soon.
But more importantly, you can
read a description about it.
And because these descriptions, when
you're in less comfortable mode,
are written by me and the course's
teaching fellows, teaching assistants,
and course assistants, you'll find them
to be much more in layperson's terms.
And so long story
short, rely on this site
once you want to learn
how to use some function
and also what other functions exist.
In fact, if I go back
to the main page here,
you'll see that there are all of
these functions like are frequently
used in CS50.
And there's hundreds
more that come with C.
But learning a programming language
is not about learning all of those
but rather just getting a sense of
where you find answers to questions when
you do want to try something new.
But what is important
to know for CS50 today
is that we have our own header file
called cs50.h which has functions
that we have written
just to make life easier
in the first few weeks of the class.
These are training wheels that
we'll eventually take off.
But it turns out in C,
especially if you've
programmed before, it's actually
really hard and annoying just
to get input from users, to get them
to type a word or a number or something
else.
Like, C does not make this easy, in
part because it's one of the earliest
languages that wasn't zeros and ones.
So you have to do a lot of
the heavy lifting yourself.
But we'll put on these training
wheels today and for a few weeks
so that we can focus really on the
intellectually interesting ideas of C
and programming without getting
bogged down in certain weeds
that we will come back to before long.
So for instance, CS50's own
documentation is there at that URL.
But within the library
are these functions,
a function called get_string
to get a string of text.
"String" is a synonym for just
text in a programming language.
So get_string will prompt the
human for a string of text.
Get_int is shorthand for
"get integer," if you
want to get a number from the user.
Get_float is a little more arcane--
get a floating point number,
like a real number with
a decimal point in it.
And dot, dot, dot, there
are others, as well.
So this is to say within CS50, we've got
some user-friendly functions via which
we can actually get some input.
And let's go ahead and use one
of these, for instance get_string
because recall that last week
our second program in Scratch
was this one here, where we
didn't just say "hello, world."
We said "hello, David,"
or "hello, Carter,"
"hello, Julia," whoever it
was typing their name in.
But to do that, we needed
this Ask block in Scratch.
And then we used the Say block.
And then we used the Join
block to make all of this work.
So let's translate
this program now into C
because it's a little more interesting
and representative of the kind of code
we'll start to write.
But we need a slightly
different mental model.
Still have a function here, which is the
implementation in code of an algorithm.
We still have some
inputs called arguments.
But previously, I said that
the Say block and, in turn,
printf have side effects, which is
just something visually, typically,
that happens on the screen.
Other functions actually have, what
we called last week, return values.
And this is kind of analogous to a
function maybe doing something for you,
writing down the answer on a slip
of paper, and then handing you,
the programmer, the slip
of paper to do whatever
you want with it without
just broadcasting it
to the world with, like, a
speech bubble on the screen.
So a return value is germane
for a program like this
because recall when we used the
Ask block and I typed in my name,
where did my name end up initially?
It didn't go on the screen yet.
Where did it end up?
STUDENT: In an answer.
DAVID MALAN: In an
"answer" puzzle piece.
And that special oval puzzle
piece I claimed at the time
represents a return value, so
the metaphorical piece of paper
that the answer is written down on
so that I can then use it later.
So that's what we want
to get to now in C,
a return value that I can
then do anything I want,
whether it's print it to the
screen, change it in some way,
save it in a database, or anything else.
So here, for instance, is
what we did with Scratch,
the input to the Say block-- or the Ask
block was "what's your name," quote,
unquote.
The function, of course,
is the Ask function.
And the return value was "answer."
If we now consider how we
might translate this to C,
it's going to look a
little weird at first.
But it's going to follow a
pattern today, next week, the week
after any time we do code like this.
So get_string, I claim, is going to
be the most analogous function in C
to the Ask block.
And to be clear, this is a CS50-specific
thing, training wheels of sorts.
But we'll show you in a few weeks what
this function is doing and how you
cannot use it moving forward once you're
comfortable with the language itself.
Notice I've put
parentheses, left and right,
as sort of a placeholder for user input.
And that user input is going
to be "what's your name?"
But I can't just put "what's
your name" in parentheses.
What do I minimally need
to add in there, too?
STUDENT: Quotes.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so the
double quotes, left and right.
So let me go ahead and add those in.
I left a space here, not for a new line.
I could move the cursor
to the next line.
But I minimally at least want to move
the cursor at least one space over
just so it looks pretty, so that
when I'm prompted for my name,
there's a space between
the question and my answer.
But it could also be backslash n.
That's just an aesthetic
choice on my part.
But what do I do with the answer
that comes back from get_string?
This is where the text is
going to look different today.
In C, you start to use an equals
sign from left to right respectively.
And on the left, you put the
name of the variable in which you
want to store that return value.
So a return value is kind
of a conceptual thing.
You can do with it what you want.
And if I want to store it
longer term in a variable,
like x or y or z in math class, I
can just give it a name here-- x
or y or z or, more reasonably,
"answer," or any other English word.
No spaces, generally lowercase, same
heuristics as before, but this means
now, ask the user, what's their name?
Whatever they type in, go
ahead and store it from right
to left in this variable
called "answer."
But C's not done with us yet.
If you've learned Python
or certain other languages,
you'd kind of be done
writing code at this point.
In C, though, you additionally have to
tell the compiler what type of variable
you want to use.
So if it's a string of
text, you say "string."
If it's an integer, a number, you say
"int," as we might have seen before.
So it's a little more pedantic.
It's more annoying, frankly, the more
onus on you and me, the programmers.
But this just helps
the compiler know how
to store it in the computer's memory.
And I'm so close to being done with
this line of code, but what's missing?
STUDENT: Semicolon.
DAVID MALAN: So semicolon.
And mark my words, if you've never
programmed before, sometime this week,
this semester, you will
forget a semicolon.
You will raise your hand.
You'll get frustrated because you can't
understand why your code's not working.
You will run into
stupid issues like that.
But do take faith that
they are stupid issues.
It doesn't mean it's not clicking
for you or you're not a programmer.
It just takes time to see these
things if it's a new language to you.
So there now is my semicolon.
All right, let's go ahead
then and do something
with that return value using the second
of the big puzzle pieces in Scratch.
So when I wanted to say, "hello,
David," or whatever the human's name is,
I kind of stacked my
puzzle pieces like this.
This is actually similar to Python and
maybe some other languages some of you
have learned.
But C is a little bit different.
And the closest analog to this Scratch
solution is going to look like this.
I still use printf because
printf is the equivalent of Say.
Inside of my parentheses, I'm going to
go ahead and say, weirdly, "hello, %s."
So there's no real analog in C of Join.
Instead, there's a way to specially
format text using printf, hence the F
in "printf."
And what you do in printf is
you type whatever English word
or human words that you want.
You then use %s a placeholder.
If you want a string of text
to be added to your own text,
you literally write "%s."
And let me anticipate a question from
the crowd-- how do you print out %s?
There's a solution to that, too, if you
literally ever want to print out %s.
But it's deliberately a
weird choice of characters
so that the probability that we
ever need to type this ourselves
is just low that no one really
worries too much about it.
All right, but that's not quite enough.
In addition to saying "hello",
comma, space, placeholder %s--
and just for vocabulary
sake, that's a format code.
Again, "format" being the F in printf.
I still need my double quotes
around the whole thing.
In this case, to match
my previous program,
I am going to go ahead
and add the backslash n
to move the cursor to the next line.
And now I've left a crazy amount of
room here, but that's deliberate.
Does anyone have an instinct
for what I'm probably
going to want to add after the quotes
but still inside of the parentheses?
STUDENT: The answer.
DAVID MALAN: So answer itself.
I need to somehow tell
printf with a second input,
otherwise known as an argument, what
I want to substitute for that %s.
And so I put a comma and
then the name of the variable
that I want printf to figure
out how to plug in here.
So honestly it's a little annoying,
and this is kind of a dated approach.
Newer, more modern languages,
like we'll see later
in the course, Python
and JavaScript, actually
have much more user-friendly
ways of doing it.
But once you wrap your mind around
the heuristics, the rules here,
it's just formatting a string
by plugging in whatever you want
into this format string, so to speak.
And again, the comma here is important.
This signifies that it takes one input
at left and a second input at right.
But notice this comma.
There's technically two commas.
But I'm not claiming that this
function takes three inputs.
Why?
This comma I'm pointing
out doesn't mean the same.
STUDENT: It's because that comma's
part of the quotation marks
and it's been part of the string.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
This comma that I'm pointing to is part
of the quotation marks and therefore
part of my string of English text.
So this is just English grammar.
This is sort of C syntax.
And again, these are the sort
of annoying little details
that we're using the same symbol for
different things, but context matters.
So just stare at your code,
look carefully left to right,
and generally the answer will
pop out, no pun intended.
OK, questions now on this syntax
before we actually write it and run it?
Yeah?
STUDENT: Why is the backslash
n not after the answer?
DAVID MALAN: Why is the
backslash n not after the answer?
So the way functions
work, including printf,
is that you pass to them one
argument inside of the parentheses.
And then if you have a second argument,
you put it after this comma here.
But the way printf works is that its
first argument is always a string
that you want to be formatted for you.
So anything you want printed on the
screen has to go in those quotes.
And you can perhaps
extrapolate from this.
If I actually wanted to say multiple
things in this sentence, so "hello,"
maybe first name, last name, I could
actually do "hello" comma, %s, space,
%s, if I had two variables, one called
First Name, one called Last Name.
But then I would need another comma
for a third input to the function.
And so it's very general
purpose in that sense.
Questions?
Yeah?
STUDENT: Can you abstract this further
by [INAUDIBLE] the "hello" [INAUDIBLE]??
DAVID MALAN: OK, so can you abstract
away the format string itself, "hello,"
comma answer?
Short answer, yes, but
not nearly as easily in C
as you can in other languages.
So that's why we're
keeping it simple for now.
But you're going to love something
like Python or JavaScript,
where a lot of this
complexity goes away.
But you'll see also in Python and
JavaScript and other languages,
they still are inspired
by syntax like this.
So just understanding it now will
be useful for multiple languages
down the line.
All right, so let's actually
do something with this code
rather than just talk about
what it might be doing for us.
Let me go over to, for
instance, VS Code again.
And I'm going to go ahead now and
remove this middle line of printf.
I'm still in my same
file called "hello.c."
I'm going to clear my terminal
window just to eliminate distraction.
And to do that, I can
literally type "clear."
But this is just for aesthetic's sake.
That's not functionally that useful.
Or you can hit Control L to
achieve the same on your keyboard.
But I'm going to go back to line
5 here, where I previously just
said "hello, world."
And I'm going to do this instead.
I'm going to give myself
a variable called string.
Sorry, I'm going to give
myself a variable called
answer, the type of which is string.
I'm going to set it equal
to whatever the return
value is of get_string, asking an
English question, "what's your name?"
with just a single space
just to move the cursor over,
followed by a semicolon.
Then I'm going to go ahead
and say printf, quote,
unquote, "hello,
placeholder, backslash n,"
comma, and then what goes here again?
STUDENT: Answer.
DAVID MALAN: This is where answer goes.
And then I just need a
semicolon on the right of that.
But I think now that I'm done.
But let me point out
a couple of details.
This got very colorful,
very pretty quickly.
And it's not like the black and white
code I had on the screen a moment ago.
This is because what programs like VS
Code do for us is it "pretty" prints,
or rather it syntax
highlights our code for us.
So syntax highlighting means
just add some colors to the code
so that different ideas pop out.
So you'll notice, for instance,
that printf here, get_string here
are in purple because they represent
functions, just like the Say block.
Here, "what's your name?",
quote, unquote, in VS Code
is a light blue instead of white.
But it's still going to be consistent
if I use strings of text elsewhere,
as well.
So I didn't type anything special.
This isn't like Microsoft
Word or Google Docs,
where I'm highlighting and
changing colors of things.
This is all happening automatically.
But it's just unicode text.
It's just being
interpreted automatically
and having these colors applied so that
things pop out more usefully visually.
Now, I've unfortunately made a mistake.
But I'm going to deliberately
induce this one because you, too,
will probably make this mistake.
I'm going to go ahead
and run "make hello"
again, because I've changed my code.
So I have to regenerate the machine
code from the new source code.
But unfortunately, when
I hit Enter now, my God,
the errors don't even fit on the screen.
So let me make this bigger.
I'm going to click the
little caret symbol here just
to make my terminal
bigger for just a moment.
And you'll see that there's
more lines of errors
than there are of code
that I actually wrote,
often which is written pretty
arcanely, again, for programmers who've
been writing code for 10, 20 years.
But there are some details that pop out.
So notice the problem is
definitely with hello.c.
So great, it is my fault. This syntax
here means that line 5 is the problem.
And this next 5 means character 5.
So you can literally triangulate your
bug, your mistake by going to line 5
and then over five, and
it's somewhere in that area.
Specifically, "the area is use
of undeclared identifier string.
Did you mean standard in?"
I don't think I did.
Like, I do want string, and then
there's some other complexity here.
But what's important here is not the
specifics of this error but really
the implication that it
doesn't recognize the word
"string" or "get_string."
Now, why might this be?
Yeah?
STUDENT: You said that
in order to [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Because we are using
get_string, which I claimed
is a CS50 thing that
we'll use for a few weeks,
C does not know about it
out of the box, so to speak.
I have to teach the compiler
that get_string exists,
just like I taught the compiler
that printf exists by including
the appropriate header file.
And in this case, quite simply,
it's called includeCS50.h.
That now teaches the
compiler, oh, someone else
wrote this function already, get_string,
and with it this type of variable
called "string."
So now if I go back
to my terminal window
and rerun the exact same command, "make
hello"-- maybe crossing my fingers--
now nothing in fact goes
wrong because the compiler
has been brought up to speed with
all of the functionality it needs.
And now if I do ./hello, Enter,
there it is, what's my name?
And notice the cursor
is one space over just
because I thought that looked
prettier than having the cursor right
next to the question mark.
D-A-V-I-D as my input, and Enter.
And "hello, David."
Questions on any of this code thus far?
Questions?
Any of the code.
No?
All right, so let's introduce some
other functionality into the mix.
It turns out that there
are other types of data,
other types of variables in
the world, not just strings
but indeed, per before,
we have things called
integers, "int" for short, floating
point values, "float" for short,
and a few others as well.
So rather than only
focus on string, let's
get a little more
interesting with numbers
here and see what we can do with
something like integers, again
"int" for short, by taking a look at
not get_string, as before, but now
how about get_int.
And for this, I'm going to give us
a few other tools in our toolkit,
those format codes to which
I alluded earlier, like %s,
fortunately are pretty straightforward.
And here is a list of most
of the popular format codes
that you might ever
care about with printf.
In particular, we saw %s for string.
And you can perhaps guess which one
we're going to use for integers.
STUDENT: %i.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so %i is what
we're going to use for integers.
And this is the kind
of thing that you can
consult in the manual
pages or a slide like this.
There's only a few of them
that you might frequently use.
But let's go ahead and use integers
in a more interesting context, not
just using functions.
But let's revisit this
idea of conditionals.
And conditionals in Scratch were like
these proverbial forks in the road.
Like, do you want to do this thing
or this thing or this other thing?
It's a way of making
decisions in a program, which
is going to be super useful and pretty
much omnipresent in any problems
that we try to solve.
So let me give you a
few more building blocks
in C by doing the
side-by-side comparison again.
So here in Scratch is how we might
say if two variables, x and y,
one is less than the other, then
go ahead and say, quote, unquote,
"x is less than y."
So kind of a stupid program.
But just to show you the
basic syntax for Scratch,
this is how you would ask the question,
if x is less than y, then say this.
So Say is the function.
"If" is the conditional.
And the green thing
here we called, what?
What did we call it?
Yeah?
STUDENT: A Boolean.
DAVID MALAN: A Boolean
or a Boolean expression,
which is just a fancy way
of saying a question whose
answer is true or false, yes or no, 1 or
0, however you want to think about it.
In C, the code is going
to look like this.
So it'll take a little bit of habit, a
little bit of muscle memory to develop.
But you're going to say
"if," then in parentheses,
you're going to say "x less than
y," assuming x and y are variables.
You're then going to
use these curly braces.
And then if you want to say,
quote, unquote, "x is less than y"
in C, what function should
we use here presumably?
So printf.
So printf, quote, unquote,
"x is less than y."
So it's a bit of a mouthful,
but again notice the pattern.
Name of the function is printf.
In the parentheses, left and
right, is the argument to printf,
which is, quote, unquote,
"x is less than y."
And again, just for aesthetics, to
move the cursor to the next line,
which you don't have to worry about
in Scratch because everything's
in speech bubbles, we're
adding a backslash n, as well.
So notice that these
curly braces, as they're
called, much like the
orange puzzle piece here,
are kind of hugging the code like this.
And I'll note that
technically speaking in C,
If you only have one line of
code inside of your conditional,
you can actually omit the
curly braces altogether.
And the code will still work if
you have one single line of code.
Why?
Just saves people some keystrokes.
If you have two lines, three
lines, or more in there,
you need the curly braces.
But I'll always draw it with
the curly braces in class
so it resembles Scratch
as closely as possible.
As an aside to some of you
who have programmed before,
you might be cringing now
because like you really
like your curly brace to be
over here instead of here, that,
too, is a stylistic choice.
And we'll talk, too,
about this in the class.
Aesthetically, stylistically there
are certain decisions we can make.
But generally in a class, in a company,
you as a student or an employee
would simply standardize on
one set of rules, so to speak.
So we'll use these rules for formatting
our code in class consistently.
All right, any questions
on this snippet of C code?
All right, a couple of others then.
So here is how, in Scratch, we might
have a two-way fork in the road.
If x is less than y, say x is less
than y, else say x is not less than y.
In C, It's going to look
pretty much the same.
But notice I'm adding an "else" keyword
here with another set of curly braces.
I'm going to have a
couple of more printf's.
But in C, even though it's
clearly keyboard based,
it's just text, no more puzzle
pieces, it's kind of the same shape,
so to speak, and it's
definitely the same idea.
So it's following a pattern.
What about a three-way fork in
the road, if x is less than y,
then say x is less than
y, else if x is greater
than y, say x is greater than y, else
if x equals y, then say x is equal to y.
Well, you can probably
see where this is going.
On the right-hand side,
it looks almost the same.
In fact, if I add in the printf's,
it's really almost the same,
at least logically.
But there is at least one
curiosity, seemingly a typo
but it's not this time.
Yeah?
STUDENT: The double equals.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, the double
equal signs does not match Scratch,
but it's not in fact a bug
or a mistake in C. Anyone
have an intuition for why I did use
two equal signs instead of one here?
Yeah?
STUDENT: Because otherwise it
could be mistaken for a variable.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Well, otherwise it would be mistaken
for a variable, specifically
assignment of a variable.
So recall that in previous code,
when we used the get_string function,
we used an equals sign to assign, from
right to left, the value of a variable.
And that's a reasonable decision.
"Equal" kind of means that
the two should ultimately
be equal even though you think
about it from going right to left.
Unfortunately, the authors of C kind of
[? painted ?] themselves into a corner.
And presumably, decades ago
when they realized, oh, shoot,
we've already used a
single equal sign, how
do we represent equality of two values,
the answer they came up with was,
all right, we'll just use two instead.
And thus was born this decision.
Is it the best one?
Who knows?
Crazy enough, in other
languages, like JavaScript,
you have not just one, but
two, but also three equal signs
in a row to solve yet another problem.
So reasonable people will disagree as
to how good or bad these decisions are.
But in C, this is what you must do.
But there's a bad design
decision here, too.
It's still correct, the
code, left and right.
But I bet I could critique the quality
of the design of both the Scratch code
and the C code for reasons, what?
STUDENT: Do we have to do
else if x equals [INAUDIBLE]??
DAVID MALAN: OK, no,
really good intuition.
Do we have to ask this third
question, "else if x equals y?"
So short answer, no, logically, right?
Just based on arithmetic, either x
is less than y or x is greater than y
or, what's the only
other possible answer?
They must be equal, logically.
So technically, you're just kind
of wasting the computer's time
by asking this question
because it already knows,
at that point, the answer.
And you're wasting your time
as the programmer bothering
to type out more code
or more puzzle pieces
than you need because logically
one stems from the other.
So I can tighten this up, get rid of
the "else, if," just use an "else."
And I can do the same thing
over here in C, thereby avoiding
the double equal sign altogether,
but not because it's wrong
but because you're wasting time, because
now you're potentially asking only two
questions, two Boolean expressions,
instead of 50% more by asking
a total of three questions at most.
Other questions then on this kind
of code, logically or otherwise?
No?
All right, so if we have these puzzle
pieces, so to speak, at our disposal,
how can we go about
actually using these?
Well, suppose that we actually
want to do something with values.
Let's introduce variables in C, as well.
We saw an example using
a string a moment ago.
But what about with
something like integers?
Well, you might not have
used this in Scratch.
But here's the orange
puzzle piece in Scratch
via which you can create a variable
called counter to count things.
And you can set it equal
to some value like 0.
Now, you can perhaps guess
where we're going with this.
If I want in C a variable called
counter and I want to set it equal to 0,
I use a single equal sign
because logically you
read it from right to
left, or technically it's
executed from right to left.
But that's not enough in C.
What's missing from the screen?
STUDENT: Data type.
DAVID MALAN: I need a what?
STUDENT: You need a data type.
DAVID MALAN: So we need a data type.
And if it's going to be an integer,
indeed I'm going to use int.
And now the other mistake
I keep making is--
STUDENT: Semicolon.
DAVID MALAN: So a semicolon
at the end of the line.
So it's a little more
verbose than some languages.
But if you read it
left to right, this is
how you tell C to give you a
variable called counter of type int
and initialize it to a value of 0.
That's all.
All right, how about, in Scratch, if
you want to change that variable by 1,
by adding 1 to it?
In Scratch, it's super simple.
You just change it by
1 or even negative 1
if you want to go up
or down respectively.
In C, it turns out you have a
few different ways to do this.
And this looks like it's
not mathematically possible,
but that's because equals
is assignment, recall.
So this line of code is not saying
that counter equals counter plus 1,
because that's just not
possible using typical numbers.
But this means take
counter's value, add 1 to it,
and assign it back to
the counter variable.
So it's like incrementing
counter in this way.
But this is such a common
thing in C and in programming
to increase or decrease
the values of variables,
there's a more succinct syntax.
This is identical.
And it might take you a little
practice to get used to it,
but it just saves you some keystrokes.
But it similarly adds 1, or
whatever number you use there.
And this is such a common
operation in C especially
that there's an even tighter
way of executing the same idea.
And you can literally just say counter++
and then semicolon in this case.
All three are exactly the same.
All three are perfectly correct.
But you'll learn over time
that typing less on the screen
is probably going to save you some time.
Meanwhile, if we wanted to do the
opposite and do something like minus 1
in Scratch, we could similarly do
minus minus in C. Or we could do--
yeah, we could do minus
minus in C here at right.
All right, so just some additional
building blocks, translating
from scratch to C. Why don't we go
ahead and try using this perhaps
in the following way?
Let me go ahead and go back to VS Code.
And let me propose that
we do something like this.
In VS Code, I'm going to go ahead
and clear my terminal window.
I'm going to close
"hello.c" by just clicking
the X. I'm going to go ahead and
create a new file called "compare.c"
because the purpose in
life of this program
is going to be to compare
integers on the screen.
This time I'm not going to mess up.
I'm going to preemptively
include CS50.h.
include stdio.h.
And here, too, is a very common mistake
in learning C. It is not "studio.h."
So when you email us asking
why "studio.h" is not working,
that's because that is not the word.
It is "standard io.h," meaning
standard input and output,
stuff involving the
screen and the keyboard.
Then I'm going to go ahead and,
just as before, int main(void),
but we'll come back to that
eventually as to what it means.
And now inside of "main," which is just
where the main part of my program goes,
again you can think of this as being
analogous to "when green flag clicked."
This just kicks everything off.
I'm going to go ahead and do two things.
I'm going to go ahead and
get an integer called x,
and I'm going to prompt
the user for that int
and just say something
like, "what's x?", space.
Then I'm going to do int y equals
get_int, quote, unquote, "what's y?",
space.
And then let's just do something
simple like, if x is less than y,
then go ahead and print
out, quote, unquote,
"x is less than y
backslash n," semicolon.
So it's not a very deep program.
It's just going to do what most any
human brain could do pretty quickly.
But it's at least demonstrating
how we might use now
something like a conditional in code.
So let me go ahead and re--
let me compile this code for the
first time, make compare, enter.
Nothing bad happens, which is good.
"./compare" is how I run the program.
And just to tease this apart,
dot, as we'll soon see,
essentially means that the
file is in your current folder.
So dot means in your current folder.
And we'll eventually see that
dot dot means your parent
folder, like the one
that contains wherever
I am on my computer's hard drive.
All right. ./compare.
What's x?
1.
2 for y.
And hopefully it should
say that x is less than y.
So pretty straightforward.
Proof by example.
And hopefully this would
work in other cases, too.
But if I flip that around and I rerun
it, ./compare, and I do 2 and 1,
nothing's going to happen.
But you would expect
that because there's
only one Boolean expression
deciding whether or not
I should actually type this out.
So what's going on?
Well, if this helps
you, you might find it
useful to think about the logic of
any program, be it in Scratch or C,
as kind of a flowchart of sorts.
And we'll put up a few of
these over time just in case
you're a particularly visual thinker.
And this represents
what it is I just did.
So here in this picture is where
the program starts conceptually.
And any time you see a diamond, think
of that as a Boolean expression,
a question that's being asked.
And the question being
asked is, is x less than y?
That has two possible answers, true
or false, yes or no respectively.
So let me propose, per the arrow, that
if the answer is true, then print out,
per this rectangle, "x is less than
y," just quote, unquote, and then stop.
That's it for the program.
But logically, if x is
not less than y, that
is that question's answer is false,
we'll just skip right to the end
and stop.
So this is a control-flow diagram.
It's just a pictorial
way that you could write
on a piece of paper that just represents
what it is the program is doing.
And this gets a little
more interesting if now we
do something else with the code.
For instance, instead of just concluding
that it's less than 1 or the other,
let's go back to the code here.
Let me clear my terminal window.
And let me add an "else."
So else, go ahead and print out "x"--
I don't think I want to say
this-- "greater than y."
It's not quite right.
What would be reasonable to say here?
STUDENT: "x is not less than y.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, subtle, but "x is not
less than y" because it could be equal.
We don't know if we're only
checking two scenarios here.
So if I recompile this,
make compare, ./compare.
Now if I do 1, comma 2, I
still get the same answer.
If I rerun ./compare 2, comma 1,
I now get the opposite answer.
It's not as good as might be ideal.
It'd be nice to know if it's
equal to or greater than.
But at least that's all of
the code that we have here.
And just to now paint
a picture, if I go back
to my control-flow diagram,
my flow chart here,
this is what it looked
like before logically.
Now that I've added in a
second branch, so to speak,
now, if the answer is false, I first
print out x is not less than y,
and then I stop the program.
So same idea, but the
decision tree, if you will,
if you've taken a 10 or the like,
is getting a little bit bigger now
conceptually.
All right, what if we do
something more than this?
Let's actually have
that third condition.
Let me go back into my code here.
I'm going to hide the terminal window
just to make room for more code.
And I'm going to say,
"else if x is greater
than y," then go ahead and say
not "x is not less than y,"
but rather "x is greater than y."
And then down here, I'll do an
"else if x equals equals y,"
then I can go ahead and say printf,
"x is equal to y backslash n,"
close quote.
All right, so now if I run it-- let
me open my terminal window again.
Let me rerun make compare.
Let me rerun ./compare.
1 and 2 are the same.
Let me rerun it.
2 and 1 are the same.
Let me rerun it a third time.
1 and 1 are now in fact equal.
So this works correctly.
But why did I make a point
of using these "else if"s?
Put another way, couldn't I just
make my life a little simpler
and just say, if this, then that?
If this, then that.
Just ask all three questions.
Keep the code simple.
Don't bother with these else's.
Would this work for me?
Yeah?
STUDENT: It just seems like
[INAUDIBLE] the program
doesn't have to run the rest.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so it saves a little
bit of time because in this case,
just like in English, this is like
asking three separate questions.
And it's not harnessing any
information from previous questions
in order to decide whether you should
bother asking that other question.
In other words, if x is less
than y-- and you already
figured that out because it's
1 and 2 respectively-- you're
going to print this.
Why would you waste time
asking this question when
it's not going to be true?
Why would you waste time
asking this question when
it's not going to be true?
And so the point I wanted
to make here, which
is that if we visualize
that particular design,
what the flow chart looks
like is actually this.
And let me zoom in at the top.
If you ask the question
"is x less than y," well,
you're going to go ahead
and say, x less than y.
Then if you go down
to the next question,
you're still going to
ask is x greater than y.
And then below that, you're still
going to ask is x equal equal to y?
So no matter what x and y are, you're
asking one, two, three questions all
of the time.
But if we actually go in and
do what we did the first time,
where if I go back to my code and I undo
this edit and add back the "else if"s--
and now let me go back
to the flow chart,
which I claim is bad because it's
one, two, three questions, one
or two of which might not be necessary--
now if I visualize what I just did,
the flow chart gets a little
more complicated looking,
but it's going to be better
designed, more efficient.
Why?
Well, because if I start at the
top here, I ask one question,
is x less than y.
If the answer is true, OK.
I say x less than y.
And then, boom, I sort of
cheat and go all the way
to the end of the program and stop,
having asked only one question.
If, though, x is not less than y, OK,
fine, I'll ask you a second question.
But if the answer is true, boom,
I print out x is greater than y,
and then I stop.
And only in a perverse
case where x actually
equals y, which I'm going to claim
is very unlikely or infrequent,
only then am I going to ask one, two,
three questions to figure out whether
or not to print something at all.
So this is what we mean by
distinguishing between correctness
of code-- because it's still correct--
but this version is better
designed because hopefully you're
going to go down this branch or this
branch rather than the longest one
frequently.
Any questions now about this code
or this visualization thereof?
Yeah?
STUDENT: I don't know if [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: A perfect segue.
Why did I bother, though,
even asking this question?
Don't need to because
when I hit this button--
hopefully I have the
right slide in place--
this would be even
better than that design.
So thank you for teeing that up.
This is the same picture.
It sort of got bigger
because there's fewer nodes,
fewer shapes in the picture.
Notice that if x less than y,
boom, we say as much, and we stop.
If x is not less than y but it's
greater than y, boom, we stop.
Or if it's not greater
than, we immediately
conclude x indeed is equal to y.
And again, we stop.
So this picture is about
as efficient and as
well designed as we can make our logic.
That's about as good as
we can solve this problem.
So if I go back to my
code now to make my C code
match that, the only thing I need to
do is stop wasting the computer's time.
Don't ask that third question.
Just logically, mathematically
conclude that of course it's
going to be equal at
that point in the story.
All right, any other questions on this?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Sorry, a little louder?
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
What if I put in something
that's not a number?
So here, too, is where the CS50 library
and the implementation of get_int
will be your friend.
So for instance, if I run ./compare
and I want to compare cats and dogs,
I could type in "cats," Enter.
It's just going to prompt
me again and again.
It's not going to let me
type in "dogs" either.
It's going to force me
to give it an integer.
C does not do that by default.
And in fact, as we'll soon
see over the course of CS50,
C is actually a very dangerous
language at the end of the day
because it just trusts that the
human is doing what it wants.
And as such, a lot of today's
software that is hacked in some ways,
if it's using C or another
language called C++,
are actually very vulnerable
to certain types of hacking,
whereas other languages that we'll get
to in the class are less so for reasons
like this.
All right, so besides this, let's
consider just one other data type.
how about.
So besides strings, besides chars,
there's some others on this list here.
Sorry, besides strings,
besides integers,
there's this other data type here in C
known as a char for a single character.
So here, let me just tease this apart.
A string is indeed a string of text.
It is zero or more characters together.
A char is always
precisely one character.
Not all languages bother distinguishing
between a single character
and a string of characters.
But in C, a string is
typically multiple characters,
but technically can be zero.
Coincidentally, it could be one.
But it's capable of being more.
But a char is literally, as the
word implies, a single character.
All right, given that, notice
that in the CS50 library,
besides get_string, besides
get_int, we also have get_char,
so another handy function for
just getting a single character
from the user.
Now, why would it be useful to get
a single character from the user?
Well, what if you're
just doing something
that you and I do pretty frequently
when you install new software
or fill out some form?
You agree to some form
of terms and conditions.
So in fact, let me go
back over to VS Code here.
And let me propose that I create
a new program called agree.c,
so something akin to asking
for the user's agreement.
So in VS Code, I'm going
to type "code agree.c."
And I'm going to do
some quick boilerplate.
So include CS50.h, include
stdio.h, int main(void).
And then inside of main, which
is like the "green flag clicked,"
I'm going to do this.
Go ahead and get a
character from the user,
and ask them something
simple like, "Do you agree?,"
expecting a yes/no response.
But at the beginning of this line, I
need to put the return value somewhere.
So I'm going to put it
in a variable called
C. And in programming, if you're
just getting a single value,
it's OK sometimes to use X
and Y or C when you're using--
in larger programs, you'll benefit
from using actual words like "answer,"
like we did from the get go.
But C has to be a specific type.
So I'm going to literally
say "char," and then
I'm going to finish my
thought with a semicolon.
And here's now how I could
check if the user agrees or not.
I could do something like this.
If the value of C equals
equals, quote, unquote,
lowercase 'y,' then go ahead and
print out "Agreed backslash n."
Else if the variable C has a value
equal to lowercase 'n', let's go ahead
and print out, say, "Not agreed," as
though I'm agreeing or not to some
terms and conditions.
But notice these are not typos.
What did I do ever so subtly
different from last time I used text?
Yeah?
STUDENT: Single quotes
instead of double quotes.
DAVID MALAN: Single quotes
So here's the heuristic.
When using strings, which are
generally multiple characters,
have to use double quotes.
When using a single character,
you should use single quotes
around the single character.
So let me go ahead now and, make agree.
Nothing went wrong, which
is good. ./agree, Enter,
and let me go ahead
and type in y for yes.
It seems to work.
Let me run it again. ./agree.
n for no, and it seems to work.
And just if I type in something random
like question mark, I don't know,
it doesn't crash.
It just ignores me because I only
had two Boolean expressions there.
But notice that it's actually
a little buggy arguably.
Let me run it again. ./agree, Enter.
How about capital Y because,
like, my Caps Lock is down.
OK, it just ignores me.
Let me do it again. ./agree,
capital N because my-- oops--
because my Caps Lock is down.
OK, it just ignores me.
But this should make sense because
I'm literally checking for lowercase.
So how could I fix this?
How could I fix this without just
changing lowercase to uppercase,
because that would then break
it in the other direction?
Yeah?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, let's just add
another branch here, so to speak.
So if variable C equals equals
capital Y, then I can go ahead here
and say printf agreed.
And then let me close my
terminal to make more room.
Otherwise, down here, else
if C equals equals capital N,
let's go ahead and again
say printf not agreed.
And I claim that this
would actually now work.
It's a four-way fork in
the road, but I'm at least
checking for lowercase, uppercase,
lowercase, uppercase for y and n
respectively.
I claim that this is
correct, but this too,
even if you've never programmed
before, should start today
to rub you the wrong way.
Like, we can do better.
This isn't the best design.
Why might that be?
Yeah?
STUDENT: Could you change the character
c to be uppercase, like before you even
[INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID MALAN: Ah, clever.
So could we change the variable
c to just be forced to uppercase
or maybe forced to lowercase?
No matter what the human types, we
just do that ourselves so that way
we can just simplify this again
to two possible scenarios.
I love that, but we haven't
seen any functions yet
in C that would let me change
things to uppercase or lowercase.
So we'll get there, but a
good instinct and correct.
Other thoughts?
STUDENT: Use "or."
DAVID MALAN: So we could use "or"
in some sense, like a logical "or."
What I don't like about this, to be
clear, is that it's repeating itself.
And there's this principle in
programming, and in life in general,
like, don't repeat
yourself unnecessarily.
And by that I mean I literally
have the same line 10 as 14.
I have the same line 18 as 22.
And if anything, one, I literally wasted
twice as much time as I needed to.
Put another way, per our
discussion of Scratch,
what if I go in and just
change something like,
I want to be more
excited, like "Agreed!"?
Well, I might forget to
change it in the other place.
And let's just claim for today's
purposes that that looks stupid,
it's a bug, because I want
them to be consistent.
So don't invite situations
where you might change something
in one place but not another.
Just only write it in one place total.
So I like this idea of
"or"-ing things together.
So let me go ahead and
delete what I just did.
And just to be clear, too, while this is
on the screen, when you highlight code
in VS Code based on how we've
configured it, these dots just show you
how much I've indented because in
C, stylistically, the convention
is generally to indent four
spaces and maybe four more spaces.
So those dots just help
you count without having
to manually eyeball things yourself.
But let me delete those lines.
Let me delete these lines.
And this is going to
look a little weird,
but the way you can "or"
two thoughts together, so to
speak, like "or" them together,
is you don't say "or,"
but you use two vertical
bars, which syntactically
means the English word "or."
And you can just ask the
other question, if C equals,
quote, unquote, capital 'Y.'
And then down here, I can say
or C equals equals capital 'N.'
So it adds a little more
code to each of those lines,
but it doesn't add redundancy,
because I've not duplicated my printf.
I've not added more curly
braces unnecessarily.
Now as an aside, there's the opposite
of "or", logically is the word "and."
Just so you've seen it, I could do this.
"&&" in C is how you express that
the thing on the left must be true
and the thing on the right must be true.
But why would this make no
sense in this context of line 8?
STUDENT: It can't be
uppercase and lowercase.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, at
least to my knowledge,
a character can't be both
lowercase and uppercase.
That just makes no logical sense.
So indeed "or" is what
we want in this case.
Other questions?
STUDENT: In CS50.h, is there a way to
directly compare strings [INAUDIBLE]??
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
Via CS50.h, is there a
way to compare strings.
Short answer, no.
But C is going to give
us that capability.
And in fact, next week, among the things
we'll do is actually compare strings.
And if you've programmed
before, you'll see in C
that it actually doesn't work
the way that you might expect.
But that's a problem,
too, that we will solve.
But that transcends CS50.
That's a question for C. Other
questions on this kind of logic?
Just to make this real then,
anytime you click one of those EULAs
or terms and conditions on a
form in a piece of software,
odds are there is code as simple
as this underneath the hood.
Maybe it's graphical.
Maybe it's checking for
you clicking this button
or maybe hitting the Enter key.
But underneath the hood
is presumably some kind
of conditional checking
for those kinds of outputs.
All right, how about
another building block
from last time, which
we'll now translate to C,
namely loops, things that
happen again and again?
And these, too, are everywhere in code.
So in Scratch, here's how we might
meow three times, super simple.
In C, it's going to look a little weird.
But you will get used to this over
time if you've never programmed before.
It looks like a mouthful, OK.
But let's tease it apart line by line.
And you'll see that you won't have that
reaction frequently because it's all
going to start to look
very similar to itself.
But what are we doing here?
In C, you don't have the luxury of
these cute and fun puzzle pieces
that just do the work for
you, repeat three times.
In fact, in C and programming
in general, sometimes
the work is on us to
actually figure out, OK,
how can I use functions,
variables, conditionals, and loops
and implement some idea like
repetition, like looping?
And in C, here's how this might work.
How can I go about doing something
like printing "meow" three times?
Well, I know about variables now.
We're about to see loops.
And I've seen how I can update
variables by plussing or minusing
some value to them.
Let's combine those ideas.
So first, I'm doing what with
this highlighted line in English?
If a friend cared to ask you, like,
'what is this line of code doing'
later today, what would you say?
STUDENT: It's creating a variable called
"counter" and setting it equal to 3.
DAVID MALAN: Good, it's creating
a variable called "counter"
and setting it equal to 3.
I'll use slightly new jargon.
I'm defining a variable, would be
the term of our "called counter"
and setting it equal to 3.
So I'll use my hand to
represent the counter.
And that's all a variable is.
It's like storage in some case that
I'm representing information, using
my hand in this case or
the computer's memory here.
Now what happens when using a loop in C?
There's different types of loops, one
of which is called a for loop-- oop--
one of which is called
a while loop-- spoiler.
A while loop works like this.
Inside of parentheses is a Boolean
expression just like inside
of a conditional that asks a question.
But this time the question
is going to determine,
do you keep going through the
loop again and again and again?
So it's not a one-time
thing potentially.
It is checked again and
again and again to decide
when it is time to stop
looping, to stop cycling.
All right, so it's asking
this question first.
Is counter greater than 0?
OK, obviously the answer is true because
I'm still holding up three fingers.
So what happens?
C goes inside of the curly
braces per the indentation
and executes printf of "meow," which
prints out a "meow" on the screen.
The next line of code
executes, which, recall,
is the same as just
subtracting 1 from counter.
So I think I take down one
finger, so I'm left with two.
And what happens next?
Well, this you just kind
of have to memorize.
Once you get to the end
of the inside of a loop,
you go back to the
beginning of a loop here
and ask the same question,
the same Boolean expression.
So is 2 greater than 0?
OK, obviously so.
So you go into it, you print a "meow."
You go into it and decrement
counter further by one.
So now my hand is holding up one.
Now we wrap back around
to the Boolean expression.
Is 1 greater than 0?
Obviously.
We print out a third "meow."
We then decrement counter
again, and my hand goes to zero.
We go back around once more.
Is 0 greater than 0?
No.
And now the program just terminates.
Or if there were more
code here, it would just
jump outside of the curly braces
and keep going lower on the screen.
So that's all that's happening.
And so this is what MIT has the
luxury of doing with pictures.
But at MIT, someone
probably essentially wrote
code that looks like this to give us
the illusion, the abstraction of this.
So what we're learning today is how
they invented these puzzle pieces
by just using lower-level plumbing,
if you will, like this here.
Yeah?
STUDENT: What would happen if you
created the variable "counter"
inside of the curly braces?
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
What would happen if you created the
variable inside of the curly braces?
Short answer, it just
wouldn't work in C,
because if I were to
try with my slide here,
for instance, to move this line of code
here down inside of this, for instance,
now the very top line is trying to
use counter before it even exists.
So C is very literal it.
Reads top to bottom, left to right.
And if it hasn't seen you
define or create a variable yet,
you're going to get some scary
error message on the screen instead.
All right, other questions
on this here code?
No?
All right, so if we want to then
maybe tighten this up a bit,
let me propose that we
could do this instead.
So besides this version
of the code, let me just
do something more canonical,
more conventional.
So you're totally fine with
using a variable like counter .
It's what Scratch uses by
default. It's very verbose.
It does what it says.
Frankly, once you get
comfy with programming,
like most typical
programmers, whenever they
have a single integer in a program
whose sole purpose in life is to count,
they'll just use "i" for integer
just like I used "c" for character.
When you have larger
programs, you don't want
to start using A and B and C and D and
E and F and so forth for your variables
because nothing's going
to make any sense.
But when you're doing something super
simple like counting with an integer,
using a short-named variable is
totally stylistically reasonable.
But I can tighten this up further,
not just renaming counter to i.
What else can I do, if you recall?
Over here?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
STUDENT: A for loop?
DAVID MALAN: Oh, OK, for loop.
Yes, that was my spoiler.
But while in a while loop, I can
tighten this up slightly more.
Over here?
STUDENT: Instead of i equals i minus 1.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, instead
of i equals i minus 1,
I can actually tighten this up this way.
And we didn't see the
minus before, but it's
the same idea-- i minus equals 1, or
even more succinctly, i minus minus.
So when you get comfortable with
programming, any of these approaches
are correct.
This would be more
conventional at this point.
So if you want to write
code like most other people
write code, adopt ultimately
these kinds of conventions.
All right, so that just does
the exact same thing, though.
But let's now put this into practice.
Let me go back to VS Code here.
Let me go ahead and clear my terminal
and close agree.c from before.
And let me go ahead and
create a file called "meow."
So code meow.c.
And let me do this
the sort of wrong way.
Let me include stdio.h.
at the top, int main(void) thereafter.
Inside of there, let
me do printf "meow."
And then you know what?
I don't want to keep typing that.
Let me just go ahead and
copy/paste two more times.
So I claim this is correct, make meow.
./meow, done.
I've got code that prints
"meow" three times.
But this, again, should
already rub you the wrong way.
Why?
Yeah?
STUDENT: There's duplication.
DAVID MALAN: Because what?
DAVID MALAN: Because I have duplication.
I mean, I literally
copied and pasted it.
And that's kind of a good rule of thumb.
If you, in the future, start finding
yourself copying and pasting code
within the same program, you're
probably doing something wrong.
There's a better way to design
it even if it's correct.
So this is clearly a
candidate for a loop.
So let me go ahead and actually do that.
Let me just go ahead and
remove all of this duplication.
Let me give myself a variable
called i, set it equal to 3.
Let me go ahead and
give myself a while loop
and check that i is greater than 0.
Inside of this loop, let me
print out just "meow" once.
But I'll reuse that code again
and again because here I'm
going to do i minus minus.
So that's the exact same code, the tight
version of it that we saw a moment ago.
Let me go ahead and "make meow"
again, ./meow, and it still works.
Why is this version better?
Because if you want the cat to meow
five times, you change it in one place.
If you want to make the cat a dog, you
change the meow to a woof in one place,
albeit changing the file name
eventually, but changing it
in one place, not worrying about
changing it again and again and again.
But there are other ways to do this.
For instance, let me propose that.
And actually, let's see, let me propose
that instead of just doing it this way,
just to be clear--
yeah, let's go ahead and propose
that instead of doing this,
we can actually count
in different directions.
I'm kind of forcing this idea of
starting at 3, going down to 0.
But when normal humans in this
room, if you ever count something,
you probably do 1, 2, 3, and done.
Like, that's how we would
count in the real world.
Well, we can do that,
too, here code-wise.
We could initialize i to 1.
We could check that i is
less than or equal to 3.
And we've not seen this
syntax before, but there's
no easy way on a typical keyboard
to type a less than or equal sign
like in a math book.
So we use two characters, a
less-than sign and then an equal sign
back to back.
And that means less than or equal to.
And this is the same idea so long
as I plus plus i inside of it
because that'll start at 1,
then 2, but it won't stop then.
It will go up to until i is equal to 3.
Once i becomes 4, then that Boolean
expression isn't going to be true.
So it stops after three "meow"s total.
But there's another way,
too, and this is probably
the most conventional and
the way you should do it
even though it's just as correct.
In CS, if you've seen already last week,
we almost always start counting from 0.
Why?
Just because, so we're not
wasting a pattern of bits.
So generally when you start
writing code that counts,
you should, quote, unquote,
"almost always" start at 0,
count up to but not
through the total you
care about so you don't
get one extra by accident.
And so this would be the
most conventional way
of doing what we just described.
But they're all correct.
You can make an argument that
all of them are equally good.
This is what most people,
quote, unquote, "would do."
OK, other questions on
this here syntax or logic?
No?
All right, how about--
we got some cookies on the horizon.
But before we get there, let's
meow a few more times, if we may.
So how about doing a little bit
differently versus the while loop.
And I think we heard it over here.
Turns out there's another
type of loop altogether.
So this one here.
And this one, if you can believe it,
is probably even more conventional
than the other way.
And this is going to be
thematic in programming.
There's rarely one way,
one right way to do things.
You're going to have bunches of
different tools in your toolkit.
And your code might look different
from someone else's because each of you
tends to reach for a different
tool in that toolkit.
And here's another tool--
and as you proposed earlier--
a for loop.
A for loop is just another way
of achieving the exact same idea
using slightly different syntax.
And it's appealing, frankly in general,
because it's a little more succinct.
It just saves some keystrokes
even though you have to memorize
the order in which it works.
This code is identical to
this code here functionally.
But aesthetically, of
course, it looks different.
How does it work?
In a for loop, notice
that in the parentheses
is not a single simple
Boolean expression.
There are three things.
One, before a semicolon, is a
place to initialize a variable
to do your counting typically.
Second is the Boolean expression.
So it's still there.
It's just surrounded on the left
and the right by two other things.
Lastly is the update.
What do you want to do at the end of
every loop through this block of code?
So you can probably imagine
where we're going with this.
How does this work?
The first thing that
happens is that a variable
called i is defined and
initialized to the value of 0.
That happens once and only once.
Then we check the condition.
Is 0 less than 3?
Obviously yes.
So now we don't do the plus plus yet.
We go into the loop.
And this is where the for loop's
a little confusing at first.
We print out "meow."
Then what happens?
There's no more lines.
So we go back to the for loop,
and we increment i at that point.
So now i is 1.
Then we check the
condition. i is less than 3?
Yes, because 1 is less than 3.
We go back into the
loop and print "meow."
Now we go back to the
plus plus, so i is now 2.
We check the condition.
2 is less than 3 obviously.
So we go back into the
loop and print "meow."
Then we do the increment. i is now 3.
Is 3 less than 3?
No, so we exit the loop,
and we're done, or we keep
going down here if there's more code.
But how many times did I say "meow?"
1, 2, 3 total, when my
hand was 0, 1, and 2.
Questions on this alternative syntax?
It takes some getting
used to, but most people
would write loops using
a for loop, I would say.
STUDENT: Could you now in the curly
braces, use just one line of code?
DAVID MALAN: Yes.
If you really want to
be cool and save syntax,
yes, it is correct and common to
eliminate the curly braces if you only
have one line of code therein.
We in class will always
put the curly braces there
because this is the kind of thing where,
if you get forgetful, you go in later
and add a second line.
Like, darn it, like you
forgot the curly braces,
things will not work as expected.
So in general, use the curly braces,
but you do not have to strictly.
Other questions on 6?
Yes?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Can be used without, what?
DAVID MALAN: Oh, could you
do it without the condition?
Yes, there are very fancy things you
can do that we won't focus on today.
But yes, if you want to get rid of the
condition, you could get rid of this
here.
And that would actually
make the loop go forever,
which may be a good thing
if it's like a clock
that you want to tick forever, but
often not a good thing in code.
Good question, though.
All right, so beyond that, let's just
go ahead and put this into context.
Just in case it helps
you to think about this,
this is just another
flow chart, if you're
more of a visual
thinker, that represents
what it is this loop is now doing.
Previously, all of our arrows went
from top to bottom and stopped.
But now there's an arrow
going back, up, and around
because of this loop, this cycle.
So when we start this
program, we set i equal to 0.
We then check, is i less than 3?
Obviously it is, so we print "meow."
We increment i, and then we go
back to that same condition.
We check the condition.
We print "meow."
i plus plus, go back, go back.
Now, if i equals 3, 3 is not less
than 3, so the answer is false.
And we stop.
So again, it's just
another way of thinking
about how the code in
Scratch, how the code in C
might alternatively work
in each of these contexts.
But there's this one other
puzzle piece in Scratch,
recall, that's not the
repeat block, which
is for finite numbers of
repetitions, but forever.
And in C, there is a way to do this,
but it's a little weird looking.
There's no forever keyword.
But you can use the while
loop or, as you inferred,
you can actually use the for loop
without a condition in the middle.
So here, I can actually say this.
If I want to do
something forever, I want
to make sure that the answer to my
question, the Boolean expression,
is always true, always
true, always true,
the easiest way to achieve that goal
is just literally write "true" there
because true is true no matter what.
And it's a trick for
making the loop forever
go around and around,
as you might if you
want the cat to live
forever and meow incessantly
or if it is a clock that you
want to tick forever or the like.
So here, for instance, is how we
might have a cat meow endlessly,
using this so-called for loop instead.
But recall that in Scratch,
we also had this ability
to create some of our own puzzle pieces.
And this, too, is something that we're
going to be able to do here in C.
And let me propose
that we do exactly that
by introducing the C analog of this.
So here, for instance, is,
in Scratch, our definition
of a function called meow
whose sole purpose in life
was to just play the sound
"meow" until it's done.
This is going to look a
little weird at first.
But you'll notice some
similarities with main.
So recall this thing I keep typing with
main, int main(void), int main(void).
That's just the "when green flag
clicked" equivalent for today.
But if you want to create your own
puzzle piece or your own function in C,
you, for now, literally do this.
You say, void, the name of the
function you want to create, and then
void in parentheses.
And technically what this means is
that this function has no return value.
It doesn't hand you anything
back like get_string or get_int.
And the "void" in parentheses
means it takes no inputs.
It only meows.
You don't have to tell it how to meow.
It's just going to meow.
So no arguments, so to speak.
This literally just prints out "meow."
But what this does for me is it
abstracts away the idea of meowing.
I don't need to know how to
use printf or that you're
using printf to make the cat meow.
I now have a function in life called
meow because in Scratch, recall,
I used it like this.
When the green flag is clicked, I could
repeat three times this new custom
puzzle piece.
But in C, I could now do this.
In my main program, I can use a for
loop just like we saw a moment ago,
copy/pasted from earlier.
But now I can call my own
C function called meow.
And let me go ahead now and do this.
If I go over to my C code here,
back in VS Code, let me go ahead
and delete everything inside main.
Let me go ahead and do for int i
equals 0, i is less than 3, i++.
Inside of my curly braces, let
me go ahead and say "meow."
But I now need this meow
function to exist because if I
do "make meow" again, notice error.
"Implicit declaration of function
meow is invalid in C99"--
the 1999 version of C.
What does that mean?
Well, it doesn't know
what the meow function is.
And the meow function is not in CS50.h.
It's not in stdio.h.
I have to create it.
So let me type out or really copy/paste
what I had on the screen a moment ago--
"void meow meow"--
[CHUCKLES] "void meow(void)" printf,
quote, unquote, "meow," close quote,
semicolon.
But here, too, let me
scooch this down a bit
so you can see all the code at once.
Let me now do make meow.
And unfortunately, I
still have an error.
If I scroll up, still
on line 7 of meow.c,
my compiler thinks that meow is
invalid, that it does not exist.
This too is a common mistake.
And as simple as this code might
be in spirit, where did I screw up?
Yeah, in the middle.
STUDENT: You need to define the
function like above where you use it.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I need to define
the function before I use it.
So again, C is going
to take you literally.
If you try to call meow on line 7,
you better not define it on line 11.
You better define it higher up.
So the simplest fix is
going to be just to do this.
Let me clear my terminal.
Let me highlight and just
delete the meow function.
And let me just paste it up here.
And this will actually
solve the problem.
Make meow now works.
And if I do ./meow, that, too, works.
But this isn't really the best solution
because if your solution is constantly,
oh, well, just put it up there,
put it up there, put it up there,
I bet we could contrive
a situation where
one function needs to
be above the other,
but it needs to be above the other.
And that's just not
going to work in general.
And more importantly, it just pushes
main lower and lower and lower
in your file.
But the whole point
of your main function
is like, that's the entry point.
That is what happens when
the green flag is clicked.
And so just in terms of user
conventions, it's just useful for main
to always be at the top of a file
because then you can find it fast.
Your friends can, your TFs can
find it quickly if it's at the top.
So the other solution here would
be to leave meow at the bottom
and leave main at the top.
But this is the only time, if
I may, that copy/paste is OK.
What I've highlighted here in line 11 is
what's called the function's prototype.
It is enough information to give you the
return type, the name of the function,
and the return value--
and any arguments.
And so if you just copy/paste that
one line and end it with a semicolon
up there, that's enough
of a hint to the compiler
that, OK, it doesn't
exist yet, but it will.
And it will look like that.
That's the only time
it's OK to copy/paste
the very first line of a
function you've written
to the top of the file
with a semicolon so
that you can make the compiler happy.
So if I do make meow now, still no
errors. ./meow, and it now works.
But let me add one final feature,
coming back to Scratch here.
And then it's time for a snack.
So here, recall, was sort of the last
fancy thing we did in Scratch, where
we created not only our
own custom puzzle piece,
but it took an input so that we didn't
need to keep using the loop ourself.
We could just let the meow
function be told how many times
do you want the cat to meow.
So in C, we don't have to make
that many changes except this.
We change the prototype to take
an argument inside of parentheses.
And this is the syntax for that.
If you want your own function in
C to take one or more arguments,
you give the arguments a name, n,
or whatever you want to call it.
But you have to tell C what
the type of that input is.
So it's an int n.
So it knows it's a number.
And then you can just
use n in your program.
So instead of hard coding,
typing manually the number 3,
I'm just using n here.
So this is equivalent to what I did with
Scratch, by just dragging and dropping
the n variable there.
And then "meow" will get
printed that many times.
If I want to then use this-- notice,
this is the last version of the cat
that we did last week-- you
just say "meow" this many times.
So in C, this is where now
the code gets very succinct
because all the main part of the
program does is meow three times.
So this, again, is an abstraction.
I don't need to know, care, or
remember how meow is implemented.
I just need to know what its return
value, its name, and any arguments
thereto are.
So if I make this change,
I think we can get the cat
to meow any number of times.
Let me go back over to my C code here.
Let me go back into the file and
change "void" here to be int n,
where n just means number.
I could use i, but n tends to be
a quantity instead of a counter.
I then, inside of this function,
am going to do a for loop--
for int i get 0; i less than n--
instead of 3-- i++.
And then inside of here,
I'll paste that "meow" again.
I need to change my prototype to be
identical, so another copy/paste,
or just manually edit it.
But now notice what's
cool about main, is
that now I can meow maybe three times.
Make meow, Enter, ./meow.
OK, or if I really want to be cool,
I can change this to 30,000 times.
Go back here, make meow.
Increase the size of my terminal window
for a dramatic pre-break flourish.
And there are 30-- that was a fast cat.
There are 30,000 meows.
I think now let's go ahead and take--
that's a lot-- a 10-minute break.
We'll see you in 10.
Cookies are now served outside.
All right, so we are back.
And I realize this has
been a lot so far, right?
So there's a lot of new syntax.
There's a lot of translation
of Scratch over to C.
But among the goals of having
spent last week in Scratch
and having spent problems at 0 in
Scratch is that none of today's ideas
are really all that new.
It's just a lot of syntax that
will get more comfortable and more
in your muscle memory as time passes.
Up until now, though, we've focused
largely on these side effects,
like things happening on the screen.
And that was akin to the speech bubble
appearing in the world of Scratch.
But let's focus for just a bit--
before we then explore things
we can't do very well
in code-- on return
values instead in C.
We've seen them already.
Like, get_string returns a value.
Get_int returns a value, a
string and an int respectively.
But what if we want to make our
own functions that don't just
meow and visually have this side
effect of meowing on the screen
but actually hand us back some value?
Well, I bet we can do
this in C, as well.
Well, let me propose
that to go that route--
let me go back to VS Code here.
And let's make our
very simple calculator
that just adds some numbers together.
But the same calculator,
we'll soon see, is
going to get us into trouble if you
don't understand what the computer is
doing underneath the hood.
Let me go ahead and run
code of, say, calculator.c.
And in here, let me go
ahead and give myself
access to the CS50 library with CS50.h,
the stdio.h library with stdio.h,
int main(void), which, again, we'll
just take for granted today that we have
to include atop any of these programs.
And let's just add two numbers
together-- super simple calculator.
So it gives me a variable called x.
Assign it the return value of get_int.
And I'll ask the user to give us x.
Give me another variable called y.
Assign it the return
value of get_int again.
But this time, ask the user for y.
And then, lastly, let's just go ahead
and print out the value of x plus y.
But I don't think I can
get away with something
like this, x plus y
semicolon, because if I
do this, based on what
we've seen before,
what's actually going
to get printed out?
STUDENT: x plus y.
DAVID MALAN: Right,
literally like x plus y.
So I think this is where I need
the F in "printf" for formatting.
What I think I really want to do is
print out the value of some placeholder
because, what do I want to
substitute for percent i
maybe as a second argument
to printf intuitively?
Maybe just x plus y.
So indeed, I can get away with
this because it turns out in C,
there's a bunch of arithmetic operators,
all of the ones that you might expect,
including addition, subtraction,
multiplication, division,
and even this one, the
so-called modulo operator,
which generally gives us the ability
to calculate a remainder when
you divide one number by another.
But I'll keep it simple with addition.
And indeed, with printf, if I want
to print out the value of x plus y,
I can do that.
But I have to tell printf what kind
of value to expect, an integer,
thus the percent i
instead of %s for string.
And I think this should do the job.
So let me go back to my terminal.
Make calculator, Enter.
All is well so far. ./calculator,
and let's keep it simple--
1 for x, 2 for y.
And indeed, I get 3 as the output.
It's not very dynamic.
It can't do a subtraction or
multiplication or much more.
But it does at least do
those kinds of calculations.
But let me propose now that we
maybe make a reusable addition
function, right, because addition
is something I'm going to do a lot.
And maybe it should be
abstracted away with a function
just like meowing was
abstracted away a moment ago.
So let me go ahead and
instead of doing this,
let me go ahead and give
myself a function called add,
but instead of last time
where I had a meow function,
I'm obviously going to
call this "add" instead.
And instead of last time,
taking in no arguments,
I think I want add to
work a little differently.
I don't want add necessarily
to take an argument yet,
but I do want add to
return some type of value.
And just intuitively, what type of value
should an addition function return?
STUDENT: An integer.
DAVID MALAN: An integer, so an int.
So I'm going to change void, which
means the absence of a return value--
nothing's coming back--
to literally "int."
But I'm not going to change the
thing inside parentheses yet.
I'm going to go ahead and
copy my prototype up here.
And I'm going to make this
change, return x plus y.
And then here, instead of printing out
x plus y, let's go ahead and do this.
Let me give myself a third
variable just for now.
z equals the return
value of this brand-new
add function that's going
to add x plus y for me.
And then let me print
out the value of z.
Instead of x plus y, I'm
outsourcing now to this add function
so it will do the addition of x plus y.
So similar in spirit to meowing,
but the return values, I claim,
are about to create an issue.
So let me make calculator again.
And there's definitely some errors.
So here we have, "use of
undeclared identifier x."
And that's on line 17.
So that's pretty far down in the file.
So specifically, my compiler does
not like my use of x on line 17.
But wait a minute, x is
clearly defined on line 8.
What intuitively might
explain this issue
even if you've never programmed before?
Yeah?
STUDENT: Well, because x and y are
defined in the main function, not
the add function.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, because x and y
are defined in the main function,
not in the add function.
So the term of art here that
we're about to introduce
is something called "scope."
So "scope" just refers to the
context in which variables exist--
the context in which variables exist.
So by that, I mean this.
On line 8, I've declared x.
On line y, I've declared--
[CHUCKLES] on line 9, I've declared y.
But the catch is-- and here's where
the curly braces are helpful--
those variables only exist in the
context of the outer curly braces
that are nearest to them, like this.
So I can use x and y on lines
10, 11, 12, and even up to 13,
but not thereafter.
So I certainly can't use
x down here on line 7.
But this is a problem, because if
add's purpose in life is to add x and y
but add can't access x plus y,
well, we have an issue of scope.
Like, x and y are not in
scope for this add function.
But that's OK because remember that
every function we've seen thus far
can have maybe a return
value or a side effect,
but it can also take 0 or one or two
or more inputs, known as arguments.
So what if I instead do this?
Let me clear my terminal window.
And let me update add
to not take nothing
as input but maybe two integers.
And I'll call them arbitrarily a and b.
But I have to tell the
compiler what type of arguments
they are-- two integers,
one after the other.
And now what I can do is this.
Let me change this up
here, too-- int a, int b--
just so that the prototype
is exactly the same.
And the only purpose of this prototype
is just to avoid the previous error,
where the compiler didn't
realize add was going to exist
because it came later in the file.
So here on line 11 now, if I
want to add two values, x and y,
this is now the syntax.
We saw syntax in Scratch
for passing in inputs
to tell it how many times to meow.
So this is just telling add what
two numbers to add together.
So now I have to change this to a
plus b, for reasons we'll soon see.
And let me see if this is right.
Make calculator.
So far so good. ./calculator.
Let's do 1 and 2 for
x and y respectively.
And hopefully we should, again, see 3.
Now, what's going on?
So here, again, if I zoom in on my add
function, this "int" here on the left,
on line 15, means what about add?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: This means that it has
a return value, that it's an int.
So it's going to hand me back,
metaphorically, a slip of paper
with an answer on it
that is of type integer.
It's not a word, like my name.
It's a number instead.
These mentions of int here and here
are inside the parentheses, which means
this function, add, takes two inputs.
The first is an int.
The second is an int.
And just so we have something to call
them, I call them a and b respectively.
So what happens essentially when I
call the add function now on line 11,
I'm kind of passing in x.
I'm passing in y.
But the add function is going to
think of them as a and b respectively.
It could call them anything I want.
I could change this to the
word "first" and "second."
And then I could literally
change this to "first + second."
Those are perfectly acceptable
as argument or variable names.
But who really cares?
Like, a and b for such a simple
function is perfectly reasonable, too.
Technically, if your
mind is going there,
I could even call them
the exact same thing.
But let me propose for today,
certainly don't do that because it just
confuses things if you've got x's
and y's here, x's and y's here,
but they're clearly different.
Just don't do that.
Try to come up with different
variables just to keep yourself sane.
But here, I have a function that takes
now two integers, a and b respectively.
It just returns the sum of them
so that I can now store the return
value of add in a variable called z.
And then, quite simply, print it out.
But there's one other
thing I can do here.
Now, if we think about design, even
if you've never programmed before,
do I really need the variable z?
Because I'm defining it on line 11, and
then I'm quickly using it on line 12,
and that's it?
Like, sometimes you
don't need variables.
And they might make
your code more readable.
But strictly speaking-- and this is
just kind of like substitution in math--
if z is the same thing as "add
(x, y)," well, let me go ahead
and just delete line 11 altogether.
Let me get rid of mention of z.
You can actually get
away with doing this.
And much like the Join block in
Scratch, where I kind of overlaid it
on the Say block, kind of stacking
them, you can stack functions in C,
or nest them really,
kind of mathematically.
Honestly, it makes it
a little harder to read
because your mind has to dive in
conceptually deeper and deeper
into this second argument.
But it's perfectly acceptable, too.
And just to connect the dots to
maybe something from high school,
this is kind of analogous
to a function in math class
being like f of x, where
f is some function name,
x is some arbitrary
input to that function.
And when you start to put
functions inside of functions
so that the output of one
becomes the input to the next,
it's like using this syntax,
f of g of x and so forth.
If you've never seen
that before, don't worry.
But if you have, it's a way
to connect some of these dots.
Any questions, though,
on just this idea of now
having a function that doesn't
just have a side effect
but instead has a return value?
Yeah, in back?
STUDENT: In our declaration
of main, why did we
show it as returning an
integer instead of void?
DAVID MALAN: In our definition
of main, why did I do, what?
STUDENT: Why do we show
it as returning an integer
instead of returning as void?
DAVID MALAN: Oh, a really good
question that I was trying
to sweep under the rug for today.
But in every one of
our programs thus far,
I have indeed said "int main(void)."
Technically speaking, whenever you
write a program and it finishes running,
it actually returns a
value somewhat secretly.
It returns the number 0 by
convention, which means all is well.
And it can return any other
integer if something goes wrong.
In fact, on your Mac, PC, or
even phone, if you've ever
gotten like a weird message on the
screen, like something went wrong
and it's like a weird numeric code,
like error negative 129, or something
arbitrary like that, that tends
to mean that some program running
on your Mac, PC, or phone had something
go wrong with the main function.
And that is the number
that was returned.
But that's more than we
want to talk about today.
But we'll come back to this.
But main always returns a number.
By default, it is 0.
More on that soon.
All right, so with that
said, let's actually tease
apart what it is we've been
using underneath the hood
here a little bit by returning
to VS Code's interface itself.
It turns out that all
this time, even though I
keep alluding to macOS and
Windows, which like 99% of us
are probably running on
our laptops or desktops,
there's actually other very popular
operating systems in the world,
among which is Linux.
So Linux is a very
popular operating system,
the thing that turns on--
the thing that boots up
when you first turn on a computer.
And it's very commonly
used for servers nowadays.
All of CS50's own servers
run some version of Linux.
Those students more
comfortable sometimes
run Linux on their own Macs or PCs even.
So Linux is a very
popular operating system.
And it's particularly characterized
by its textual interface,
its command-line interface, even though
it also comes with graphical ones,
as well.
So again, this term we started today
with, a graphical user interface
is a thing with menus and buttons.
It's literally what you and I
use every day on our devices,
otherwise known as a GUI.
But today onward, you'll
get more comfortable
with and more practice
with this terminal window
down here, which represents a
command-line interface, or CLI.
And just so you have a mental model
of what's going on in the cloud here,
when you access cs50.dev, you are
accessing this version of VS Code
in the cloud, a piece of software
just running in a browser.
But that piece of
software is automatically
connected to your very own personal
server in the cloud, so to speak.
Technically speaking,
it's a "docker container."
But it means that you have essentially
your own mini server in the cloud
that only you have access to.
And that server or container is running
an operating system called Linux.
And in fact, every time I've
been running a command down here,
whether it's code or make
or ./hello or anything else,
I've been running commands from here in
Sanders Theatre on a server somewhere
in the cloud, my own
Linux container or server.
And you'll have the same yourself.
This is the thing that
we have pre-configured
for you by installing the compiler
in so many other pieces of software
you'll soon see in the class.
But underneath the hood, then, of Linux
is a soon-to-be familiar environment
that allows you to run
different types of commands.
And those commands
include things like this.
And this is something you'll
develop muscle memory for over time.
But I wanted to give you a sense of some
of the most popular textual commands
because we're essentially
about to take away
muscle memory you have from a GUI
world and have you type out words that
represent double-clicking on
things, dragging on other things,
and other such commands that
you and I take for granted.
It'll be a little painful at
first in the first days or weeks,
but it will make you far more productive
long term so that even after CS50,
if you start using your programming
skills in some other domain, class,
or real-world job, you'll just
be a lot faster at the keyboard
and able to do more work more quickly.
So with that said, let me go
back to VS Code over here.
I'm going to go ahead and open
up my File Explorer over here.
And you'll see at left
all of the files that I've
created thus far in class
and all of the programs
that I've compiled thus far in class.
I also have this source
1 directory, which
you can download from the course's
website, which has all of today's code
pre-written in advance, so you
don't have to type everything
that I literally type.
But all of these files are
things that I've created.
And you'll see that in
white are the C files.
And grayed out are actually the
binary files, the machine code
that I created that I was running.
So you can click on any of these
files in VS Code to open them.
For instance, here is hello.c.
And voila, it opens in the text editor.
But if I try to open "hello,"
that's not going to work,
because that's zeros and ones.
And frankly, the computer could
show me all those zeros and ones,
but it's just not going to be useful.
And honestly, it's too easy to make
one mistake and break the whole thing.
So instead, VS Code says that it can't
display the text, because it's binary
or maybe unsupported more generally.
So know that you want to only click
on the .c files when writing C code.
But let me go ahead
and do something else.
Suppose that I decide that, wait a
minute, we're nearing the end of class.
And we're not done yet, but what if
I want to change hello.c to goodbye.c
or if I want to change meow.c to
woof.c and turn it into a dog?
Well, let's actually do that.
I could go over here and right
click or Control click on the file,
just like on a Mac or PC.
I can find the Rename option.
And I can do it all via the GUI.
But you should get more comfortable
using commands like these here.
And among the commands on this
list are "mv" for move, a.k.a.
rename.
So for instance, if I want to
change meow.c to be woof.c instead,
I literally type "mv" space,
the original file name, space,
and the new file name.
So this is very similar
to what I've already
been doing with the code
program or the make program.
I not only type the name of
the command but also the thing
that I want to code or the
thing that I want to make.
In this case, I type the thing that
I want to move from old to new.
Now, if I hit Enter in a moment,
watch on the left-hand side,
meow.c in the GUI should
automatically change
even though I'm doing this all via
the command-line keyboard interface.
And now it becomes woof.c.
I mean, it's not all that exciting.
But this is just to say that
they are one and the same.
One is a GUI, one is a CLI,
but it's the same exact thing.
Moreover, let me go ahead
and close now the GUI
at left, the so-called explorer.
And in my terminal window alone,
now I'm kind of out of my element,
like wait a minute, what was
the file I created earlier?
Well, there's other commands as well.
On this list is, coincidentally,
"ls," which lists
the file in your current folder.
And as you might have gleaned
here, "mv" for move, "ls" for list,
CS people like to be
succinct, terse, and type
the minimal number of keystrokes.
That's why these are all abbreviated
commands instead of full words.
But if I go back to my terminal
window and type "ls," voila,
there is exactly the same contents
of my server but displayed textually.
And there's some heuristics here.
In green with an asterisk
is all of the programs
that I made with make
that are executable.
So the asterisks just means this
is executable with dot-slash.
Meanwhile, the source 1 directory, which
only I have because I downloaded it
in advance, has a slash to indicate
that it's a folder instead of a file.
But all of these white files ending
in .c we created together here today.
Now, what if I really am embarrassed
by my very first program, hello.c?
Well, I can very destructively go
and use the rm command for remove.
And rm hello.c is going to
prompt me, a little cryptically,
"remove regular file 'hello.c'?"
And amazingly, this rm program has code
just like we wrote earlier for agree.c,
where I can type 'y' to delete it.
I can type 'n' not to delete it.
But let's delete it.
Let's go ahead and hit y, enter.
Nothing seems to happen.
But in general, that's a good thing.
But if I type "ls" again,
notice what is now missing?
And in fact, the list
is a little shorter.
So it's one line instead of two.
"hello.c" is now gone.
Now, if you do that, there are not
easy ways to get the file back.
So don't do that unless
you really want to.
But there are backups maintained
of these files, as well.
Well, what else is there, too?
Well, there's all of
these other commands.
And you'll experience them over time.
Like, "cp" is copy.
"mkdir" is make directory.
"rmdir" is remove directory.
And for instance, let me
just show you one folder.
If I type "ls," there's
that source 1 folder
that I claimed I downloaded in advance.
If you want to see what's
there, you can type "cd"
for change directory, source 1, enter.
And voila, notice that your
prompt has now changed.
And let me clear the screen.
Just as a visual reminder of where you
are, you can see before the dollar sign
now the name of the folder
that you're inside of.
So in Mac or Windows, you'd see
obviously a graphical folder.
Here, you just see a little textual
reminder of where you now are.
And if I type "ls," you'll see that
I wrote a crazy number of files
before class.
And each of these represents
different versions of the files
that we've been coding here
in real time that I usually
have printouts of just to
go through things in series
so you have copies online, as well.
So in short, all of these commands,
if you've never used them before,
they will soon become
like muscle memory.
And they do the most
basic of operations.
But there will be other
commands that we'll see over
time that do even much more than that.
But let's go ahead now and
solve some actual problems.
And it's no coincidence that
we keep showing or alluding
to Super Mario Brothers in
some form, an older game
from the Nintendo Entertainment
System, that allows you ultimately
to have this two-dimensional world,
where Mario moves up and down
and side scrolls from left to right.
But you'll see we can distill
even some aspects of "Mario"
into some fairly representative
programming problems.
And in fact, let me propose
that we consider this screen
from the original Super Mario Brothers.
So there's these four blocks in
the sky, each with a question mark.
And if you click on one of
these-- or if Mario jumps up
underneath each of
these question marks, he
gets like a coin or
something else that pops out.
Let's distill this, though, into its
essence and consider in C, how can
we make, not a blue sky yet, not
a green grassy hill, and so forth,
but how can we just make
four question marks in a row,
because I dare say that we do have the
building blocks via which to do this.
Well, the simplest way might be to
go over here and run code of mario.c.
And then in mario.c, let's include
some stdio.h so we have printf.
Let's do int main(void),
as we keep doing.
And inside of main, let's
keep it super simple--
1, 2, 3, 4, backslash n.
Doesn't get much simpler than that.
This is not going to be
the prettiest of games.
But if I make Mario now, ./mario, I
get my four question marks in the sky.
All right, so it's not
all that interesting.
But this is clearly a candidate for
what type of programming feature.
STUDENT: Scratch.
DAVID MALAN: Not to Scratch, though
Scratch would make it more interesting.
yeah?
STUDENT: A loop.
DAVID MALAN: So some
kind of loop, right?
So print the thing out
iteratively instead.
So let me do that.
Instead of just printing
this out all at once,
let me go ahead and remove this and
do for int i gets zero; i less than 4;
i++.
And then in here, let me go ahead
and print out just one question mark
instead.
And now let's run this.
So "make mario" to
recompile it, ./mario.
And does anyone not want
me to hit Enter yet?
Why?
STUDENT: Because it's
gonna print a new line.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it's going to
print out a new line every time.
So notice it's four question marks,
but there each on its own line.
All right, well, let me fix this.
It's obviously because
of the backslash n.
So let me remove that.
Let me rerun make mario, ./mario.
And it's better in one
way but worse in another.
So wait, but now the
dollar sign is doing
that thing where it's
on the same line, which
just looks stupid if nothing else.
So how can I fix that?
Yeah?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so logically, we
don't have that many building blocks
today.
It's a lot of new syntax, but
it's not that many new ideas.
Let's just use printf to print
out literally one and only
one of these backslash n's,
but outside of the loop so
it happens after all four
of those have been printed.
All right, let me do make
mario again, ./mario.
And OK, now we're back in business.
So sort of silly syntactical
details, but if you
reduce the problem to its essence,
it should hopefully, logically,
become clear over time.
All right, well, how about not just
something like that but vertical?
Well, we've done something
vertical already.
And so I can imagine we
could change the program
to very simply print out three bricks
instead of four question marks.
But what if we consider
a two-dimensional world?
And later on in this game
if you go underground,
everything looks like
this with lots of bricks.
And let me propose, for
the sake of discussion,
that this big wall here is
like a 3-by-3 grid of bricks.
So it's not just a single brick.
It's like three by three, or nine total.
Now things get interesting.
And let me go back to mario.c.
I could take the easy road out
and just say, all right, well,
let's printf, how about 1, 2,
3, backslash n, close quote.
And then, OK, let me just copy/paste.
And I'm using hashes instead
of the actual bricks.
But aesthetically, it's pretty close.
Let me now go ahead and
"make mario" again, ./mario.
And it doesn't quite look like a square.
But that's just because the hashes are
a little taller than they are wide.
But it is correct,
but not well designed.
So here, too, what would be better
designed than just hardcoding, typing
literally all of these hashes?
Yeah?
STUDENT: We could use maybe two loops.
DAVID MALAN: Interesting, two loops.
And why two loops instead of one?
STUDENT: Oh, wait, nevermind.
Well, I was going to say you could
do it one for vertical and one
for horizontal.
DAVID MALAN: OK, it's
the right instinct.
So one for vertical, one for horizontal.
And even though these
predate most of us,
old-school typewriters
you might know or might
recall that if you feed a piece of
paper into it, you can print like line,
then it scrolls, line, then it
scrolls, line, then it scrolls.
This is kind of how the
terminal window works, too.
You can print rows and
columns, but you have
to print one row at a time, one
row at a time, one row at a time.
It's not easy, but it is possible
to go backwards and go up and down.
But just going row by row
by row is more typical.
So how can I do this?
Well, I could use at least one
and maybe even indeed two loops.
And this is where we're just
now composing different ideas
from today and even last week.
So let me go ahead and say, for
int i gets 0; i less than 3--
for a 3-by-3 grid--
i++.
And now let me cheat slightly.
Let me print out just three
of these here, and that's it.
So I'm kind of cheating.
I'm printing out rows dynamically, but
I'm still printing three columns all
in one breath.
But let's see what happens.
Make mario, ./mario, and it does work.
But what if you said, no, I
want 4 by 4 or 5 by 5 or 6 by 6?
Now I have to change the 3 to a 6, and
I have to add another three hashes here.
Things get messy if we don't
do this mathematically.
So let me now do this instead.
Why don't I go ahead and
print out every row at a time.
But for each row, let me use another
loop to decide, like, rat-a-tat-tat,
from left to right, how
many do I want to print.
So to do this, I could
do another for loop.
I could call this variable something
different. j is pretty common.
We start at i, we go to j.
If you go past k, maybe l, you're
probably doing something wrong.
You don't want nested, nested,
nested loops, but two is OK.
j equals 0; j is less than 3; j++.
And then here, I can print out a
single one of these and no new line.
I don't want to screw
up like I did before.
So I'll just do one.
Let me go ahead and do
make mario now, ./mario.
But when I hit Enter,
this is not correct yet.
What's it going to look like?
STUDENT: A single line?
DAVID MALAN: A single line
of nine hashes, I think,
because I never used
a single backslash n.
So that looks wrong.
So between what line number should
I insert a printf of backslash n?
Let me look a little
farther back if I can.
How about over here?
Yeah?
STUDENT: 10 and 11.
DAVID MALAN: Between 10 and 11.
So I'm going to go in here.
I'm going to add printf, quote,
unquote, "backslash n" semicolon.
Let me go back and recompile mario--
./mario.
And crossing fingers-- voila, perfect.
I printed out now a 3-by-3.
Now, it's correct.
It's not, if we want to be
really nitpicky, maybe still not
the best design.
Where am I perhaps repeating myself?
Yeah?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I mean,
it's not a huge deal.
But now I have two, people
would call these magic numbers.
"Magic" in the sense of,
where did that come from?
You just randomly put it
in the middle of your code.
And you also put the same thing here.
Now I have to make sure I don't screw up
and make one change but not the other.
So it turns out we can factor these out.
I can actually do something
like this, int n equals 3.
And then I can just
change this to n and this
to n, which is marginally
better because now
I only have to change n
in one place if I want
to make this thing bigger or smaller.
It's still going to work the same.
So make mario, ./mario.
There's our 3-by-3.
But if I want to make a 5-by-5, let me
change the n to 5, rerun make mario,
./mario.
And now it's a bigger grid, 5-by-5.
But this is a little fragile.
And it turns out there's another
trick we should introduce.
It turns out that C supports
what are called constants,
whereby if you have a variable that
you want to exist because it's useful
but you don't want to
accidentally change it,
or if you're working with a partner
in class or a colleague at work,
you don't want your partner or
colleague to accidentally change
that value with their own code, you
can go into your code and tell C,
this is actually a constant
integer, a const, so to speak.
And this will just prevent
you or someone else
from doing something stupid by
accidentally changing it elsewhere.
The code is still going
to work the same, ./mario,
but you won't be accidentally able
to change it very easily to something
else.
And honestly, what we've now
done, too, is set ourselves
up to make this more dynamic.
Let me go up here, and let me add the
CS50 library so that we have access
to get_int because now
we could do something
fancy like ask the get_int function
for the size of this brick wall.
And then we can use n dynamically.
So for instance, let me increase
the size of my terminal, make mario,
./mario, size 3.
Gives me a 3-by-3.
./mario size 5 gives me a 5-by-5.
./mario, how about 50, gives me a
crazy big one, but it's all dynamic.
And now I don't have to
even change the code.
It just now works.
As an aside, if you're wondering
how I type so darn fast,
sometimes it's just because
I'm hitting the up arrow.
It turns out that Linux
will remember, if you
configure it this way, all
of your previous commands.
So if you hit up, up, up, I can go
through the past couple of hours
of commands that I've typed,
which is useful sometimes--
not for hours of commands
but the past few--
just to save yourself some keystrokes.
And another trick in a
terminal window is to do this.
If I do ./ma and I get bored and
I don't want to type out "rio,"
I can also just hit Tab, and it will
autocomplete based on the characters
that do match.
So those kinds of tricks, too,
will save you time over time.
But let's do this.
It's kind of broken,
arguably, if I do this.
How about "cat?"
All right, well, that works.
That prevents me from
doing something stupid
because get_int only accepts integers.
But it will accept 0,
which does nothing.
It will accept negative
1, which does nothing.
And that's not bad.
It's not doing something weird.
But it would be nice to
catch that and force the user
to give us a positive integer
instead so we at least
see something on the screen.
So let me go back into my code,
and let me propose that now
that we have the CS50 library, why
don't we do something like this?
I'm going to change this.
I'm going to get rid of
the constant just in case
the user needs to type it again.
And what if I do this?
While n is less than 1--
so if it's 0, negative 1, negative
2, or whatever, let's go ahead
and again ask the user for an int,
and ask them for the size again.
And therefore, only once
n is not less than 1 will
this loop break out and will
proceed with the rest of the code.
So now let me try this.
Make mario, ./mario 0--
didn't like that.
Negative 1-- didn't like that.
Negative 2-- didn't like that.
3-- it did like that.
So using a loop now, I can ensure
that the human is providing me
with input that I actually want.
So this is correct.
But I dare say 6 through
10 could be done better.
Why is this poorly
designed instinctively?
Yeah?
STUDENT: There's repetition.
DAVID MALAN: What's the repetition,
to be clear, what lines?
STUDENT: Lines 6 and 9.
DAVID MALAN: 6 and 9.
OK, so they're literally the same,
and that's generally not a good thing.
And maybe I could change this
one to remind the user like, hey,
that's not a positive number.
So you might want to
customize the message.
But just having copy/paste here for
the most part is not a good thing.
So it turns out-- and there's just one
feature of C we wanted to introduce you
to today-- it turns out there's one
other way that would actually help us
eliminate this redundancy of using
get_int twice and particularly asking
literally the same question-- size--
twice in duplicate.
So I'm actually going
to go into my code here,
and I'm going to delete the loop
as we've written it thus far.
And instead of using a
while loop, I'm going
to introduce instead
something that we typically
call a do while loop, which
is a little bit different.
Indeed, we begin with the
keyword "do," and then
inside of the curly braces,
what I'm going to do here
is that thing I might want to do
once and more times thereafter.
So for instance, I'm going to say n
equals get_int quote, unquote, "size."
And then at the bottom of
this block of code, then
I'm going to use the keyword "while,"
as well as parentheses as always
for a Boolean expression.
And here.
I'm going to ask the question,
do this while n is less than 1.
But there's one fix I still need to do
here because notice on the current line
8, I actually haven't given n a type.
I haven't declared n yet.
But it would not be correct to declare
n here, inside of that do block.
But why might that be?
Why would it not be a good thing to
declare n inside of these curly braces?
Yeah, so recall that this
is an issue of scope.
Recall that the scope of
a variable is generally
confined to the most recently opened
curly braces in which that variable is
declared.
And so if I declare
this variable on line 8,
I'm not going to be able
to use it on line 10.
But there is a fix, even though
it might look a little strange.
I'm going to go above my do block here.
And before I go into
this loop, I'm actually
going to declare n to be an integer,
but semicolon, end of thought.
I'm not going to bother
giving it a value, because I
know logically I'm going to end up
giving it a value anyway now on line 9.
And so what's different about
this version of the code
is that the do while loop ensures that
we prompt the user for input at least
once.
And then while that input is not what we
expect, for instance less than 1, then
it's going to execute
again, again, again.
And indeed, the semantics are just that.
Do the following while this
Boolean expression is true.
So if I go ahead now and rerun
make mario, compiles OK-- ./mario.
And now I'll go ahead and input
something that's not correct, like 0.
But I'm prompted again.
I'll input something like negative
1, and I'm prompted again.
But if I go ahead and
input, for instance, 10,
now, because that's a positive integer,
I indeed get a 10-by-10 grid of bricks.
And there's one other thing we should
introduce here, too, in C, too.
C supports comments.
And a couple of you
have asked about this
if you come from other
programming languages.
Suppose I want to remember what it
is I just did with this program.
Let me go in between lines 5 and 6 here
and do "// prompt user for positive
integer."
This is what's known as a comment.
And it's grayed out only in the
sense that the compiler is not
going to care about this.
The computer is not
This is a note to self, like a sticky
note in the context of Scratch.
And it starts with "//," which
essentially tells the compiler ignore
this, this is for the
human, not for the computer.
But this comment, so to speak, is a way
of just reminding yourself, reminding
your colleague,
reminding your TF what it
is a few lines of code are meant to do.
And now this comment might be print,
and how about n-by-n grid of bricks?
And what's nice about comments is that
theoretically you can get away with,
or someone else can get away
with, just reading this comment
and then not even have to
look at the rest of the code.
They can look at this comment and not
have to look at the rest of the code
because you've described for
them what it's meant to do.
Yeah?
STUDENT: I just had a question
about the hashtag [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
STUDENT: That's for [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Correct, the hash
sign in Python is a comment,
is not the same thing in C. In C, hash
include means to include the library's
header files in that way.
Other questions on these here tricks?
No?
All right, so as promised, what
is maybe C not actually good at?
Well, let me propose
that we consider what's
actually inside of your computer.
At the end of the day, whether it's
a Mac, PC, iPhone, Android, phone,
or some other computer device, there's
something that looks like this.
And this is memory, otherwise known
as RAM, or random access memory,
for reasons we'll get to in a few weeks.
But this is where data is stored.
This is where "hello, world" is stored.
This is where 1 and 2 and all
of those numbers are stored.
Any data in your program is stored
ultimately in the computer's memory.
And the most important takeaway
for today is that all of us
only have a finite amount
of memory in our devices.
You might have a high-end device
which has a lot of memory,
but it's still finite,
which means you can only
count so high with that device.
You can only store so many
files with that device.
There are fundamental physical
limitations even though mathematically,
theoretically, we should be
able to count toward infinity.
So what are the implications for this?
Well, consider this.
In the world of numbers, as per week
0, if you're only using three digits--
and I've grayed out the fourth one
just to make the point-- if you're only
using three digits, we can count from
0 to 1 in decimal, to 2, to3, to 4,
to 5, to 6, to 7.
And as soon as you count to 8,
you technically, per last week,
need a fourth bit.
But if you don't have it,
the number 7 might seem
to be followed by what number instead?
STUDENT: 0.
DAVID MALAN: 0.
The number overflows,
so to speak, right?
You carry the 1.
But if there's no place to put the 1,
because there's no fourth light bulb,
if there's no fourth transistor,
if there's no fourth bit,
the lower bits, the zeros, are going
to be mistaken for the number you
and I know is 0.
So integer overflow is
a thing in computers
whereby if you don't have enough
memory, if you count high enough,
the number will wrap around back to 0.
Or sometimes it will wrap
around to a negative number,
depending on whether the code supports
negative and positive numbers and 0
alike.
So that has some very
real world implications
in integer overflow that's sort
of a fundamental limitation of how
numbers are typically stored.
Now, thankfully, we
typically don't store things
based on number of digits
but number of bits.
And a bit is just a 0 or 1.
And recall from last week
that a common unit of measure
is minimally eight bits, or a
byte, but even more commonly is 32.
So for instance, here
are 32 bits, all zeros.
And if you do out the
math, this is the number
you and I know in
decimal is of course 0.
But if I change all 32 zeros to ones,
this is a really big number now.
If we're only using positive
numbers, not negatives,
what number roughly is this, 32 ones?
It's roughly 4 billion in total--
roughly 4 billion in total.
Why?
Well, if you've got 32 bits, each can
be two possible values, 0 or 1, that's
2 to the 32nd power, which is roughly--
I'll stipulate--
roughly 4 billion total.
The problem is, what if you
want to count to 4,000,000,001?
That's a bit of a white lie.
It's not precisely that.
But what if you want to
count just higher than that?
You'd need a 33rd bit
because all of the others
are going to go to 0 at that point,
and you might count from 1 to 2
to 3 to 4 billion back to 0, or worse
if you're dealing with negative numbers,
too.
So the fact that there are finitely many
bits used in computers is a problem.
And negative numbers do add a
complexity because this is specifically
the 4 billion in question--
4,294,968,295.
That is as high as you
can count with 32 bits
if you don't bother with negatives.
But if you want negative
numbers, you've got to half
that because you've got to save half
of them for negative, half of them
for positive, give or take.
And so if you're supporting
negative numbers, as you probably
should for a calculator, for
Microsoft Excel, Google Spreadsheets,
you can only count as high
up as 2 billion roughly,
or negative 2 billion roughly instead.
So it turns out that when you
are using data types in C,
you have some control over how
many bits are actually used.
And this list is longer
than we've covered today,
but we did talk about
integers for a while.
Those are, by convention
nowadays, 32 bits.
If that's not enough, you can upgrade
your variables to longs, which
tend to be 64 bits instead, which
isn't just twice as big as an integer,
it's actually 64 bits,
which is exponentially more.
It's an unpronounceable
number, at least for me.
That's a crazy big number,
but it's available to you.
Moreover, we can see this if we
actually are a little reckless with how
we're using code.
And just so you know
too, though, there are
functions even in
CS50's library that let
you use these larger values, get
long of course, will get you a long.
And this one's a little non-obvious,
but "%li" is the format code for printf,
just so you know, for printing a
long integer and not just an integer.
So it's two characters instead of one.
Suppose, though, we actually want to
use code involving some large numbers.
It turns out that certain
bad things can happen.
So let me go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go back
over to VS Code here,
and I'm going to modify my calculator
to do something that, at glance, should
be perfectly reasonable.
Let me go ahead and open
up calculator.c, as before.
And where we left off,
we had this add function.
And you know what?
I'm going to simplify it back
to its very original version.
I'm going to go ahead and
get rid of the add function
and just distill it to its essence,
which is not to add any more.
But let's just do division.
I want to print out this
time maybe x divided by y.
So here we go. x divided by y is a
nice simple program in my calculator.
Let me do make calculator
again, ./calculator.
And let's divide something like
1 divided by 3, which should--
hm, OK, weird.
It gave me 0 instead
of probably 0.3333333,
as you might have expected for 1/3.
So what might the takeaway there be?
Why am I seeing zero perhaps?
Yeah?
STUDENT: If 0's the integer [INAUDIBLE],,
then if you want decimals [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so 0 is an integer.
And indeed, that's what I'm
telling the thing to print.
And in fact, if we go over to my little
cheat sheet here of format codes,
I'm currently using %i.
I should actually, when I do division of
numbers that might have floating point
values, a decimal point
that floats left to right,
otherwise known as a real number,
I want to use %f for float instead.
So I'm actually going to
go back to my code here.
And let's try this-- %f instead of %i.
And let me go ahead
and "make calculator."
Huh, all right.
Well, this didn't work then.
"Format specifies type 'double,'
but the argument has type 'int.'
All right, so that, too,
is not quite working.
So I think I actually need to
make a change here further.
Let me actually go ahead and do this.
It turns out that
besides integers, there
are these things called
floats, and also doubles.
A float uses 32 bits, and
a double uses 64 bits.
And that doesn't
necessarily mean you can
count higher as much as
it means you can have
more numbers after the decimal point.
So if you want a more precise
value, you throw memory at it
by using a double and 64
bits instead of a float.
But we'll keep it simple, and
let me go ahead and do this.
Let me just do the math using the type
of variable that I should be here.
Let me do not int, but float
z equals x divided by y.
And now let me go ahead and
print out the value of z.
Strictly speaking, I
don't need the variable.
But I'm trying to be pedantic and
actually use a float explicitly
this time so we see a real number.
All right, let me go ahead and
do make calculator, ./calculator.
1 divided by 3 equals--
damn, now it's just showing me more
zeros, which clearly isn't the case.
Well, this is because of an issue
that we'll generally call truncation.
So truncation is just a term of art
that means if you take an integer
and you divide it by an integer,
even if you get a fractional value,
the fraction just gets thrown
away because you're only
doing integer-based math.
So if there's anything
after the decimal point,
it just gets truncated,
literally discarded.
So what should 1 divided by 3 be?
Obviously, 0.33333333-- ad nauseum.
Fortunately, you throw away
everything after the decimal point,
which leaves you still with just 0.
And even though I'm seeing more zeros,
that's because we threw away all
of the 3's.
That is just what happens
when you use integers and do
any kind of division like that.
But there is a solution.
We can actually convert, or cast,
integers to floating point values.
So we can tell C, I know
this is an integer now.
But go ahead and treat it as
though it has a decimal point, even
if it's .0 At the end of the number.
So I can go into this, and I can
use parentheses and literally write
"float" in parentheses.
And over here for y, I can literally use
parentheses and convert y to a float.
The term of art here is type casting.
You're converting one type to another
effectively, or technically treating
one type as though it's another
even if it doesn't necessarily
have a mathematical impact.
But what it means now is
that z will be defined
by dividing one float by another.
So truncation will not now happen.
So let me do make
calculator, ./calculator.
And now 1 divided by 3, there it is.
Now the math is actually correct.
But my God, we had to jump through
hoops just to get this to work.
So to be clear, the two issues
we-- well, the issue we encountered
was truncation.
If you divide an int by an int,
you will get an int no matter
what it should be mathematically.
But if you instead type cast the values,
the variables to a floating point
value, or a double for that matter, then
a float divided by a float will give
you a float and preserve
all of those 3's.
But here's another catch, or at least a
limitation potentially with computers.
What if I go ahead here and do--
let me do this.
Let me show you one trick here, even
though the syntax is a bit weird.
Instead of printing out %f
alone, let me print out % dot,
maybe 5f So this is weird syntax.
And it's only specific to printf.
"%.5f" means 'show me five
decimal places specifically.'
So if I do make calculator,
./calculator, 1, 3, voila,
I get five decimal places.
If I want six, let's do this.
I'll change the code to 6.
Make calculator, ./calculator, 1,
3, and now I get six 3's instead.
All right, well, wouldn't it be
nice to be even more precise?
Let's give me 20 significant
digits after the decimal point.
So make calculator, ./calculator,
1 divided by 3, and-- woo.
So your middle school teacher seems
to have lied to you at this point.
1 divided by 3 is apparently
not 0.33333 with a line over it,
or just infinite number of 3's.
OK, that's not quite the
right conclusion, though.
Oops.
Why might I be seeing
these weird numbers instead
of just lots of 3's, intuitively?
Why this rounding error?
Yeah?
STUDENT: The computer just has
a [? limited ?] [? memory. ?] So
there's [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
The computer only has limited
memory, finite memory.
So it just can't represent every
possible number in the universe
because we know from grade school there
are infinitely many of those numbers.
So what you're essentially seeing
is the closest it can actually get.
It's rounding to the nearest
floating point value, if you will.
And it also relates to how the
numbers themselves are represented
in memory underneath the hood.
I can do a little better, though.
Let me zoom out.
And let me upgrade, so to speak,
from 32 bits to 64 bits and use
doubles instead.
I can still use %f.
You don't use %d for double.
Let me do make calculator
again, ./calculator, 1, 3.
I get more 3's but still some rounding.
It's more precise, but
it's not 100% accurate,
because that's just not
going to be possible in terms
of the computer's memory.
So this is a whole other issue known
as floating point imprecision, which
is another type of limitation.
We saw integer overflow,
if integers can only
count so high before you run out
of bits and things wrap around.
Floating point imprecision
means that you can't possibly
represent the infinite number of real
numbers that exist in the universe
if you only have a
finite amount of memory.
You would need an infinite
number of bits, it would seem.
So these are two issues
that actually fundamentally
can influence the
correctness not only of
your code but code in the real world.
And case in point, back in my day--
I graduated in 1999--
and a lot of the world
thought the world was
going to end around then
because around the time the years
rolled over from 1999 to 2000,
there was a lot of old software
still running in the world.
And in fact, that old
software, reasonably so,
only used two digits to represent years.
Why?
Memory was very expensive early on.
And if you could use half as much
memory to store a year, that was a win.
That saved you money.
That saved you memory.
The problem though, of
course, is that a lot
of old software from the '70s and
prior was still running in 1999.
And unless companies or
individuals updated that software,
1999 might be mistaken for
the year 1900 instead of 2000,
because all of the code just
assumed that, of course,
we're talking about the 1900s.
This code is not going to
be running 50 years later,
but it was still in that case.
So people had to scramble,
and they essentially
had to solve this by using more
digits, so upgrading from two to four.
Nowadays, and really
since the '70s too, we've
used 32-bit integers
to keep track of time,
specifically keeping track
of the number of seconds
using an integer from January 1,
1970, the so-called epoch whereby
that's just an arbitrary date early on
where we just started counting time.
So all of the clocks in your
Macs, PCs, and phones pretty much
just have a single integer
that gets updated every second,
but it's just keeping track
not of absolute time per se,
but how many seconds have
passed since January 1, 1970,
just because that's
the date humans chose.
The problem is you can only
count as high as 4 billion,
give or take, with 32 bits and
actually 2 billion, give or take,
if you support negative
numbers, as well.
And the problem with that is that
we're about to trip over the same issue
again in not too long from now.
This is the 2038 problem because in the
year 2038, on that date, mark my words,
things could break again.
Why?
Because that 32-bit value is
going to accidentally wrap
around back to a 0 or a negative value.
So we're going to go through
the whole darn process again.
Now, thankfully the solution, as
you might expect, is kind of just
to kick the can even
further down the road
and use 64 bits, which I think will get
us another 290 million years of runway.
It's more than twice.
So it's not our problem
anymore at that point.
But that's fundamentally
going to be the solution.
But it will still be finite.
So we're just deferring
to our descendants
to actually deal with the issue
some millions of years from now
if these things are still running.
So if that does happen,
here's the specific date
that, in 2038, all of a
sudden our clocks will still
think because a negative number will get
subtracted to the current epoch time.
So it will think we're back in 1901.
So this has had some fun and
very real world implications.
So for instance, this is the game
Pac-Man, which you might have played.
It kind of came out around
my day, back in time.
And if you get to the 256th
level, this unfortunately
is what happens because
they didn't really
expect that players would spend all this
much time playing Pac-Man apparently.
And they didn't really
have a condition saying,
you win if you get to
the 255th or 266th level.
And so what happens here essentially
is that the whole screen gets very
garbled because there's an integer
in the original Pac-Man that
counts to 256, but that's too
big, so it wraps back around to 0.
And it doesn't know when to stop
printing fruits on the screen,
as in this case, to collect.
Another example of this is actually
from the original Donkey Kong
game, which looks something like this
in my day, too, whereby in Donkey Kong,
there was this mathematical
formula, whereby
the number of seconds you have to solve
the game was a function of 10 times
your current level
number plus the number 4.
That dictated how many seconds you get.
So of course, the higher the
level, you get more and more time
as the level climbs.
Unfortunately, once you hit level
22, the math ends up being 10 times
22 plus 4, which gives
you the number 260.
And they, too, were using
8-bit values, a single byte
to represent numbers, which
means 260 is bigger than 256.
And the way that math
worked out was, well,
260 minus 256, if it wraps back around,
gave people four seconds to solve level
22, which is just impossible.
Like, Mario can't even
get up a couple of levels
or so from where he actually was.
So that, too, was sort
of a well-known bug,
as well, since that
works out to be there.
Lastly, and this one is
all the more real, in 2015,
Boeing 787 was documented as having
not a hardware bug but a software bug
in the following sense.
"A model 787 airplane that has been
powered continuously for 248 days
can lose all of its power due to the
control unit simultaneously going
into failsafe mode.
This condition was caused by a
software counter that will overflow
after 248 days of continuous power.
Boeing at the time was in the process of
developing a CPU software upgrade that
will remedy the unsafe condition."
And people did the math.
It turns out that Boeing was probably
using an integer that was 32 bits.
And they were keeping track of time not
in seconds but hundredths of seconds,
because if you do out the math, after
a 32-bit value has reached 4 billion--
or 2 billion one hundredths of a second,
the number wraps around back to 0,
or negative 2 billion.
And the implications was literally
the plane's power would stop.
And if you can believe it, if you grew
up with Windows, macOS, or whatnot,
anyone want to conjecture
what the solution was
until Boeing updated their software?
STUDENT: Turn it off, turn it back on.
DAVID MALAN: Turn the
plane off, and turn it
back on because that has the effect
of resetting its memory and therefore
all of its variables back to 0.
So this is ultimately to say as you dive
into problem set 1, your first in C,
you, too, will make quite a few
mistakes when it comes to correctness.
You, too, will encounter opportunities
for better design and better style.
In the real world, there
are very much these issues.
So even if you struggle, know
that for better or for worse,
you're in very good company.
But some three months from now,
you will be in much better shape
because this was week
1, and this is CS50.
[APPLAUSE]
[INTRIGUING MUSIC]