[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right, this is CS50.
And this is week 5.
And among our goals for today are to
revisit some topics from past weeks
but to focus all the more on
design possibilities, particularly
by way of data structures.
So data structures, again, is this way
via which you can structure your data.
But more specifically
in C, It's how you can
use your computer's memory in
interesting and, daresay, clever ways
to actually solve
problems more effectively.
But we're going to see
today that there's actually
different types of data structures.
And we'll make the distinction
between abstractions,
like high-level descriptions
of these structures
and the lower-level implementation
details so to speak.
So in particular, we'll talk first today
about what we call abstract data types.
So an abstract data type
is like a data structure.
But it offers certain properties,
certain characteristics.
And it's actually up
to the programmer how
to implement the underlying
implementation details.
So, for instance, there's actually
this abstract data type that's
common in computing known as a queue.
And from the real world, most of us
are presumably familiar with queues,
otherwise known in the US typically
as lines or forming lines.
In fact, I have here
three bags of cookies.
Could I get three volunteers to
come up on stage and queue up?
OK, I saw your hand first.
How about your hand second?
And in the blue.
OK, come on down, just you three.
Come on over.
And if you want to queue
up over here if you could.
Come on down.
Thank you.
As we begin, do you want to
introduce yourselves first?
NAFTALI HOROWITZ: Hi.
My name is Naftali Horowitz.
I'm a first year studying
computer science and economics.
And I sleep at Hurlbut Hall.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right, next.
CATHERINE: Hi, everyone,
my name is Catherine.
I'm planning on studying engineering.
I'm not sure mechanical or
electrical yet but one of the two.
And I'm currently in Kennedy.
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
Nice to meet.
ISABELLA: Hi, everyone.
I'm Isabella.
I'm in Strauss.
And I plan on majoring
in computer science.
DAVID J. MALAN: Wonderful.
Well, welcome to all three of you.
And I think this will be
pretty straightforward.
I have here these three bags of cookies.
You formed nicely this
line or this queue.
So if you'd like to come up first
and take your cookies, thank you.
And right that way, that's all
there is to this demonstration.
Your cookies as well.
Right this way.
And your cookies.
Wonderfully well done.
Thank you to our volunteers.
The point is actually sincere, though,
simple as that demonstration was.
And as easy as it was
to get those cookies,
queues actually manifest
a property that actually
is germane to a lot of problem solving
and computing and the real world.
Specifically, queues offer this
characteristic, FIFO, first in first
out.
And indeed as our
volunteers just noticed,
as they queued up on stage, 1, 2,
3, that is the order in which I
handed them their cookies.
And daresay it's a very
equitable approach.
It's very fair.
First come, first served
might be a more casual way
of describing FIFO, first in, first out.
Now, structures like these
actually offer specific operations
that make sense.
And in the context of queues, we
generally describe these operations
as enqueueing and dequeueing
So when our first three
volunteers came up, they enqueued.
And as I handed them
each a bag of cookies,
they dequeued and exited
in that same order.
Now, how could you go about implementing
a queue in code, specifically in C?
Well, we can actually implement
it in bunches of different ways.
But perhaps the most obvious is to
borrow our old friend, namely arrays.
And we could use a data structure
that looks a little something
like this, whereby we specify the
total capacity of this data structure.
For instance, we might store a total
of 50 people or just 3 in this case.
We might define our structure
then as containing those people
as simply an array.
And if a person is a data type
that we've defined in week past,
you could imagine each of our
volunteers is indeed a person.
And we've stored them one after
the other contiguously in memory
by way of this actual array.
But we do need to keep track inside of
a queue using one other piece of data--
namely, we need to keep
track of an integer,
like the size, like how many people are
actually in the queue at this moment.
Because if we have a
total capacity of 50,
I'd like to if I only
have three volunteers.
Then I can do some quick
arithmetic and know
that I could have fit another
47 people in this same queue.
But it's finite.
Of course, if we had 50 volunteers all
wanting cookies, that's as many people
as we could actually handle.
So there is this upper bound
then on how many we could fit.
But there's yet other ways for storing
data inside of a computer's memory.
And there's this other abstract
data type known as a stack.
And stacks are actually
omnipresent as well
even though it's not
necessarily the system
you would want when
you line up on stage.
For instance, could we
get three more volunteers?
OK, I saw a hand here,
right here, and right here.
Come on down.
We'll have the orchestra
come up this time.
All right, come on over.
And if you wouldn't mind, come on over.
We'll do introductions first.
This will be almost as easy as the last
one if you want to introduce yourself.
And let me just stack you
against the lectern this time.
So if you could go there.
And if you could come over here.
And if you could come over here,
we'll stack all three of you.
So you were first.
So you're first in the stack.
SPEAKER: Hi.
I'm [INAUDIBLE].
I have no idea what I'm studying.
And I live in Strauss.
DAVID J. MALAN: Wonderful.
And next?
SPEAKER: Hi.
I'm [? Tanai. ?] I'm
studying econ and CS.
And I live in Canada.
CLARA: Hi.
I'm Clara.
I want to study applied math.
And I'm in Wigglesworth.
DAVID J. MALAN: Wonderful.
Welcome, to all three of you.
And if I may, let me just advance a
bit more information about stacks.
The catch is that
stacks actually support
what's known as LIFO, so
last in, first out, which
is sort of the opposite
really of a queue or a line.
So in fact you were last in line.
So here we have your cookies.
Thank you so much.
And if you'd like to exit that
way, we have your cookies here.
Thank you so much.
We'd you to exit this way.
And even though you were
first, LIFO doesn't really
give you any cookies because
you're first in, not last in.
So, yeah, OK, point's made.
We'll give you the cookies.
All right, so thank you to
all three of our volunteers.
But LIFO, suffice to say,
doesn't offer the same fairness
guarantees as a queue or
a line more traditionally.
And imagine just lining up in any
store or the dining hall or the like.
Ideally, you want the people running
the place to adhere to that queue,
to that line so that FIFO is preserved
if you indeed care about being first,
whereas there are contexts in which
LIFO does actually make sense.
In fact, if you think about
Gmail, your inbox, or Outlook,
typically you're viewing
your inbox as a stack right.
Because when you get new
mail, where does it end up?
It actually ends up in the top.
And if you're like me, odds are
which emails do you tend to first?
I mean, probably the ones
on the top, the ones that
came in last, most recently
that is and that might actually
be to the detriment of people who
emailed you earlier today or yesterday.
Because once they sort of fall
off the bottom of your screen,
frankly, unless you click next, you
may never see those emails again.
But stacks are indeed
one way of storing data.
And Google and Microsoft
presumably made the judgment
call that, in general, we users want
to see the most recent data first.
The last information might
be the first we want out.
Now, just in terms of
nomenclature, the two operations
that are analogous to
enqueueing and dequeueing
but with this property of LIFO
are instead called push and pop.
So when our first volunteer
came up on stage, so to speak,
I pushed him onto the stack
against the lectern there.
Second person was pushed.
Third person was pushed.
And then when it was time
to hand out the cookies,
we popped them, so to speak, one after
the other but preserving that LIFO
property.
But here's where things are
a little interesting in terms
of implementation details.
A stack could be implemented almost
identically underneath the hood
to a queue because what do you need?
You need an array of people,
which we could use our person data
type for past classes.
We have to keep track of how
many people are in the stack
so that even if we have
a capacity of like 50,
we know at least that we can
store 3 plus maybe 47 others.
Now, there's still going to be a
change in the underlying implementation
details because not pictured here is
the actual C code that actually pushes
and pops or enqueues and dequeues.
So whatever loops you're using,
whatever code you're using,
odds are that's where those properties
are going to be implemented.
FIFO versus LIFO, you're going
to implement maybe the loop
in this direction instead of this
one or some such distinction.
But at the end of the
day, stacks and queues
are just abstract data
types in the sense
that we can implement them in
bunches of ways, two of them
among them here thus far on the screen.
But that array is going
to come back to bite us.
Because if you only
have a capacity of 50,
what happens if 51 people
want cookies next time?
You just don't have room for them
even though, clearly, we have
enough room for the people themselves.
We have enough memory.
So it seems a little shortsighted
to limit just how much data
can fit in our data structures.
So with that said, a friend of ours,
Shannon Duvall at Elon University,
kindly put together a
visualization of the same.
And allow me to introduce you to
two fellows known as Jack and Lou.
If we could dim the
lights for this video.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
- Once upon a time, there
was a guy named Jack.
When it came to making friends,
Jack did not have the knack.
So Jack went to talk to the
most popular guy he knew.
He went up to Lou and
asked what do I do?
Lou saw that his friend
was really distressed.
Well, Lou began, just
look how you're dressed.
Don't you have any clothes
with a different look?
Yes, said Jack.
I sure do.
Come to my house and
I'll show them to you.
So they went off to Jack's.
And Jack showed Lou the box
where he kept all his shirts
and his pants and his socks.
Lou said, I see you have
all your clothes in a pile.
Why don't you wear some
others once in a while?
Jack said, well, when I
remove clothes and socks,
I wash them and put
them away in the box.
Then comes the next
morning, and up I hop.
I go to the box and get
my clothes off the top.
Lou quickly realized
the problem with Jack.
He kept clothes, CDs,
and books in a stack.
When he reached for
something to read or to wear,
he chose the top book or underwear.
Then when he was done, he
would put it right back.
Back it would go on top of the stack.
I know the solution,
said the triumphant Lou.
You need to learn to
start using a queue.
Lou took Jack's clothes
and hung them in a closet.
And when he had emptied
the box, he just tossed it.
Then he said now, Jack, at the end of
the day, put your clothes on the left
when you put them away.
Then tomorrow morning
when you see the sun
shine, get your clothes from the
right from the end of the line.
Don't you see, said Lou?
It will be so nice.
You'll wear everything once
before you wear something twice.
And with everything in queues
in his closet and shelf,
Jack started to feel quite
sure of himself all thanks
to Lou and his wonderful queue.
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: So the same--
wonderful, thanks to Shannon--
so you might have noticed
I wear black all the time
so we could make a similar gag about
here's what my stack of clothes at home
looks.
Even though I might own a
blue and a red sweatshirt,
it doesn't really work if you're popping
everything from a stack every time,
cleaning it, replenishing the blacks
sweaters before the red or the blue
even get popped themselves.
But we're going to focus today
not just on stacks and queues
which for us are really
meant to motivate
different ways of designing data even
though the implementation details might
differ.
But we're going to start
focusing on solving some problems
that invariably we'd be
bumping up against anyway as we
develop more and more real
world software, not just
smaller programs as in class.
And arrays, recall, are what?
What's the key
characteristic or definition
of an array with respect
to your computer's memory
and storing things in it?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: It stores
the data contiguously.
DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
So it stores the data
contiguously back to back to back.
And as we've seen thus far, when
you allocate space for an array,
you typically do it
with square brackets.
You specify a number in those
brackets or maybe a constant,
like capacity, like I just did.
And that fixates just how much data
you can actually store in there.
We did see last week,
though, that we could
start to use malloc to allocate
an equivalent number of bytes.
But even that, when
you call it just once,
gives you back a specific
finite number of bytes.
So you're similarly deciding
in advance how much memory you
can store in an array.
So let's consider what kinds of
problems this could get us into.
So here's an array of size three.
And suppose for the
sake of discussion we've
already put three numbers
into it 1, 2, and 3 literally.
Suppose now we want to add a
fourth number to that array.
Well, where does it go?
Intuitively and pictorially, you'd
like to think it could go there.
But remember the context we
introduced last week when
we talked about computers' memories.
There's lots of stuff going on.
And if you only ask the
computer, the operating system,
room for three integers, who knows
what's here and here and here,
not to mention everywhere
else on the screen?
So if we zoom out for instance, we
might like to put the number four there.
But we can't if in that greater context
there's a lot more stuff going on.
So for instance, suppose that elsewhere
in my same program or function
I've already created a string like
H-E-L-L-O, comma, space, world,
backslash 0.
Just by bad luck, that could be
allocated right next to my 1, 2, 3.
Why?
Well, if I ask the operating
system for space for three numbers,
then I ask the operating
system for space for a string,
it's pretty reasonable for the computer
to put those things back to back,
because it's not going to anticipate for
us that, well, maybe they actually want
four numbers eventually
or five numbers or more.
Now, as for all of
these Oscars the Grouch,
that's just meant to
represent pictorially
here the notion of garbage values.
There's clearly other
bytes there and available.
I don't know what it is.
And I don't care what it is.
But I do care that I can't just
presume to put something right where
I want in the computer's memory unless
I preemptively ask it for more memory.
Now, if all of those are
garbage values, which
is to say that who cares what they
are-- it's just junk left over
from previous runs of the
function or the like--
there's clearly plenty of
room for a fourth number.
I could put the number four here or here
or here or down here or here or here.
But why would I not want to
just plop the four wherever
there is a garbage value currently?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Because you want it to
be next to your array of 1, 2, 3.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly, I want
it to be next to my array of 1,
2, 3 because, again, arrays must
be and must remain contiguous.
Now, that's not a deal breaker
because where else could I
put maybe the entire array?
Well, there's room up
here for four numbers.
There's room down here for four numbers.
So that's fine.
And that could be a
solution to the problem.
If you've run out of space
in your fixed size array,
well maybe I just abstract
everything else away,
and I just move my array to a different
location that's a little bit bigger.
But there is going to be a downside.
Even though this is a solution,
even though I can certainly
copy the 1, the 2, the 3-- and
now I can plop the 4 there.
And, heck, I can then let go
of the old memory in some way
and give it back to the operating
system to be reused later.
This is successful.
But why intuitively
might we not want this
to be our solution of creating a
new array that's a little bigger,
copying the old into the new,
and getting rid of the old?
Good, yeah, I think I had one more step.
Suppose I want to add a
fifth number, a sixth number.
That's a lot of work.
And, in fact, what's the expensive part
or what's the slow part of that story?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: It takes a lot of time.
DAVID J. MALAN: It takes a lot of time.
But specifically, what's taking
time if we can put our finger on it?
Yeah, in the back?
AUDIENCE: You're using twice as much.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK,
for a period of time,
I'm using twice as much memory,
which certainly seems wasteful
because even though I don't eventually
need it, it is going to mushroom
and then shrink back down, which seems
like an inefficient use of resources.
But what specifically is
slow about this process too?
Yeah, in the middle.
AUDIENCE: You're iterating through
the original array to copy it over.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
good choice of words.
You're iterating over the array to copy
it over using a for loop, a while loop.
So it's probably like
big O of n steps just
to copy the array and technically
big O of n plus 1 if we had one more.
But that's still big O of n.
So it's the copying, the moving
of the data, so to speak,
that's certainly correct.
But maybe it's not the best design.
Wouldn't it be better if we
could do something otherwise?
Well, let's consider what this might
actually translate into in code
and what the implications then might be.
Let me switch over here to VS Code.
Let me propose to open up a
file called list.c brand new.
And let's create this list of
numbers and then add to it over time
and see when and where we actually
bump up against these problems.
So let me include standard
io.h in order to simply
be able to print things out
ultimately, int main void, so no need
for command line arguments here.
Let me give myself an array
called list just of size 3
for consistency with
the picture thus far.
And now let me go
ahead and just manually
make it look like in memory
what it did on the screen.
So list bracket 0 is going
to equal to number 1.
List bracket 1 is going
to equal the number 2.
And list bracket 2 equals number three.
So even though the array
is, of course, zero indexed,
I'm using more familiar
1, 2, 3 as my digits here.
Now, suppose I want to
print these things out.
Let's just do something
as a simple exercise.
So for int i equals 0, i
is less than 3 i plus plus.
Inside of this loop, I'm going
to do something simple like print
out iteratively, as you note,
backslash n list bracket i.
So very simple program.
It's not the best design because
I've got this magic number there.
I'm hard coding the 3.
But the point is just to
go through the motions
of demonstrating how this code works.
Good, you got it in
before I hit compile.
So wait.
Thank you.
All right.
Maybe round of applause.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
All right, so this is going to get
aggressive, though, eventually.
So let me add the semicolon.
Let me recompile this list.
Seems to compile OK.
And if I do ./list, I should
see, of course, 1, 2, 3.
So the code works.
There's no memory constraints
here because I'm not
trying to actually add some values.
But let me consider how I could go
about implementing this idea of copying
everything from the old
array to the new array,
frankly, just to see how annoying
it is, how painful it is.
So you're about to see
the code escalate quickly.
And it will be helpful to try to wrap
your mind around each individual step
even though if you
take a step back, it's
going to look like a crazy amount
of code to solve a simple idea.
But that's the point.
We're going to get to a
place, particularly in week 6
where all of what we're about to
do reduces to one line of code.
So hang in there for now.
So let me go ahead and do this.
If I want to create a version of this
code that can grow to fit more numbers,
for instance, how can I go about doing
this or at least demonstrate as much?
Well, I cannot use an array in this
traditional way of using square
brackets because that makes list,
the variable, forever of size 3.
I can't free it.
Remember free you can
only use with malloc.
So you can't give it back and then
recreate it using this syntax.
But I can use this trick
from last time, whereby,
if I know there is this function
called malloc, whose purpose in life
is to give me memory, I
could, for instance re-declare
list to be a pointer so to speak that
is the address of a chunk of memory.
And I could ask malloc for a chunk
of memory namely of size 3 but not 3
per se, three integers for good measure.
So technically that's three times
the size of whatever an int is.
Now, for our purposes today,
that's technically 3 times 4 or 12.
But I'm trying to do this very
generally in case we use it
on an old computer or maybe a future
computer, where the size of an int
might very well change.
That's why I'm using size of int.
It will tell me always the
correct answer for my computer.
So to use malloc--
not going to catch me on this one--
what header file do I need to add?
Standard?
AUDIENCE: Standard lib.h.
DAVID J. MALAN: Standard lib.h.
So I'm going to go ahead and
include standard lib.h, which
gives me access to malloc.
And what I'm going to additionally do
is practice what I preach last week,
whereby in extreme cases malloc
can return not the address
of an actual chunk of memory.
What else can malloc
return in cases of error?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Null.
DAVID J. MALAN: Null,
N-U-L-L in all caps,
which represents technically address 0.
But you're never supposed
to use address 0.
So it's a special sentinel value
that just means something went wrong.
Do not proceed.
So it's going to add
some bulk to my code.
But it is good practice.
So if list at this point
actually equals equals null,
there's no more work to be done here.
I've got to abort the demo altogether.
So I'm going to return
1 just arbitrarily
to say we're done with this exercise.
It's not going to be germane for class.
We can surely find room for
three integers but best practice
whenever using malloc.
Now, this code here does not need
to change because list is now still
a chunk of memory of
size 12, I can actually
get away with still using
square bracket notation
and treating this chunk of
memory as though it's an array.
And this is a bit subtle.
But recall from last time, we talked
briefly about pointer arithmetic,
whereby the computer can do some
arithmetic, some addition, subtraction
on the actual addresses to get
from one location to the other.
And that's what the computer
is going to do here.
Because it says list bracket
0, that's essentially
just going to put the number
1 literally at the beginning
of that chunk of memory.
And because this is a modern computer,
it's going to take four bytes in total.
But I don't want to put the number
4 here to shift it over myself.
Because I'm using square
brackets and because the computer
knows that this chunk of
memory is being treated
as a chunk of addresses of integers,
pointer arithmetic magically kicks in.
So what the computer is going to do
for me is put this 1 at location 0.
It's going to put this number 2 at
location 1 times size of int, so 4.
And it's going to put this
number 3 at location 2 times
size of int, which gives me 8.
So in other words, you
don't have to think
about how big that chunk of memory is if
you already gave the compiler a clue as
to the size.
For our purposes today, don't
worry too much about that.
The bigger takeaway is that when
you allocate space using malloc,
you can certainly
treat it as though it's
an array using week 2 notation,
which is arguably simpler than using
dots and stars and all of that.
But this isn't quite
enough now because let
me stipulate that for
the sake of discussion,
at this point in time here on line
16, where the cursor is blinking,
suppose I realize just for
the sake of discussion,
oh, I should have allocated space
for four integers instead of three.
Now, obviously, if I were
writing this for real,
I should just go fix the code
now and recompile it altogether?
But let's just pretend
for the sake of discussion
that somewhere in your program you
want to dynamically allocate more space
and free up the old in order to
implement this idea of copying
from old to new memory.
So how could I do that?
Well, let me go ahead and temporarily
give myself another chunk of memory.
And I'm going to literally
call it tmp for short,
which is a common convention, tmp.
I'm going to set that equal
to the amount of space
that I actually do now want.
So I'm to say four times
the size of an int.
So technically it'll give me 16 but
space for four integers this time.
And what that's doing for
me in code is essentially
trying to find me space
for four integers elsewhere
that might very well
be garbage values now.
But I can, therefore, reuse them.
So once I've done this,
something could still go wrong.
And I could check if
temp equals equals null,
then actually I should exit
altogether and finish up.
But there's a subtlety here.
And you don't need to dwell
too much on this for today.
But there is technically
a bug right now.
Why based on week 4, last week,
might it not be correct technically
to immediately return 1 and abort
the program altogether at this point?
AUDIENCE: I think when you allocate
memory sometimes it has garbage values.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, so
when you allocate memory,
sometimes there might be garbage
values there that is true.
But that is to say that those 16
bytes might be garbage values,
have Oscar the grouch's
all on the screen.
But tmp itself will literally
be the return value of malloc.
And malloc will always return to you
the address of a valid chunk of memory.
Or it will return null.
So this line is actually OK.
What I don't love is that
I'm returning 1 immediately.
AUDIENCE: I think [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Yes, so
this is where it's subtle.
It's not quite right to just
abort right now and return 1.
Why?
Because up here, remember,
a few moments ago
we used malloc presumably successfully.
Because if we got all the way down
here, we did not abort on line 9.
So we kept going.
But that means we've allocated three
times size event, so 12 bytes earlier.
So frankly, if you compile this
code, run it, and then ask Valgrind,
it's going to identify a memory leak
of size 12 because, as you know,
we did not free the original memory.
So this is where frankly C does get
a little annoying because you and I
as the programmers have to
remember all of these details.
So what I really want to do here,
before I return 1, to be best practice,
I want to free the original list.
So I give back those bytes
to the operating system.
Now, as an aside, technically when
any program quits, all of the memory
is going to be given back
to the operating system.
But practicing what I'm preaching now
will get you into better situations
later.
Because if you don't free up
memory, you will have leaks.
And that's when our
own Macs and PCs tend
to start to slow down and use
up more memory than they should.
But let's avoid discussion
of more error checking there.
Let's just assume that
now I'm on line 23
of this program, whereby I have
presumably successfully allocated
enough space.
So the next step after allocating these
four bytes is to, as you noted earlier,
iteratively copy the old
numbers into the new space.
So this is actually
pretty straightforward.
I'm going to go ahead.
And for int i gets 0, i is
less than 3 i plus plus just
like I was printing last time.
I'm going to go ahead and
set the i-th location of temp
equal to the i-th location
of list, semicolon.
And that's it.
I'm just copying into the temporary
array whatever was in the old array.
But that still leaves me with
this fourth byte, of course--
or, sorry, this fourth location,
where I want to put the number 4.
But if I'm going to do that
for the sake of discussion
even though this isn't really a
compelling real world program,
I'm going to just manually go into
the last location in tmp, a.k.a.
tmp bracket 3 and set that
equal to my fourth number.
So that's all.
The whole point here is to mimic in
code what it was we wanted to do here.
But now there's one more step.
What was the next step after copying
the 1, the 2, the 3, and adding the 4?
What do I want to do?
Now, I can safely free the list.
Now I want to go ahead and
get rid of the original memory
or at least hand it back
to the operating system.
So here is where I can free the
list, not in the case of an error
but actually deliberately free
the original list because I
don't need those 12 bytes anymore.
But now if I want to really
have quote, unquote list
point at this new chunk of memory,
well, then I could also do this,
list equals temp.
So this is a little weird.
But recall that list
has just now been freed.
So even though list technically contains
the address of a chunk of memory,
it's no longer valid
because, again, it was freed.
So, yes, it's still technically there.
But it's effectively garbage values now.
So I'm certainly free--
no pun intended.
I'm certainly allowed to
update the value of list.
And I want list to now point
to the new chunk of memory.
So sort of metaphorically,
if list was originally
pointing at a chunk of memory there,
maybe now I want it to point over here.
So I'm just updating the
value of list ultimately.
All right, now that
I've got this all done,
I think I can just use
this same loop as before.
I could change the 3 to a 4
because I now have four numbers.
At the very bottom of this
program though, also subtle,
I should probably now at
the very end free this list.
And for good measure, let
me go ahead and return 0.
But now I think I have a
complete program that, again,
to be clear is not how you would
write this in the real world
because you would not
allocate three integers then
decide you want to allocate
four then fix all of this.
But we could probably
borrow, copy and paste
some of this code into production
code eventually, whereby this would
solve some actual problems dynamically.
So let me cross my fingers, make list.
So far so good, ./list.
And I should see 1, 2, 3, 4.
So long story short, it's a lot of work
just to get from the original array
to the second.
So ideally, we would not do
any of this in the first place.
Ideally, what could we do instead?
Well, maybe we should
just allocate more memory
from the get go in order to
avoid this problem altogether.
So how might I do that?
Well, instead of having allocated an
array of size 3, let alone an array
of size 4, why don't I just proactively
from the beginning of my program
allocate an array of size
30 or heck 300 or 3,000
and then just keep track of
how much of it I'm using?
That would be correct.
It would solve the problem of not
painting yourself into a corner
so quickly.
But what remains as an issue?
AUDIENCE: You're using a lot of memory.
DAVID J. MALAN: I'm using
a bunch more memory.
Especially if this program's only
going to ever manage a few numbers,
why are you wasting 100 times more
memory than you might actually?
And there's an another corner
case that could still arise
even though this solves the problem.
AUDIENCE: If you add another
list, you'll run out of memory.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly,
we can eventually
still run into the exact
same problem because if I
want to put 301 numbers in
the list or 3,001, well,
I'm still going to have to
jump through all of these hoops
and reallocate all of that space.
And, honestly, now per year concern
about the looping, iterating 300 times
3,000 times is certainly
eventually going
to start to add up if we're doing it
a lot in terms of speed and slowdown.
So maybe there's a better way
altogether than doing this.
And indeed there is if we start to
treat our computer's memory as a canvas
that we can start to use to design
data structures more generally.
Arrays are a data structure, arguably.
They're super simple.
They're contiguous chunks of memory.
But we could use memory a little more
cleverly, especially now per last week
that we have pointers, which
is painful as they might
be to wrap your mind around sometimes.
They really just let us point
to different places in memory.
And so we can start to stitch things
together in an interesting way.
So the only syntax we'll really need
to do that to stitch things together
in memory and build more
interesting structures
are these things, struct, which allows
us to represent structs already.
And we did this with persons.
And we played with
this last time as well.
And we saw it already
for queues and stacks.
The dot operator, we
haven't used it that much.
But recall that whenever
you have a struct,
you can go inside of it
using the dot operator.
And we did that for a person,
person.name and person.number
when we were implementing
a very simple address book.
The star was new last week.
And it can mean different
things in different contexts.
You use it when declaring a pointer.
But you also use it when
dereferencing a pointer, to go there.
But just so you've seen
it before, it actually
tends to be a little annoying, a little
confusing to use star and dot together.
You might remember one example
last week where in parentheses I
put star something.
And then I used a dot operator to go
there and then go inside the structure.
Long story short, we'll
see today that you
can combine simultaneous
use of star and dot
into something that actually
looks like an arrow, something
that vaguely looks like a foam finger
that might be pointing from one place
to another.
So we'll see that actually in some code.
So where can we take this?
Well, let's implement the first of
these ideas, namely something that's
very canonical in computing
known as a linked list.
And let's see if we can maybe do this.
How about Scully, could we get you
to come on up and volunteer here?
So our friend Scully--
there's some cookies in this for you.
So Scully has come prepared
with a whole bunch of balloons
to represent chunks of memory because
we'd like to paint a picture here
of what's involved in actually
allocating space that's not necessarily
contiguous and might be over
there or over here or over here
in the computer's memory.
So, for instance, if I want
to start allocating space
one at a time for a
list of numbers, Scully,
could you go ahead and
malloc one balloon for me?
And in this balloon I'll store for
instance, the number one ultimately.
So we have a balloon here.
We rehearsed this before.
And these balloons are actually really
hard to blow up and tie off quickly.
So thank you.
So here we have a chunk of memory.
And I could certainly for instance
go in here and store if I might the--
here we go.
I could certainly go ahead
here and store in this balloon,
for instance, the number one.
But in the world of an array, it
would just be back to back to back.
And actually, frankly, why
do we need the balloons even?
I could just use these numbers, 1, 2, 3.
But the problem doesn't
indeed arise note,
that when we want to put a fourth
number, well where does it go?
Well, again, just to
paint a picture, ideally I
might allocate space for four.
But if this is my array of
size 3 like where does it go?
This is the point.
We can't just put it next to the 3.
Maybe there's room for the 4 over here.
But we have to somehow connect
these from one to the other.
So, in fact, let's act that out.
So if I instead use this balloon
metaphor of just allocating space
from wherever it is, can
you go ahead and allocate
like another chunk of memory for me?
And here is where I'll now have a
chunk of memory in which I can store
the number computers a little slow.
So in here, the second balloon I'll
have a separate chunk of memory.
AUDIENCE: Oh my gosh.
DAVID J. MALAN: There we go.
OK, good.
Second chunk of memory,
thank you, Scully.
Now, I can certainly--
Thank you.
I can certainly now store the
number two in this chunk of memory.
But it's not necessarily contiguous.
This chunk came from over here as
per Scully's position originally.
This chunk obviously is
coming from over here.
And if you don't mind
holding that for a moment,
this is breaking the metaphor of an
array, which was indeed contiguous.
And even though I as the human can
certainly go over and walk next to her,
that's the equivalent of copying
values from one place to another.
What if we're a little
more clever, though?
And if Scully found space for
this number one over here,
let's just leave this balloon here.
And if she found space for
the number 2 over there,
let's leave that balloon there.
But we do somehow have to
connect these numbers together.
And here is where to--
I'll try to do this on the fly.
Maybe I could do something like this.
I can take this balloon here.
And I can actually tie a
string to it so that if I
want to connect one to the other, we
can link these, if you will, together.
And so here now I have a linked list
that is not necessarily contiguous.
There's a whole bunch of memory
that may very well have real values,
may very well have garbage values.
But I've somehow now
linked these two together.
And maybe just as a final flourish,
if we could blow up one more balloon
to represent more space--
and now she's finding room
for that balloon over there.
Nice.
This one is a Yale chunk of memory.
So now I'll need one
more link, if you will.
And if I actually connect
these two in this way,
let me go ahead and tie this off here.
Now I can go ahead
and connect these two.
If you never see this demonstration
again in next year's videos,
it's because this did not go very well.
Here now we have the number
one where we first malloced it,
the number two roughly where we
malloced it, and the number three--
OK, so maybe we'll fix
this some other year.
Now, we'll have the
number 3 allocated there.
But the whole point
of this silly exercise
is that we can certainly use the
computer's memory as more of a Canvas,
put things wherever we want, wherever
is available so long as we somehow
connect the dots, so to speak and can
make our way from one chunk of memory
to the next to the next, thereby
literally linking them together.
But, of course, we're using
balloons for this metaphor.
But at the end of the
day, this is just memory.
So how could we encode one chunk
to another chunk to a third chunk
might you think?
What's the trick?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Pointers.
DAVID J. MALAN: Using pointers.
That's why we introduced
pointers last week.
Because as simple as an
idea as it is, as hard
as it is to write
sometimes in code, it's
literally just a pointer, a foam finger
pointing to another chunk of memory.
And so these pointers
really are metaphorically
being implemented now in
with these pieces of string.
So we'll have to debrief later and
decide if we ever do this demo again.
But thank you to Scully
for participating.
OK, we have plenty of--
OK, fair's fair.
There we go.
Thank you Scully.
So let's now actually translate this
to something a little more concrete
and then get to the point where we can
actually solve this problem in code.
So here's that same canvas of memory.
And if in this canvas
of memory now I actually
want to implement this idea of the
number 1, the number 2, the number 3,
let's stop tying our hands in
terms of expecting our memory
to be contiguous back to back and
start to move away from using arrays.
So, for instance, suppose I want
a malloc space for the number 1
just as I first asked of Scully.
Suppose it ends up over
there on the board.
The important thing
for discussion here is
that that number one, wherever it ends
up, is surely located at some address.
And for the sake of
discussion as in the past,
suppose the number one just
ends up at location 0x, 1, 2, 3.
So 0x, 1 2, 3 is where Scully was
originally standing right here.
Then we asked for malloc
for another chunk of memory.
Suppose that it ends up over
here at address 0x, 4, 5, 6.
So that's maybe roughly here when Scully
was standing in her second position.
Lastly, we allocate the number 3.
Maybe it ends up at
location 0x, 7, 8, 9,
which was again per Scully's third
malloc roughly over here on stage.
Now, this picture alone
doesn't seem to lend itself
to an implementation of the string,
metaphorically, to the pointers
unless we allow ourselves a new luxury.
Instead of just storing the number
1, 2, 3 in our usual squares,
I think what I'm going to have to
do is cheat and use more memory
to store what?
The pointers as you proposed.
So here's a trade off
that I promised we would
start to see more and more if you want
to improve your performance in terms
of time and avoid stupid
copying of data from one place
to another again and again and again.
If you want to save time, you're
going to have to give up some space.
And there's going to be this
trade off between time and space.
And it's up to you to decide
ultimately which is more important.
So if you allow yourself not enough
memory for the numbers 1, 2 and 3
but twice as much memory for the
numbers 1, 2, and 3 and three pointers,
one for each, what could we now do?
Well, if this node--
and this is a computing term.
Node is just a generic term describing
a box of memory, a chunk of memory
in this case.
If I've given you this
blank slate here, what value
would make sense to store here if
it's associated with this number one?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Maybe the address
of the next element.
DAVID J. MALAN: Good, maybe the
address of the next element.
So the next element technically
is supposed to be the number 2.
So at this location, I'm going
to store the value 0x, 4, 5, 6.
What then logically should
go here in the second box?
0x, 7, 8, 9.
And then here's a little non-obvious--
it's the end of the list as of now.
So we can't afford to
let it be a garbage value
because a garbage value is a value.
And we don't want Oscar to effectively
be pointing to some random location
lest we go there.
So what would be a good special value
to put here to terminate a list?
So null, so not null, which we used
for strings but same idea, N-U-L-L,
which we keep using now for pointers,
otherwise known as the 0 address,
which I could just write for
shorthand as 0x0 in this case,
which is the same thing as null.
So here then, even though we've changed
nothing about how a computer works--
this is just my computer's memory--
I'm using more memory now to effectively
link one chunk, to the next chunk,
to the next chunk.
So easy, just to note that
the downside is more space.
But now we don't have to worry about
ever copying and moving this data
around, which maybe over
time for really big programs
big data sets could very well be
a net positive and a win for us.
So any questions first on this notion
of what a linked list actually is?
No, all right, well,
recall from last time
too that rarely do we actually care
what the specific addresses are.
So this is one node, two
node, and three nodes.
And inside of each of these nodes
is two values, the actual number
we care about and then a pointer.
And now this is actually an
opportunity to introduce a term
that you might see increasingly
nowadays, data, so 1, 2, and 3,
which we obviously care
about in this case.
And then we could actually
refer to these pointers
more generally as metadata.
It's actual data because it's helping
me solve a problem, get from one
place to another.
But metadata is distinct from
data in that I don't fundamentally
care about the metadata.
That's an implementation detail.
But it does help me
organize my actual data.
So this is more of a high-level concept.
So what, though, is a linked list?
It turns out the store linked list
will generally use just one more value.
And I'm going to draw it only
as a square, a single box,
because if I declare now
in my code, as I soon will,
a variable maybe called list
that points to a node, this
is effectively how I could
implement a linked list.
I use one node per value.
And I use one extra pointer to
find the first of those nodes.
And, in fact, here again is where
I don't need to care fundamentally
where any of these addresses are.
It suffices to know that, yes,
computers have memory addresses.
So I could just abstract this away.
And this is how I might
pictorially represent
a linked list, a cleaner
version of those three balloons,
whereby I was here.
This was Scully's first balloon,
second balloon, third balloon.
These arrows now just represent
pointers or strings with the balloons.
So with that said, how can we go about
translating this to some actual code?
Well, here's where we can call into play
some of that same syntax from last time
and even a couple of weeks ago when we
introduced the notion of a structure.
So here for instance is how we defined
a couple classes ago the notion
of a person?
Why?
Well, C doesn't come
with a person data type.
But we concluded it was useful to
be able to associate someone's name
with their number and maybe
even other fields as well.
So we typedef'd a structure
containing these two values.
We learned last week that
string is technically char star.
But that doesn't change what
the actual structure is.
And we call this struct a person.
Well, here's what we revealed last time,
again taking those training wheels off.
It's just a char star.
Let's keep going in
this direction, though.
If I want to define not a person
but maybe more generically
something I'll call today
a node, like a container
for my numbers and my
pointers, well, I similarly
just need two values,
not a name and a number,
which isn't relevant today but
maybe the number as an actual int
so I can store the 1, the 2,
the 3, the 4 and so forth.
And this is a little less obvious.
But conceptually, what
should be the second value
inside of any of these nodes?
Yeah?
So indeed a pointer.
A pointer to what, though?
AUDIENCE: Another node.
DAVID J. MALAN: A
pointer to another node.
And here's where the
syntax gets a little weird.
But how do I define there to be a
pointer in here to another node?
Well, you might be inclined to say
node *next because this means next is
the name of the property or the
attribute the variable inside
the struct.
Star means it's a pointer.
What is it a pointer to?
Clearly a node.
But here's where C can bite you.
The word node does not exist until
you get to this last line of code.
C goes top to bottom, left to right.
So you literally can't use the word node
here if it's not existing until here.
The simple fix for this is to actually
use a slightly more verbose way
of defining a structure.
You can actually do this.
And we didn't bother
doing this with person
because it didn't solve a problem.
But if you actually make your
first line a little more verbose
and say, give me a definition for a
structure called node, now in here
you can actually do this.
This is an annoying
implementation detail
when it comes to
implementing structures in C.
But, essentially, we're
leveraging the fact
that because C code is
read from top to bottom
if you give this structure
a name called struct node,
now you can refer to it here.
But you know what?
It's annoying to write struct node,
struct node, struct node everywhere
in your code.
So this last line now
just gives you a synonym.
And it shortens struct
node to just node.
So long story short,
this is a good template
for any time you implement some
notion of a node as we will today.
But it's fundamentally
the same idea as a person
just containing now a
number and a pointer
to the next as opposed to
someone's name and phone number.
So let me go ahead and
walk through with some code
how we might actually implement
this process of allocating a balloon
and putting a number on it,
allocating another balloon
and putting a number on it and then
connecting those two balloons again
and again.
So we'll do this step
by step in a vacuum
so you can see the syntax that
maps to each of these ideas.
Then we'll actually pull up
VS Code and combine it all
and make a demonstrative program.
So here, for instance, is
the single line of C code
via which I can give myself
the beginning of a linked
list that is a pointer that will
eventually be pointing to something.
So metaphorically, it's
like creating a pointer.
I know we've gotten some complaints
about that in the audience.
We'll use the Harvard one to
represent a pointer to something.
But if I only do this
and I only say give me
a variable called list that
is a pointer to a node,
that's going to leave a garbage value.
So this is like pointing
to some random location
because it's previously some value.
Who knows what it is.
But we can solve that how?
What would be a good initial
value to set this equal to?
So null.
At least if it's null, we then know
that this isn't a garbage value.
This is literally 0x0, a.k.a. null.
And I'm just going to leave
it blank for cleanliness.
So this would be the right way to begin
to create a linked list of size 0.
There's nothing there.
But at least now that foam finger is not
pointing to some bogus chunk of memory,
some garbage value.
So this is how the world might
exist now in the computer's memory.
How do I go about allocating
space now for a node?
Well, it's just ideas from last week.
Once the word node exists
as via that typedef,
I can just use malloc to
ask for the size of a node.
I don't have to do the math myself.
I don't care how big a node is.
Just let it do the math for me.
Then that's going to return presumably
the address of a chunk of memory
big enough for that big rectangle.
And I'm going to store that for now
in a temporary variable called n
that itself is a pointer to a node.
So this might look
like a lot altogether.
But this is just like before when
I allocated space for a string
or I allocated space
for a bunch of numbers
and set it equal to a pointer to
integers, for instance, [INAUDIBLE]
recently.
All right, so this gives
me a box in memory.
This gives me a pointer called n.
So it's similarly just a single
square because it's just an address.
And it similarly gives me
a bigger chunk of memory
somewhere in the computer's
memory containing enough space
for the number that's going to go
there, a 1, a 2, or 3, or whatever,
and a pointer to the next value.
So these lines of code collectively,
this half creates this in memory.
This half creates this in memory.
And the assignment here,
the equal sign, essentially
does the equivalent of that.
I don't care what the address
is, the actual number.
It's as though n is now pointing
to that chunk of memory.
But this isn't very useful.
If I want to store the number 1
here, with what code can I do that?
Well, I could do this, borrowing
an idea from last week.
So *n presumes that n is a pointer.
*n means go there, go to
whatever you're pointing at.
The dot operator means if
you're pointing at a structure,
go inside of it to the number field.
And we did this a couple of
weeks ago with number and person
when we implemented an address book.
So star n is go there.
And the dot operator means
go to the number field.
The one on the right hand
side and the equal sign
means set whatever is there
equal to the number 1.
It turns out this is the
syntax, though, that I
alluded to being a little bit cryptic
and not very pleasant to remember
or type.
Here, though, is where
you can synonymously
instead use this line of code, which
most C programmers would use instead.
This means n is still a pointer.
The arrow literally with a hyphen and
a greater than sign means go there.
It's the exact same thing as
the parentheses with the star,
with the dot.
This just simplifies it to look
like these actual pictorial arrows.
So this would be the most
conventional way of doing this.
How now do I update the next field?
Well, I think I'm going to
just say the same thing,
n go there but go into the next
field and set it equal to null.
Why null?
If the whole point here was to allocate
just one chunk of memory, one node,
you don't want to leave
this as a garbage value
because that value will be
mistaken for an arrow pointing
to some random location.
All right, that's a lot.
And, again, we're doing
it in isolation step
by step just to paint the
picture on the screen.
But any questions on any of these steps?
Each picture translates
to one line of code there.
All right, so if you're comfy
enough with those lines there,
what can I proceed to now do?
Well, let me propose that what I
could now do with this same approach
is set list itself equal to n.
Because if the whole goal is
to build up a linked list,
and list represents
that linked list, list
equals n is essentially saying
whatever address is here, put it here.
And pictorially what that means
is, temporarily point both pointers
to the same exact place.
Why?
Because this is the list
that I care about long term.
This is maybe my global variable
that I'm going to keep around forever
in my computer's memory.
This was just a temporary pointer so
that I could get a chunk of memory
and go to its locations and
update it with those values.
So, eventually, this is probably
going to go away altogether.
And this then is a
linked list of size 1.
This is what happened when
Scully inflated one balloon,
I wrote the number 1 on it, and
I pointed at that single balloon.
All right, if I want to go ahead
and do this again and again,
we'll do this a little more quickly.
But it's the same kind of code for now.
Here's how I allocate
space for another node.
Here's how I can
temporarily store it in n.
And I'll re-delcare it here just to make
clear that it's indeed just a pointer.
So the left hand side of the
expression gives me this.
The right hand side of the
Where could it be?
I mean, I put it here.
It could have been there.
It could have been anywhere else.
But malloc gets to decide that for us.
n equals this, just sets that temporary
pointer equal to that chunk of memory.
I should clean this up.
How do I now put the
number 2 into this node?
Well, I start at n.
I go there.
I go to the number field,
which I keep drawing on top.
And I set it equal to 2.
Now, it's a little non-obvious
what we should do here.
So I'm going to be a
little lazy at first.
And rather than put these numbers
into the linked list in sorted order,
like ascending order
1, 2, 3, 4, I'm just
going to plop it at the
beginning of the list.
Why?
Because it's actually a little simpler.
Each time I allocate a new
node, I just prepend it,
so to speak, to the
beginning of the list
even though it's going to end up
looking backwards in this case.
So, notice, at this
point in the story, I've
got list pointing to the
original linked list.
I've got n pointing
to the brand new node.
And, ultimately, I want to
connect these just as Scully
and I did with the strings.
This is just temporary.
So I want to connect these things.
Here's how I could do it wrong.
If I proceed now and update, rather,
after one more line setting this equal
to null-- sorry, let's at least
get rid of that garbage value--
here's how I could proceed
to maybe do this wrong.
Let me go ahead and update,
for instance, list equals n.
So if I update list
equaling n, that's going
to point the list at this new node.
But what has just happened?
What did I do wrong?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Nothing's pointing to 1.
DAVID J. MALAN: So
nothing's pointing to 1.
And even though you and I obviously
have this bird's eye view of everything
in the computer's memory,
the computer doesn't.
If you have no variable remembering
the location of that node,
for all intents and
purposes, it is gone.
So what I've essentially done is this.
When I update that pointer to point
at the number 2, it's as though--
this was a much nicer idea in
theory when we talked about it.
But it's not really working.
But this is effectively what we've tried
to achieve, which is I've orphaned,
so to speak, the number 1.
And that too is a technical
term in the context of memory.
If no one is pointing at it if
no string is connected to it,
I have indeed orphaned a
chunk of memory, a.k.a.
a memory leak.
And Valgrind would
not, in fact like this.
And Valgrind would,
in fact, notice this.
So what would be the better approach?
Let me rewind.
Instead of updating that address
to be that of this node, let's
rewind to where we were a
moment ago where list is still
pointing at the original, n is still
pointing at the new chunk of memory.
And what should I do instead?
Well, what should I do is maybe this.
Let's go to the next
field of the new node.
So follow the arrow.
Go to the next field.
And what should I put here instead?
Why don't I put the memory
address of the original node?
How can I get that?
Well, that's actually this.
So if list is pointing
at the original node,
I can just copy that address
into this next field,
which has the effect of doing
that, albeit in duplicate.
I've updated the next field
to point at the very thing
that the original list
is already pointing at.
And now for the sake
of discussion, let me
get rid of my temporary node called n.
And what you'll see,
ultimately, is that once we
set list equal to n
and get rid of it, now
we can just treat the whole linked list
as being connected and linked this way.
How do we do this?
Again, we won't belabor
the point with more.
But suppose I want to
allocate a third node.
I have to do the exact same thing.
But I have to update this next
field to point at the existing list
before I update list itself.
Long story short, order of operations
is going to be super important.
And if I want to stitch these
data structures together,
I would encourage you to
think ultimately-- certainly
when it comes time to
write something like this,
think about what it is that we're
actually trying to tie together.
So let me go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go over to VS Code here.
I'm going to delete the
old code for list.c.
And perhaps now we can transition
away from our old approach
and actually do something
with these pointers instead.
So I'm going to go ahead,
and let's say #include
as before, #include standard io.h.
Let's go ahead and include
standard lib.h proactively.
And let's go ahead and
create that data type.
So typedef a struct called node.
And inside of this node, let's
give us an integer called number
to store the 1, the 2, the 3, the 4.
And then let's create a struct node star
value called next whose purpose in life
is going to point to the
next node in any such list.
I'm going to shorten the name of
all of this to just node simply.
And then in main, let's
go ahead and do this.
We'll bring back our
friend argc and argv
so that I can actually implement
a program this time that
lets me construct a
linked list using numbers
that I just passed at the command line.
I don't want to bother with getInt
again and again or the CS50 library.
So let's just use argc and argv.
But with argv, recall string now as of
last week is synonymous with char star.
So that's the exact same thing as we've
used in week 2 onward for command line
arguments.
So what do I want to do?
My goal in life with
this demonstration is
to create and code this linked list
here or at least the beginnings thereof.
So how can I do this?
Let me go back into VS Code.
Let me declare a linked list called
list but initialize it to null.
So there's nothing there just yet.
How now can I go about
building this linked list?
By taking numbers from the command line.
So let's do this.
For int i equals 1, i is less than
argc i plus plus, let me go ahead
and do this.
I'm going to go ahead, and just
for the sake of discussion,
let me print out where
we're going with this.
Let me go ahead and print out %s
backslash n whatever is in argv bracket
i.
So I'm not doing
anything interesting yet.
But let's just demonstrate
where we're going with this.
Let me go ahead and make list, ./list.
And let me put the numbers 1, 2
and 3 as command line arguments.
Enter.
There, we just have
those numbers spit out.
I'm just jumping through
this hoop to demonstrate
how I'm getting those values.
But notice the values in argv
are always strings, a.k.a.
char star.
So if I actually want to convert
a string to an integer like this,
how can I do this?
I want to set the number
variable equal to argv bracket i.
But argv bracket i is a string.
How can I convert a string
to a number anyone recall?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Atoi.
DAVID J. MALAN: Atoi, so ASCII
to I, so ASCII to integer.
So if I do atoi, I can actually
convert one to the other in this way.
And now I can actually print this
as an int instead of a string.
Now, that's not going to change
the aesthetics of the program
if I print it out again.
But it does, in fact, give
me an integer to work with.
But let's not bother printing it.
Let's instead put this number and
any other number at the command line
into a linked list.
So let me go ahead and
allocate a pointer called n.
Let me set it equal to
the return value of malloc
asking malloc for the size of one node.
Ideally that will give
me a chunk of memory
that can fit this number and a pointer.
Just for good measure, I'm going to
check, well, if n equals equals null,
then actually this isn't going to work.
So we should probably
free memory thus far.
So I'm just going to
leave this like this
because there's a few steps involved.
So free memory thus far.
And then we can go ahead,
for instance, and return 1.
All right, if now I don't have an
error and n is not in fact null,
but it's a valid
address, I can go into n.
I can follow that pointer
to the number field
and set it equal to the actual number.
So this is a little
strange at first glance
that I've got number on the
left and number on the right.
But they're different.
n is currently pointing
at a chunk of memory big
enough to fit a node.
n arrow number means go
to that chunk of memory
and go to the top half of the
rectangle and update that number
to be whatever the human typed in
after we've converted it on line 16
here to an actual integer.
All right, what next do I do?
n arrow next should probably be
at this point initialized to null.
And how now do I actually add this
node n to my original linked list?
Well, I could just do list equals n.
And that would update a la the
foam finger my list variable
to point at this new node.
But we said before that
that's potentially bad.
Why?
Because if list is already
pointing at something,
we can't just blow
kindly change what it's
pointing at because we'll have
orphaned any previous numbers.
It's not relevant at the
moment because we're still
in the first iteration of this loop.
But we don't want to
orphan or leak any memory.
So what do I first want to do?
Before I actually point the
linked list at that new node,
I'm going to instead say, go to
this current node, arrow, next,
and actually set that equal to list.
So strictly speaking, I don't actually
need to initialize it to null.
I can initialize the next field of this
new node to point at the existing list.
So what I'm going to do here is,
instead of initializing the next field
equal to null, if I want to insert this
new node in front of any nodes that
already exist, I can simply say set
the node's next field equal to whatever
the list currently is.
And now in this last line I can
update the list itself to point to n.
So after this, let's just go ahead and
do something relatively simple even
though the syntax for this is going
to look a little complicated at first.
How do I go about
printing the whole list?
So print whole list.
Well, there's a couple
of ways to do this.
But if you imagine a
world-- if we fast forward
to a world in which we now have a
linked list of size 3, for instance,
here's where we might be at some
point in the computer's memory.
We've inserted the 1.
Then we inserted the 2.
Then we inserted the 3.
But because we're prepending everything,
it actually looks like 3, 2, 1.
So how could I go about printing this?
Well, ideally, I could do this.
If a computer can only look
at one location at a time,
I can grab my foam finger and point at
the 3 and print it out, point at the 2
and print it out, point
at the 1 and print it out.
And then because this is null, I'm
all done pointing and printing.
But how can I translate
this to actual code?
Well, I could implement that
foam finger, so to speak,
in the following way.
I could give myself a pointer often
abbreviated by computer scientists
as ptr, specify that that's indeed a
pointer to a node, as per that star,
and initialize that pointer
to be the list itself.
So this is the code equivalent of, if
I have this same picture on the screen,
declaring a pointer variable and
point it at whatever the list
itself is storing first.
And, now, that's akin to doing this.
If I now go back into my
code, how can I do this?
Well, so long as that
pointer does not equal
null-- that is, so long as that
pointer is not at the end of the list,
let me go ahead and print out using
printf an integer with percent i.
And then let's print out
whatever I'm currently
pointing at in ptr arrow number.
So whatever I'm pointing at, go there
and print the number that you find.
After that, what do I
want to go ahead and do?
I'm going to set pointer
equal to pointer arrow next.
So what does this mean?
If I go back to my
picture here and I want
to actually walk through this
thing, that first line of code
ensures that this foam finger,
a.k.a. ptr, represented here,
is pointing at the first
element of the list.
Once I've printed it out with
printf, I'm then doing pointer
equals pointer next, which
is following this next arrow.
So ptr now points at the 2.
I then print that out and set
pointer equal to pointer next.
That's like following this arrow and
updating pointer to point at this node
instead.
At that point, the next step is
going to be to point it to null.
So for all intents and
purposes, I'm done.
And that's why we can actually
get away with this while loop
because while pointer is not null, it's
going to print and print and print.
Now, let me go into my terminal window.
Let me go ahead and make
list and really hope
I didn't make any mistakes because
this was a lot all at once.
Seems to have compiled OK.
When I run ./list of 1, 2, 3--
theoretically, this code is
correct, should unbeknownst to me
build up an entire
linked list in memory.
But what's it going to
print out ultimately?
What do you think it's going to print?
Yeah?
It could print out null if
I really screwed up, yes.
What else?
AUDIENCE: 3, 2, 1.
DAVID J. MALAN: Or it
could print out 3, 2, 1.
And frankly, that's what I'm hoping for.
So even though I've
given it in argv 1, 2, 3,
because I'm prepending to the beginning
of the list, the beginning of the list,
beginning of the list
each time, I think,
indeed, we're going to see 3, 2, 1.
Now, that's fine.
That's correct.
But it's not necessarily
what we might want.
So how could we actually go
about inserting things maybe?
Otherwise, because, in fact,
if we consider this algorithm,
what's the running time insert?
How many steps are required right
now, given a linked list of size n
if you want to go ahead
and insert one more node--
there's actually a reason I took this
lazy approach of prepending prepending.
In big O notation, how much does it
cost us to insert into a linked list?
Think about it this way.
Does it matter how
many nodes are already
in the linked list, whether it's
1 or 2 or 3 or 300 or 3,000.
If you're prepending, it
doesn't matter how long
that chain is, you're
just constantly putting it
at the beginning, at the
beginning, at the beginning.
Now, how many steps is this?
I don't know exactly.
I'd have to count the lines of code.
But it's some small number.
It's like two steps, three steps.
How many lines of code is it?
It's very few to prepend, prepend.
So I would dare say that the running
time of insertion into a linked list
is actually constant time.
It's big O of 1.
And that's super fast because it
doesn't matter how big the list is.
Boom, boom, boom, you've
prepended to the list.
But there's a flip side.
What's the running time of
searching a linked list,
looking for something in
it, finding a number in it?
Well, if it looks like
this, how long does
it take you to find
some arbitrary number
that the human might ask you for?
How many steps will it take to
find me the number 1 if it's there?
So big O of n-- because in the worst
case, the number you're looking for
might be all the way at the end.
And even though you and I,
again, have this bird's eye view,
and we can obviously see where the 1
is, the only way we can get to the 1
is by starting at the 2.
How do you get to the 2?
You got to start at the 3.
How do you get to the 3?
You've got to start at the
beginning of the list itself.
And so whereas in the world of
arrays where you had this contiguous
chunk of memory, just like we had
lockers on the stage weeks ago,
and you could jump to the middle
and then the middle of the middle
and the middle of the middle.
That was all predicated
on contiguousness.
Why?
Because if you know where
the first locker was, and you
know where the last locker
was, you can substract one
from the other, divide
by 2, and, boom, you
get the index or the location
numerically of the middle locker.
And you can do that again and again.
I cannot do any such math here.
The middle of this linked
list is obviously here.
But it doesn't matter what the
location of this one is in memory.
It doesn't matter what
the location of this
is in memory because they could be
anywhere in the computer's memory.
So you can subtract one
from the other, divide by 2,
and that's going to put
you in some random location
because these chunks of memory are
not back to back to back to back.
They're every which way.
So this is to say, what
algorithm from week zero
can we not use on linked lists?
So binary search.
So that very algorithm
we started the class with
was all predicated on contiguous
chunks of memory, like an array.
The problem with an
array of course, though,
is that you paint
yourself into this corner.
And you have to in advance
how many locations you want.
And if you round up,
you're wasting space.
If you round down, you're wasting time.
So you're screwed either way.
A linked list avoids those problems.
It's more of a dynamic data
structure that can grow.
And frankly, if we code it
up, it could even shrink.
We could remove these
nodes back and forth.
And so we're not necessarily
wasting time on insertion,
but we are on searching this thing.
We're back to Big O of n when it comes
to searching a linked list as opposed
to it being log n, which
was much, much better.
So the upside of prepending
the nodes in this way
is that we have constant
time insertion of new nodes
because we just continually
insert, insert, insert
into the very beginning of the list.
Of course, a side effect
of this is that the numbers
might end up in completely
reverse order as they have here
because I first inserted 1.
But then I prepended 2.
And then I prepended 3.
Well, we could perhaps take a
completely different approach
and append the nodes
upon insertion instead.
So, for instance, if I start off with
an empty list, I could then insert 1.
I can insert 2.
And I can insert 3.
And, in this case, I actually
get a bit lucky that now they
are in fact in sorted order.
Now, to be fair, that's not guaranteed.
But let's at least
consider what the code
would look like if we were to take
this alternative approach of appending
nodes instead of prepending.
Well, rather than write
out the code from scratch,
let me open up a premade version of
list.c that even has some comments
to explain what's going on.
Some of this code is
pretty much the same.
But allow me to scroll down
roughly to the middle where
we'll see the actual logic in question.
So, first, on line 35 here, we're
checking if the list is null.
Because if there's no list
yet, it's actually pretty easy
to prepend or append.
We're just going to go
ahead and update the list
variable to point to this new node n.
But if the list isn't empty, and
there's at least one node there already,
well, then what we're going
to do is this in line 45.
We're going to iterate over
that existing linked list.
And I'm going to do so with a
temporary variable called pointer,
or ptr for short, that's initialized
to the beginning of the list, a foam
finger pointing at that
first node initially.
I'm going to on every iteration
update that pointer variable
to point to the next node, to the
next node, pointing one node ahead
with that foam finger.
But on each iteration, I'm
also going to make sure
that the pointer variable is not null.
Because if it is null, that means I'm
pointing past the end of the list or,
that is, the list has ended.
But if inside of that loop I notice that
the current node's next field is null,
I actually know logically that
I'm at the end of the list
without going past it.
So at that point, if my goal
is to append this new node,
I'm going to go ahead and
set pointer arrow next,
which is currently null, but set it
equal to the address of this new node
effectively appending that
node to the end of the list.
So, for instance, if we started with a
list of 1 and 2, what we've just done
is updated 2's next field to be equal
to the address of the node containing 3.
Meanwhile, the node containing
3's next field is null by default
because it is now the
new end of the list.
Now, what are the implications for
maybe performance or efficiency now?
Well, we are now appending
to the list, which
means we're no longer gaining
constant time of insertion.
Because any time we prepend it, it
took us some finite number of steps.
We just had to update a couple of
pointers at the beginning of the list--
beginning of the list.
And it doesn't actually matter
how much longer the list
is getting because
we're never traversing
the list when we're prepending.
But when we're appending, by definition
we're finding the end of the list,
finding the end of the list,
finding the end of the list.
And so our running
time now for insertion
is no longer big O of
1 or constant time.
It's now big O of n because if
there's n nodes in the list already,
just to find the end of it we need
to actually traverse the whole list
to actually find where
this new node should go.
But even so, we've gotten
lucky in this appending case
that we inserted 1 then 2 then 3.
That's just because of
my choice of inputs.
Suppose that we don't in advance
what the inputs are going to be.
They might be large numbers, small
numbers, or anything in between.
But they might not
necessarily be in order.
But if we want to maintain this
linked list in sorted order,
I think our logic's actually
going to have to change.
So let me actually go ahead and open up
a new version of my linked list code,
this one too made in advance.
And in this version of my
code, as we'll soon see,
I've gone about changing the logic just
a little bit so that I can actually
now handle this additional case because
when inserting nodes in arbitrary
order, if I wanted them
to end up being sorted,
I have to consider a
few possible scenarios.
Maybe there's no list whatsoever.
So let's actually look for that.
Let me scroll down in this final
version of my linked list code.
And, actually, that case here on
line 35 is pretty much the same.
If there's no list there, and
the list variable is null,
well, let's just update it
to point to this new node.
But things get more interesting when
there is at least one node there.
Because if the goal is to maintain
sorted order, we now need to decide,
does this new node,
whatever its number is,
go before the beginning of the
list, at the end of the list,
in the middle somewhere of the list?
So let's break that down.
If we find that the new node's number
is less than the list's number here,
well, then it belongs at
the beginning of the list
because it's smaller than any
of the numbers already there.
So what I'm going to go ahead and do
is update this new node's next field
to point at the current linked list.
And then I'm going to update
the linked list variable
to equal the address of this new node.
The effect then is, no matter how long
the existing list is if this new node's
number is smaller than
everything else in the list,
I want to just splice
it in at the beginning.
So that's actually pretty
straightforward with just a couple
of pointer updates.
But the other scenario
is that it doesn't just
belong at the very
beginning of the list.
It's somewhere else in the list.
And that itself is two scenarios.
Maybe it's in the middle of the list.
Maybe it's at the very end of the list.
So let's consider those
scenarios as well.
Let me scroll down here.
And in my else clause, it's
a bit bigger this time.
Why?
Because on line 51, in this case,
I'm going to induce another for loop
as before.
But this time I'm trying to determine
if this node belongs at the end
or somewhere in the middle.
So I'm not just looking
for the end this time.
I'm actually comparing the value,
the integer inside of this new node,
against what is currently in the list.
So, for instance, if logically
I actually find my way
all the way to the end
of the list, whereby
the next field in the pointer
variables node equals null,
well, then logically I didn't find
an earlier spot for this node.
So let me go ahead and update
that pointer's next field
to equal the address of this new node.
And then like before, let's
just break out because I'm done.
I somehow mathematically got all
the way to the end of the list
because there is that null pointer.
So it must be the case logically here
that this new node belongs at the end.
But this is the juicier,
slightly more challenging one.
But it's what ensures that we
can maintain sorted order even
if the new node belongs
somewhere in the middle.
So down here on line 62, I'm
going to ask this question.
If the new node's number is less than
the number in the next node-- that
is to say, if my foam
fingers pointing here,
but the number I'm trying to insert is
smaller than the next node over there
and implicitly the same as or greater
than the current node's number,
well, then I'm going to
go ahead and do this.
I'm going to update the
new node's next pointer
to be equal to whatever the current
node I'm pointing at next pointer
so that I can then update that pointer's
next field to equal the new node.
And then I can break out
altogether, doing a similar splice
in the middle of this list but
manipulating a node effectively
to the left and the right to
make room for this new node.
So, collectively, what
does this code do?
Well, if we start out with
that initially empty list,
and maybe we insert the number
2, it just goes right there.
But suppose that we insert next the
number 1, which, of course, is smaller,
this code now ensures
that the 1 is going to get
inserted at the beginning of the list.
If we then insert the number 4, well,
that's bigger than 1 and bigger than 2.
So it logically is going to
end up at the end of the list.
And, lastly, in this example, if we
insert 3, which, again, is initially
out of order, this code can ensure
that we still insert it in sorted order
because it's going to end
up in between nodes 2 and 4.
So here too in terms of running
time, insertion is still big O of n.
It's not quite as bad in
practice as always adding it
to the end of the list,
the end of the list
as was the case when we
blindly appended new nodes.
But it is going to be in big O
of n because, in the worst case
here, if we've got n nodes in the
list already, then in the worst case
it might indeed be such a big number
that it belongs at the end of the list.
All right, that was a lot.
Let's go ahead and take a
delicious cookie break here.
And we'll be back in 10.
All right, we are back.
And to recap, the problems we've solved
and the problems we've created are--
arrays were problematic
because they were a fixed size.
And that can get us into trouble.
Or it causes us to waste
more space preemptively
even though we might not ever use it.
So we introduce the linked lists
again to solve that problem
by being more dynamic and
only allocate as much memory
as we need on demand step by step.
But, of course, we're spending
extra space for the pointers.
We might gain performance if we at
least prepend all of our elements to it.
But we lose time again if we
append or insert in sorted order.
So it's not clear,
frankly, I think, to me,
even hearing these upsides and
downsides, if there's a clear win.
But maybe there's a way to
get the best of both worlds
by trying to capture the upsides
of having information that
is kept in sorted order that allows
us to maybe divide and conquer still
but still gives us the dynamism to
grow or shrink the data structure.
And thus we're born trees.
So what we're about to explore are
variants of these ideas of arrays
and linked lists and see if we can maybe
mash up some of those building blocks
and create more interesting,
more compelling solutions
that are even not just
one-dimensional left to right
but are maybe two dimensional and have
different axes to them or dimensions.
So a tree in the real
world, of course, tends
to grow up from the ground like this.
But it tends to branch out.
And branches branch.
And that might already in your
mind's eye evoke notions of forks
in the road or
conditionals as we've seen.
And let me propose that
we first consider what
the world calls binary search trees.
And so bi is back in that we can
do things in half and half and half
somehow if maybe we think about
arrays a little bit more cleverly.
So here's an array of size 7.
And I chose that deliberately
because there's a perfect middle.
There's a middle of middle and so forth,
just like the lockers a few weeks back.
So when the world of arrays--
this was actually pretty
efficient because we
can do binary search and middle of
middle, middle of middle, and so forth.
And that gave us
logarithmic running time.
But its only size 7.
And we concluded that it's going
to be like big O of n headache
to copy this into a slightly
bigger array, free the old memory,
and so forth.
And thus were born linked list.
But with linked lists, we
lost log of n running time.
Why?
Because we have to always
start at the beginning to
get, for instance, to the middle or to
the end of the list in the worst case.
But what if we start to think a little
more cleverly in multiple dimensions?
So just for the sake of discussion, let
me highlight the middle of this here
array.
Let me highlight the
middle of the middle
and then the middle of the middle.
So there's implicit structure here.
There's a pattern of sorts.
And, in fact, just to
make this more obvious,
let me not treat this as one dimension
left to right but how about two
and give myself a bit of vertical space.
So it's the exact same array.
But allow me to just
think about it now as
though the middle elements way up here.
The middle of the middles
are slightly lower.
And the middle of the
middles or the leaves
really are at the bottom of this tree.
And that word is deliberate.
We actually borrowed vernacular
from the world of trees
where the leaf nodes or leaves
are the ones at the very bottom.
And the root node is
the one at the very top.
So for the sake of discussion,
computer scientists
draw trees like this, instead of this.
But it's the exact same idea.
They just tend to grow down in
discussions, more like a family tree
if you drew those
growing up, for instance.
So what's interesting here?
Well, at the moment, we've
broken the array model
because this memory is absolutely not
contiguous because this number is here.
This number is here,
here, here, and here.
It's all over the place.
But we do have pointers
now in our toolkit, whereby
even if these numbers are
anywhere in the computer's memory,
we can stitch them together like
we did string and those balloons.
Now, it's not sufficient just
to have one piece of string
for each node or one pointer.
But what if we actually give each
of these nodes, not just a number,
like the number 4, the
number 2, the number 6--
let's give them each a number and
two pointers, a so-called left child
and a right child so to speak.
So we could do this.
And I'm going to abstract away now.
They're not even rectangles anymore.
They're really long rectangles.
Or they're upside down Ts
that have three boxes to them.
But I'm just going to abstract away
nodes now as just simple squares.
And it's an implementation detail
as to what the structs actually are.
But the arrows suggest that each of
these nodes now has two pointers.
You don't have to use them.
The leaf nodes have nothing to point to.
So those can all be null probably.
But each of these nodes
now has two pointers.
Now, what's the implication of this?
This is what we call
a binary search tree
because, one and first and
foremost, it's obviously a tree.
But it also is a data structure
that's kept in sorted order,
whereby notice what is true.
If you pick any node in this
tree, like the number 4,
everything to the left of it, its
left subtree so to speak, is smaller.
Everything to the right of it,
its right subtree, is larger.
And that's true elsewhere.
Look at the six.
Everything to the left is smaller.
Everything to the right is
bigger and same thing over here.
So in some sense, this is
a recursive data structure
because you can say the same
thing about each of these nodes
because each of these subtrees
compose a larger tree.
Or, conversely, this big
tree is a composition
of 1, 2 subtrees plus one more node.
So think back to our [INAUDIBLE]
example in those bricks.
Well, what's a pyramid of height 4?
Well, just a pyramid of
height 3 plus one more row.
What's a tree of height 3?
Well, it's two subtrees of height
2 plus one more row or really
one new root node to connect them.
So this already is a recursive
data structure by that logic.
How do we translate this into code?
Well, we won't sludge through so much
low level C code this time around.
But let me propose that we
could implement a node now
as being similar in spirit to what we
did last time where every node used
to have a number and a next pointer.
But, now, let's actually
make some room for ourselves
and redefine a node as still having
a number but now having two pointers.
And I'll call them
obviously left and right
though we could call
them anything we want.
I could call it next and previous.
But really left and right would seem
to make more sense with children
of a given node like this.
So this in C is how we
might implement, therefore,
a node in a binary search tree.
And so let's consider pictorially
what the running time is
of searching for something.
If this here is the tree and it
follows that binary search tree
definition where everything to the
left is smaller everything to the right
is bigger, well, how many
steps might it take if you
have n nodes in a tree like this?
Well, it's not going to take
me n steps because I certainly
don't have to look through every node.
And, in fact, just like
a linked list starts
on the left hand side, so to speak.
So that's just an artist's rendition.
Just as a linked list
starts on one end and you
have to traverse the whole thing, a
tree, because it's two dimensional,
always starts in memory
at the root node.
So this is always where you
start any operation, insertion,
deletion, searching.
So by that logic, in the worst
case if there's n nodes here,
how many steps would it seem to take?
It's not big O of n.
So it's actually back to bi O of log n.
Why?
Because, actually, if
you think of the height,
there's roughly eight nodes in here.
And log base 2 of 8 is actually 3.
And so 1, 2, 3 is the
height of this tree.
So in the worst case
at the moment, it seems
that it's only going to take me like
1 node, 2 nodes, 3 nodes, or really
just two steps to get to
the very bottom of this tree
to decide is a number there or not.
I certainly can ignore
this entire subtree.
Why?
Because I'm searching for the number 7.
Just like the phone book from week 0,
I can divide and conquer this problem.
If I'm looking for 7,
I don't need to bother
wasting any time looking at this
entire subtree, which is almost 50%
of the picture on the screen.
And so I can focus on
this half then this half.
And, boom, I'm done.
So we sort have binary search back.
We have the metaphor of the lockers
back by operating now in two dimensions
to mitigate the reality that our
memory is no longer contiguous.
But that's fine.
We can follow these arrows.
We can use these pointers instead to
get anywhere that we actually want.
So any questions now on trees or
specifically binary search trees,
which I dare say are the best of both
worlds, all of the upsides of an array.
And it's log n running time.
And all of the upsides of the dynamism
of linked list because this thing
can grow and shrink and
doesn't need to be contiguous.
Any questions on this?
All right, well, the code too lends
itself to relative simplicity.
And here's where recursion applies
not just to the structure of the data
but also the code itself.
So just for the sake of
discussion, we won't run this code.
We'll just look at it on screen here.
Suppose you're implementing a function
called search whose purpose in life
is to search a tree and
return, true or false,
I found the number you're looking for.
Well, here's the number I'm looking for.
It's one of the arguments.
And the first argument more importantly
is actually a pointer to the tree
itself a pointer to
the root of the tree.
And that's all the information
we need to search a tree
and go left, go right,
go left, go right.
How?
Well, let me do this.
As always, we'll have a base
case when it comes to recursion.
Because if there's no
tree there, then it
makes no sense to even
ask me this question.
I'm just going to return false.
If you hand me null, there's
nothing to do, return false.
But suppose that you don't hand me null.
And suppose that the
number I'm looking for
is less than the number in the tree at
the moment, the number at that root.
Well, what do I want to do?
I effectively want to go left.
I want to search the left subtree.
How do I do that?
I'm going to return the recursive
return value from the same search
function passing in a slightly
smaller tree, a so-called subtree
but the same number.
And this is where
recursion is beautiful.
Look at the relative simplicity of this.
If search exists, which it
doesn't exist in its entirety yet.
But we'll get there.
If you want to search half
of the tree, just go there.
So go to the root of the tree.
Follow the left child pointer and
pass that in because it's a tree.
It's just a smaller tree
but pass in the same number.
What if, though, it's a bigger number?
So what if the number
you're looking for is
bigger than the number
at the root of the tree?
Well, then just search
the right subtree instead.
And now, logically, what's
the fourth and final case?
So I can express that as if the
number you're looking for equals
equals the number in the tree,
that is, the root of the tree,
then I'm going to go
ahead and return true.
And you might remember
from our days with Scratch
even this conditional is not necessary.
I just did it to be explicit.
We can tighten it up as
just an else instead.
And that's it.
And this is where,
again, recursion finally
is maybe a little more accessible, a
little more obvious in its cleanliness.
There's relatively little logic here.
But what's important is that these
recursive calls here and here are
dividing and conquering
the problem implicitly.
Why?
Because it's solving the same
problem search for a number.
But it's doing it on just half of the
tree or the other half of the tree.
And because we have this
base case here, even
if you get all the way
to the bottom of the tree
and you try to go down the left child
or you try to go down the right child
but those pointers are
null, then you know
you didn't find it because you
would have returned true sooner
if anything had been in fact equal.
So that then is recursive code for
searching a binary search tree, which
is, again, just to connect
the dots of what we introduced
last time of actually doing
things now recursively
and revisiting some of
our own week 0 problems.
But I'm kind of lying to you here.
Yes, this is a binary search tree.
But it's not always as pretty as this.
It's certainly not
always seven elements.
But it doesn't actually have to be
as well-balanced as this one here is.
In fact, suppose that we
insert the following numbers
into an empty list starting with 2.
I can plop the 2 right there.
That's the current root of this tree.
Suppose, though, that I
insert next the number--
how about 1?
Well, it stands to reason that
it should go now to the left.
And so now this is the tree of size 2.
Now, I insert the number, say, 3.
It, of course, can go there.
So that makes perfect sense.
And I just got lucky.
Because I inserted these
numbers as 2 then one then 3,
I very cleanly got a balanced tree
that waited properly left and right.
But what if you have a more
perverse set of inputs so to speak.
You're not lucky.
And the worst possible
situation happens in terms
of the order in which the
human is inputting data
into this data structure.
What if the human inserts 1 first?
OK, well, it goes as
the root of the tree.
But here's where things
start to devolve.
What if the human then inserts 2?
OK, it goes there.
What if the human then inserts 3?
Well, according to our
definition, it goes there.
It looks like part of a tree
because of how I've drawn it.
But what is it really if
you tilt your head, right?
It looks really just like a linked list.
And there really is no second dimension.
I've drawn it this way.
But this for all intents and
purposes is a linked list of size 3.
Why?
Because there's no halving.
There's no actual
choosing left or right.
Now, this is fixable.
How could you fix this?
It's still the same numbers 1, 2, 3.
And it does adhere to the
binary search tree definition.
Every number to the right is greater.
Every number to the left
is-- well, it's inapplicable.
But it certainly doesn't
violate that definition.
Could you fix this tree
somehow and make it
balanced so it's not
devolving into big O of n
but is still technically log of n?
What should be the root?
AUDIENCE: You just reverse
the pointer from 1 to 2.
DAVID J. MALAN: So I could
reverse the pointer from 1 to 2.
And so sort of
pictorially if I take this
and I just swing everything
over and make 2 the new route,
then, indeed, this could
be the new root up here.
1 could be hanging off of it over
here and 3 can be hanging off of the 2
as is.
So long story short, when it comes
to binary search trees, by themselves
they don't necessarily
guarantee any balance.
So even though theoretically, yes, it's
big O of log n, which is fantastic,
not if you get a perverse
set of inputs that
just happen to be, for instance,
the worst possible scenario-- now,
it is fixable.
And, in fact, in higher level
courses in computer science,
specifically on algorithms
and data structures,
you'll be introduced, if you
go down that road, of how
you can tweak the code for insertion
and deletion in a binary search tree
to make these fixes along the way.
And it's going to cost you a
few more steps to fix things
when they get out of whack.
But if you do it every
insertion or every deletion,
at least you can
maintain a balanced tree.
And you'll learn about different
types of balanced trees.
But for our purposes
now, we don't necessarily
get that property even if
we do want log n unless you
keep it balanced along the way.
Now, what about other combinations
of arrays and linked lists?
We can really start to mash these things
up and see what comes out of them.
Dictionaries are another
abstract data type
similar in spirit to stacks and
queues in that you can implement them
in different ways.
A dictionary is a data structure
that stores keys and values.
And those are technical
terms, keys and values.
The analog in the human world
would be literally a dictionary
that you'd have in a classroom,
a dictionary with words
and definitions, more generally
known as keys and values.
So that's all a dictionary is.
It associates keys with values.
So, for instance, you
could think of it almost as
like two columns in a
spreadsheet, where on the left
you put the key, on the
right you put the value.
Or, specifically, you put the word
in a dictionary and the definition
thereafter.
And that's roughly how the printed
pages in a dictionary are laid out.
So dictionaries associate words
with definitions or more generally
keys with values.
But it's an abstract data
type in that we could
implement this in a bunch of ways.
We could use maybe two arrays,
one array for the keys,
one array for the definitions.
And you just hope that they line up.
Bracket i in this one maps
to bracket i in this one.
But an array is not going to give
us the dynamism that we want.
You might run out of space
when Merriam-Webster or whoever
adds new words to the English language.
You might not want to be using an array.
You might want to use a linked list.
But, again, linked lists
then devolve into big O of n.
And that's not good for
dictionaries and spell checking.
If you have to check every
possible word to find something,
getting something that's a little
faster than that is compelling.
So let's consider how maybe Apple,
maybe Google, maybe others are actually
implementing contacts.
Because even though I implied in
week 0 and maybe outright said,
it's an array-- it's a big list of all
of your names of contacts maybe of some
fixed size--
they probably better be using some
variant of a linked list, otherwise,
you could never add more
friends potentially.
You'd max out.
And they'd say you have to
unfriend someone just to fit it.
As an aside, this is sort of
true in the social media world.
Once you have 5,000 friends on
Facebook, you can't have 5,001.
Once you have some number on LinkedIn,
you can't have more connections.
That's not necessarily
that they're using arrays.
But it is the same
implication that they've
chosen some finite size for memory.
So how might we consider implementing
a dictionary specifically
for your address book
or your contacts so you
can store the names of
everyone ideally alphabetically
but also their phone numbers
and maybe anything else?
Well, ultimately, we want to be
able to get at someone's name
and lead to their number.
So the keys and values
for our discussion
here will be names are the keys
and phone numbers or the values.
But the values themselves could also
include email address and a mailing
address and all of that.
But we'll keep it simple,
names and phone numbers.
So here's how you might
think about this or draw it
on a chalkboard, two columns or
in a spreadsheet, left and right.
But how could we actually
implement this in memory?
Because, ideally, we don't want it
to devolve into something linear.
We don't want to have to look
through all of my friends
and family and colleagues to
find someone whose name starts
with Z, for instance, or anything else.
It would be nice to have something
logarithmic with binary search.
But with binary search again, we
have to maybe use a tree instead.
But now we have to use two
pointers instead of one.
there's a lot of trade offs here.
But let's see how else we
could solve this same problem.
Because wouldn't it be nice-- and we've
not really talked about this before--
if we instead aspire to this
Holy Grail of algorithms?
The best algorithm out there is
surely one that's big O of 1,
like constant time,
because what that means
is it doesn't matter if you have
1 friend, 10 friends, 100, 1,000,
a million, a billion friends--
it doesn't matter how big n
is, your searches will always
take you the same amount of time.
It is independent of n.
And that's why it's sort of the
ultimate goal for performance.
So can we get to this aspiration?
Well, a couple of building blocks.
There's this notion in
computing known as hashing.
And hashing is a technique,
literally a function
in math or in code that actually
takes any number of inputs and maps
them to a finite number of outputs.
So if you think back to high
school math, domains, and ranges,
you can take an infinite domain
with any values in the world.
But it reduces them, a hash function,
to a finite range of specific values.
So, for instance, it's no accident that
we have these four buckets on the stage
now, each of which has a
suit from a deck of cards.
We got for visibility's sake
the biggest cards we can.
These are the super,
jumbo playing cards.
And in this box are a bunch of
randomly ordered playing cards.
And, typically, if you
were to ever play some game
or you wanted to these
for some reason, how would
you go about sorting them
by suit and also by number?
Odds are if you're like me, you'd
probably take some shortcuts
and maybe pull out all of the
hearts, pull out all of the spades,
pull out all of the clubs, or
you bucketize it into categories.
And that term is actually technical.
Here are four buckets
to make this clear.
And, for instance, if the first
card I find is the five of hearts,
you know what?
Just to make my life easier, I'm going
to put that into the hearts bucket.
Or here we have 4.
Here we have 5.
Here we have 6.
Here we have queen.
And notice that I'm putting these
cards into the appropriate buckets.
Why?
Because, ultimately, then I'm going
to have four problems but of smaller
size, a 13 size problem, 13, 13, 13.
And, frankly, it's just going to
be easier cognitively, daresay
algorithmically, to then sort each
of the 13 cards in these buckets
rather than deal with four suits
somehow combined all together.
So if you've ever in life made piles--
if you've ever literally used buckets
like this, you are hashing.
I'm taking some number of
inputs, 52 in this case.
And I'm mapping it to a finite
number of outputs, 4 in this case.
So hashing, again, just takes
in inputs and hashes them
to output values in this way.
So beyond that
terminology, let's consider
what we can now do with
hash functions that's
a little more germane to storing
things like our friends and family
and colleagues in dictionaries.
A hash function is just
one that does that.
I as the human was just implementing
or behaving like a hash function.
But technically a hash
function is actually
a math function or a
function in C or scratch
or soon Python or other languages
that takes as input some value,
be it a physical card or a name
or a number or something else,
and outputs some value.
And we can use hashing as
an operation to implement
what we'll call hash tables.
And that's what that dictionary was.
If you think about how I drew
it on the screen as two columns,
it's like a table of information,
keys on the left, values on the right.
So what is a hash table?
The simplest way to think
about it is that this
is an amalgam, a combination of
arrays and linked lists right.
We borrowed some ideas of
linked lists a moment ago
to give us trees in two dimensions.
What if we stick with this idea
of having two-dimensional worlds
but now use an array initially?
So we get the speed benefits of arrays
because everything's contiguous.
We can do simple arithmetic and jump to
the middle or the middle or the middle
or the first or the last very easily.
And then you know what?
Let's use the horizontal
part of the screen
to give us linked lists as needed.
So, for instance, if the goal at hand
is to implement the contacts in my cell
phone or my Mac or PC, let me propose
that we start at least in English
with an array of size 26.
Of course, it's 0 index.
So it's really location 0 through 25.
And for the sake of discussion, let
me propose that location 0 represents
A. Location 25 represents z.
And then everything else in between.
Why?
We know from C that we can convert
thanks to ASCII and Unicode
from letters to numbers
and back and forth.
So in constant time, we can find
location A. In constant time
we can find location Z. Why?
Because we're using an
array just like in week 2.
All right, well, suppose
that I want to think
about these more as letters of
the alphabet, the English alphabet
rather than numbers.
So it's equivalent to
label them A through Z.
And suppose now I want to start
adding friends and family and contacts
to my address book.
How might this look?
Well, if the first one
I want to add is Mario--
Mario's name starts with an M.
And so that's A, B, C, D, E, F--
OK, M goes there.
So I'm going to put Mario at
that location in the array.
After that, I add a second person,
for instance, how about Luigi?
Well, L comes just
before M. So it stands
to reason that it goes
there in the array.
Meanwhile, if I go and add
another character like peach,
she's going to go there a few
spots away because her name starts
with P. Meanwhile, here's a whole
bunch of other Nintendo characters
that happen to have unique
letters of their first names.
And there's room for everyone,
room for everyone on the board A
through Z with some
blanks in the middle.
But you can perhaps see
where this is going.
When and where might a problem arise
with this array-based approach?
AUDIENCE: When you add [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
so when we add someone
else who's name collides with
one of these existing characters,
just because by accident, they have a
name that starts with the same letter--
So, for instance, there's Lakitu here
who collides with Luigi potentially.
Here is Link who collides
with both of them.
But I've drawn a solution
to this along the way.
I could if I was Kronion just
remove Luigi from the data structure
and put Lakitu in or remove and
then put Link in there instead.
But that's stupid if you can only have
one friend whose name starts with L.
That's just bad design.
But what if we now in the off chance
I have two friends whose names start
with the same letter, well,
I'll just string them together,
link them together, no pun
intended, using pointers of sorts.
So my vertical here is an array.
And this is just an artist's rendition.
There's no actual notion of up, down,
left, right in the computer's memory.
But this is my array always of size 26.
And each of the elements in this
array are now not a simple number.
But it's a pointer to a linked list.
And if there's nothing there,
it's just null, null, null, null.
But, otherwise, it's a valid address
that points to the first node.
And you know what?
If we have multiple names
with the same letters,
we can just string these nodes together
together using pointers as well.
So a hash table then as implemented
here is an array of linked lists.
And that allows us to,
one, get some speed benefit
because look how fast we inserted
or found Mario, Luigi, and Peach.
But it still covers the
scenario where, OK, some people
can have the same first letters.
Some of these names will collide.
So collisions are an expected
problem with a hash table,
whereby two values from some domain
happen to map to the same value.
And, frankly, you'll see this here too.
So these buckets are
technically a finite size.
They're definitely big
enough for 13 cards each.
But you could imagine a world where if
I'm using 2 decks, 3 decks, or 4 decks,
I'm going to run out of space.
And then my data structure
can't fit any more information.
But we're not going to
have this problem here
because the linked lists, as we've
seen, can grow and even shrink
as much as they want.
In the world of Nintendo there's
actually lots of collisions.
And these aren't even
all of the characters.
So that's then a hash table.
So with a hash table in
mind, how fast is it?
Did we achieve that Holy
Grail of constant time?
Well, for some of these names if I back
up, yeah, it's kind of constant time.
Yoshi and Zelda, boom, constant
time, location 24, location 25.
Some of them, though,
like Luigi, Link, it's
not quite constant time because I
first have to get to Luigi's location.
And then I have to
follow this linked list.
So, technically, then what's the
running time of searching a hash table?
Sometimes you'll get lucky.
But sometimes you won't.
Consider the worst case.
Big O is often used to
describe worst case.
So what would be the worst
case in your own context?
A little louder.
So NY.
AUDIENCE: Because you
might use [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID J. MALAN: Correct.
And so to summarize
in some weird scenario
all of your friends
and family and contacts
could have names that
start with the same letter.
And then it doesn't matter
that this is a hash table
with an array of linked lists.
For all intents and purposes,
if your friends names only
start with the same letter,
all you have is a linked list.
Much like with a tree, if you don't
keep it balanced, all you have really
is a linked list.
So technically speaking, yes,
hash tables are big O of n
even if you're good about--
even if you have--
in the worst case, hash
tables are big O of n.
Why?
Because it can devolve
into this perverse scenario
where you just have lots and lots of
collisions all at the same values.
But there's got to be a way to fix this.
How could we chip away at the
length of these chains so to speak?
Could I decrease the length
of these linked lists
so that with much higher
probability there's no collisions?
Well, maybe the problem is that
I started with just 26 buckets.
I mean, four buckets here, 26 here.
Maybe the problem is
the size of my array.
So what if I instead just
give myself a bigger array,
and it's too big to fit on the screen--
but what if I instead have a dollar
for names that start with Laa and Lab,
and Lac, Lad, do, dot,
dot, all the way down?
Now, when I hash these
names into my hash table,
Lakitu is going to end
up at their own location
here, link at their own location here,
Luigi at their own location here.
And so now I don't have linked lists.
I really just have an array of names.
So now I'm actually
back to constant time.
Why?
Because so long as every letter of
the alphabet has an ASCII value,
I can get that in constant time.
And we did that as far back as week one.
And so I can figure out
what the arithmetic location
is of each of these
buckets just by looking
at 1, 2, 3 characters or the total
number of letters that I care about,
which is just 3 in this case.
So this feels like a solution.
Even though I haven't
drawn all the names,
it feels like we've solved the problem.
But what's the downside or trade
off of what we've just done?
AUDIENCE: Memory.
DAVID J. MALAN: Sorry?
DAVID J. MALAN: Memory.
So not pictured here is the
dot, dot, dot, and everything
above and everything below.
This just exploded in terms of the
number of locations in this array.
Why?
Because if I'm taking into
account not just the first letter
but the first, the second, and
third, that's 26 to the third power,
26 times 26 times 26.
And even though there's going
to be a crazy number of names
that just don't exist--
I can't think of a Nintendo character
whose name starts with Laa--
you still need that bucket.
Why?
Because, otherwise, you
don't have contiguousness.
You can't just arbitrarily
label these buckets.
If you want to be able
to use a function that
looks at first, second, third letter
and then arithmetically figures
out where to go, whether it's 0 to 25
or 0 to 26 to the third power minus 1
being the number of buckets there--
so there's a trade off there.
You're wasting a huge amount of memory
just to give yourself that time.
But that would then
give us constant time.
So in that sense, if we have
an ideal hash function whereby
the function ensures
that no values collide,
we do actually obtain that that
Grail of big O of 1 because it only
takes one or maybe three steps
to find that names location.
Now, to make this clear, how do we
translate this to something like code?
Well, here again is the struct we
used last time for that of a person
and a person had a name and a number.
Here, for a hash table, we might do
something a little bit differently.
We might now have a node in a hash
table storing the person's name,
person's phone number, and a
pointer to the next such person
in that chain if needed.
Hopefully this is going to be null
most of the time, all of the time.
But we need it just in case
we do have that collision.
We've seen in our pictures the names,
like Mario, Luigi, and so forth.
We didn't see the numbers.
But that's what's inside of
those boxes on the picture.
But that node would give us what we
need to build up these linked lists.
Meanwhile what is the hash table itself,
that vertical strip along the left?
Well, it's really just a variable.
We could call it table
for short of size 26.
And each of the locations in
that array that was on the side
here, at least in the simple, small
version, was a pointer to a node.
So it's null if there's
no one there or it's
a valid address of the first
node in the linked list.
So this then is a hash table.
And each of those nodes, to be
clear, would be defined as follows.
So what's the takeaway
then with a hash table?
Ideally, with a good hash
function and with a good set
of inputs where you're not presented
with some perverse set of inputs that's
all of the friends whose names
start with the same letter,
ideally what the hash function
will be doing for you is this.
The input is going to be someone's name.
The algorithm in the middle is
going to be the hash function.
And the output is the so-called
hash value or location in this case.
So, for instance, in the case
of Mario, when we had just--
when we had just 26 buckets total,
the input to the hash function
would be Mario.
That hash function
would really just look
at the first letter, M in that case,
and would ideally output the number 12.
I did the same thing.
But in my head, whenever I pulled out
a card like the five of diamonds here,
I figured out, OK, that's location 0 out
of my 0, 1, 2, 3, 4 four total buckets.
Here we're doing it
instead alphabetically.
And so someone like Luigi meanwhile
would have a hash value of 11.
These numbers would
be bigger, of course,
though, if we're looking at 1,
2, 3 letters instead of just one.
So with that said, if we were to
implement this in actual code,
a hash function?
I did it physically by
acting out the cards.
Here is how we might
implement this in code
using C. I could have a function called
hash whose argument is a string, a.k.a.
char star, a name of which
is word where the word is
like the first word in their name.
We want this function
to return an int, which
ideally in this case of 26 buckets
would be a number from 0 to 26.
And how do we achieve that?
Well, if we use our old friend ctype,
which had a function like toUpper
from a couple of weeks back, we could
pass in the first letter of that word,
capitalize it, which is going to
give us a number that's 65, 66, 67
on up for the 26 English letters.
And if I subtract 65,
a.k.a., quote, unquote--
single quotes because it's a char--
that's going to mathematically give me
a number between 0 and 25 inclusive.
There's a potential bug.
If I pass in punctuation or
anything that's not alphabetical,
bad things will happen.
So I should probably have
some more error checking,
but this is the simplest
way in code that I
could implement a hash
function that looks only
at the first letter of their name.
Probably not ideal because I can think
of friends in the real world who have
the same first letter of their name.
Whether this is better or worse than
looking a 2 letters, 3 letters, 4
letters, it's going to depend on
how much memory you want to spend
and how much time you
want to ultimately save.
Let me tweak this though a little bit.
It's conventional in
C, just so you know,
that if you're passing in a string
that is a char star to a function
and you have no intention of letting
that function change the string,
you should probably declare the
argument to the function as const.
And that will tell
the compiler to please
don't let the human
programmer actually change
that actual word in this function.
It's just not their place to do so.
And we can actually do something else.
In a hash function because you're using
in this case, the output, the integer
as a location in an array, it had
better not be negative You want it to be
or positive.
And so, technically, if you
want to impose that in code, you
can specify that the int that's being
returned has to be unsigned, that is,
it's 0 on up through
the positive numbers.
It is not a negative value.
So this is slightly better
than the previous version
where we didn't have
these defenses in place.
All right, so what does this
actually mean in practice?
You don't get to necessarily
pick the hash function based
on the names of your friends.
Presumably, Apple and
Google and others already
chose their hash function independent
of what your friends names are.
So ideally, they want to pick a hash
function that generally is quite fast,
big O of 1.
But practically
speaking, in a hash table
unless you get really lucky with the
inputs, which you generally won't,
really it's big O of n running time.
Why?
Because in the worst possible scenario,
you might have one long linked list.
But in practice, ideally--
and this is a little
naive-- but suppose that you
have a uniform distribution of
friends in the world where 126 of them
have names starting with and
then another 126 out of B
and then dot, dot, dot Z. That would be
a nice uniform distribution of friends.
Technically then, your
running time of a hash table
for searching it or
deleting or inserting
would technically be big
O of n divided by k, where
k is the number of buckets, a constant.
So it's technically big
O of n divided by 26.
Now, again, per our discussion of big O
notation, that's still the same thing.
You get rid of constant factors.
So, yes, it's 26 times faster.
The chains are 126 the length.
But asymptotically in terms of big
O notation, it's still big O of n.
And here's where now we
can start to veer away
from what is theoretically right
versus what is practically right.
In reality, in the real world, if you
work for Google, Microsoft, Apple,
and others, 26 times faster is
actually faster in the real world
even though a mathematician might
say, that's really the same thing.
But it's not.
The real world wall
clock time, if you watch
the number of seconds passing
on the clock, n over k
is a much better running
time than big O of n.
So here too we're getting to the
point where the conversations need
to become a little more sophisticated.
It's not quite as simple
as theory versus practice.
It depends on what
matters ultimately to you.
But ideally and literally if somehow
or other they picked an ideal hash
function, big O of 1 would
really be the ideal here,
would really be the
running time we achieve.
And what you'll generally
find in the real world
is that you don't use hash
functions that are as simplistic
as just look at the first letter.
And, honestly, they won't
generally look at the first
and the second and the third letter.
They'll use some even fancier
math to put real downward pressure
on the probability of collisions so
that, yes, they will still happen.
But most of the time a really good hash
function, even if it's not quite ideal,
will be darn close to constant time,
which makes hash tables and in turn
dictionaries one of the most universally
compelling data structures to use.
Now, with that said, we have time for
just another data structure or so.
And this is not a typo.
This one's called and try.
And a try is short for retrieval, which
is weird because you say retrieval.
But you say try.
But that's the etymology of try.
And a try is of the
weirdest amalgamation
of all of these things, whereby
a try is a tree of arrays.
So a hash table is an
array of linked lists.
A try is a tree of arrays.
So at some point computer
scientists just started
mashing together all of
these different inputs,
and let's see what comes out of it.
But a try is actually
really interesting.
And what you're about to see is a
data structure that is literally
big O of one time, constant time.
But there is a downside.
So in a try, every node is an array.
And every location in
that array generally
represents a letter of the alphabet.
But you could generalize
this away from words too.
In this case, if we have a
root node, that root node
is technically a big
array with 26 locations.
And if you want to insert names or words
more generally into a try, what you do
is this.
You hash again and again
and again creating one array
for every letter in your word.
So what do I mean by that?
If we've got 26 elements
here, this would
be representing A. This
would be representing Z.
And initially these are all null by
default when you have just this root.
But suppose I want to insert a
few friends of mine, including
Toad for instance.
T-O-A-D is the name.
So how would I do that?
I would first find the location for
T based on its number 0 through 25.
And if this is T, what would I then do?
I would change the null to actually
be a pointer to another node, a.k.a.
Another array.
And then I would go
into the second array
and hash on the second letter of
Toad's name which is, of course O.
And then I would set a
pointer to a third node
in my tree, which would be represented
here, so another 26 pointers.
Then I would find the
pointer representing A.
And I would create finally a fourth
node, another ray representing
the fourth letter of Toad's name.
But because Toad's name
ends with D and therefore
I already have four nodes here,
we need to specially color
though we could probably
use an actual variable here.
I need to somehow indicate
that Toad's name stops here.
So it's not null per se, this actually
means that T-O-A-D is in this data
structure.
But I did this deliberately
because another friend of mine
might be Toadette in the Nintendo World.
And Toadette, of
course, is a superstring
of Toad, that is, it's longer
but it shares a common prefix.
So Toadette could continue.
And I could have another node for
the E, another node for the T,
another node for the second T,
and another node for the last E.
But I somehow have to mark that
E as the end of her name as well.
So even though they
share a common prefix,
the fact that there's two green boxes
on the screen means that T-O-A-D is
in this dictionary as a key as
T-O-A-D-E-T-T-E is another key.
And technically speaking,
what's in these boxes
too-- it's not just a pointer.
It's probably Toad and
Toadette's phone number and email
address and the actual value of
the dictionary, which is to say,
this too is in fact a dictionary.
A dictionary is just an abstract data
type, a collection of key value pairs,
just like I claimed a
stack and a queue was.
And how you implement it can differ.
You could implement it with a hash
table an, array of linked lists
as we just did, or you can implement a
dictionary as a try, a tree of arrays.
And let me add one more name
to the mix, Tom, for instance,
a valid name from the universe.
T-O-M just means that, OK, that name
exists in this structure as well.
Now, what is the implication
of storing the names
in this way, which is implicitly.
I'm effectively storing Toad and
Toadette and Tom in this data structure
without actually storing T or O or
A or D or any of the other letters.
I'm just implicitly
storing those letters
by actually using valid pointers
that lead to another node.
And so what's the
implication of this encode?
Well, encode it might look like this.
Every node in a try is now redefined
as being an array of size 26--
and I'll call it children just to
borrow the family tree metaphor--
and that in each of these nodes there
is room for the person's phone number,
for instance, a.k.a.
a string or char star.
So what does this mean?
Well, if there's actually
a non-null number there,
that's equivalent to
there being a green box.
If you actually see plus
1, 617 dash whatever there,
that means there's a green box
because Toad's number is right here.
Or Toadette's number is down here.
Or Tom's is over there.
But if this is null, that just means
that maybe this is the T or the O
or the E, which are not
actually ends of people's names.
So that's all these nodes actually are.
And if we think back now to what
this data structure looks like,
this is in fact a data structure that
can be navigated in constant time.
Why?
Well, all we need to keep track of this
data structure is literally one pointer
called try that's a pointer to the
first of these nodes, the so-called root
of the try.
And when it comes to now thinking
about the running time of a try, well,
what is it?
Well, if you've got n friends
in your contacts already
or if there's n keys
in that data structure,
how many steps does it
take to find anyone?
Well, whether I have three names, Toad,
Toadette, or Tom or three million names
in that data structure, how many steps
will it take me to find Toad ever?
T-O-A-D. How many steps for Toadette?
T-O-A-D-E-T-T-E. Eight steps.
How about for Tom?
1 2, 3.
And, frankly, I'm sure
if we looked it up,
there's probably a limit on the number
of characters in a Nintendo character's
name.
Maybe it's 20 characters total
or maybe a little longer, 30.
There's some fixed value.
It's not unbounded.
There's not an infinite
number of letters
in any Nintendo character's name.
So there's some constant value.
Call it k.
So no matter whose name
you're looking for,
it's going to take
you maximally k steps.
But k is a constant.
And we always said that big O of
k is the same thing as big O of 1.
So for all intents and purposes, even
though we're taking a bit of liberty
here, searching a try, inserting
into a try, deleting from a try
is constant time.
Because if you have a billion
names in the dictionary already,
it's going to take up
a huge amount of space.
But it does not affect how many steps it
takes to find Toad or Toadette or Tom.
That depends only on the
length of their names
which effectively is a constant value.
But there is a downside here.
And it's a big one.
In practice, I daresay most
computers, most systems,
would actually use
hash tables, not tries,
to implement dictionaries,
collections of key value pairs.
What's the downside of this here
data structure might you think?
And this is just a representative
picture for Toad, Tom, and Toadette.
All the space it takes up--
I mean, even for these three names, look
at how many empty pointers there are.
So they're null to be sure.
But there's 25 unused spaces here,
another 25 unused spaces here,
24 unused spaces here.
And what's not pictured is if
I've got more and more names,
this thing's just going to blow up with
more and more and more and more arrays
even though there's not going
to be someone whose name starts
with like Laa or Lba or Lbb.
There's going to be so many
combinations of letters
where it's just going to
be null pointers instead.
So it takes up a huge amount of space.
But it does give us constant time.
And that then is this here trade off.
So I would encourage you here
on out as we exit the world of C
and so much of today's code
in the past several weeks code
will soon be reduced in
a week's time to just one
line of code, two lines of code.
Because Python and the
authors of Python will
have implemented all of this week's
and last week's and prior week's
ideas for us, we'll be able to operate
at a higher level of abstraction.
And just think about what
problems we want to solve
and how we want to do so algorithmically
and with data structures.
And data structures in
conclusion are everywhere.
Has anyone recognized this
spot in Harvard Square?
Anyone?
What are we looking at?
AUDIENCE: Is that Sweetgreen?
DAVID J. MALAN: So this is
Sweetgreen, a popular salad place.
And this is actually a dictionary
or really a hash table of sorts.
Why?
Well, if you buy a very
expensive salad at Sweetgreen,
they put it on the shelf for you if
you've ordered via the app or online
in advance.
And if I, for instance,
were to order a salad,
it would probably go
under the D heading.
If Carter were to order a salad,
it would go under C, Julia under y.
And so they hash the salads
based on your first name
to a particular location on the shelf.
Why is that a good thing?
Well, if it were just one long
shelf that wasn't even alphabetical,
it would be big O of n
for me to find my salad
and for Carter and Julia to find theirs.
Because they've got 26
letters here, it's big O of 1.
It's one step for any of
us to find our salads.
Except, again, in
perverse situations, where
to might this system devolve at like
12:30 PM in the afternoon for instance?
What could go wrong?
AUDIENCE: A lot of people with
names with the same first letter
order a salad.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, a lot of
people with the same first letters
of their names might order a salad.
So there's lots of like D, D, D.
Where do we put the next person?
OK, well, maybe we overflow to E.
What if there's a lot of E people?
It overflows to.
F What if it overflows?
Then we go to G. And it
devolves anyway into a linked
list or really multiple arrays that
you have to search in big O of n time?
I've even been to Sweetgreen
at non-popular times.
And sometimes the staff just don't
even choose to use the dictionaries.
They just put what's closest to them.
So you have to search
the same thing anywhere.
But you'll start to see now that you've
seen some of these building blocks
that data structures are everywhere
algorithms are everywhere.
And among the goals of CS50 now are to
harness these ideas most efficiently.
So that's a wrap.
We'll see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]