BRIAN: In Mario, your
task is going to be
to re-implement some pyramids
from the game Super Mario Brothers
in code in a C program.
So we're going to take this
stage in Super Mario Brothers
and take those two
pyramids and represent
them using hash marks on the screen.
So you'll want to create a pyramid that
looks a little something like this,
with a left pyramid and a right
pyramid and a gap in between them.
How should your program work?
Well, if the user runs a ./Mario, they
should be prompted to type in a height,
any number between 1 and 8 inclusive.
If they type in the
number 8, for example,
this is what should be
printed to the screen--
two pyramids-- one right
aligned, one left aligned--
separated by two spaces in
the middle with a height of 8.
And of course, if the user
typed in a different number--
for example, if the user
typed in a height of 3,
then you should display two
pyramids with a height of 3,
for example, also with the
two-space gap in between.
But if the user types an invalid input--
for example, they give you a negative
number, or they give you zero,
or they give you a
number that's too big--
then you should continue
to reject that input
and re-prompt the user
to type in a number
until the user gives you a
number between 1 and 8 inclusive.
Once they do, then your
program should display
the pyramids of the appropriate height.
So how are you going to do this?
The first step of your
program is probably
going to be prompting the
user for input, asking them
to type in how tall or short
they want their pyramid to be.
In order to do this, you
can use the GetInt function,
defined in the CS50 library.
The GetInt function is going to ask
the user to type in an Int as input.
And it's automatically going to handle
dealing with users that type in input
that are not integers.
So if the user types in a
character or a word, for example,
GetInt will automatically take
care of rejecting that input
and re-prompting the user
to type in another number.
However, it's up to you
to check to make sure
that the integer that
the user does type in
is inside the valid range
of 1 to 8 inclusive.
If the user types in a number
that's outside of that range,
then it's up to you
to re-prompt the user,
to ask them to type in another integer.
How might you do that?
Well, you might consider
using a do while loop,
which is a loop that runs at least
once and might continue to repeat
if some particular condition is true.
You might imagine inside the
body of the do while loop,
prompting the user to
type in a number, and then
having some condition that checks to
see whether or not you should re-prompt
the user to type in another integer.
I leave it up to you to figure out
what that condition should actually be.
Once the user has typed in some valid
height between 1 and 8 inclusive,
the next step is going to be
actually building that pyramid.
Ultimately, this is what a sample
pyramid is going to look like.
In this case, we have
a pyramid of height 7.
But I'll go ahead and
replace the spaces with dots
so that we can visually see every
character that you're going to be
responsible for printing to the screen.
Notice that on every
row, we have some number
of dots representing the
space before the left pyramid.
Then, we have some number of hashes
representing the left pyramid itself.
Then, on every row, we have two
spaces or two dots represented here
to separate the left half of the pyramid
from the right half of the pyramid.
And then, we have some number of
hashes representing the right pyramid.
You don't need to worry about adding
spaces after the right pyramid,
because nobody will see those.
So what does that mean in
terms of what you need to do?
Well, for each row, you'll want
to print some number of spaces.
Then, print the appropriate
number of left hashes.
Then, print a gap of two spaces.
And then, print all the hashes
to make up the right pyramid.
But how do you know how many
spaces or hashes you should print?
Well, you'll want to think about,
given the height of the pyramid
and given what row number
you're currently on,
how can you calculate the number of
spaces that should be on that row,
how many hashes should be on
the left side of the pyramid,
and how many hashes should be on
the right side of the pyramid?
And for this, it might be
helpful to draw some examples.
Draw a pyramid of height 3 or 4 or 8.
And see if you can come up with
some sort of pattern or formula
that will let you calculate how
many spaces and hashes you'll need.
After you implement
that in code, the result
should be that you have a pyramid
that looks something like this--
a left pyramid and a right
pyramid separated by two spaces.
And you can test your code by first
compiling it by running Make Mario,
and then running ./Mario, typing in
some height between 1 and 8 inclusive,
and then seeing whether the resulting
pyramid matches what you expect it
to look like.
My name is Brian.
And this was Mario.