CARTER ZENKE: OK.
Well, hello, one and all, and
welcome to CS50's very first section.
My name is Carter Zenke, one of the
course's preceptors here on campus.
And the goal of sections is to help
you bridge the gap between lectures
and problem sets.
So let's say there's
something in the lecture
that you think you
might have understood,
but now it's your turn to try to
put that idea into practice actually
writing some code along the way.
That is the goal of these sections here.
So this week's section is on our
very first week in CS50, week one.
We're moving from Scratch into learning
this language called C that you use
to build increasingly complex programs.
So, again, my name is Carter Zenke.
If you'd like to reach out to me
at any time after this section
or while you're taking CS50x
online, you can reach out to me
here at this email,
carter@cs50.harvard.edu.
But what's on the agenda today?
So today, we have a few
different things from lecture.
We have this idea of
variables and types,
how we store information
inside of our programs.
We also have an idea of
taking input from a user
and trying to print some of
those values back out to the user
as they use our program.
Later on, we'll see these
ideas of functions and loops
and conditionals allowing us to
design ever more complex programs.
And finally, towards the
end, we'll work a bit
on those very first steps in Problem
Set 1 to help you get started
and go on your way to completing
that very first problem set.
So let's dive in here into our first
topic, this one called Variables
and Types.
So, as we said before,
a variable is simply
some way of storing information
inside of a computer.
But I'm curious, for
those of you who are here,
how would you describe a
variable in a single sentence?
Let's say we have a contact application.
We're trying to store information
about, let's say, different people
we're in contact with.
How would you describe what a
variable is in a single sentence?
I'm seeing a container.
Certainly, that's a good idea.
A variable is a
container for some value.
It could hold some piece of information,
like a number or a character.
Any other ideas too?
Containers, something like a group.
I think that idea could work.
It's something like trying
to put some piece of data,
like a number or a character or even
some word, into a particular container,
maybe something we could
call a group and often,
if I could add on to the
idea, is giving it some name.
So I see someone else in the chat has
said, it's a name given to some value.
So often we'll have
these containers that
will have some values inside of them.
And a variable allows us
to give that value a name.
So visually, you could think
of a variable a bit like this.
Let's say we have a container
represented by this black box here.
And inside is some
value, like this value 0.
But it's not quite a variable yet,
really any place in our computer
could have some value.
But what makes this piece special
is that it has a particular name.
In this case, if we're building a
contacts application, we could say,
this variable's name is calls.
So this variable, this
container for some value,
now has this name called calls.
And calls could store
really any particular value.
That's why it's a variable.
This value could change over time.
Maybe I'm calling my
sister, for instance.
And maybe I'm tracking how
many times I've called her.
So I've called her currently 0 times.
But let's say I call her.
That value gets updated from 0 now to 1.
It could also be 2 later on
in time, maybe 3 or so on.
We could think of this variable as
a name for a value that can change.
In this case, our
variable is named calls.
And it has this value, first
0, then 1, then 2, then 3,
that is changing over time.
So this works visually.
But there's also some syntax we
can use in this new language called
C to actually give us
this variable, give us
this value in memory in our computer.
And syntax, as you'll learn,
is simply the characters
we type to write some C code and
tell our computer what to do.
So, in this case, if we wanted to
have this variable called calls,
we'd simply write
something a bit like this.
We'd say int calls equals 3
and a semicolon at the end,
int calls equals 3
followed by a semicolon.
And I'm curious, for those of you
in the room who maybe have seen this
from lecture, what are the three parts
you notice inside of this syntax here?
What parts do you notice here?
I'm seeing a type, some name for
the variable, maybe its value.
And I think we're on to something here.
So if we break this down into smaller
pieces, this single line of syntax,
we'll see there are really
three important parts to it.
So the first part is the
name for the variable.
What are we going to call this place
in memory that now has this value 3?
Well, as we see on the right, we have
this container that has the value 3.
And up above, it has
this name called calls.
So we can say that when we
type int calls equals 3,
we're telling our computer that
this variable is named calls.
Now, there's one more piece, also
the type, as somebody else said.
So here we say, what kind of
value does this container store?
We've given it a name called calls.
But then we have to define, what kind
of value could I put in this container?
Is it going to be maybe a character
or an integer, as in a whole number,
or something else entirely?
That's the type of this variable.
And we often define that up front, up
first, even before the variable name.
And then finally, as somebody
else pointed out here,
we have the actual value for this
variable, in this case, the value 3.
Now, there is still one piece
of syntax, actually maybe two,
we haven't quite talked about yet.
We've seen the type, the name
of this variable, and the value.
But what have we not talked
about yet in this syntax?
I'm seeing that equal sign.
So this equal sign, we
haven't yet touched on.
But it does have a special name.
It's probably less so an
equal sign and more so
what we'd call an assignment operator.
So I see some folks saying in the chat
too, this is our assignment operator.
We're not so much saying that this
value, this calls here, is equal
to 3 as much as we're saying
we've created some container
and called it calls.
And we're going to assign
the value of that container
to be equal to 3, so difference between
equals and the assignment operator
here.
And if we wanted to read this in
terms of just plain old English,
we could do so a bit like this.
We could say we're going
to create an integer named
calls that gets the value 3.
So now that we've seen this overview
of variables and, in this case,
types as well, I want
to ask you a question.
Let's say I give you this variable
here, a variable called country_code.
And it looks a bit
like this on the right.
I'm curious, how would you read the code
on the left-hand side in plain English?
Based on what we saw
before, how might you
read the code on the left-hand side?
What exactly are we doing here?
So I'm seeing a few folks saying
something a bit like this.
So if we had this syntax
on the left-hand side,
we could read it exactly as follows.
We could say, we're going to create
an integer that is named country_code.
And that container that is an
integer called country_code,
that will get the value of 65.
And if you're curious
here, country_code refers
to a cell phone number or a
regular phone number where oft,
if you're calling somebody
outside of your own home country,
you prepend some number.
Like for the United
States, it's the number 1.
For, I believe, Singapore, it
is the number 65 in this case.
So if you wanted to call
somebody in Singapore,
you'd call them using
this country code, 65,
and then add their phone
number right afterwards.
Now, one question we often get is, why
do we begin all of these statements
about variables with this type?
Like, here we have int.
And it's the very first thing we
say when we declare or initialize
some variable.
But why?
And I'm curious about
your idea for this too.
Feel free to chime in.
Why do you think the very first thing
we write is the type of this variable?
Why do we even care about types?
Why do we even have them in this case?
I'll give you a minute to think here.
Why do we care about types?
So I'm seeing a few ideas.
So someone says that it will determine
what we can make the variable do
or what aspect it possesses.
I like that idea.
So certainly we can do some things
with numbers, like add them up,
for instance, that we
couldn't do with characters.
Someone else says, it tells us how
to handle that value in memory.
That's also a good idea.
So you could think of, perhaps, maybe
different numbers and characters
are represented differently underneath
the hood inside of our computer.
As we saw in lecture, for instance, the
letter A corresponds to the number 65,
which in binary is something like--
well, I don't know the exact binary.
But it represents something.
It tells us how to represent
that character in memory.
Other ideas here too, to reserve
enough space to store that data type.
That's also a good idea as well.
So why don't we give a
bit of a concrete example
as to why we really
care about these types.
So here I'm trying to store
this value, 65, as part
of this variable called country_code.
But as we just discussed,
everything in our computer
is stored in terms of zeros
and ones, these little bits
that we can use to represent
all kinds of things.
And for the decimal number 65, well,
if we want to represent that in binary,
it would be exactly this, 01000001.
This is the binary, what
our computer is actually
storing, to represent that number 65.
So underneath the hood, we
could kind of see it like this.
We have this value,
the decimal number 65,
and our computer is actually storing
what you see underneath, 010001,
and so on.
But let's say we actually changed
the type of this variable from an int
instead to what we call a char, or a
character, here representing not 65,
but now the letter A.
Anyone else have an idea
of why if we change the type from an
int to type char, we get A instead?
Any ideas?
So I'm seeing somebody saying,
we learned from lecture
this idea of ASCII, the
American Standard Code
for Information Interchange.
And the ASCII folks, they decided
that decimal number 65, when
you want to think of that
value as instead a character,
it represents the letter A. So here
with this code on the left-hand side
I'm saying, let's store that decimal
value 65 but treat it as a character.
And if we say we are
representing a character,
well, I'm not going to get
that decimal number anymore.
I'm going to get the actual
character represented
by that decimal number,
which in this case
is A. As we'll see later on in the
course, these decisions about types
actually influence how much
memory we're going to use
and how we actually store the data
on our computer underneath the hood.
So more on types a bit later.
But let's keep going here.
And let's see what we can do
that's more interesting than just
focusing on single pieces of variables,
like single variables themselves.
We can also try to add things up
or change variables over time.
And there's a few
operators you might want
to know to be able to
actually do that kind of work.
So, for instance, here
are a few of them.
We have this variable now called calls.
And we're setting it to that value 4.
But let's say later on I
want to add 2 to that value.
I could use this operator
here, that plus sign,
to say take calls, add 2 to it,
and reassign it to that container
that we called calls.
And then later in my program, maybe
they could subtract from calls.
I could say, well, let's make calls
1 less than what it currently is.
To do that I could
say, let's take calls,
subtract 1, and then reassign it back
to that variable called calls, and so
on, for multiplication
here on that fourth line
and division on that fifth line,
so multiplication using our star
and division using our slash.
But there's an even
shorter way to do much
of this in C, this language
we're currently using.
There's this thing called
syntactic sugar we could
use to actually shorten these lines.
I could take the very same
operators, plus, minus, star,
the slash for division here, and I could
append an equal sign of it like this.
I could say calls plus equals
2, calls minus equals 1.
And that is shorthand for
saying calls equals calls plus 2
or calls equals calls minus 1, just kind
of a way to update that value in place
over time.
So I'm curious here, if you
were to walk through this step
by step, what do you think
the value of calls would be?
We have some code on the left-hand side.
Maybe pause the video, take a moment.
What would be the value of calls?
So I'm seeing 5, and I
believe that is correct.
So we'll start with 4 here.
And we're going to add 2.
So 4 plus 2 is 6, minus 1 is 5.
Multiply that by 2.
That's 10.
Divide it by 2.
That's back to being 5.
So you're correct.
Calls, in this case, would be 5.
Now, here's a different
kind of question.
Let's say we take a look at this.
So, again, calls here is 5.
Let's say we take a look at this
next set on the left-hand side.
What would be the value of calls now?
Here, again, is our code.
What would be the value of calls?
Now, I'm seeing a few options.
So I'm seeing 4.5.
And I'm seeing 4.
And I'll ask you, which one of those
do you think is correct, 4 or 4.5?
So let's walk through this step by step.
We have calls first being 4.
We'll add one, which makes it
5, subtract 2, which makes it 3,
multiply that by 3, which is
now 9 because 3 times 3 is 9,
and divide 9 now by 2.
And technically, if you were
doing it on your own head,
you might think, well, 9
divided by 2, that's 4.5.
But actually, it'll be 4 in the end.
And I'm curious, why do
you think it will be four?
I'm seeing somebody saying that it's
4 because we're storing an integer.
And you're correct.
So calls here-- up front, we said
calls is going to be an integer.
That is a whole number.
And if we take 9 and divide it by 2,
we get this decimal number, 4.5, also
called a floating point number.
But because calls is strictly
an integer, it can't store 4.5.
So what will happen instead?
In C, it will simply do what
we call truncating that value.
We'll say, we have 4.5.
There is some decimal value
after that decimal point.
But we're going to simply get
rid of it, not care about it,
and take whatever whole
number we see up front.
So if our calculations yielded
4.1, what would we get?
Well, just four.
If we even had 4.8, we'd get simply 4.
So to be clear, it's
not rounding, but it
is truncating, taking off that last
bit of the decimal place there.
So I'm curious now, what questions do we
have about variables, about assignment,
about updating them over time?
Any questions we can take
while we're here live?
And feel free to write those
questions in the chat for those of you
who are here.
OK.
Not seeing too many questions,
which maybe is a good sign.
But certainly feel free to ask if
you're watching this recording.
Ask a friend.
Ask online in CS50's
communities, certainly
get those questions answered for you.
Now, we'll continue here and try
to do something a little more
interesting with our variables.
I think what we'll do is think about
how to take input from the user
and then print that input
back out to the user.
So we'll talk about
input now and printing.
One of the first things you might want
to do is get input from your users.
If you're running some program,
you want them to control
how that program is actually working.
So there are a few ways, at least
in CS50 and in C in general,
to get input from your user.
Let's say I want to, in
this case, get an input
from the user that will tell me,
what should the value of calls be?
Well, in CS50, you'll have access
to this function called get_int.
And there's a few pieces here.
Get_int takes this argument, this
input, called calls, in this case,
calls colon followed by a space.
And you'll see that
separated by quotes here.
And moreover, that then is
surrounded by these parentheses
that tell us this is the
input to this function
that we're going to call calls.
So there's a few things to
keep in mind as we start to use
these functions to get user input.
First, what we're doing right here,
this is called a function call.
So before we assign the value of
calls, we're going to run this function
and wait for the user
to input some value.
So get_int, this function
on the left-hand side,
that will first be run before we store
that value inside this variable we
created called calls.
But let's say that the user
does give us some value.
And they give us the value 4.
Well, the whole point of get_int
is that once it finishes running,
it returns to us or gives us
back the value the user entered.
So let's say they enter this value 4.
Well, it's kind of like saying this
function runs and gets almost replaced
by this value 4.
Such that in the end, it's almost
exactly like writing some code
like this, int calls gets the value 4.
How do we get that?
By running this function
called get-int that
returned to us what the user typed in.
So we're going to get user input here.
But now we can think about how
we can print that back out.
And to print things in C, we'll
use this function called printf.
So here we have that same line of code.
Int calls gets the value 4.
Notice how now calls is
storing that value called 4.
But now on the bottom, we see calls is--
well, calls is %i
backslash n comma calls.
And that seems a little cryptic.
So I'm curious, for those
of you who are here,
what do you think will
actually get printed out
if we were to run this line of code?
What will we actually see on the screen?
So I'm seeing we'd literally see the
text, "calls is 4," the actual value 4.
And to show you here, we'd see this.
Calls is, again, that numeric value 4.
And this is a special
property of printf.
And if you're wondering, well,
why is there an F at the end?
Turns out that F stands for Formatted.
So I'm going to print something
that will be formatted.
And I have, on the inside of this
string if you will, calls is %i.
I will replace that %i with the
value of this variable called calls.
Now, the follow up question is,
well, how did I know to put the value
of calls in that placeholder, %i?
Well, what I did is I followed up
my text, denoted in quotes here,
"calls is %i backslash n" with a comma.
And I gave another input to printf.
This time I said, I want to put in the
value of this variable named calls.
So whatever follows,
your text that you give
to printf by a comma, whatever
variable you include there,
the value of that
variable will be included
inside whatever format
code you've included there
or in replacement of
that format code itself.
So there are a few other format
codes you're probably familiar with.
A few of them look like this.
We have this one for integers,
%i, that we saw earlier,
one for floats or decimal numbers,
%f, one for characters, %c,
and one for strings, actual
not just single characters,
but whole collections of
text like we saw earlier.
That would be %s.
So you'll see these over time as well.
So questions then on types and
format codes, which ones we
should use in which cases?
All right.
So seeing none so far here.
What we'll do is actually get
some practice writing code.
So I think this is enough
review of the lecture so far.
And one of our first steps
in this week's problem set
is to write a program
called hello, world.
And this is often the first program
many people write when they're beginning
their computer science journey.
In this case, we're going
to write a program that
simply says hello, world to the user
and, of course, perhaps, to the world.
So I'll go over and
I'll open up cs50.dev.
So you should see something a bit like
this if you were to go to cs50.dev
and log in with your GitHub account.
No need to follow along
exactly like this.
But if you're watching the
recording, you certainly can.
Notice how I have a few
different areas in cs50.dev.
I have a top area up
here that will soon be
able to have a file that I
can actually edit things in.
And down below, I have this
place called the terminal.
I can interact with this computer
that I've loaded up in the cloud.
So I'm now connected to some
other computer, not my own,
where I actually write my
own code and where we, CS50,
have installed some software for you
to actually write C code very easily.
So let me try, in this case, to
open up a file called hello.c.
I'll type code hello.c in my terminal.
Let me zoom in a bit so
you all can see that.
Here I now have code hello.c.
I'll hit Enter.
And I'll see this blank
file up top called hello.c.
So now I'll actually go ahead
and type in some C code.
Maybe I want to say hello to the user.
What's the first thing I should do?
For those of you who watched
lecture, what might I
need to do at the top of my file?
I need to include some
stuff people are saying.
So in CS50, and actually
in C in general,
we have this idea of a library or some
code somebody else has written for us
that we could then use
in our own program.
And it turns out that somebody else
wrote this function called printf.
And because they wrote it and
included it in this library,
we can then actually use
that function in our own code
without worrying how they made it.
We just kind of know that it just works.
So to get access to
functions like printf,
I can type this special
piece of syntax up top.
I can say, #include
stdio.h and hit Enter here.
So this is allowing me to include this
file called stdio.h, a header file that
has printf defined inside of it.
And now, what's the next
step I might need to do here?
I have Standard I/O included.
But how I might start off my
program as we usually do in C?
So I'm seeing we need
to make a main function.
So by convention, in C, when
we want to make a new program,
we always include that
entire program inside this
function we call main, int main(void).
And now here i have-- let
me fix that formatting here.
I have this function called main.
Yours might be syntax
highlighted, not quite sure
why mine isn't highlighting here.
But I'll resolve that
a little bit later.
So here we have int main(void).
And we could type in our actual
code inside of this function
that we are calling main.
Now, what kind of code
could we type to say hello
to the user based on what
we saw a little earlier?
What function should we use?
Probably printf, right?
So I'll say, printf.
And then why don't I do this?
I'll say, hello, world.
And now if I hit a period here
to say a sentence, backslash n,
I should be able to hopefully run
this program down in my terminal.
So let me try this.
If I want to run, I could try
saying ./hello and hit Enter.
But I get this error, no
such file or directory.
So what did I actually
miss in this case?
Yeah, some of you are saying
I forgot to make this file.
So as we saw in lecture,
there's this idea
of taking the source
code that is this C file
and compiling it to machine
code or the zeros and ones
a computer actually understands.
So to take this C code and convert it
to the code a computer understands,
we have this special
program called make,
which is a compiler that simply
says take whatever is in hello.c
and convert it for me to an actual
program my computer can run.
So in my terminal, I will
choose to make hello, hit Enter,
and now nothing seemed to happen.
But that's actually a good sign.
If I type ls to list my
files, I'll see hello star,
which means this is a
file my computer can run.
I'll say ./hello, hit Enter,
and now I see hello comma world.
So syntax highlighting
aside, which you hopefully
see in your own code space,
this is how we can actually
write our own hello, world program.
What questions do we have
then on these lines of code?
I'm seeing a question here.
What is the difference between
a library and a header file?
So that's two pieces of
vocabulary we've used here.
We often say we're going to include
a header file or, conversationally,
include some library.
But there's a difference
between these two things.
So notice how this, stdio.h, that is
an actual file we're calling a header
file.
And in this particular
file, we've defined
all the functions that are included
in this library, like, for example,
printf.
But in that header file,
we haven't actually
defined the entirety
of the printf function.
We've just defined a few particular
things, like what inputs printf takes
or what outputs it gives to us.
Now, the entire library
likely has more files
than just this header file under
which those functions are actually
defined under which they tell
us what exactly does printf do.
So the library, in general,
you can think of it
as including all kinds of
functions, some like printf.
But the header file is our way of
defining what functions are inside
this library to begin with.
A great question.
So let's keep going and make
this a little more advanced.
So our next step in problem set 0 is
to not just say hello to the world,
but to say hello to a particular user.
So in this case, we want
to get input from the user
and allow them, in this case,
to say hello back to themselves.
So I'll go back to my program, hello.c.
And now I want to get
input from the user.
So what could I do?
Maybe I want to make a variable.
And I'll actually ask you all who
are here, what kind of variable
should I make?
If I want to store some text from the
user, what type might be good for that?
I'm seeing a string.
A string is a variable that can
store a collection of text, not just
a single character, but
a whole collection of it.
So I'll type string here.
This is the type.
And now, what should
I name this variable?
What might be an appropriate name here?
We could just call it name.
This is a variable whose
name is name because it
stores someone's actual
name, kind of confusing,
but we'll go with it, string name.
And then it gets some value.
So I'll use this
assignment operator here.
What value should it get?
I could type just Carter here,
like this, to get my own name.
But I want to get the user's name.
So what could I do?
I'm seeing I could use
get_string as we saw before.
So get_string is a
function that is included
in the CS50 library that
allows you to safely get
some user input that is a string.
And as input inside
these parentheses here,
get_string can take some piece
of text itself or a string.
So I'll say, "What is your name?"
And leave a space so the user can
type in their name after that.
And now, down below, I should think
about what I should update here.
I have hello, world.
But now what should I change this to?
Not hello, world, but what?
Probably a placeholder, as
I'm seeing some folks say.
I want to have a placeholder for
this variable we created called name.
So I'll say hello comma
and then a space %s.
%s is our format code, our placeholder,
for a variable of the type string.
And now, how could I make sure that
the value of name gets included here?
I could simply follow this text with
a comma, then say the variable name.
And now I'll make sure that whatever
value is stored by this variable called
name, I should be able to have
a placeholder for it here in %s.
So now let's try it.
I'll do make hello to
recompile our program,
update it, and turn it
back into machine code.
I'll hit Enter.
And I get a fatal error.
Let's see.
What might be wrong?
So there's a few clues here, "use
of undeclared identifier string."
Did I mean standard in?
It's actually not what
I meant in this case.
But often if you'll see, you might
get some errors saying something
is undeclared, undefined in some ways.
When that happens,
you might want to take
a look at which files you're
including at the top of your program.
And in this case, I
told you that get_string
was included in the CS50 library.
But I didn't include it up top.
So let me go ahead and include it.
I'll say, #include and then cs50.h
to include that CS50 header file.
And just for style's sake,
what I'll do is actually
move CS50 above Standard I/O just
to keep things alphabetized up here.
So C comes before S. I'll make
sure I have all my header files
alphabetized just for style's sake.
It would work the
other way too, but just
to keep things a little
cleaner around here.
So let me try this.
I'll say make hello, hit Enter, nothing
seemed to happen, which is good.
I'll type ./hello, which
is my program, hit Enter.
I'll see, "What is your name?"
And I'll type Carter.
And I should see, "Hello, Carter."
So all seems to work in this case.
Now, what questions do we have on
writing our very own hello to you
program?
Seeing none so far.
And now let's move on to something
that's a little more advanced.
Actually, there is one question here.
So why do we put name
after %s backslash n?
So it's kind of just by convention.
The people who wrote printf, who came
before us and made this function,
they simply decided that printf
would take one or more inputs.
So here I say, hello %s backslash n.
And if I want to include--
if I want to take the value of this
variable name and put it in this
placeholder, I just simply follow up
with this first input called hello
comma %s backslash n and
include that variable itself.
If you want to get more advanced
with this, you actually could.
So let's say I want to take
a first name and a last name.
I could actually have two
placeholders, hello %s space %s.
And now if I wanted to
include another variable,
one let's say changes name to first
name and then have one later called
last name, here's how
I could use printf.
I could now have three
inputs separated by commas.
The first is the actual string I
want to print with the placeholders.
The next one is the first variable to
replace that is the value of first name
will go into this first
placeholder and then
the second variable, last name, that
will go into the second placeholder
here.
So I'll update my program.
I'll say hello string first name.
What is your first name?
And then here I'll say,
string last name gets
the value of get_string
asking, what is your last name?
--and a semicolon to finish.
So now I'll type make hello.
And I'll run ./hello.
I'll type Carter followed by Zenke.
And now I'll see "Hello, Carter Zenke."
So there's some other ways to use
printf if you want to actually involve
more than one variable in your output.
Now, building on this,
let's actually continue on.
And let's try actually making a more
advanced program to store our contacts.
So I'll go back to my slides.
And I'll show you this.
We're going to write a program that
takes in and stores and then later
prints out a user's contact information.
And so if you're going
to write this program,
I want you to include the following
three attributes of somebody.
Make sure you include,
let's say, their name.
You can treat it as either first name
or first name and last name, their age,
and also their phone number,
so name, age, and phone number.
And I want you to, if you're
watching this as a recording,
maybe pause the video here
and try to write this program
yourself and then come back and
we'll write it all together.
All right.
So if you're back from
writing this program,
let's go ahead and try to
write it all together here.
Go back to my code space.
And this time, I'll get rid of hello.c.
I'll x out up top.
And now I'll type code contacts.c
to create this new file that
is a C program called contacts.
And I'll include my initial libraries.
I'll say include stdio.h and include,
perhaps up top here, cs50.h as well.
Now I'll type int main(void), what we do
to kick off all of our C programs here.
And now I need to get the
information from the user.
So I'm curious, for
those of you who are here
live, what should I be doing to
actually get the user's name?
Well, probably similar
to what we did before.
I could say, string name equals
get_string what is your name?
Just like this.
But now I want to get their age.
And I'm curious, what type might
be good for getting their age?
Maybe an integer.
So I could say int age equals
get_int what is your age?
Just like this.
And then finally, down below, I
want to get their phone number.
But what type might be
best for a phone number?
Seeing a few options here.
So one might be an integer.
It is a phone number.
So it could just be an integer value.
But it might be better
to find as a string.
So the difference here
is that if I say int,
let's say just number for phone number,
get_int what is your phone number?
Well, that restricts the
user to entering only digits.
And sometimes you might see phone
numbers written with dashes or plus
signs for country codes.
And if I wanted to include
those, well, if I have an int,
I actually can't include those.
So if I wanted to be able to have the
user type in pluses along with numbers,
a string might be good for this.
So I'll say instead
string number and use
get_string what is your phone number?
Now the user could include not
just numbers, like 7 or 1 or so
on, they could also include
parentheses, dashes,
plus signs, whatever they need
to enter their phone number.
And now to print all this
out, I'll go back down below.
And I'll say, let's say, why don't we
print out name followed by their name?
And why don't we print
out, in this case,
the age followed by their age using %i
for our integer here and then printf
and then number followed by
%s backslash n semicolon.
And now I'll be able
to include all of these
as placeholders, name, age, and number.
And I'll be able to take the value of
name and put it in this placeholder,
for instance.
So why don't we do this?
I'll say, make contacts,
then ./contacts.
Hit Enter.
What is my name?
Carter.
What is my age?
25.
I'll type in a phone number.
I'll say, plus one.
Let's go with 555-555-5555 for
a random phone number here.
Hit Enter.
And now I see that same information
being printed back out to me.
So what questions do we have on
this contacts application here?
OK.
So I'm not seeing any
from our live audience.
But what we'll do is kind of
round out this week's section
by focusing now on not just
getting input from the user
and storing it in variables,
but actually writing
our programs with our very own
functions and loops and conditionals.
And I think things get
a lot more interesting
when we get to use other
kinds of building blocks here.
So let's talk now about, again,
functions, loops, and conditionals.
And in this week's
problem set, you'll see
you'll be tasked with making your very
own pyramid like the pyramid that's
in Mario, that very old game
and also somewhat new game
coming out very soon that Mario has
to go through and fight enemies and go
through a higher level by jumping
over things like this pyramid
that we see on this video here.
So there are a few kinds of loops.
And one of these loops
is called a while loop.
A while loop is great for when
you want to maybe do something
while some condition is
true in your program.
So as one example of
this, let's say I have
a while loop that looks a bit
like this on the left-hand side.
Well, I will tell you right now that
the output of this piece of code
is going to look a bit like
this on the right-hand side.
I'll get four hashes
on the right-hand side.
But how did we get here?
Let's walk through it step by step
using the syntax that we see here.
So the very first line of
code, int j, gets the value 0.
Well, that creates this
container in memory
called j that has this value called 0.
And now here's where things
are a little more interesting.
I have this variable.
But I want to do something with it.
I could make a condition out of it.
I could say, I want to do
something in my program
while it is true that the
value of j is less than 4.
That is this condition right here.
Now, what do I want to do while
the value of j is less than 4?
Let's say I first want to print
this single hashtag down below.
So now I've gone and I've
said, well, is j less than 4?
It is.
It's currently 0.
So I'll print out a single hash.
And then what will I do?
I'll then say, let's
increase j by one using
the syntax of plus plus, some
syntactic sugar here, to say j
is now one more than
what it previously was.
And now, logically in this loop,
I'll go back up to the top.
And I'll reassess this condition.
I'll say, is j still less than 4?
And for those of you who are here
live, is j is still less than 4?
I think it is, right?
So we'll keep going.
We'll go through this
loop one more time.
I'll say, print out another hash.
And then I'll increase j by one.
So now what is j?
j is 2.
I'll ask again.
Is j less than 4?
It is.
So let's do this again.
I'll print out a hash.
And I'll increase j by one.
And finally, I'll go back up to
the top, ask, is j less than 4?
Well, it still is.
It's still 3.
I'll print another hash, add one,
and now when I go back up to the top
to assess this condition,
is j less than 4?
Well, j is equal to 4.
It's not less than 4.
So we'll stop doing
the code in this loop.
And we'll instead print
out the special character
we saw in lecture, backslash n,
that says we'll move to a new line.
So that is one way, in this case, to
get some set of hashes going along
the bottom of, let's say, our pyramid
using some kind of while loop.
But there's also another way to do this.
We could think of it not just
in terms of a while loop,
but in terms of another
tool called a for loop.
So a for loop is--
it can allow you to do very
similar things to a while loop.
But it's good for when you
know the exact number of times
you want to iterate.
A while loop is great if you're
not exactly sure how many times you
want to do something, but you know you
want to do it while something is true.
A for loop is great when you
know the exact number of times
that you want to actually
loop, in this case.
So we could actually write that very
same while loop using code a bit
like this on the left-hand side.
There's a few components here
though that we need to break apart.
So maybe the first piece here is going
to be this part on the left-hand side.
Let me actually zoom through this.
Let me show you-- oops.
Let me come back here.
What do I want to show you?
Yeah.
So let's actually go back to
the very beginning of this.
If we go here, let's look at
the very top of this for loop.
So for int j equals 0 semicolon j is
less than 4 semicolon j plus plus.
That probably looks familiar
from our while loop, right?
We had those kind of very
same things in our while loop.
We first set j to be 0.
Our condition was, is j less than 4?
And the thing we did each loop was
increase j by one using j plus plus.
So we've taken all those same components
but simply put them at the top of our
for loop.
And it allows us to
simplify our syntax here.
So on the inside, we
just say what we're going
to do for each iteration of this loop,
which is print out a single hash.
So to visualize this,
on the right-hand side,
let's say our very first
thing we do in this for loop
is we create a variable called
j that gets this value called 0.
Then we're going to
print out a single hash.
We're going to ask that question again.
Is j less than 4?
Well, it is.
So we'll do that thing we said we'd
do at the very end of this for loop, j
plus plus.
Now j becomes 1.
We'll go through,
print out another hash.
And then we'll say, is 1 less than 4?
It still is.
I print another hash and keep going.
And now we'll see, is 2 less than 4?
Well, it is.
So it will print another hash. j is 3.
Now j is 4.
No longer will it be
printing out these hashes.
That condition, j less
than 4, is no longer true.
We'll instead print backslash n to
finish things off at the bottom.
So what questions do we have here on the
syntax for while loops and for loops,
if any?
A good question, is there any
difference between the while
loop and the for loop other
than the initial condition
and the update in the
same line in the for loop?
Any differences?
I think the main
difference is more syntax.
So as you see here, they are
in a different kind of order
as we saw in the while loop.
I'm going to go out on a limb
and say I think that most
things you could do in a
while loop, you can also
do in a for loop and vice versa.
Generally though, the
syntax of a while loop
is better suited for if
you have some condition,
you're not sure when it will be true,
but you know what that condition is.
So you'd include that in the
while loop, whereas a for loop
is good because you kind
of get to actually specify
the exact number of
times you want something
to do that loop over and over again.
If that makes sense and answers
your question, let me know.
If not, I can give you
another take on that.
Let's see.
Why is the j plus plus now outside of
those brackets here, these curly braces
that you see on the left-hand side?
So that's simply the way that the
makers of C decided it would be.
You might see some very similar
syntax across different languages
beyond C, also in things like Java
and maybe even Python as well.
Basically this allows us to simply
make things a little more compact.
We're moving that increment, what we do
each loop, to increase this variable,
j.
We're moving it to the actual
definition of the for loop.
Nice.
OK.
So with these kinds of tools,
I want to pose a question
to you, which is, let's say
we're able to get to a point
where we're printing out
a single line of hashes.
This code here prints out a single line
of hashes and moves to that new line.
But let's think for a moment.
What could I do to get not
just a single line of hashes,
but maybe even a full square of
hashes, having multiple lines now?
I have one loop to make a single line.
I'm seeing an idea
coming up in the chat.
Maybe we could use another loop
to have more than one line,
not just a single line, but maybe
multiple, like four lines of four
hashes to make a square of hashes.
And it's actually true.
You can take a loop, like
this, and put it inside
of another loop, a bit like this here.
So notice how the inner loop, this
for int j equals 0, j is less than 4,
j plus plus, that is still printing
out a single line of hashes.
But now I'm going to do that step
four times per the for loop that
is around that loop, for int i equals
0, i is less than 4, i plus plus.
The result of this will be the square
we see on the right-hand side of hashes.
So as you're working on a program like
Mario, don't be afraid to make a loop
and then put that loop
inside of, perhaps,
another loop to help you
solve the problem you're
trying to solve in this case.
Now, to help us focus
even more on functions
even beyond loops in particular,
let's go ahead and actually try
to take a first step towards
writing that Mario problem that we
see in this week's problem set.
And, in this case, we're going to--
well, actually in the
problem set, you're
asked to write a right-aligned pyramid.
In this case though, we'll actually
write a left-aligned pyramid.
So if you think of your right hand
and your left hand and thinking which
way should the pyramid go, a
right-aligned pyramid kind of
goes up to your right, whereas
a left-aligned pyramid goes up
to your left.
And I would probably argue a
left-aligned pyramid is a bit easier
than a right-aligned pyramid.
But I'll leave that part up to you
as you work on the problem set.
And today we'll focus on
our left-aligned pyramid.
So a left-aligned pyramid
looks a bit like this.
Oops.
Looks a bit-- oh, sorry.
I didn't have those slides
in this presentation.
That's OK.
We will do, instead,
talking about functions
and what we could do to create
a left-aligned pyramid if you
can visualize in your head.
Let me go to my actual code space
over here, what that looks like.
I'll say, code pyramid.txt.
And I'll show you an example.
So here, this is an example
of a left-aligned pyramid.
This is a pyramid of height five.
But if I wanted to have
a pyramid of height four,
I could simply get rid of a
hash here and a hash there
and a hash there and a hash there.
And now I have a pyramid of height four.
And pyramid of height three too, I could
say get rid of this hash and this hash
and this hash and this hash.
And now I have a
pyramid of height three.
I could keep going, a pyramid of height
two and even a pyramid of height one,
just to help you visualize what's
at stake in this problem here.
So if we want to make our very
own pyramid, a program that
prints our very own pyramid, why
don't we go ahead and make a file
called Mario.
I'll say code mario.c.
And inside I'll do the usual things.
I'll include stdio.h.
I'll include cs50.h, these header files
that have the CS50 library and Standard
I/O library somewhat defined in them.
I'll then say int main(void)
to kick off this program.
And on the inside, what's
the first thing I should do?
I probably want to get
height from the user.
But how could I do that, those
of you who are here live?
How could I get a height from the
user to print out this pyramid?
So I'm seeing, maybe I want to
use something like an integer
to store the height because, again, this
pyramid will be some number of blocks
tall.
So I like the idea.
Let's go with that.
I'll say int height here.
And I could, for instance, say
int height equals 5 off the bat.
But I could probably get the input
from the user using that function
we saw earlier, get_int, like this.
And I'll prompt the
user for some height.
So now it's a good idea, once I'm at
some stopping point in my program,
to try to compile it
and see if it works.
I'll then type make mario, hit
Enter, and I'll type ./mario.
I'll see I'm prompted for a height.
I'll hit 5 here and nothing happens.
But at least I know my program tends
to work at this particular stage.
So let's think about how we could use
functions to be solving this problem.
Now, here we have this
function called get_int.
But it's worth actually diving
into what get_int is doing for us
and talking through some vocabulary
that can help us understand
what get_int is actually doing.
So for that, we'll focus on functions.
And notice here how we can
actually define get_int.
We, at CS50, define
this function for you.
You don't see its definition
in your actual code
because you can only just use it now.
But we did work on defining
this function for you.
And notice a few pieces
of this function.
Notice how, up front, we have this
idea of the name for this function,
this one called get_int.
We could think of it kind
of like that black box
we saw Dave mention in lecture.
We have some algorithm, some
function, that is called get_int,
some black box here that's going to
take an input and give us some output.
Now, we can also define
the output of get_int.
We could do this part for you.
We said that it will take
an input, in this case,
called prompt that is of type string.
So notice how when I used get_int,
I typed in a string as the input
to get_int.
This input was called
height followed by a colon.
So now, in this case, we see
that get_int takes a string that
within that function is called prompt.
And then what does get_int give us?
Well, at the very end of the day, it
gives us back an integer, in this case,
a whole number that the user
actually typed in themselves.
And so, of course, we would use
this function a bit like this.
We could say, take in a prompt to
give us back two or four or so on.
But we use it using int height
gets the value of something
like this function,
get_int followed by height.
And when this function
runs, it returns to us
what we said it would return over
here, something of type integer,
if that makes sense.
So questions then on this function
declaration, what we did over here
to define what get_int is doing for us?
OK.
Not seeing too many questions here.
So why don't we keep working
on our Mario program?
I'll go back over here.
And we saw before that I could
print out a single row of hashes
using a for loop, right?
But maybe it would be
worthwhile to consider
how I could put that code that
prints out a single line of hashes
into its own separate
function that I could
use in my main part of my program,
this one called main up here.
If I wanted to define that code that
writes that line of hashes for me
separately, I could probably
put it in its own function.
And to define my own function, I
could probably go down below here
and say something like this.
Why don't I create this new function.
I'll call it, in this case, print_row.
And what kind of input do you think
print_row should take, ideally?
Maybe I want to modify
the length of the row.
How could I say print_row takes
an input to modify the length?
Any ideas in the chat?
One thing I could do is think,
well, the input to this function,
I want it to be the number of
hashes to print on the row.
So that seems to be
a number, an integer.
So I could say, print row takes
an input that is of type integer.
And I have to give it a name.
I'll call it, in this case,
length, the length of that row.
And now I'll think, what
should print_row return to me?
Well, it doesn't really
return me a value.
If I'm going to use it, it simply
just prints things out to the screen.
In lecture, we saw a difference
between return values and side effects.
In this case, it just has a side effect.
It just prints things to the screen.
So actually make sure that this
return value is simply void.
It's nothing in particular.
So now print row is a separate function.
It has an input called
length that is of type int.
And it returns to me
nothing in particular,
just prints things out to the screen.
So now inside of print row, I
could have that very same loop we
saw earlier, perhaps a for loop.
I'll say for int i is 0.
And i is less than--
i is less than what?
Before, we saw 4 to get a length
of 4 or 3 to get a length of 3.
But now I want it to
be a variable length.
I could decide later what
I want the length to be.
I'm seeing some folks
saying maybe I could
use this variable that's input
to print_row called length.
I'll try that.
i is less than length i plus plus.
So now when I use this function
print_row, I could pass in some number.
And then I'll loop that
many times in my for loop.
And what will I do for each loop?
Well, I'll print out, in this case,
I will print out a hash each time.
At the end of all that looping,
I'll print out simply backslash n
to move to a new line.
So this is my print_row
function down below.
Now, if I go up top, I
could try to use print_row.
I could say, well, I want to print a row
that has the length of four, like this.
So I'll first get the input
of height from the user.
And I'll not use it for now.
I'll just use print_row
with the value 4.
I'll go to my terminal here,
type make mario, hit Enter,
and I seem to be getting an error.
What is the error?
You'll see here, implicit declaration
of function print_row is invalid in C99.
What ideas does that
bring up for you here?
What might I be doing wrong?
Yeah, so it seems I
haven't actually included
what we're calling the
prototype for this function.
So if I look down below here-- actually,
if I read my program top to bottom,
like C would, I'll see I'm
going to include some files,
have a main function, get the
height, and then call this function
or use this function called
print_row and give it the value 4.
But up until now, if I'm
reading top to bottom,
I actually haven't seen the
definition for print_row.
Where is it?
Well, it's below.
It's down here on line 10.
But I can't be calling
this function if I
haven't told C that's going
to come up in my program yet.
So what I should do instead is
take the function prototype, that
is its name, its input,
and its return value,
and put it at the top of my program,
often by convention, below my includes.
And I'll follow it
with a semicolon here,
saying this is my function prototype.
This is the line of code
that tells C, I promise
I'm going to define for you
what print row is later.
But for now, just let me use it
when I say I'm going to use it.
So now in main, hopefully
C doesn't actually
complain when I use print_row
because up top I told it
exactly what I'm going to use as well.
So now I'll type make mario, hit
Enter, and that seems to work.
So now I'll type ./mario, hit Enter,
say the height is 6, hit Enter,
and I get this line of only four hashes.
But what could I do
to update this program
to print out not just four hashes, but
the same number that the user typed in?
I want to modify this piece here.
But how could I modify it?
Yeah, I'm seeing some ideas.
I could probably use this
variable called height.
So we know that this
variable called height
is a container for the number
I typed in, in this case, 6.
So if I want to pass in that same
value to print_row for it to print out
a row of that length, I could instead
say print_row parentheses height
and save that.
Now I'll type make mario, ./mario,
and type in a height of 5.
Now I get, in this case,
five hashes down below.
And notice in particular that in this
case, the name of the variable that I
am, what we call, passing
into, or inputting to,
this function print_row that
is not the same as the variable
I said I would get down below,
this integer called length.
What actually happens is height, we
have storing a value, in this case,
five down below, that value for
height is given to print_row.
And as long as I'm running
the code in print_row,
that value, 4, will be associated
with this name, length, in this case.
So I took the value that height
stored, 5, I gave it to print_row.
And as long as print_row
is running, that value, 5,
is now called length in the
context of this function print_row.
We call that this idea of
scope in computer science.
So here we have a way to take
the user's height and a way
to print a row of that height.
We're not quite all the way there yet.
But what questions do we
have on the code so far?
I'm seeing a question here.
Is there any situation where
not prototyping but declaring
the function above main would be better?
So notice here we had the
prototype for print_row above main.
But we had the definition
for print_row below it.
Now, I think the question is asking, is
it ever useful to do essentially this,
to cut and paste this and put
it above main, a bit like this?
You certainly could.
But I find it more
readable, in this case,
to have the main function up first
because when we run our program,
the main function will always be
the first to run, so more style
for style's sake than
anything else, in this case.
Question here.
In line 4 and 12, you have declared
void print_row int length two times.
Why is that OK because we
can't do that with variables?
That's actually a good observation.
So if I were to, for instance on line
eight, create a variable called height
and then later on create a new
variable called height, like this,
I would find that C, when I try to
compile my program, doesn't like that.
I can only have one variable
under one name at the same time.
I can't have two variables
with the same name.
Here though it seems like I have
two functions with the same name.
I have one called print_row up
here and print_row down below.
I think the answer to
this is that built in to C
is this syntax that if you have a
function you want to use and to define
later in your code, you simply
copy and paste the prototype,
its name, its input, its output,
put it at the top of your file,
and C knows this is a function
that will later be defined.
It's on a separate function
with the same name.
And one more question here.
Why is height printing length when
logically height is up and down
and not left to right?
That's a great question.
We're going to fix
that in just a moment.
So here we notice that,
in my separate file--
I'm going to make code pyramid.txt.
If I wanted a pyramid of
height, let's say, three,
notice how the bottom row has
length three, in this case.
So a pyramid of height three, the bottom
most row, that has the length of three.
But also notice how above this has
length two and then length one up top.
So there's probably an
association between the height
and the actual length of
these rows I'm printing.
So what if we tried
something a bit like this.
I know I want to print
more than one row.
And I probably want to do it
in a way that involves a loop.
We saw a loop as a way to
do things more than once.
So I could say maybe something like,
for int i equals 0 i is less than--
well, how many rows should
I print in this case?
If I have a pyramid of height
three, how many rows should I print?
Seems like three.
So I think, in this case, it's
safe to loop height number of times
and increase i by one every time we go.
So now inside this loop, I'll print_row.
And maybe I'll keep it the same
with this input called height.
So let's try that.
I'll say make mario,
./mario, height of three.
And I got a square.
So it seems like we're getting there.
But I need to change
something about this program.
What should I change do you think?
So I'm seeing a few ideas.
One is actually to use
this variable here,
i, that we declared and
initialized inside of our for loop.
So as long as we are within this
for loop, within its curly braces,
I actually have access to this variable,
i. i is what's called in scope.
I could use it throughout
this portion of my code.
So maybe I don't want to print
a row that is of length height,
but maybe of length i.
So first, i would be zero.
And then it would be one.
And then it would be two and so on.
So actually, if I look at my
pyramid, my very first row
is one, then two, then three.
So maybe I don't want to first print
out zero, I want to print out one.
But how could I change this to
not print out zero first, but one?
Any ideas?
I'm seeing maybe I could
just add one as we go.
So that's actually a good idea.
Why don't I say, first i is zero.
But when i is zero, I want
to print out one hash.
So I'll say, just take i
and increase it by one.
Well, next, i will be one
after going through this loop.
Then I'll say, well, how many
hashes do I want to print?
Well, just one more than
what i currently is.
So I'll maybe say that's print out
a row of length i plus one again.
And then i will be two.
I want three hashes.
So I'll just say i plus one again.
And so maybe this should work.
So I'll say, make mario and then
./mario, pyramid of height three.
And now I seem to be getting somewhere.
So I'll make my terminal bigger.
I'll say, make mario, ./mario
again, height of five.
And I seem to be getting what I'm
looking for, this left-aligned pyramid.
So let me ask, what questions do we
have on this implementation of Mario
using left-aligned pyramids
and functions in general?
All right.
So seeing none here.
And, again, the goal
for these sections is
to give you some tools to which you can
go off and solve this week's problem
set.
And now, one more tool
I'll give to you is
to think about how you could use
the same idea of defining a function
to actually work in your favor
on this next Mario problem that
asks you to write not a left-aligned
pyramid, but a right-aligned pyramid.
So we saw just now we created
some function that looked
a bit like this called print_row.
In this case, it takes
an input called bricks.
We called it length, same thing.
Here we're able to take a
length of hashes to print
and then just print that out as we go.
But now you could consider
expanding that function's capability
to take not just one input, but two,
maybe one for some number of spaces
before the actual bricks or
hashes come up and then one
that takes in the number of bricks
to actually print out those hashes
as you go.
So notice how over here, in pyramid.txt,
if I want this to be right-aligned,
I first print out some
number of spaces and then my
hashes as we go to move this
pyramid from being left-aligned
to now being right-aligned.
So we'll leave you with that to
consider as you solve Mario this week.
But that was section one here for CS50.
We'll hope to see you in future weeks.
Thank you all for joining
and see you next time.