SPEAKER 1: OK.
Well hello, one and all, and
welcome to CS50's Week 9 section.
This one on this framework called
Flask, where you can actually build
your very own dynamic web applications.
And there are many topics
we'll get through today,
but the goal is that you're able to
ask the questions you want to ask,
so we can bridge that gap between
lecture and this week's problem set.
So, among the topics
for today are these.
We have this idea of
Flask, this framework
we could use to write web
applications more dynamic than those
we wrote last week.
We also have this new,
kind of templating language
we're going to work with called Jinja.
And along the way, we'll learn all
the more about forms and databases,
where we can actually store user
data in our web applications.
And what I find so
exciting is we're going
to be tying together
a lot of the material
from these past few weeks of
CS50 now to build our very
own application on the web.
So, let's begin by jumping
into this idea of Flask.
So Flask is, again, what
we call a framework.
Flask is a bit like being
handed some tool kit,
and inside that tool kit
are all kinds of tools
you can use to more easily
build some web application.
And as you get more familiar
with the tools of Flask,
I think you'll find you're able to build
applications more quickly, and even
more securely than you could do without
having those tools at your disposal.
That's exactly why people
make things like Flask,
to help you as a programmer
get started with things faster
and do things more securely.
Kind of standing on the shoulders
of people who came before you.
So, Flask, at its core, is a way
of handling interaction on the web.
And we saw in lecture that often when
you're using the web application,
you're interacting with
a site using its routes,
and using what we call HTTP requests.
So let's do a bit of a
refresher here and look
at what you might see in the browser
bar as you go to some web application.
So let's say we go to
birthdays.com, which is
a hint as to what we'll be doing today.
And this very first part that you
will see, https, colon, slash, slash,
is the protocol you're using to talk
to this server called birthdays.com,
let's say.
Now, HTTPS stands for
Hypertext Transfer Protocol,
and the secure version of that.
So this is kind of like a
way of us extending our hand,
and the server then saying
I'm going to shake that hand
and together, we'll know how to
communicate with each other securely.
So this first part is saying,
how are we going to talk?
What is the common language we're going
to use to talk about what you want,
and how I can give it to you.
There's the next part though,
birthdays.com, that we call our domain.
So maybe if you go on
the web, and you try
to get your very own domain like
cartersinc.com, or yourname.com,
you could actually do that
from several providers online.
But this idea of a domain
is kind of like the user
friendly name for our site.
How does a user get to the server
that has all these files on it
that other people can access?
And then the most important piece
here, at least the most important piece
for today, is going to be what
follows this domain, which
is called our route, where
we're accessing the application.
So by default, the basic route
is just a slash at the end.
And means give me, let's say,
the home page of this site.
Whatever is the default page, I want
that page when I go to the slash route.
But we can make all kinds of
different routes on our applications.
Some of them might look like this.
Maybe you've seen websites
that have an about us page.
So the route for that might be
something like slash about dash us.
Or if you're trying to
register for an account,
the route might be slash register.
Or if you're trying to submit some
form, it could be slash submit.
The idea here is that
the application could
come up with their own
names for routes, and then
define what happens when the user goes
to an application at that particular--
or goes to that particular
route on the application.
If that makes sense.
So let me pause here and ask,
what questions we have so far
on this idea of interacting
with a web application
through the routes it might offer us.
What questions do we have so far?
OK.
So not seeing any yet, but feel free
to chime in the chat if you'd like.
What we'll do to explore this idea of
how to build applications with Flask,
is I really jump into
this week's problem set.
And in particular, we'll work
together on the very first problem
in problem set 9, which is this idea
of keep track of our friends birthdays
through a web application.
So I will go to this very particular
problem here called Birthdays.
And as you can see
down below, our goal is
to have this application that allows
us to have a form, like this, where
I could submit somebody's name,
the month of their birthday,
and the day of their birthday.
So if me, Carter, if my birthday is on
January 1st, I would type in Carter.
And the month would be one
for January, and the day
would be one for the
first day of January.
And then down below, we keep track
of all of our friends birthdays.
So it seems like Harry was
born on 7/31, for instance.
We generate this table of birthdays
so we can actually visit this site
and remember whose birthday is when.
So a few things going on here.
We're able to submit a form
to store data persistently
across multiple instances of the site.
And we're also able to
dynamically add things to our site
when we click that Add Birthday button.
So, Flask can help us with
all of these kinds of problems
we're seeing here today.
Now, to get started with
birthdays, I will scroll down,
and I'll go to Getting
Started, and I'll then
click here to download what we call
the distribution code for birthdays.
So I'll go to my code space, and I
will just simply copy paste this in.
And I'll download that birthdays.zip
file containing all the distribution
code for birthdays.
I'll then unzip birthdays.zip.
And then I will type CD birthdays.
And now, if I type ls to list
all the files in this folder,
I should see a few here that are
hopefully familiar from lecture.
So we saw in lecture,
this idea of app.py.
We saw its idea of databases a few
weeks ago, I have birthdays.db.
And we have these two new folders
we learned about briefly in lecture,
static and templates,
where static stores, let's
say, images that don't often change.
Maybe our CSS for instance.
And template stores our
HTML that is rendered
every time the user visits some site.
So let's see what
questions we have here.
I see a few coming in.
One question is about,
we saw this route called
slash submit earlier, which is
one example of some kind of route.
And the question then is, do we have
to have some underlying HTML file
called, let's say, submit.html?
So if the user goes to
slash submit, does the HTML
file they get have to
be called submit.html?
In this case, in the world
of Flask, it does not.
So Flask helps us by allowing
us to have more flexibility
with the naming of our
files, and actually
with generating our files before
they even get sent to the user.
What we call rendering our files,
like we'll see in just a bit.
All right.
So let's keep going.
And one thing in particular, that we
saw in a week prior in week eight,
was this idea of http-server.
So here, I could still use http-serve.
If everything in here
is my Flask application,
I mean, I could still use http-server,
and let me see what happens here.
I'll get this URL where I can
actually access these files.
So I'll connect to this
forwarded port and I'll
see all of those same files now
accessible to me on my own HTTP server.
So let's try going into templates.
And I see index.html,
so I'll click on that.
And I'll see, All Birthdays.
Kind of not complete all the
way yet, but we'll get there,
and we'll work on this together.
I could also go through and let's say
I want to see what's inside static,
I could click on that.
And I see I have this CSS file that
seems to be styling index.html.
We won't focus too much on this today.
But the idea here is that HTTP server
allows us to access these files,
but what it doesn't allow us to do
is actually have interactivity here.
So if I wanted to use HTTP
server to submit a birthday
to store in a database to show
it to my user, at the end,
I couldn't do that with a HTTP server.
I have to use Flask, as we'll
see, to be able to actually
get form data to store it
in a database, and to return
that information to the user.
So if you want to build a
more dynamic application,
you need to use some framework like
Flask, as opposed to a simple HTTP
server here.
So I will hit Control C to
get outside of my HTTP server,
and why don't I try running
my Flask application.
Does anyone remember how we run
a Flask application from lecture?
How do we run a Flask application?
Yeah, so I'm seeing an answer here,
which is by default, we type flask run.
And this is just what the
developers of Flask decided.
They say, when you have your very own
Flask application denoted by app.py,
with your own static folder, and a
templates folder, maybe a database,
you can then run that application
with flask, space, run.
So I will hit Enter here.
Let's see what happens now.
So I'm again given this
URL that seems to be
a server I could access to see my site.
I'll click on that.
And now, I'll see something
pretty familiar from HTTP server.
I'm able to see our Birthdays site,
kind of half finished right now.
There's no form.
No birthdays.
But at least I can see this
index.html page being rendered for me.
So we'll see, as we actually
add more functionality,
what Flask can do for us.
But for right now, Flask seems to just
be giving us that very basic HTML file
inside of our templates folder.
A question here.
What is the base file it runs?
Like what is the runner?
What is the application here?
A very good question.
So let me open up a
new terminal, and let
me go back into our birthdays
folder, and let me show
you the structure of this site again.
So, here we have a few different files.
The main one, when you're talking
about a Flask application, is app.py.
This is what you might call
the brains of the operation.
It is what listens for requests to our
server, and decides how to handle them.
For instance, if I, a user,
accessed the slash route,
app.py will decide what
kind of content I should
get when I access the slash route.
We call this framework like a
model-view-controller framework.
So app.py is the controller
deciding what we actually
see at the end of the day.
All right.
And just to formalize this a
little bit, let me go to this slide
here and show you what
Flask can really do for us.
So really, the reason
you might use Flask
is, again, to listen for
requests to a certain route.
That is what app.py is doing.
Maybe a user goes to
the slash route, then
they should be sent some
particular HTML file.
Flask is what can do that for us.
Importantly though, it can also
execute Python code, depending
on the route that gets requested.
And it can also render HTML files,
depending on the route requested,
which makes it very
powerful because we're
able to build up HTML files as the
user requests them from our server.
So as we saw in lecture, one
of the most basic applications
we can build in Flask
looks a bit like this.
So we have app.py.
And we then might add in some starter
code, some boilerplate template
code like this.
And this is simply just
how the developers of Flask
decided we would indicate that
this is a Flask application.
We're going to first
import this idea of Flask,
this class called Flask,
from the Flask library.
And we're then going to
say, in that very same file,
that we're going to create some app.
App equals Flask, and then
parentheses we call dunder name, which
is the name of this file we have here.
All that line of code
does is say, this file
is going to be our Flask application.
And then, really the heart of
things come in a little bit
later, where we can
actually specify what
we want to have happen when a
user requests a certain route.
So here, at app.route.
And then in the middle means
that this function index
will be run every time the
user tries to access that slash
route on our application.
And what could we do?
Well, we could return to the user, like
we saw in lecture, something as simple
as Hello, world, where they would
just see Hello, world in their browser
if they go to the slash
route of our application.
But really, the power of Flask comes in
by not just returning regular old text,
but by returning templates
that get rendered as we go.
So what we tend to use
instead is this function
called render template,
where Flask will take an HTML
file that we give it, like index.html,
will render it, add in some data,
and then show that data back to us
as we go on our own application.
So let's see what this looks
like in birthdays here.
So why don't I go back
to our application.
Go back to our application.
And I will now code app.py to
see what is going on inside.
So it looks like we have a
few things going on here,
but let's focus on what's
familiar at least at first.
Up top, I see we're still
importing from Flask.
Import Flask, that seems
familiar from before.
We're still configuring our application.
And if I scroll down
some more, I should see
that we do have a function to run when
the user requests this slash route.
And this is called index here.
Doesn't have to be called index, but
at least for our purposes, it is.
Now on the inside, we
have to make a choice did
the user make a request
with POST or with GET,
and it seems like we need to maybe
fill in these TODOs as to how we
can make our application actually work.
But notice here, at the
very base, if I simply
make a GET request to this
website using the slash route,
I should get the rendered
version of index.html,
which is exactly what's happening here.
If I go to my application, go
to the simple slash route here,
I'm simply rendered index.html here.
So let's see what
questions we have so far.
I see one, which is, is the at Flask
syntax or is that Python syntax?
That's a great question.
So here we see at, the
at sign, app.route.
So this at sign is a character
that we use in Python
to denote what we call a decorator.
So a decorator is a
function, in this case
app.route, that we
extend the functionality
of with our very own function here.
So you can use decorators to extend the
functionality of some base function.
In this case, the authors
of Flask, they wrote
this function called route that
handles a lot of things for us.
When the user asks for
a route, there's a lot
that goes on between the
server and the client, that
is their very own computer.
And by making this a decorator,
what Flask allowed us to do
is not worry about all these
kinds of low level details,
it allows us to specify
just what we want
to have happen as the user
asks for this particular page.
So Flask will handle all
the underlying details.
All we have to do is specify,
through our very own function
here, what we want the user
to see at the end of the day.
And so here, we do that
by specifying the return
value of this particular function.
Do we want to redirect the
user to the slash trail,
basically send them back there
again with a GET request,
or do we want to simply render
this template called index.html.
A good question.
Let's see what other ones we have.
What is GET and what is POST?
A great one.
So we learned about this
very briefly in lecture,
and I think it's an important
one here because we're seeing
GET and POST come up in various ways.
So let's take a look at these
different request methods
and how they can actually
influence our application,
before we dive into working on this
birthdays application ourselves.
So, when we're working with
applications on the web,
there are a few ways
to interact with them.
They all involve requests,
but among these requests
are two methods with which we can
actually access our application, which
we can request a route.
So on the one hand, we have
a very simple GET request,
where let's say we have a server
on the right hand side here,
and a client or a computer
on the left hand side here.
And if this client, this computer,
wants to access some web page,
they might make what
we call a GET request.
Maybe they say, I want to see what's
on that slash route of this page.
They would send a GET
request to get whatever
is available at that slash route.
So here is them sending that request.
The server, meanwhile,
then says, OK, I understand
you want to get whatever
is at the slash route.
Why don't I give you this file, which
is right there at that slash route.
Maybe in terms of Flask, it says,
let me render this file for you,
and let me give it back to you so you
can see it on your own computer here.
Now one other kind of
request exists as well.
Maybe the user is also
sending the server some data.
Maybe, for instance, it's sending a
birthday for that server to store.
So that's when we would
use a POST request.
A POST request generally allows
us to send data to a server,
and generally implies the server
will do something with that data.
So maybe the user fills out some form.
They say I want you to store Carter's
birthday, which is supposedly
on January 1st.
Then it will be able to send
that data to the server,
and then that data will
be stored by the server.
So GET is more about trying to get
some file from the particular server,
whereas POST involves posting
some information to that server,
in the hopes that it will
store it or do something
with it at the end of the day.
And I asked you a few questions here.
One is that, is POST
encrypted by default?
And is it better to POST
sensitive data versus using GET?
So whether or not POST
and GET are encrypted
depends on the underlying
protocol you're using.
So we saw before, HTTP versus HTTPS.
You could have both of these methods
under HTTP or HTTPS, in either case.
So that has nothing
to do with encryption.
What is different though, is that POST--
when you use POST, it doesn't put
your data in the URL parameter.
So recall in lecture,
when we use GET and we
had the greet application,
when we used GET,
we saw that the name ended
up in the URL address bar.
But when we used POST, it did not.
So POST is better for keeping
information secret because it
doesn't end up in your URL itself,
and thus, in your browser history,
for instance.
So POST is better for things
like credit cards, et cetera.
All right.
So now that we have an
idea of GET and POST,
it seems like we can better understand
how to build up this application.
So let's go back to our code space here.
And let us try this.
We know we want to be able
to submit a birthday here,
but what do we need to do first to
allow the user to submit a birthday?
Just thinking visually, what might
we want a user to be able to do?
Maybe have some kind of like
input box, like a way for them
to type in some information.
Maybe they could click a calendar.
I like what you're thinking there.
But I think we'll stick today with
this idea of a basic form, where they
could submit and type in that data.
So let's go ahead and try to add a
form to our birthdays application.
Well, what could we do there?
Let me go back to some slides and
visualize what we could do with forms.
So with forms, there's
a few things to note.
One, is that a form generally comes
from this form HTML element here.
So if my application is
on the right hand side,
and my code is on the
left hand side, my HTML.
Generally, it could look like
this, where I have an opening
tag and a closing tag for a form.
But now it's up to me to
decide what kinds of text boxes
we'll give to the user.
And as people have been saying, maybe
we can have our very own input box.
So here, I might make
two kinds of inputs.
One, is simply of type text.
And one is actually a
button of type submit,
and maybe I would say submit as the
kind of text the user would see there.
And this would show up on
our application as follows.
I would see this blank text box
for user to type in their text.
And I would then see down below a
button for them to click Submit on.
And because this button has type
submit when they click this form,
that data will then be
submitted to our application.
But for those of you who are feeling
a little more comfortable with forms,
what is this form still missing?
Let's say we have everything
we need in terms of data.
What is it missing?
So giving a few ideas, well, we need
to have a place to submit this data to.
So, as we saw before, it's important
to think about routes and the request
method we're going to use.
So when the user clicks submit, we want
this data to be submitted to the site.
But we need to specify that in our form.
So in the form itself up above, we
could specify two attributes, the action
attribute and the method attribute.
So action says, here is where I want
you to request after you click Submit.
When the user clicks
submit, the next thing we do
is request the particular route.
And then the method attribute
says, which method should
we use to actually access that route.
Should we POST or should it be GET?
Most often for sensitive information,
or really most information in general,
we would use POST for
our form, because POST
is most often about
sending data to our site
and having the site do something
with it at the end of the day.
So, let's see here.
Let's go ahead and try to actually
implement this in our own application
here.
So I currently see nothing
in terms of a form.
But if I go to, not app.py, if I
instead go to my templates, CD--
let's say, templates, and then
type ls, I'll see index.html.
So let me code index.html
to open that file.
And I should see a
little, bit down below,
a TODO that says Create a form for users
to submit a name, a month, and a day.
So, maybe we'll fill in this form here.
As we saw-- whoops.
Defining something I
don't mean to define.
Let me go back to line 17 here and
let me try to actually add this form.
I'll say, have an opening tag
and a closing tag for our form.
And now let me ask you, what
kinds of input should we have,
or input boxes, for our form?
We want to keep track of names, and
months, and days for birthdays, so
what might we need?
Yeah, so one thing we might want to
have is an input box for the name.
And to add an input box, we
simply go within our form element
and add a child, a child input element.
And here, we don't need a
closing tag for an input element
just by convention, but I
should specify a few attributes.
So one of these attributes is,
what kind of data it will accept?
In this case, the type.
So the type will be text
for a name like this.
And one more thing we should
specify is the name for this input.
So that is how do we identify
this particular input
box among the other input
boxes we might have?
So maybe we could call this input box
name itself because we're actually
accepting some person's name.
OK.
What else?
Well, we know we want
an input for the month
that the user is actually able
to have their birthday in.
So I'll say the name
equals here, maybe month.
And the type, well the type
is, in this case, a number.
We want to be able to have the
user type in their input as one
through 12 for the month.
And we also, of course,
want them to be able to type
in the day of their birthday, and the
type of that will be number as well.
Now are we done here?
What else are we missing?
We have three input boxes, but
we're still missing a few things.
What are they?
One of them is a Submit button.
So we saw before, we could make our very
own button element, and make it of type
submit.
That is one approach we could take here.
We could also make an input element
and have that be simply, type submit.
And then have the value be
whatever we want the text to be.
So a few ways here, I'll
show you one new way
that's different from the slides.
This will allow us to have a
button that says Add Birthday,
because the type is submit
and we specified a value here.
Now, when the user clicks that button,
it should allow us to submit this form.
But we're still missing one more thing,
and I have seen people say it already.
We need an action and a method.
So if I say, the action here is, I want
to submit all this data to the slash
route.
As we saw in our app.py, we can accept
both POST and GET request to slash.
So I'll make this method,
the method here, POST.
So now when the user clicks submit,
I should be posting that data
to the actual slash route.
So let's go ahead and go back to our
application here and refresh the page.
I'll use Command R. And I'll see a
place where me to type in some data.
So why don't I try Carter here.
And maybe my birthday is
on January 1st, and I'll
go ahead and add that birthday.
And maybe it's working, maybe it's not.
But it seemed to, at least allow
me to, type in a birthday here
and submit this form, which
is making some progress.
All right.
What questions do we have on this form?
What do we have here?
A good question.
So one is, don't we need
like placeholders for this?
And that's a good idea.
So if I go and look at this,
it's kind of confusing what
I want the user to actually type in.
So I could use placeholder.
I could go in and say the placeholder
for this element is, let's say, name.
The placeholder here is month.
And the placeholder
here is, let's say, day.
Just like this.
So let me go back and
refresh the page, and now we
see some placeholders inside
of our text, which is good.
Question, does this automatically
post to the database?
So, no, it does not.
That'll be up to us, as we
actually implement the dynamic part
of this application inside of app.py.
OK.
So, let's keep going, and this is going
to be a little more exciting than what
we did last week, because I imagine
this is kind of similar to what
we did last week in terms of HTML.
But now that we're using
Flask, we can actually
do things that are a bit more exciting.
So one of these things
we can do, is actually
have an application see whatever
we submitted to our form.
Now we saw in lecture, we can use a
special Flask method, request.form.get,
to actually access whatever
data is inside our form
as it's submitted to a particular route.
So the catch here is that simply,
when we use request.form.get,
we need to make sure that the name we're
requesting, like in this case an email,
matches up with the
name we give our input.
So if the name of this
input is email, then we
have to use request.form.get,
and give as an argument
that very same name,
email, case-sensitive.
Just like that.
So let's try it on our own
application and see what we can see.
I'll go back to my app.py now.
Our code app.py over here.
And-- oops.
Wrong place.
Let me go back up one level
to the birthdays folder.
And now let me code app.py.
And let's see in this.
So here is our route for
this application slash.
And now, we're using the request
method POST because, notice our form,
the method is POST, and
the action is slash.
So, inside of this conditional,
if the request method is POST,
we want to perhaps first
see what the user submitted.
So I could try something like this.
I could maybe say, name
equals request.form.get, name.
And that should hopefully
give me the name
the user entered when
they submitted this form.
I could say, maybe
month, and we'll do month
equals request.form.get,
and now month here.
And then day.
Day equals request.form.get,
and finally day.
So notice how these, name, month,
and day correspond to the names
we gave to these three inputs here.
And then just to be sure,
to a question earlier
about how to debug a Flask
application, one thing I could do
is use print statements.
And I could print out the following.
Name is, and then we
have a f string here.
Name is, and I will interpolate name.
And I'll also maybe print, just for the
sake of knowing whether it's working,
month is month.
And then down below, I'll
also print day is day.
Just like this.
And now hopefully we should
see the very same information
the user entered in the
form, but now in our terminal
helping us know that
at least in this case,
Flask will be able to grab that
form data from our submission.
So I'll open up my terminal, and why
don't I go back to our server here.
Let me refresh the page.
And now I'll type my name
Carter, month one, and day one.
I'll type Add Birthday.
And now let's see.
Seems to have worked.
So Flask is telling me
here, in my terminal,
that it does see that the name
is Carter, the month is one,
and the day is one.
So we've been able to now submit some
data from our form into our app.py.
So let's see what
questions we have here.
One is, how do you specify the form
you are interested in if you have more
than one?
A great question.
So let's say I'm on my
index.html, over here.
And here is kind of easy because
I only have one form, right?
It would be harder though, it would
be harder if I had multiple forms.
And there are a few ways to handle this.
One, is to have those different
forms submit to different routes,
and that would allow me to have
different functions to handle
these different form submissions.
Another way to do this is to
make sure that every input
box has some unique name to it.
So if I have two different forms, it
might be helpful for me to make sure
that those forms have different
names in the input boxes.
So when I go to my app.py, if both these
forms are submitting to the same route,
I can use the name attribute
to only get data from one form
and not from another.
There are probably other ways
to solve this problem too,
but I think the most common way
is to have different forms submit
to different routes.
So, good question there.
Let's see.
Can you store all values in
an array from multiple forms?
So the nice thing about Flask
being a Python framework
is that you can really use
any Python data structure
you'd like to work with form data.
If I wanted to, I could make
a list of all these things.
I could say data is now a list, and
it involves name, month, and day.
And now we'd have a list of these very
variables inside my Python program.
So you can be creative
with these as you'd like.
OK.
So I think we're making
some progress here.
We're able to actually
access, in this case,
the form data from our
submission, which is great.
But the next step--
the next step is going
to be to figure out
how we can store this data
inside of our database.
So currently, it's just all
inside Python, which is fine,
but I want to persist this information.
Have it recognized in my
database, kind of long term.
So if I show you what's
currently inside my database,
I will open up a new terminal here
and I will do sqlite3 birthdays.db.
Just like this.
I can type .schema, And I'll see
that this is the table inside
of birthdays.db.
We have a column for name, a column
for month, and a column for day.
So now I'll SELECT star
FROM birthdays, semicolon,
and I'll see I actually already
have three birthdays in there.
But now I want to be able
to add in my own birthday,
and see some more birthdays
inside this database.
So, one way to do this is
to take advantage of the way
that Flask can communicate with
our very own database here.
So if I scroll up, I should
see this line on line 13.
And this-- thanks to the
CS50 library --allows us
to talk to birthdays.db using Python.
And in particular, if I scroll down, I
can use this method called db.execute.
Db.execute.
And the way db.execute works is, I can
type in a SQL query as an argument,
and then run that SQL query,
in this case, on birthdays.db.
So if I wanted to
select all birthdays, I
could simply say SELECT
star FROM birthdays.
And then that would be it.
I would get back a list of dictionaries
of all the birthdays in that database.
But in this case, we
want to insert some data.
And let me ask now,
what kind of SQL query
could we write to insert some
birthday into our database?
We could focus just on SQLite here.
What could I type to add in a new
birthday to this table of birthdays
here?
Seeing insert into is a good start.
So I'll insert into, in this case some
particular table, birthdays, like this.
And now I'll specify the
columns I want to add data to.
So if you're familiar,
I want to add data
to the name, month, and day
columns, just like this.
And now add a new line
here, just for style sake.
Now, what should I do?
Let's say we're trying to
add my own birthday here,
I need to say the values.
So I'll say the values, and then let's
say, I'll go with a different one.
I'll go with-- let's
just choose Charlie.
Charlie, and their birthday
is on February 1st, like this.
Semicolon, Enter.
And now if I SELECT
star FROM birthdays, I
see that Charlie has been
added to this database.
So I can do this same
thing, but now in app.py.
Why don't I go to db.execute
again and type in that same query.
INSERT INTO birthdays, the name,
the month, and the day columns.
The values are going to be---
what are the value is going to be?
I don't quite know yet.
I'm seeing some question marks, which I
think is less indicative of a question
and more so what we
should actually use here.
So a question mark is our way of
having a placeholder in this query.
So similar to what we've seen
with print F, earlier in C,
we're able to specify a
special kind of character
to indicate a placeholder in our query.
And that in this case,
is a question mark.
So I'll say values, question
mark, comma, question mark, comma,
question mark.
So three placeholders for
three different values.
Now what are those three values?
Well, they're whatever we get in
name, month, and day from the user.
So the first one is name, then
month, then day, just like this.
And that hopefully should allow
us to actually take this form data
and then run this SQL query to
add it into our birthdays.db.
So, let's try it and see if we see
anything pop up in our database.
I will clear my SQLite prompt, and
I will SELECT star FROM birthdays.
So this is what we currently have here.
Why don't I now go back to my
application, refresh the page.
And now I'll choose Carter,
January 1st, Add Birthday.
And now, if I SELECT
star FROM birthdays,
I should see that now Carter is added
into our list of birthdays, all thanks
to db.execute.
So what questions do we have here
on how we added data to our database
using Flask and the CS50 library?
Is there another SQLite
library to use similar to CS50?
So I think our own library is based
on a library called SQLAlchemy,
if you're familiar.
If you want to learn more about
that, you can look it up online.
Question, if you have a long
query, how should you properly
format on multiple lines?
That will depend on your own style.
I think generally, one way
to do that is as follows.
If you have a long query,
I tend to do something
like this, where you have three
quotes, and then hit Tab or Enter.
Here it is on multiple lines.
And then close again with three
quotes down below like this.
Some people would say,
looks a little messier.
Let me see if I can make
it any better, actually.
Something like this.
And then, name, month, and the--
there are formatters that
will actually do this for you,
so you don't need to specify
exactly how this needs to look.
But you can do things like
this if you want to make
it a little more readable, overall.
Other questions too.
I'll leave it all as one line for now.
Can we use an F-string
instead of question mark?
You could, but you really
shouldn't, and that's
because of SQL injection attacks,
which you learned about a little bit,
I think two weeks prior
in our week seven.
SQL injection attacks allow the
user to add in any kind of SQL code
they want to.
When you use these question marks here--
these question marks, they
take care of guarding you
against SQL injection attacks.
Whereas an F-string, a
regular F-string, does not.
So you could use them,
but you really should not.
OK.
I think that just about covers
most of our questions here.
So let's keep going.
Now one thing before we move on--
I'll only touch on this briefly
--is that what we've done here
is we've kind of trusted that
the user will give us some data.
And let's see what could
go wrong if for instance, I
don't follow that assumption.
I'll SELECT star FROM birthdays.
Why don't I then go and just not--
I'll click Add Birthday,
but I won't type anything
in to this particular form.
I'll Add Birthday, and now, let me
try selecting star from birthdays,
and I don't know if I want
this row in my database.
This is kind of not
what I expected here.
So, I think what happened
is, when I clicked Submit,
I simply trusted the user
would have some data to insert.
In this case though, they didn't.
They just sent me some empty
strings, and then my application
added those empty
strings to my database.
So, why don't I just delete this.
I'll DELETE FROM birthdays
WHERE id equals 6.
And then I'll SELECT star
again, so that is gone.
But I could guard against
this by being a little more
smart about when I request user input.
So when I get user
input, it's a good habit
to actually check if it
matches my expectations.
So I could say something like this.
If not name-- if I don't get back
a name, maybe it's an empty string,
maybe it's a special
keyword called none,
I should just redirect the
user back to the slash route.
So here, I won't actually
get down to the portion
where I execute the SQL statement.
I will instead, just prematurely
redirect them to the slash route.
I could do the same for month.
I could say if not month, that
is if month is an empty string,
then redirect to the slash route.
And if not day, then redirect
to the slash route as well.
This will simply return the user
back to that slash route overall.
I could maybe make this
a little more shorter,
I could say if not name or
not month, and et cetera.
But for now, I'll leave it as this.
The main thing though,
is that you're often
testing for things you
don't want to have happen,
and handling them before you do what you
think you want to do with the user data
down below.
All right.
So now that we've seen
some validation, I
think our last step is to see these
birthdays actually printed out
on the screen.
So let's try that.
And to start, let's go down to
this else here in this final TODO.
Which is display the entries
in the database on index.html.
Display the entries.
So here, we've handled the case
where the user submits data via POST.
But when they simply go to this
page, perhaps for the first time,
or they just refresh it
without submitting the form,
we want them to see some
birthdays down below here.
But the question first is, well, what
data should we show in index.html?
Seems like the data in our database.
What ideas do you have
for how we can actually
pull all that data from our database?
We've seen a tool we could use before.
What could we use to get that
database information now?
So I see some suggestions.
We could maybe use request.form.
That is good for getting
data from the form itself
when the user submits
that data via POST.
In this case, we want to actually
get data from our database,
and we could use db.execute to
execute some query on our database.
So I could choose db.execute,
and then maybe whatever query
would give me back all entries
in the database on index.html.
So why don't I say SELECT
star FROM birthdays,
which would give me back
every row inside of birthdays
and every column, which
seems good enough for me.
Why don't I then give that a name.
I could say, maybe I'll call this rows.
These are the rows
returned by my database.
And then I'll print
out rows to my terminal
to see if this is working so far.
So I'll go to Birthdays,
and I will refresh the page.
You're making a GET request there.
Now I'll go back to my Flask
server running in my terminal,
and I'll see some data.
You can see this down below here.
This is what db.execute returned
to me, and notice that it
seems to be a list of dictionaries.
It's a list because, notice on the
outside it has these square brackets.
And it's a list of dictionaries
because on the inside, notice
how we have curly braces, and in the
middle, lots of key and value pairs.
So the id is a key.
The value is 1.
The name is the key.
The value is Harry.
Same for month and day.
And notice how for each row, we have
our very own dictionary and some data
in terms of keys and values.
So this is what we could use to
render our birthdays in index.html.
But first we need to pass this
information into index.html in order
to render it.
And as we saw in lecture, we can do this
by adding in a special keyword argument
to render template.
So in index.html, if I want to be able
to access this particular data, rows,
under some name in index.html, I
could say something like as follows.
Maybe birthdays equals
rows, and that will
allow me to access the same data
that's in rows, but now under the name
birthdays in index.html.
So let's try that.
I'll go to index.html.
And I will scroll down, and
I'll go down to my table body.
And let's say I want to show
whatever's inside birthdays.
Because remember, I told render template
that inside of this variable birthdays,
they would have the data
that's inside of rows.
So now I'll make the
special placeholder syntax.
This comes from Jinja, our
templating syntax, that says,
whatever is inside of birthdays, show
it to me right here on this page.
So now let me go back
to our application.
I will refresh the page.
And I see some data, but it
doesn't look properly formatted.
So I think things are
happening, which is
that I'm able to pass in that same
data from Rose to my application,
it just doesn't look very pretty.
So what I could do is use
some other features of Jinja
that are very similar in
spirit to Python to print
this information out row by row by row.
And for this, what I find very handy
is that Jinja has a special kind
of for loop similar to Python.
If I want to make a for loop in
Jinja by convention, I do this.
I could have this denoted inside of
this bracket percent sign, and then
percent sign bracket.
I could say for, and
then similar to Python,
let's maybe do for
birthday in birthdays.
This could be anything, it
could be for a row in birthdays,
but I'll stick with birthday
here, kind of by convention.
And now I need to close this
for loop, endfor down below.
This is just syntax you would learn
by using Jinja more frequently.
Now in the inside, I could do the very
same thing I would do in a Python loop.
I could, for instance, say, give me,
let's say, birthday.name, which means,
on this particular dictionary,
for this particular row
in my list of dictionaries, access
the value with the key, name.
So birthday.name says,
in this dictionary,
give me the value for
the name, the name key.
And to make sure this is actually
being added properly to my table,
let me try inside this
for loop, to add a td--
or a tr element.
Sorry, a tr means table row.
And then inside of this, I'll add a td
element, which stands for table data,
or kind of like a table column.
So here I have the name
associated with the birthdays.
I'll go back to my page, refresh it.
And now I actually see the names
more nicely formatted for me.
And if I choose to go to Developer
Tools, if I Zoom in a little bit
over here, notice how if I go to
container, this table, tbodyy--
notice how for every birthday
in my list of birthdays,
I now have a tr element here.
All thanks to Jinja and the
templating syntax there.
So let's clean this up.
I'll make sure I have not just
birthday.name, but also birthday.month,
and then slash birthday.day, like this.
And that should complete my for loop.
So if I refresh the
page again, now I should
see that I have all my
birthdays very nicely listed out
in terms of this table down below.
So let me ask now, what questions we
have on our templating for Jinja here?
A good question I see, who
plugs in these values for us?
So, here, I'm using this
placeholder notation,
with these double curly braces.
But who is actually in charge
of substituting these values?
Well, Flask actually is, in particular,
the render template function is.
So notice how when I make a
GET request to the slash route,
if it's not a POST
request, we'll go down here
and we will select all birthdays
from the birthdays table.
Then I will render the
template index.html,
passing in data for
this birthdays variable
that we're having to use in index.html.
So what render template does is
it takes this HTML file, exactly
as you see it here, it looks
through it and it says something
like, I see this variable
called birthdays,
but what data should
go inside of birthdays?
Well hopefully, I was told
what data should go in there.
It will then look and
see, OK, I was told
which information should go in there.
I will render that for me, and I will
actually substitute in these values
and return it to you
as this version here.
So notice how in this
version, its render template
has replaced all of the placeholders
with actual pieces of data.
So you don't see the placeholder syntax
anymore, but you see the actual data.
Let's see, would each user get a
new table for their saved birthdays?
In fact, every user would get a
new row, because in for loop here,
we said for every birthday in birthdays,
add some new table row to our table.
So let's try this out.
Maybe I'll add in another birthday.
I'll add one for--
let's go ahead and add
Amy's Birthday, which
is the fifth month and the fifth day.
I'll add the birthday and we
should see that Amy pops up
down below, with the birthday on 5/5.
All right.
How did these get their formatting?
So we saw here, this is a number, and
then a slash, and then a number again.
We simply specify that in our HTML.
So if I go to index.html
here, notice how in this td,
I have a placeholder for the
month, followed by a slash.
This slash, which is like
literally, I want to show up there.
And then afterwards, I
have the birthday.day.
So this is how it renders, where
I see the birthday.month, and then
a literal slash, and
the day afterwards too.
Good question.
Let me actually let you see it.
So here we have the two, and
the slash, and then the one.
Like that.
Cool.
OK.
Other questions on Flask in general?
So suffice to say for now,
there are a few improvements
still to be made to this application.
One, is this idea of trying to
add more validation to user input.
So notice how on app.py,
all we did was simply
ask if the user didn't
give us information.
But it could be useful,
maybe on your own,
to try to check if the
user gave us a month.
That's great, but we
also want to make sure
that that number is between one and 12.
Or for the day, we want to make sure
that the day is between one and 31.
So always try to not
trust your user input,
and try to have those
validations in place.
Similarly, in our index.html,
if I scroll up, let's see this.
I can also specify other attributes.
I could maybe specify for this
input of type number, a minimum.
The minimum the user could type
in is one, and the max is 12.
That allows me to have some
client-side validation.
And same for day.
Maybe it's minimum one and maximum 31.
But that's all fine and
good, we just also want
to have that validation as
well on the server side too.
So I'll leave that part up to you.
And I think with that, we have really
seen a lot of what Flask can offer us.
We're able to build our very
own birthdays application.
And I think with that, we'll go ahead
and conclude our last CS50 section
for this week.
This was CS50'S Week 9 section,
and we'll see you all next time.