CARTER ZENKE: OK,
well, hello one and all
and welcome to CS50's week two section.
This week we learned about arrays.
That is how to store data inside of
a computer using our very first data
structure, if you will,
this way of storing data
back to back in a computer's memory.
So the goal of these sections here is to
help you bridge the gap between lecture
and this week's problem set.
So we'll go through a few
of the lecture topics,
have you all ask the
questions you want to ask,
and get some practice that
might help you as you go off
and work on the problem set
individually on your own.
So to begin, my, name is Carter Zenke.
I'm one of the course's
preceptors here on campus.
If you want to be in touch with me, feel
free to email me at this email right
here, carter@cs50.harvard.edu.
But a brief overview of today.
Today will look a bit like this.
We'll begin focusing on
this idea of compilation.
How do we take the code that
we write in C, for instance,
that source code we write
in a file, and how do we
convert that to the zeros and
ones that a computer actually
understands and can run?
We'll then focus on this idea of arrays.
How do we store data more
efficiently than we've seen before?
And then we'll focus in particular
on this idea of a string.
How do we store characters
that then themselves
form entire words or sentences
inside of our computers?
And finally, towards
the end, we'll focus
on this idea of command line arguments.
So you've already been using programs
that use command line arguments in CS50
already.
But now you get to see
exactly what they are
and how you could write programs
that actually use them yourself.
So let's dive right
into compilation then.
So in lecture, we
learned that compilation
was a way of taking the source code
we write, let's say some code in C,
and converting it into the actual
binary a computer understands.
And our computer, as much as
we might like to think so,
it doesn't understand
C as a language itself.
There's an extra step that we have
to follow called compilation that
takes that source code and
converts it to the binary
that our computer actually
understands at the end of the day.
So here, for example, is some
piece of source code in C.
And I'm curious, for
those of you who are here,
can you spot the bug
in this source code?
This is some C code here.
If I were to run, make to compile
this code, I might get some error.
And I'm curious if you can
spot what that error might be.
So I'm seeing a few people saying
that we're missing the F in printf.
There is no function in C
called just print, at least
in the standard library.
So we have to say this is printf.
And the point here is that when you're
using source code, these kinds of bugs
are, well, they're
more obvious to catch.
If you're writing source code, it's
kind of obvious, at least more so
in other cases, what
bugs you might have.
But now let's consider, like
we learned from lecture,
that the next step in compilation
is taking this source code
and converting it into this middle
language called assembly code.
And this is an example
of assembly code here.
And I'm curious, for
those of you in this room,
can you spot the bug in this program?
Or could you tell me if there
is a bug in this program at all?
Feel free to take a
look at this code, even
if you're not familiar with assembly.
I'm seeing some shaking heads here.
So the point here is that
you get this lower level
language, going beyond C, which is our
source code, moving to assembly code,
it gets a little harder
to spot the kinds of bugs
that arise in our programs.
And now let's take it one step further.
Let's go from assembly code
down to the binary itself.
And I'll ask the same question.
Could you spot the bug in this code?
Feel free to chime in if
you think you have it.
I'm hearing some folks
say, not a chance.
You can't find the bug in this code.
That's to be expected, right?
Nobody among us is going to
be an expert in binary that
can kind of parse through
each individual 0 and 1
and find the bug in this code.
So there's this idea of
trust in computer science,
that when you run this program,
called Make at least in cs50,
or other programs, like
compile other source code,
you're kind of trusting that it's going
to take your source code as you have it
and compile it exactly
as is down in to binary.
But you might not know if somebody
were to be a bit of like a hacker
and try to maliciously
alter your compile
to introduce a bug on the way of
converting your source code down
to machine code, like 0s and 1s.
So it goes to show you that
often in computer science
we use programs that we need to--
we use programs that we aren't quite
sure whether we should trust or we
shouldn't.
And the only way to find out is to
actually be trustworthy individuals.
So as you go off in the
world of computer science
and you write your own
programs, write your own source
code that converts things perhaps
from source code to machine code,
you have to kind of trust yourself
to be trustworthy in these cases
to help us make the programs we
want to make at the end of the day.
So we'll focus not so much on technical
parts of compiling here, but more so
on the actual ethical aspects of it too.
So questions then on
compilation, this idea
of converting source
code to machine code?
Any questions so far?
All right, so the key thing to take away
here is just that when you are in CS50
and you're working on compiling your
code, you'll use this program called
Make that converts your source
code in C down to machine code.
As you go off and learn
more computer science,
you'll see just how up in
the air these things can be
and how much you have to actually
trust the programs you're
using along the way.
All right, and a question here.
What will we be using in the
real world to compile our C code?
So in the real world,
just like in CS50, you'll
likely use a program called Make.
And there are various
options that Make can have.
In this case, in CS50 we've
kind of specified those for you.
As you go off in the
world of computer science
and you try to expand your horizons,
you might yourself set the options
for Make to more
clearly specify what you
want the end result to be when you
convert that source code to machine
code.
All right, so let's keep going here.
And our next topic from
this week's lecture
was this idea of arrays that is a way
of storing data in a computer's memory.
So in this week's
problem set, you'll also
get to see a bit of a game that's
popular I believe kind of around
the world, one called Scrabble.
And if you're not
familiar, in Scrabble you
get these individual letter pieces,
like ones for W, or ones for H,
or ones for D, for instance.
And each of those letters has
on it a certain point value.
So let's see.
Letter H, that little square
that has H on it, that
has four points that has been awarded.
D, that little square that has D on it,
that has two points associated with it.
And as you play this game, the
goal is to take these letters
and convert them into entire words.
So if you had, for instance,
something that looked a bit like this,
you had these five letters, what word
could you make from these five letters?
You could probably make hello.
So you can take all these five letters,
convert them into this word, hello.
And in Scrabble you'll play a
word that looks a bit like this.
So notice here that H
is worth four points.
E is worth one point.
L is worth one point.
And O is worth one point.
And if you add all of these points up,
4 plus 1, plus 1, plus 1, plus 1, well,
you get a total of 8 points
for playing this word.
Now there's actually a
correspondence conceptually
between this idea of Scrabble
and this idea of arrays.
So in the same way that we're
taking individual pieces of data
or individual squares of
letters and convert them
into one long word or one
long space in computer memory,
we're doing the same thing with arrays.
We're taking these
individual pieces of data
and lining them up back to back
to back in a computer's memory
to store that data even better as
we go and work on our programs.
So let's think ahead.
And in CS50 you'll actually get to
make your very own final project.
And here is, for example, one
student's final project in CS50.
They wrote a website that allowed you
to keep track of your hours of sleep
each night.
So maybe you yourself
could make something
similar to this by
the end of the course.
But they allowed you to go to their
website, type in the number of hours
you slept that previous night.
And they would store it for you and keep
track of that day after day after day,
so you could look back and see how
many hours you've slept over time.
Now, if we only had things
like variables and not arrays,
we might be for something
a bit like this.
We might have to store this
data in individual pieces
kind of around our computer's memory.
And we might even give
them individual name,
something like, well, on night
one, we slept seven hours.
On night two we slept eight hours.
On night three we slept six hours.
And now I'm going to ask
you this question here.
Why might this not be
very well designed?
If we had to create one variable
for every single night of sleep,
why might that program
not be very well designed?
And what can we do better perhaps?
Any ideas?
If we wanted to add more
nights, that might not work.
In this case, I would say if we're using
one variable for every night, I mean,
I think you're right.
So if we wanted to later
on edit our program,
we generally specify all
the variables that are
part of that program at the beginning.
So if we wanted to add more,
I couldn't quite do that.
We'd have to find them all over
again if we wanted to add them up.
That's a nice idea.
So we'd have to think
back and be like, OK,
did I use the variable night1
for this, or night2, or night3.
Which one belongs to
this particular number?
So I would say that
this isn't the best way
to store our data using all these
individual variables because it
can get very hard to keep track of.
And so arrays here actually
help us solve this problem.
They let us take our
individual pieces of data
and put them all in a metaphorical
and actually kind of physical line
inside of our computer back to back
to back in our computer's memory.
So for instance, here's
what it might look
like to have each of these
hours inside of an array.
We'd again, just put them back to
back to back in our computer's memory.
And we would then give this
entire collection a single name,
let's say nights.
And so now we could see,
well, on this first night,
it looks like we slept
about seven hours.
On that next night, the
next integer here, we
slept eight hours, and then six, and
then seven, and then eight, again,
for a total of five nights of data.
Now, if we wanted to access not
just this entire list of values,
but some in particular, well,
we have some special syntax
we can use that C gives us.
We could say something
like this, night[0].
And that will return to us, that
will give us that very first value
in our array, so in this case, 7.
And you might be asking
here, why not nights[1]?
Well, in computer science,
it's kind of a convention
that we start counting from 0.
As you saw when we wrote
our very own for loops,
we began them by saying often
that i equals 0 or j equals 0.
We start counting from 0.
And in this case, I would argue
it actually kind of makes sense.
Like nights[0], 0 means start at the
beginning of this array called nights
and don't move any
further, move 0 places.
If we're looking at the beginning
of our array called nights
and we move 0 places, well, we
get back this number called seven.
But what if we did
this, we said night[1]?
Well, we begin.
We'd look at the first
place in our nights array.
And we'd say let's move one step over.
OK, now we found that second value.
In this case, it was 8.
And in the same way,
we could say nights[2].
Well, let's begin at the very beginning.
And let's find 7 here.
But then we're moving two spaces over.
So we go 8, and then 6.
And now we have that very
third value in our array.
So key idea here, we start counting
from 0 as we're working with arrays.
And there's a technical name for this,
which is that arrays are 0 indexed.
And what we're doing here is
using this index, or this number,
to find the value of the array
that we're actually looking for.
So to make this a little more apparent
too, you might often draw out an array.
And you might try to assign an
index to each of its elements.
For instance here, we have
this same nights array.
But down at the bottom, we've
indexed each of the elements.
So the very first one is assigned the
0 index, the next one the 1 index,
the next one the 2 index, and so on.
So we could use nights bracket
any of these numbers on the bottom
to get whatever number
we're looking for.
Now, questions here on arrays,
this indexing process here?
What questions do we have?
OK, seeing none for now.
But feel free to keep
chiming in if you'd like.
Now, one common question we get is, how
can we then actually create an array?
We've seen the structure of an
array, visually what they look like.
But how do we actually
create a structure for one?
And for that we actually
need to keep in mind
three different aspects of an array.
If we want to create an array, C needs
to know three things about that array.
So for instance, one of
the things it needs to know
is, what is the name of the array?
What should we call this collection
of data in our computer's memory?
The next thing it needs to know
is, what is the size of this array?
How many elements are we storing?
In this case, our size is five.
It also needs to know though
what kind of data we're storing
or what type of data
is inside this array.
So we also tell it what
type it will store.
And in C arrays only store
a single type of data.
So in this case, what
type might we be storing?
It seems like we were storing integers.
So to combine these three
ideas of the name, the type,
and the size of the array, we put all
this together in C syntax that looks
a bit like this int nights[5].
And so to break this down,
we first say the type
of whatever we're storing in the
array, in this case, an integer.
Then we say the name of the
array, nights like that.
And then in brackets we put
the maximum size of that array,
how many elements are
going to be inside of it.
In this case, we had five.
And note that this counting
is not zero indexed.
If I said int nights[0] here, I would
be saying I have an array of 0 elements,
which doesn't make sense.
If I'm going to have an array, I need
to have at least one element in it.
So make sure that you keep in mind
this is not zero indexed, even
though later on when you actually
try to access values in your array,
that will be zero indexed at the end.
Now, if we wanted to add items
to this array off the bat,
let's say we wanted to create the
array, declare it like we did here,
tell C what type it is, what its
name is, how many elements it had,
and also initialize it
with some values, we
could do it with this syntax
right here, using braces
and then followed by the values we're
going to input into that array spaced
out by commas here, So 7 comma
8 comma six comma 7 comma 8.
Now, one question I see coming up is,
can we change the size of an array?
So notice here we declared that
this array had a size of five.
And in C you cannot change
the size of an array.
If I say it's five at the beginning,
it has to be exactly five.
We'll see ways later on in the
course that you can actually
try to allocate more memory and
change the size of an array.
But a lot of it just involves
copying what you currently
have in one space of memory
into a new space overall.
More on that in week four.
But for now, you can
say that there's really
no way to change the size of an array.
So if you think you might
need a lot of values,
you might need to make a lot of spaces
to have those values in your array.
Let's see what other
questions we have here.
So let me find a few.
Can an array exist on multiple
planes, like a 3D array for instance?
So you could think-- this is
getting a little advanced here--
of an array that actually
contains arrays inside of itself.
And that is a perfectly
valid thing to do in C.
You could have an array, where
each element of that array
is an array in itself.
And that way you have kind of like
a 2D array, a bit like a grid.
And then if you think
even further, well, you
could have an array where each
element is itself an array.
And each of those elements then
have arrays as their elements too.
And that gets you to this
like 3D kind of structure.
No need to worry if that
made no sense to you.
But generally, you can take arrays
and put other arrays inside of them
at whatever level you'd
like to do that at.
Other questions here too.
Let's see.
A question here about
negative one indexes.
So if you've programmed
in Python, you may
have seen this kind of similar syntax
of writing the name of some list,
and then typing bracket negative some
value, like negative 1 for instance.
I believe in C this is not possible.
So that's a feature of
Python, which gives you,
I believe, the last
element in your list.
But in C there's no such
thing as a negative one index.
Indexes must be positive.
I have a question here.
Let's say we have this
array of five elements here.
Could we add maybe only three
and later on add the other two?
You certainly could.
So if you were to go back to this
model of declaring your array,
you could specify values for
the first three in this array
and later on add the other two.
Now, you have to be careful,
though, because if you don't specify
what those values should
be, those final two values,
they could probably
be literally anything.
So you don't want to touch them
unless you're sure you've already
set them from the beginning.
Now, if you follow this
kind of syntax here,
you have to specify every
single element of your array.
You can't leave any out.
All right, so I think that covers most
of our questions here about arrays.
So let's keep going.
Let's actually get some
practice using arrays here.
So we have a brief
exercise in which you're
going to write a program that
takes an array of integers
or actually builds an array of integers.
And we want it to be the case that
each integer is 2 times the value
of the previous integer.
So for instance, you could think
of a list like 1 and then 2.
And then what's 2 times 2?
Well, 4.
And then what's 2 times 4?
Well, 8.
And then 2 times 8 is 16.
So the entire list is 1, 2, 4, 8, 16.
And we want to in this program print
the entire array integer by integer.
So let's try this out.
I'll go over to my code space here.
And I'll write up this program.
I'll call it, let's say,
just double.c, meaning
I'm going to double each
element of this array.
And now I can see here that I
have a file called double.c.
Now, what's the first thing I should
do if I'm writing a new program in C?
Any ideas what should I usually do?
I want to include the header file.
So I'll say I want to include the CS50
header file, which gives me access
to things like strings and so on.
And I also want to include stdio.h,
which will allow me to print things out
to the screen.
Notice that the standard io
library, or stdio library,
contains functions like printf.
So I'll include that here.
And I'll write the beginning
of my program int main void
and follow it up with what?
Well, I probably first want
to declare this array, that
is to tell C exactly the
important features of it,
like what type will it be storing?
What name will it have?
What size will it be?
And so on this very
first line I'll do that.
We're probably going to be
storing what type of data here?
We want to be doubling numbers,
and whole numbers in particular.
So we're going to be storing integers.
So I'll say int here.
Now what should the
name of this array be?
It could be generally anything.
But I think for me I'll
just call it something
like sequence, that is some sequence
of values that will double every time.
And then how many
elements should we store?
I might just say let's go ahead
and store five off the bat.
We could change this
later if we want to.
So here I have an array called
sequence that stores five values.
And what type are those values?
Well, they're integers here.
So if we go back to
our problem statement,
we saw that the first
element of this array is 1.
Now my question for you, how do I access
the first element of this array using
the syntax we saw earlier?
What could I write to find
the first element of sequence?
You could probably try
something like this.
I could write the name of
sequence and then bracket 0.
So bracket 0 means start at the
beginning of sequence and move 0 steps,
find that very first
element in this array.
And if I want to assign it some value,
well, I could do that here in C.
I could say sequence[0]
equals some value.
In this case, I'll say it equals 1.
So now I set the very
first value of sequence.
And why don't I print
it out while I'm here?
I'll say printf % i for that
integer format code, backslash n.
And now I'll say sequence[0].
So to be clear here, what I'm doing is
holding a placeholder for an integer.
I'm going to put inside that
placeholder the value of sequence[0],
which according to line
8 we just set to be 1.
So now here comes the trickier part.
How do I try to go through this
array and update each of its values
over time?
Well, I set the very first one.
But now I want to more
dynamically set the rest of them.
I don't want to do this.
I don't want to say sequence[1]
equals 2, sequence[2] equals 4.
That's getting a little in the weeds.
I want to automate this process for me.
What kind of structure that
we've already seen could we use?
I'm seeing this idea of
maybe some kind of loop.
And we learned in our last
section that a for loop
is good when we know how many
times we want to loop over all.
So here we saw our sequence
had a total of five values.
We already set the first one.
So I think we want to
loop a total of four times
to set the second value, the
third value, the fourth value,
and the fifth value.
So I could write a for loop like that.
I could say for int i equals.
And now here's a question.
What should i be equal to?
Well, i in this case,
let's say it refers
to the index of the array
we're trying to set.
So what's the very first
index we want to set?
We already did 0.
But now we should do 1.
So int i equals 1.
Now, how long do we want to iterate for?
Well, at least until we get
to i is still less than 5.
So I'll say i less than 5 and then i++.
So now we have i going
from 1 to 2 to 3 to 4.
And that will update
our next four values.
It will not go to 5 because, again, in
this array, there is no sequence[5].
That would be going beyond
the bounds of our array.
Even though there are five
elements, again, we index from 0.
We can't move five spaces total.
We can't move forward five spaces
from the beginning of our array.
OK, so now we have this.
And the question becomes, how
would I set this value of sequence?
Well, I know I want to set
sequence[i] in the first iteration.
This will be sequence one.
And the next iteration
it'll be sequence two.
But how should I configure this value?
I know I want it to be 2
times the previous one.
I'm seeing a few ideas here.
Some of them involve actually doing
a bit of math inside of the brackets
here.
And that's something you
can actually do in C.
So I could say maybe let
me get the previous value.
What is that value?
I'll say sequence[i].
And then to look behind this
value, I'll say minus 1.
So if I'm currently at i equals 1, I'll
be saying sequence[i] sequence one,
equals sequence bracket i
minus 1 or 0, sequence[0],
so the previous value here.
Now, if I want to multiply
that by 2, I could
do the very same thing
I've done before in C. I
could say star 2, which means
multiply this particular value by 2.
So again, if i is 1 here, I'll say
sequence[1] equals sequence bracket--
well, 1 minus 1 is 0.
sequence[0] times 2, well, that
will set the next value of sequence,
and so on and so forth.
So once I do that, I can say
maybe I'll print out this value.
What is the new value of sequence[i]?
And then I will go ahead here.
And I'll say printf backslash n.
Actually, I don't think
I need backslash n here.
I already have it up there.
So I'll leave things as is.
And this is our entire program.
So let's see if we can run it.
I'll go back to my terminal.
And I will say make double,
make double to compile it.
I see no errors.
I'll now try this.
I'll say ./double.
And I seem to be getting somewhere.
I have 1, 2, 4, 8, and 16.
So I'll go back to my code here.
Let me ask, what questions do
we have on creating an array,
cycling through its values with a
for loop, setting them as we go?
For those of you who are feeling
a little more comfortable,
there's another way to do this too
that doesn't involve separately setting
a sequence[0].
You could simply declare your
array and have a single for loop
that sets things for you.
I'll leave that piece up to
you, though, to do on your own.
Now a question I see here
about this program's design,
wouldn't it be better designed
to have a variable that
says what the size of this array is?
For instance, let's say I'll set
int size equals 5, like this.
And now, maybe I'll replace this
with size and replace this with size.
And now I could change
this it seems in one place.
I could make this 10.
I can make it 7, or 6, or so on.
So I'll leave it at 5 for now.
And let's see if that
actually works here.
So I'll go back to my terminal.
And I will do this.
I'll type make double.
And I'll run it again, ./double.
And that seems to work.
So I'll go back to my program.
Maybe I now want--
let's go with eight numbers overall.
I'll go back to my terminal.
And now I'll say make
double again, ./double.
And I seem to have allowed
myself to pretty quickly change
the size of this array and print
out a longer sequence as I go just
now by changing one particular value.
And this is actually a
common, let's say, pattern
you'll see in writing
well-designed programs.
It's not really a good
practice to specify
what we call a magic number,
that is a number in here
that we're not quite sure
what it is, what it refers to.
And it might repeat
throughout our program.
If you have a number like
that, best to create a variable
and change it in one place, so you don't
have to go through later and update
all the places we had, for instance, 5.
Now, another question I see
here is, could we use getint?
Well, we know in the
CS50 library we have
this function called getint
lets the user type in what value
they want to give.
I'll try that.
I'll say size is getint.
And I'll say enter a size, like this.
And now I'll go back to my terminal.
And I'll say make double.
And I'll run ./double.
Now I'll say, let's go back
to-- maybe let's go back to 6.
That seems to be right, one,
two, three, four, five, six.
Now I'll type make double
and then ./double again.
And now I'll type 9.
And I'll see I have an even longer list.
So it seems like we could
even take user input
and then decide the size
of our array after that.
All right, other questions
here on this program?
All right, so let's keep moving on.
And let's focus now on
this idea of strings.
So we've seen this idea
of arrays, which is
this structure we have to
store data back to back
to back in a computer's memory.
And it turns out that
strings are actually not
all that dissimilar from arrays.
In fact, strings themselves
are a special kind of array.
So consider here, again,
our Scrabble example.
We had these individual pieces of
letters, like H, E, L, L, and O.
And they all formed
together this word hello
when we put them all
together back to back.
Well, in the same way do
strings actually work.
We can take individual
letters like these.
And we can then do
something a bit like this.
We can put them all together and make
entire what we might call in this case
a phrase.
So strings are nothing more than arrays,
where the elements are characters.
So here we're now seeing that
we have this array called phrase
with the letters H, E, L, L, and O. And
we can use the very same syntax that we
saw earlier.
I could say phrase[0], which gives
me the very first element of phrase.
I could use phrase[1], which gives
me the E here, and then phrase[2],
which gives me the L. So I'm able to
do the very same things I could do with
arrays, but now with strings.
One fancy feature though that
you should pay attention to,
particularly for this
week's problem set,
is that we represent characters
in C underneath the hood using
integers or numbers.
Remember from an earlier lecture we
learned about this idea of ASCII,
or the American Standard Code
for Information Interchange.
And we saw a mapping a bit like this,
where A maps to this integer 65.
B maps to this integer 66.
C maps to this integer 67.
And so when we see these
numbers, 65, 66, 67,
and they're the type
of character, we then
actually convert that to a character.
We print it out as a character overall.
So consider then that this phrase
that we see here, hello, well, it
could also be a set of numbers,
72, 69, 76, 76, and 79.
These are the ASCII codes that
correspond to those letters
we saw a little earlier.
So with that in mind, let's think
about writing a new program, one
that actually tells us if
a string has characters
that are in alphabetical order or not.
Now, we can assume here that all
the characters are uppercase.
So let's begin.
I'll go back to my code space.
And I'll now create a new program.
I'll call this one alphabetical.c.
And I'll do the very same
things I did with double.c.
I'll make sure to include CS50.h.
I'll make sure to include
stdio as well, include stdio.
And then I'll also say int main void.
And now I can write
the rest of my program.
So maybe the first thing I want to
do is get a string from the user.
So I could say, string phrase
equals get string enter a phrase.
So I'm using the CS50
libraries get string function.
And now I'm able to ask
the user for some phrase.
But now I want to ask that question,
is this phrase in alphabetical order
or is it not?
And it seems to me like
the very first step
there would be to go through every
individual character in our string.
We have to have a way of looking
at every character to test,
is every character in
alphabetical order or is it not?
So what can we do to
loop through this string
or really this array of characters?
I'm seeing this idea
of a for loop again.
So we used it for our array of numbers.
And there's no reason that
same approach can't work now
when working with a string
because, again, a string is just
an array, but an array of characters.
So I'll say this.
For int i equals 0.
We'll begin at the very first character
in our phrase, i is less than.
What should i be less than?
I mean, I don't know quite
how long this string is.
If I typed in hello, it
would be five characters.
If I typed in goodbye,
it would be longer.
What could I do to find
the length of this phrase?
So I'm seeing a few folks
who are catching on to this,
which is that in lecture I believe
we saw this function called strlen,
S-T-R-L-E-N. And strlen actually can
tell us the length of a string if we
call it and give it our string as input.
So strlen lives in this library called
string.h, or our string in general.
And the header file is string.h.
Now, if I want to test
how long this string is,
I could say int length equals
strlen, and then pass in my string,
in this case, the one called phrase.
So now I have this variable called
length that I could use in for loop,
i is less than length i++.
So whatever the length is, I'll make
sure to first calculate that and then
will I test every individual
character in my string making sure
not to go past the
length of that string.
Now, a few other ways to do this too.
I could also say int i equals 0
comma length equals strlen of phrase,
like this.
And this is getting a little long.
And I have to zoom out for this.
But this allows me to put
everything on a single line.
And it's implied here that if the very
first variable i type is of type int,
if I type a comma, the next
variable will be that same type,
in this case, an integer.
And I can assign it some value,
like the length of phrase.
This puts everything in one for loop.
What I probably wouldn't
want to do is this.
I might not want to say i
less than strlen of phrase.
But why might I not want to do that?
Let me show you the full line here.
Why would it be better
to define length here
in this initialization
step than here, which is
my condition that's checked every loop?
So I'm seeing a few
good answers, which is
that if I know I'm going to be checking
this condition every single loop, well,
why do I have to run
strlen every single time?
The length of the string
isn't really going to change.
And in fact, we'll just
add more time to my program
as it runs, probably
not a whole ton of time
if computers are so fast these days.
But it still adds some time.
So best to put it elsewhere
to calculate it once and then
use that variable throughout your code.
So I'll say int length is the result
of calling strlen with phrase.
And I'll do it this way,
keeping things separate just
for line length sake at this point.
OK, so now I'm able to access every
individual character in my phrase.
And to kind of make this a reality, I
could say printf %c for an individual
character.
And now, I'll print out,
let's say, phrase[i].
And now I'll open up my terminal.
And I'll see if my
code actually compiles.
I'll say make alphabetical.
Seems to compile.
I'll run ./alphabetical, type in my
phrase, which is hello, hit Enter.
And I see it printed back to me.
I probably need a
backslash n at the end here
to make sure that I'm actually
returning my prompt down
below the result of my program.
But I can fix that here.
I'll go back in.
And I'll scroll down.
And at the very end, I'll
include a backslash n, like this.
Now, though, I think we should take
kind of a broader look at this.
If I type make alphabetical
and I say ./alphabetical hello,
I know I'm able to access the
H, the E, the L, the L, the O.
But now there's a question of, how do
I know if something is in alphabetical
order?
I can't really say--
there's no function I believe
in C, at least that I know,
that tells me does A come before
B or does B come before A.
What could I pay attention to instead?
If we look back at this mapping
here, what pattern do you see?
So one thing I notice here is that as
we go forward in the alphabet from A
to B to C, we notice that the
integer representation is actually
increasing as we go.
So first 65, then 66, then 67.
So maybe we could use that
pattern in our own code here.
I could go back to it.
And let me change the
format code from %c to %i.
That means I want to print whatever
data is stored at phrase[i],
whatever index of phrase.
But I want to print it not as
a character, but as an integer.
I want to see what underlying
number is being represented.
So I'll try this now.
I'll recompile alphabetical.
Then I'll say ./alphabetical.
And I'll give it hello.
And now I see a lot of numbers.
So I mean, that makes sense.
I told it to print out now the numeric
representation of the characters
it's storing.
But let me try this again.
I'll make it a little clearer.
I'll go back to my program.
And I'll add a space
between every character
to separate these numbers apart.
And now I'll recompile.
I will say make alphabetical,
make alphabetical, ./alphabetical.
I'll say hello, in this case.
And I see 104, 101, 108, 108, and 111.
Now these don't seem to match.
If I go back here I see A
for 65, B for 66, C for 67.
Why might they not match do you think?
Yeah, so notice how in here I've been
actually typing things in lowercase.
And lowercase letters have
different numeric representations.
Let me try this with capital.
I'll say ./alphabetical
HELLO in all caps, hit Enter.
And now I see those familiar
numbers, 72, 69, 76, 76, and 79.
So we can assume at
least in this that all
of our words to check for alphabetical
order will be all in capitals.
So let's keep going now.
So I'm able to access each phrase
or each character in this phrase.
But now, what questions
should I be asking?
What should I ask maybe if something
is not in alphabetical order?
Or should I ask if something
is in alphabetical order?
And how would I convert that
here to an actual condition?
Any ideas?
Yeah, so I'm seeing we
could maybe compare letters
as we loop through our phrase here.
So maybe we could do
something a bit like this.
I could say if there's
some condition here.
And maybe this condition is we'll check
if characters are not alphabetical,
like this because we know that if
the characters are not alphabetical,
if any two characters are
not in alphabetical order,
well, then the entire thing
is in alphabetical order.
So what should I check?
What should my condition be to
determine if two characters are not
in alphabetical order?
Well, I could probably
look at the first one.
I could say phrase[i].
That gives me this very first letter.
But now, what condition would be true
if the following character is not
in alphabetical order?
Maybe I could say if this current
letter is greater than, let's say,
phrase i plus 1, that
is the next letter.
So here's what we have.
If this current letter has a
numeric representation that
is greater than the
previous one, well, that
means it's not in alphabetical order.
And to this more concrete,
let's go back to our slides.
Let's say we had B
followed by A. Well, we'd
first look at B. We'd
say the B integer is 66.
Then we look at the
next one, A. That's 65.
So we're seeing now that B has a
greater value than A. That means
they're not in alphabetical order.
We can do the same thing for C
and B, for C and A, and so on.
So I think we're on to something here.
Now, what should we do in this case if
these are not in alphabetical order?
Well, we could probably
print out something
like not in alphabetical order.
And now logically, what could we do?
We know that our program is done.
We don't need to check any more letters.
If something is not
in alphabetical order,
if any two characters are
not in alphabetical order,
we can return and call it good.
So I'll return 0 here.
And if you're not familiar,
as we saw in lecture,
return 0 basically means
end my program here.
Don't do anything else.
As soon as you see this line,
just quit and end my program.
Now, though, let's try this.
So I will say go back to my terminal.
I'll compile.
I'll say make alphabetical.
And I'll type in ./alphabetical.
And now I'll type in
something like CBA, which
we know is not in alphabetical order.
I'll hit Enter.
And we see not in alphabetical order.
So what if I did this?
I could say ./alphabetical.
Now I'll try ABC.
Hmm.
And I get not in alphabetical order.
What might be wrong here?
Go back to my program.
What do we see?
Any ideas?
Here's the full screen code again.
So I did remove the
correct line down here.
So I haven't actually said when these
things are in alphabetical order.
So maybe that's something
to consider here.
There's a slightly
more subtle bug though.
And that is let's consider what happens
if we go back to our alphabetical order
array here.
So let's say we checked A and B. Those
seem to be in alphabetical order,
right?
We did that when i was equal to 0.
Now, when i was equal to 1, we
checked B and C. That seems fair.
OK, so those are in
alphabetical order as well.
Now, when i was 2, we
checked C. And what?
I mean, what comes after C?
I don't think there's really
anything out there past C.
So I think we made a mistake here.
We don't want to be checking against
values that are outside of our array.
And in fact, that's kind of a common
bug, but also a very dangerous one.
We don't want to be
looking at places in memory
that we actually shouldn't be looking
because one, we'll get bugs and two,
we might touch things we're not
supposed to touch in our computer.
So let me fix this.
I'll go back to our code.
And how should we adjust this?
Maybe we go from i equals
0 up to length but minus 1.
So we get the very end of our phrase.
Let's go back to our example here.
We check A and B. We check B and C.
And if those are in alphabetical order,
well, we know the rest
is in alphabetical order.
We don't need to check C and
whatever else comes after it,
in this case, some empty value.
So let's go and try this again.
I will now go back to my terminal.
And I'll say make
alphabetical ./alphabetical.
And I'll run hello.
And I see well, that's
not in alphabetical order.
Now I'll do ./alphabetical again.
And I'll type ABC, hit Enter.
I don't see anything.
Now there's two options here.
I could say if this.
And I know they're not alphabetical.
I could try else maybe print
alphabetical order, like this,
and then return zero.
But I would argue that
might not be wise.
And why do you think
that wouldn't be wise?
Yeah, so I'm seeing that
we'll probably only check
the very first two characters.
So notice here, we
begin with i equals 0.
So i equals 0.
We check.
Are the characters in alphabetical
order or are they not?
If they're not, we'll
break out our program.
That seems fine.
If they are though, we'll say
everything's in alphabetical order
and return 0.
But we didn't yet check the rest
of our phrase, which we really
should be doing.
And then further return zero
again means exit the program
at this particular moment.
So we're going to exit and never
look at the rest of our code.
So this should be really elsewhere.
And in fact, it should be
probably at the end of our loop.
We can only say for sure that this
is an alphabetical order after we've
gone through every pair
of letters and checked
that they are, let's say,
not not in alphabetical order
or that they are, in fact,
in alphabetical order.
So I'll say printf these
are in alphabetical order,
like this, backslash n semicolon
and return 0 down below.
So this then is our entire program.
And I'll run it now to test it out.
I'll say make alphabetical
./alphabetical.
And now I'll type in ABC.
I see that's in alphabetical order.
I'll do it again with CBA.
And those are not in alphabetical order.
So questions then on this
implementation of our program,
or on strings or arrays more generally?
OK, so seeing none right now.
But feel free to keep
chiming in if you'd like.
Let's continue on then and focus on
this new idea of command line arguments.
So our final topic
for today is this idea
of running programs and giving them
input not necessarily while they run,
but even before they run.
And now you've probably seen
similar kinds of programs.
In fact, every time
I went to my terminal
and I typed make alphabetical, until
I hit Enter, Make has not yet run.
But notice how I'm not
just typing Make, the name
of the program, I'm giving Make some
input or some argument, telling it
what to make.
I'm telling it here to make
the program alphabetical.
Now, you've also probably
seen something like check50.
I can run check50.
And this is the program itself, check50.
I can hit Enter.
And I'll see I get a bit
of a help message here.
But I also see the following
arguments or inputs
are required when I run check50.
The slug in this case is required.
And the slug refers to the
problem I'm going to check,
something like cs50/problems/ and so on.
But notice here how
before I even run check50
I'm giving it some input,
some additional context
to go off of to run as a program.
And we can do the very same
thing for our own programs.
So for instance, in mario,
when you first wrote it,
you might have done
something a bit like this.
You might have run ./mario and then
while the program was running prompted
the user for a height, in this case
H. And maybe you typed in eight.
Well, in your actual C code you
probably had something like this.
You had your int main void, your
main function in your program.
And you had some variable
perhaps named height
that received the value of
getint after we finished running.
Now, we're going to
transition here and make sure
that we allow the user
to actually give input
before the program is even running.
So you can imagine Mario being
run like this, ./mario space 8.
So before Mario even
runs, the user can tell us
how high they want that pyramid to be.
And if you do something like this
and you want to capture this input,
well, you need to change your C code.
And it turns out you have to
change it a little bit like this.
What do you notice that's different now?
We still have int and main.
But what looks different now?
Yes, I'm seeing that void is replaced.
So before we had void
inside parentheses.
But now we have what seems
to be two different things,
int argc and string
argv with some braces.
So let's go through first
conceptually what's happening here.
So in our prior version of Mario,
notice that when the user ran it,
they only ran ./mario.
They didn't give any other input.
And that's actually reflected
in our main function here.
You can think of the main function
as being the function that
represents our entire program.
The int tells us the exit status code.
If it's 0, that means all was OK.
If it's non-zero,
something bad happened.
But either way, our program
will return an integer.
Now, main is the name of this
function kind of by convention.
And here inside parentheses we see void.
Our program or this
function takes no arguments.
And we saw this above.
The user just typed ./mario.
But they didn't add any arguments.
But now if we change this, if
the user actually types in an 8,
we have to change our C
code to take some input now.
So our entire program
now takes what seems
to be a total of two
arguments or two inputs.
One is called argc, which
is of the type integer.
The other is called argv, which is
itself a string, but actually not
just a string, an array of strings.
So notice here we see that
array syntax coming back?
Argv with the braces here, that
means argv is an array of strings.
And in fact, we'll see it
holds the arguments we actually
give to our program.
So here let's take a look.
We're going to write a program here that
prints each command line argument given
to our program just to
kind of practice and get
a feel for what argc and argv can do.
So I'll go back to my terminal.
And I'll type code argv.
Actually, I'll just type--
yeah, code argv.c.
And now inside of this we're going to
get a sense for what these command line
arguments are doing for us.
So I'll include, let's say, cs50.h.
I'll include stdio.h.
And now I'll type int main
and not int main void.
I now want my program to take
some input at the command line.
I could say int argc and string
argv to say my program now
has access to something called
argc, which is a number,
and something called argv, which is,
in this case, an array of strings.
So now in particular argc is the number
of arguments that my program received,
the number of inputs
it received, including
the actual name of the program itself.
So for instance, if I go back to
that mario example, I type ./mario 8.
In that case, argc would be equal to 2.
I'm giving two inputs, the name of
my program and the number eight.
Now, argv would itself
have two strings inside.
One would be the name of my program.
And the other would be the input
that I gave, in this case, eight.
So let's try this.
I'll go back to my code here.
And I will try to loop through
all the values in argv.
I'll say for int i equals 0.
i is less than--
how do I know how long argv is?
I can rely on argc.
I'll say argc then i++.
And now I'll print out something
like this, argv %i is %s backslash n.
And I'll fill this in
with a few variables here.
I'm going to refer to argv bracket i.
So I'll substitute i in there.
And then I'll also substitute
argv bracket i here.
So now I can see when
I run this program,
I should be able to
print out argv bracket 0
is whatever argv bracket 0 is.
Argv bracket 1 is whatever
argv bracket 1 is.
So now I'll go back.
And I'll try to compile this program.
I'll say, in this case, make argv.
I'll type ./argv.
And give it some input, let's say,
1, 2, and 3 separated by spaces.
Now I hit Enter.
And I see my program had
a total of four inputs.
The first was the actual
name of my program.
So argv bracket 0 is equal to ./argv.
argv bracket 1 is 1, as we saw up here.
2 is 2.
And 3 is 3.
So let me try this.
I can say ./argv.
I could even type in something
like my name, Carter.
And now I see argv bracket
1, name of my program.
argv bracket 1 is Carter.
Argv bracket 0 is the
name of my program here.
So to be clear, argc then is the
total number of arguments we get.
We can use it to figure
out how long argv will be.
But all the interesting stuff, all
the actual input to our program
will be stored in argv
as a set of strings.
So questions then on argc and argv?
What questions do we have?
OK, so while we're here, I actually
see a good question, which is asking,
we noticed that argv is storing
a collection of strings.
But what if we wanted to get a
number and use it in our program,
like in that Mario
example, for instance?
So let's consider trying
to re-implement Mario,
but now using command line arguments.
So what if I did this?
I can go back to my terminal.
And I'll type code mario.c.
I'm not going to write the whole thing.
But I will try to make it so that I'm
able to run Mario using command line
arguments.
So instead of, in this
case, running int main void,
I'll start off with int
main int argc string argv.
And again, this is allowing my program
to take inputs at the command line.
And it will store them for
me in this array called argv.
And it will tell me how
many there are using argc.
So let's try this.
I know I want to get the--
I know I want to allow the user to do
this, to say ./mario followed by 8,
for instance.
And now I'm curious.
To get this value of 8,
in which index of argv
should I look, based
on what we saw earlier?
Seems like argv bracket 1.
So keep in mind that ./mario, that
will be the value for argv bracket 0.
This value though will be
the value for argv bracket 1.
So now I'll try that.
I'll say, well, why don't I
make a variable called height
and say that it gets whatever
is stored in argv bracket 1?
Try it.
Now I'll compile my program.
I'll go up top.
I'll say make Mario.
I get an error.
And this isn't a
particularly helpful error.
But I do see this.
Initializing int with an
expression of type string.
So it seems like I'm not able to store
a string inside of this variable I
said was an integer.
So what can I do?
I have to first convert
this value to an integer.
And it turns out there is a function for
that, one included in the not string.h,
included in the standard library.
stdlib.h gives me access
to those functions.
And this function is called a to i.
a to i effectively converts any string
to an integer, assuming it's able to.
If you give it one, like the string one,
it will convert that to the integer 1
overall.
So I'll try this.
I'll say, make Mario.
And now I don't get any errors.
So it seems like using a to i I'm
able to convert this argument, which
was previously a string
into an integer and now
assign it to this value of height.
But now, what if I do this?
What if I say make Mario ./mario and I
don't give any input, I just hit Enter?
Why would I have gotten this error?
Segmentation faults often occur when
I look beyond the bounds of my array.
Why would typing just ./mario make me
look beyond the bounds of my array,
in this case argv?
If I only type ./mario, I think I
really only have a value for argv.
Let's see. argc will be one, which means
that argv will only have one element.
And I can't look beyond
the bounds of argv.
So if I had only one element,
I could use argv bracket 0.
But argv bracket 1 assumes
I have two elements.
So here's another use case for argc.
I could first check.
Before I do anything, let me first
check if argc does not equal 2.
If there are any fewer or any more
than two arguments to my program,
I want to do something.
I want to tell the user that the usage
of this program is ./mario followed
by some number, like this, backslash n.
And then I'll return 1, meaning
something went wrong, not 0.
You actually use this
program incorrectly.
So that actually assures me that
if I recompile my program now,
I do make Mario ./mario, I get this
error instead of a segmentation fault.
I'm able to catch this error before
my program actually runs as a whole.
So here, again, is our program.
What questions do we
have on argc and argv?
A question here for, again, the
summary of what argc and argv are.
In a single sentence argc
is the number of inputs
to our program at the command line.
And in a single sentence
argv is the array
of strings, the array of inputs to
our program at the command line.
Other questions too.
Another question.
Yeah, good question here.
So the question is, what counts
as being at the command line?
And in general, when
we say command line,
we're also referring
to this terminal here.
So when I type ./mario and include
any options outside of this, like 8,
or my own name, or so on,
that's at the command line.
And in lecture, we saw this
other program called cowsay
that lets me actually
specify what kind of animal.
I want to say some kind of text.
I could say, give me a dragon
that says roar, like this.
Let me zoom out so you can see it.
Here is that dragon.
So notice here in one single command
I ran cowsay, but gave it some input.
Dash f dragon means configure
the animal I show to be a dragon.
And then roar is the other
input that says what should
the dragon be saying here down below?
All right, other questions too?
All right, so seeing no
additional questions here.
I think we'll go ahead and
call this section a wrap.
Thank you all so much for
coming and joining us here.
We'll see you all next week.