SPEAKER: OK, well Hello one
and all and welcome to our week
seven section on SQL or Structured Query
Language and also on databases too.
So my name is Carter.
The course is Preceptor.
And my goal for this section is to help
you bridge the gap between this week's
lecture and this week's problems.
I'll be touching on a few different
topics that we'll get hands on practice
with today.
So among our topics for today are these.
We'll be talking about databases.
What are they and how
do we design them well?
And we'll also talk a bit
about SQL, this new language
you can use to write
queries on databases,
basically to ask questions of data and
find the answers to those questions.
We'll do a bit of practice
with problem set seven,
working in particular
on that songs problem.
And we'll also do some practice with
designing our very own databases too
at the very beginning.
Now, I'm very excited about SQL.
I love working with data.
And one of the things I find
so fascinating about data
is just how long we as humans have
been thinking about and using data.
So you'll see today, we're working
a lot with this idea of a table,
like organizing data
into rows and columns.
But that idea is certainly
not new, certainly not
particular to the computer science age.
In fact, we have historical
data showing that humans,
as long ago as over 1,000 years ago,
were working with data in tables.
So this is a transcription of some table
that was inscribed onto a stone tablet
from about 1,000 plus years ago
of worker stipends for a temple.
So you'll see here that every row
denotes some worker at the temple.
And it tells us how much they were paid
every month in the column portion here.
So you'll see as we
work with tables, we'll
get to represent individual
entities in individual rows
and often some information about
those entities in individual columns.
So that's kind of a structure
we're working with here today.
And you're probably a
bit familiar with this
if you've used software like this,
Apple Numbers, Google Sheets, Microsoft
Excel, this helps you organize data in
the information age in terms of rows
and in terms of columns.
Now, if you've used this software, odds
are it's performed pretty well for you.
But it kind of motivates the
question, like why would we
go beyond this software?
Like these pieces of software here
are not necessarily databases.
But we still use them.
They're useful.
But there are still reasons
to go beyond them too,
to not use Apple Numbers, Google
Sheets, or Microsoft Excel.
What are those reasons?
Well, we can think of
a database as being
this way we can actually help us
organize information so we can better
read it, that is, figure out what
is actually inside our database
to update it, that is to change
it, and then to delete it too.
And so we talk about in
lecture, there are really
kinds of four operations the database
can do for us, creating data, reading
data, updating, and deleting data.
And the thing about a
database is, they're
designed to do all of these
things very fast and very well.
In fact, a database is very good
for working with data at scale.
If you think about a company
like Google or like Amazon,
they're working with, not just hundreds
of rows, not just thousands of rows,
but often millions, even
billions of rows of data.
And a database works really well for
that context when Google Sheets just
might not be able to
handle billions of rows.
You could also use a database because it
helps you access data very frequently.
If you think of something like
again, like Google or Amazon,
people are often searching for
a product very, very frequently.
You can query data very fast
when you have a database at hand.
And similarly databases
just work faster in general.
They have structures
built into them that
allow you to find data all the
more quickly because you've
been able to think about
how best to store it
and best to retrieve it using
some of these data structures
you've seen in earlier weeks too.
So in summary then, you might want to
graduate from a spreadsheet software
to a database when these
kinds of things matter to you,
being able to have lots of
data, to access it frequently,
and to do all of that
at a very fast speed.
So we saw in lecture too, that there's
this idea of a database management
system.
And we saw in particular one kind
of database management system
one called SQLite.
So you can think of a database
and this database manager system
as being kind of two separate things.
A database is anything that
allows you to store data.
But this DBMS, database
management system
allows you to access that
database in certain ways
with certain, let's say,
paradigms or certain patterns.
So there are many different options
for you as you're working with DBMSs.
A few of them are these.
You might have heard of MySQL
or Oracle or PostgreSQL SQLite.
These are all software you can
use to access data in databases.
And in CS50, you'll
actually get to use SQLite,
because it's portable it's
lightweight, but it still
offers many, many features for you to
use, both in your code space online
and also on the real world, like
in applications and across the web
and on your phone and so on.
So it's very much a real world software,
even though it is very lightweight.
Now we'll also talk about SQL,
which is this idea of being
able to write these queries in
terms of some structured syntax.
And SQL actually stands for
Structured Query Language.
So actually hopefully
reveal to you the structure
of this query language
and help you actually
write those queries to update,
delete, create and read data overall.
Now we'll begin here with a bit
of an exercise on database design.
So we talked about storing
data in terms of tables
and in terms of rows and columns.
And I like to think about how I could
design something a bit more real world.
So maybe you've heard of this database
called Goodreads or this website
called Goodreads.
They allow you to actually choose
a book, see a rating for that book,
and see how other people
actually rated that book as well.
So it's this database of book titles
and authors and ratings and so on.
We actually begin by trying to
imagine what Goodreads database looks
like underneath the hood.
So, I'll go to Google Sheets here.
And let me actually ask you
all, I want to probably store
a few things about
books and about authors.
I want to store, let's say the book
title, maybe it's publication date,
the author, the author's birth
date, and maybe some idea
of a rating for that book.
So if we only had one table
here-- let me actually ask you all
if you're here live, what kinds of
columns should I have, in this table?
I want to store some of those ideas.
Maybe one called a
title, which makes sense.
So this could be my book title here.
I'll put it in bold to denote that it
is the header, the column name here.
I'm seeing, maybe author, which
could stand for the author's name.
That's a good idea.
I see like something like
publish date, publication date.
So I'll go ahead and add that in.
I'll just call this one published, let's
say, the date this book was published.
What else do we have?
Maybe one called--
I see rating.
That could be a good one.
So a rating column.
And we also want to store, let's
say, the author's birth date.
So I'll say author birth here,
for the author birth date.
So let me organize these a little bit.
With Google Sheets I can
just drag and drop here.
So I'll move author over here.
So I have some title, published,
rating for the books, and then author,
and the author's birth date here.
So let's go and actually
add in some books.
And I have a few here already.
These come from the International
Booker Prize Long List.
If you're not familiar,
is a prize for books
that have been translated from
around the world into English.
And it's basically a
way of keeping track
of what are the really good
books from this past year.
So one of the books that made the
long list over the past several years
has been this one called Flights
that was published in 2017.
05 17 here.
Let's say the rating.
I don't quite know the rating.
Let's say it was four.
And the author was Olga
Tokarczuk like this.
And Olga was born in 1962.
So this is our very first row in
our database table, let's say.
So notice here that one row corresponds
to one book, Flights, right?
Now notice here that the published
column has a certain format to it.
This is a date.
It is the year, followed by
the month, followed by the day.
So this would be May 17, 2017.
And in SQLite as we'll see, it is often
important to note that your dates are
in a certain format.
So this is the format SQLite has
standardize on to store certain dates,
at least in terms of
years and months and days
where you do y, y, y, a four digit year,
a two digit month, and a two digit day.
And the rest I simply
have a rating out of,
let's say five stars, the author's
name, and the author's birth year here.
So I'll go ahead and add a few more.
Olga also wrote The Books of Jacob.
And this was also long listed for this
prize called the International Booker
Prize.
And that was published
in 2021, November 15.
Let's say that got a
five out of five rating.
And it's also by Olga
who was born in 1962.
I'll keep going.
Why don't I add one called Paradais.
This one was published in 2020, March,
let's say 23, and got a four out
of five.
This one was by Fernanda,
Fernanda Melchor.
And they were born in 1982.
Now Fernanda also wrote another book.
They wrote Hurricane
Season, which was published,
let's say, in 2020 in February 19.
And that got a five out of five.
Also, of course, by
Fernanda, born in 1982.
So here is my basic database table.
Perhaps Goodreads has
something very similar.
Now I want to ask you, what could
be better designed about this table?
Any ideas?
If I were to keep adding more and more
books, what could be better designed?
Certainly, I could maybe have
more tables, more information .
Here that could be a good idea.
Why don't I add in a
few more pieces of data
and see if we can get
another sense here?
I'll add in the other name, which
published in 2019, October 10,
by John--
oops.
The rating let's say,
was, let's go with a five.
Was published by John Fosse in 1959.
And John Fosse also had
another book as well.
They had A New Name, A New Name,
which was published in 2021.
09/08.
That got a four out of five.
That of course, is by John
Foss, who was born in 1959.
So here is our total table.
And I'm seeing a few
ideas now coming up.
So one is, we could sort this data.
That would be a very good idea.
Maybe we sort it by
title, alphabetically.
Maybe we sort it by publication
date, earliest to latest and so on.
Those are all good ideas.
Here though, I want to
think about the best way
to structure our columns
and our tables themselves.
So I see a few ideas,
which is that we're often
repeating a few things in this table.
So notice that Olga comes up twice.
So does Fernanda and so does John.
And notice how we have to duplicate
their birth years, 1962, 1962,
or 1982, 1982, 1959, 1959.
So although this is a table
trying to store books,
we're necessarily repeating author
names and author birth years
to make sure we have that
information in the same table.
So when it comes to
organizing our databases,
there's one principle
you can keep in mind,
which is that let's try to have tables
that represent one and only one thing.
So here we wanted to store books,
originally, just individual books.
So maybe what we do is, I'll go
down to this bottom piece here,
and I'll say this is my
books table right here.
But now, I shouldn't have information
about authors in my books table.
I should make those
authors a separate table.
So I'll go and create a new table.
I'll call this one
perhaps, authors like this.
Now let me add in my columns
for authors over to this table.
So now I have Olga, Fernanda, and John.
But I don't want to duplicate them.
So I'll remove row three.
I'll just delete this row.
I'll remove row four with duplicate
Fernanda, row five with John Fosse.
And now I have a table of authors
and a table of just books.
But now I think I have
another problem, right?
If I have a table of books
and a table of authors,
what information did
I lose by doing this?
Let's say you're just seeing this table
or these tables for the first time,
what did I lose?
I lost who wrote which book.
I don't know anymore.
Did Olga write Flights
or was that perhaps John?
I don't have association, this
relationship between these books
and these authors.
So this is where this idea of a
relational database comes into play.
So we don't just have individual tables.
We also have relationships
between them, that some author
wrote some particular book, or some book
was written by some particular author.
And so to actually represent
these relationships,
we have this idea of a primary
key and a foreign key column
that we saw in lecture.
So let me clean this up a little bit.
I'll go to my ratings column.
I'll shorten it just
to visualize it here.
And why don't I do
something I should have
done from the very beginning,
which is give each of these books
its very own unique ID.
So why don't we start with one here.
I'll say one, two, three,
four, five, and six.
So each of these books has its own
unique number that refers to it.
And the idea of a primary key
is that I cannot repeat it.
Every book should have one and only
one number that is unique to that book.
So when I talk about book number six,
that is a new name and only a new name.
It won't change.
It won't ever be something else.
It is always going to
refer to a new name.
And this is helpful because I now don't
have to repeat all the information on,
let's say this particular book.
I can just say, well, it's
book number six, right?
That's pretty easy enough.
So now I'll go to authors here
and I will try the same thing.
I'll go insert new column left.
I'll say why don't I give
every author their own ID too.
So Olga has ID one.
Fernanda has ID two.
John has ID three.
And now every author
has its own unique ID.
And it is OK here that I
repeat certain numbers.
Because here I could say, well, it's
book number one or author number one.
Now I'm able to differentiate
between books and authors,
even though they have the
same ID associated, with them.
So this is helpful.
But have I solved my problem really?
If you look at this table
have I solved my problem?
I'm seeing some head shaking.
So no, not really.
What could I do?
Well, I could try to associate
these particular primary keys
with each other.
And any ideas on how I could do that?
What could I create to
associate these IDs?
I could use this idea of a foreign key.
So we saw in lecture that a primary
key used in some other table
becomes what we call a foreign key.
I think that hints at
the answer here, which
is, we probably need another table
to represent this relationship
between the authors and the book.
So why don't I go ahead and create that.
I'll call this new table maybe I'll call
it authorship, who wrote which book.
Or actually instead of
authorship, why don't I
make it like a verb like authored.
So like this author authored
this particular book.
So maybe here what I should do is have
one column called author id, which
will be like a foreign key.
It will refer to authors
and the authors table.
And maybe I'll have another
column here called book id.
And this will refer to
books in the books table.
So now if I want to, let's say,
associate some particular author
with some particular book, well,
I could find the author id,
like Olga, who is one, and then add
in whatever book id Olga authored.
So I'll go to the book table,
and I know Olga authored Flights
which is also ID one.
So now I see in this author table
that the author with the ID of one
wrote the book with the ID of one.
And now I can keep going.
I could say, well, Olga also wrote the
book with ID two, The Flights of Jacob.
Let's say, who is two?
Fernanda.
Fernanda also wrote Paradais
and Hurricane Season.
So two with three, and two with four.
And, finally John.
John wrote both five and six,
the other name and a new name.
So three and five, and
then three and six.
And this has solved some
of my problems from before.
I'm no longer duplicating
information in a particular table.
I have just the information organized
into its own separate tables.
And now I still have a way of trying
to organize the information together
and have the relationships
exist between them.
So let me pause here
and ask what questions
do we have on this idea
of organizing our tables
and relating information between them?
What questions do we have?
A good question.
What do we call this kind of table?
So, often we will see the particular
kind of format for our tables.
This table has many names.
It is sometimes called an associative
entity, sometimes called a junction
table, sometimes called a join table.
The idea of this table associating
certain two foreign keys
has many names.
But among those are the
ones I just said here.
Individually though, these individual
columns are each foreign keys.
Because they refer to the
primary key of some other table.
So remember, a primary key is that
unique ID for every row in that table.
But when it's using some other
table, like the authored table,
it becomes what we call a foreign key.
Question, a good one
here, is making a call
to three separate tables as efficient as
making a single call to a single table
even though that single table is bigger?
So remember, we first began, we had only
one single table with duplicate authors
in it.
Now I mean, you've kind of
hit the nail on the head here.
We have three different tables.
And if I want to figure
out who wrote which book,
I have to go to all three tables.
It could take more time.
Often though as you get much
bigger data sets, this pays off.
And having this kind
of organization helps
you avoid what we call
data anomalies, helping
to make sure your data is
what we call normalized,
able to stay organized over time.
So, often you'll see these
kinds of trade offs more,
let's say, clear when
you have lots of data.
And it becomes a little
more clear that this
is going to be a superior
way of organizing your data.
Let's see.
Wouldn't it be better if we had the
author id column in the books table?
That's a decent idea.
So what if I had not just this authors--
actually, let's say I got
rid of the authored table.
I go to books.
And couldn't I have
something a bit like this.
I could have an author id column here.
And then I could say, well,
author id one wrote one and two.
And then author id two
wrote three and four.
Author id three wrote five and six.
And this is kind of the same idea.
But notice here, I'm still
kind of repeating this idea.
I could do it, but I
think it's better to have
just books in their own table and
then just authors in their own table
as well.
And actually, as we
saw in lecture, there's
this idea of a one to many relationship,
a many to many relationship,
and because authors and books have
a many to many relationship, that
is one author could
write multiple books,
and one book could be
written by multiple authors,
it's often helpful to have a
joined table or a junction table
to represent that kind of relationship.
If though you have a one to
many relationship that is a book
is only ever written
by one author, it could
make sense to have this
kind of design here,
with the author id column
inside the books table.
So it does depend on
the kind of relationship
you are trying to represent between
your entities, if that makes sense.
All right.
So I think we've pretty thoroughly
explored this idea of designing
databases, at least for now.
And it's worth thinking about how we
can try to represent this idea in terms
of an actual database.
So here I have done
this in Google Sheets.
But what could I do to create these
tables inside of a database management
system, perhaps like SQLite?
So I'll go now to my terminal here.
And I will let it reload.
Let me go ahead and confirm those.
Actually, OK, it's going
to reload for me here.
And while it does that,
let me also talk to you
a bit about some design
principles to keep
in mind as you design your databases.
So I'll go back to my slides here.
And as you go off into
CS50 and beyond, I
would keep in mind
these three ideas, that
is best often to have one table
for each entity in your data set.
So an entity could be something like
a book or an author, for instance.
Those are two different entities.
, Second every table should often
have its very own primary key,
some unique ID, like a number, that
identifies it and differentiates it
from every other row in that table.
And then like we discussed here,
the information in that table
should depend on the primary key only.
Or another way of saying
this is that every table
should have only the information
on that particular entity,
so only information on
books in the books table
and only information on
authors in the authors table.
All right.
So let's go back to our code space here.
And let me try to set
up an example here.
So why don't we try to make
this idea into a reality?
I will type SQLite3 reads dot dB.
And what this will do is create for me
a new database file called reads.dB.
And it'll open with this
program called SQLite3.
So SQLite3 is the software that
allows us to open up a database
and use SQLite with it.
So I'll hit Enter here.
And it'll ask if I
want to create read.dB.
I do.
It's brand new.
I'll hit Yes here.
And now I'm brought to a new prompt.
So notice above I have a dollar
sign, which is my bash terminal.
You often use it for typing LS or
CD to move around your code space.
Now though, I'm in SQLite,
this brand new software
I could use to actually
access my database.
So one of the first
things I could do is try
to create some table
inside this database.
And for that we need some new syntax.
So I'll go back to my slides.
And here is the SQL syntax
for creating some new table.
Notice how I have create table,
which is this SQL keyword that says,
create me a new table,
and then table name.
So table name is the
name I give to my table.
And then in parentheses,
I have a variety
of columns I could add to this table,
much like we did in Google Sheets.
Here though, I have to
decide actually two things.
First, the column name, so column zero,
column one, column two, column three.
Those are all placeholders
here for actual column names.
And then in caps, the
type of that column.
So there are many
different kinds of types
in SQL, actually not necessarily
many, there are really
only a handful of them.
But here are a few.
So one is the idea of an integer, having
a column that stores whole numbers.
Another is text, having a
column that stores text.
Another is numeric, numeric could store
either integers or floating points,
like with decimals and so
on, like 1.2 for instance,
and real, which stores just let's
say floats, just 1.2 or 2.5,
any number with a decimal
point inside of it.
Numeric is often used for
things like dates as well.
So it's more flexible than, let's
say, just integer or just real,
which is why people
might use it in the end.
So these are our various
types at our disposal.
So let's go ahead and try to
actually create this table here.
I'll go back to my code space.
And I will try to create our very
own, let's say books table first.
So I'll type create table books.
And then I'll have parentheses here.
And I'll hit Enter,
just for style's sake.
And now indent 4 times, one,
two, three, four spaces.
Now I can give my very
first column name.
So our column name if I go
back here was, well first ID.
So I'll say ID.
And what kind of information
was stored in ID?
What type do you think is
best for this kind of column?
Probably integer.
So we stored whole numbers there.
So I'll say ID space integer,
and followed by a comma
for adding on additional columns here.
I'll hit Enter, hit Space four times
to indent just for style's sake.
Now I'll go my next
column, which was title.
Now what information is stored in title?
What type might be best?
Probably text, we're just
storing characters here.
So I will say title text.
And this is idea of storing
like strings or characters.
Often that's good for a text column.
Now I'll go ahead and I'll make
a new one called published.
OK, published.
And published is a bit tricky.
Like we could use text
because I see dashes in here.
But actually SQLite lets us store dates
like this as a numeric kind of column.
So I'll use numeric
here to store a date.
Another comma, because we want
to keep adding new columns.
Our last one is rating.
So I'll go ahead and say rating here.
And the type is probably
going to be integer.
So I could call this good.
I could close this statement.
But I don't want to do that just yet.
There's one thing I'm
forgetting which is what?
Any ideas?
I have all my columns.
But I should specify one thing more.
Yeah.
So I'm seeing some ideas.
I need to specify which of
these columns is my primary key.
So in SQLite to do this, I
can use the following syntax.
At the end of all my
column definitions I
can say primary key
and inside parentheses,
tell SQLite which of these
columns is my primary key.
So let me go back and I'll
have another comma here.
I'll indent four times
again, just for style.
I'll say primary key in all caps
to indicate this is a SQL keyword.
And then I'll tell it
what kind of column
I want to include in my primary key.
In this case, it's the ID column.
So now that I'm done, I
can hit Enter, no comma,
close out this beginning parentheses,
semicolon, and fingers crossed,
hit Enter.
I don't see anything which
is actually a good thing.
So now maybe I'll try this.
I'll say dot schema.
Actually before I do that,
let me type dot tables.
This is not a SQL keyword,
but a SQLite statement
that tells me what tables
do I have in this database.
I'll hit Enter.
And I see I have a table called books.
If I want to actually
figure out later on,
let's say I clear my screen like this.
I could Control L. If I
want to clear my screen
and figure out what the
columns I had in books were,
I could type dot schema, space books.
Hit Enter.
And that tells me the
create table statement
that was used to create
this table called books.
So I have the very same idea
that I had in Google Sheets,
but now in this database, in SQLite.
And we'll see later on how to
actually add data to this table here.
So let's go ahead and now
create our author's table.
I will try to create table here.
And I'll call this one authors.
Create table authors.
And then I'll add in the columns.
We had the ID column like
this, which was an integer.
We had the author
column, which was text.
And we had the author birth column.
Author birth, which was an
integer as well for the year.
Our primary key, our
primary key is still
the ID column in this particular table.
I'll hit Enter, semicolon,
and then type .tables.
I have two tables now, .schema authors.
And I'll see that same
create table statement here.
Now a few questions have come up.
One is, can you have
multiple primary keys?
In general, you can't have--
well, how to answer this.
You can have a primary
key that is composed
of multiple columns, which
means that those columns have
to be unique across all of them.
And they together form your primary key.
You can't though have multiple
different primary keys for your table.
The idea of a primary key is that
it is the single unique identifier
in your table.
Let's see.
A question about the ratings.
So we used-- if I go back to .schema
rating or .schema books here.
We chose integer for the rating column.
You're asking, could I also
store like 4.5 in this?
An interesting question.
So, even though this
column is an integer,
it has what we call an integer
affinity, I could if I really wanted to,
store something like 4.5 in it.
In SQLite, these column affinities
are not so much strict in the sense
that it will convert 4.5 to 4 for me.
If I inserted the value 4.5, SQLite
would say, OK, fine, you want to float,
I'll give it to you in that column.
But it's just generally good practice to
say what you're going to do in SQLite.
So here I'd probably going to
stick to just whole star ratings.
I won't actually include
let's say 4.5 or 3.2 or so on.
But a good question.
If you want to learn more
about that you could look up
this idea of type affinities in SQLite.
Other questions too.
I think that's all for now.
So why don't we go ahead and actually
implement the last bit of this.
So we wanted to create
the authored table too.
So I will create a
table called authored.
And this one's a little interesting.
So maybe in this
particular table, it seems
like we didn't have a primary key.
Like I didn't have a unique identifier
for every row in this table.
But if we think about it, let's
go back to that question of,
could we have multiple primary keys,
maybe the combinations of these two
columns will always be unique.
Like I wouldn't want to
duplicate, let's say,
duplicate 1 and 1 because I already
know that, let's say Fernanda wrote,
or let's say Olga wrote Flights.
I wouldn't want to duplicate that.
So maybe here what I could
do is have a primary key
composed of these two columns.
And I'll show you how to do that
syntactically in just a second.
The other thing to keep in mind here is
that these two columns are themselves
foreign keys that reference
primary keys in other tables.
So let's go ahead and first
create these columns in our table
and then decide how to define them
as primary keys and foreign keys
kind of at the same time.
So I'll go back to my statement here.
And I had at the beginning,
author id which is an integer.
And I also had book id,
which is an integer as well.
So now I get to the tricky part,
which is, which one of these
is my primary key?
And the answer kind of
is, well, they both are.
Like together the values
in both those two columns
form something unique about every row.
So I could do this.
I could say primary key author
id comma book id like this.
And that then says that the combination
of my author id and the book id
should always be unique and can uniquely
identify every row in this table.
This is a design choice.
I could very well have a
separate column called ID,
as you will see in the movies problem
set and make that my primary key.
It's kind of up to you
what you like to do.
Each one has slightly different
effects on the database.
And just because you all
asked, I want to show you
this particular way of doing it here.
But another way to
continue on here is, I
want to make sure that
each of these columns
has a constraint that says
they are a foreign key too.
So to make sure that
the author id column is
known to be referencing the
primary key and the authors table,
I could say this.
Foreign key foreign key author id
references the authors table and the ID
column in it, like this.
So this is just a SQL syntax to do so.
I'll continue on and I'll
say that the foreign key
of this table, another
foreign key, is the book
id and that references the books
table and the ID column in it.
So now I will hit Enter here, have
a closing parentheses, semicolon,
and fingers crossed.
Seems to have worked for me here.
A few questions I see.
Does the order of the keys matter?
So let me answer that from
a few different angles.
I could put these in any order.
I could put book id
first, then author id.
It doesn't quite matter
for my table here.
In my primary key column, the
order here does matter in the sense
that if I do it in the
opposite way, I will
get a very slightly different effect.
The different effect is going to be
a little bit too high level for what
we're going to talk about today.
But if you are curious,
I have a full class
on this called [INAUDIBLE] construction
database with SQL where you might
learn some of those kinds of things.
But in general, it doesn't quite
matter what order you put these in
even though it has some slight
underlying effects on your database,
if that makes sense.
All right.
So I'll clear my screen.
I'll type .tables.
And I'll see I have
authored, authors, and books.
So all three of these tables
are now in my database.
All right.
So we've seen how to
create these tables.
And the next step then is to
actually try to insert some data.
So let's get an idea of what
syntax we could use there.
So if I want to insert
some values into a table,
we saw in lecture that I
could do the following.
I could say insert into
and then the table name,
followed by the columns
I want to insert into,
and then the values I want to insert
into those particular columns.
So let's try adding,
just for the sake of fun
here, a new book into our books table.
I can go back to my SQLite prompt.
I could say insert, insert
into the books table.
And what column should I maybe include?
What should I include here?
Maybe the title, the author,
and what else do we have?
We had published and rating,
published and rating.
So now I'll hit Enter, just for style's
sake, to continue on with my query.
And now I can define what
values should go into--
oh, we didn't have author, did we?
Books, title, nope.
Oh no.
OK, so if you get to this point and
you're like, oh, no, I made a mistake.
What should you do?
You could, I think, type control--
oh, you could hit
semicolon, Enter, and it
will tell you that your query
was malformed, which is true.
I didn't finish the query.
But semicolon can get you out of
a problematic query like that.
So let's redo that one.
I'll hit up arrow twice to get back
to that very first thing I typed.
And we had title, published, and rating.
Notice here, I actually don't
have to include the ID column.
So the ID column, because
this is a primary key,
gets automatically added for me.
So I'll now do values and the
values are let's say, Flights,
which is single quoted
because it's a string,
publication which is also
a string, 2017, 05 17.
And then I'll add in the rating, which
is just the number four here like this.
Now I'll close this particular
statement, hit Enter.
Nothing happens.
But now if I use that SQL statement
select star from let's say books,
I'll now see I have a single
book inside of my books table.
And it automatically added
the primary key called ID.
Let's say I want to delete
this what I could do
is simply use delete
from books like this.
But why might I not want to do that?
Let's say I had more than
one book in here, what would
be wrong with doing delete from books?
It'll delete everything.
It'll literally delete
my entire book table.
So I don't want to do this.
What I should do instead
is I could say delete
from books where some condition
is true and maybe I'll
say I want to delete from books
where the title equals Flights.
To remove Flights in particular, I'll
hit Enter I'll select star from books.
And now I see that it's
gone from my table.
There are no rows inside of it.
All right.
So what questions do we have
on creating these tables,
inserting data, and deleting data?
I think I saw one
earlier, one about the--
I think the junction table we
had, or that associative entity,
that authored table.
Do those tables know about each other?
They do in some senses.
So if I go back and show you the
schema of the authored table here,
when I define for SQLite that
the foreign key, author id,
references the authors table
and the ID column in it,
that then tells SQLite to
make sure if I ever insert
some piece of data to
this authored table
that it is able to reference some value
of a primary key in the authors table.
So this is-- it helps me make sure
my data is all organized, et cetera.
One thing in particular
though, is that you
have to make sure that SQLite is
doing what we call foreign key checks.
So you could disable this check when
you insert into the author table.
Maybe SQLite just doesn't
check anything at all.
You have to make sure you
enable that check to make sure
that it does look in
the other table to make
sure you do have that particular primary
key it can associate with the author
table row.
Does that make sense?
All right.
Can we insert many
rows at the same time?
You absolutely can.
So to insert many rows--
let me go back to my
slides --you would simply at
the end of this statement here,
you would not have a semicolon,
you would have a comma
and you keep adding
parentheses of values.
So it's like values, then
you can imagine values
0 comma value one end parentheses
comma, maybe a next line.
And then another parentheses values
0 comma value one parentheses.
And keep going and going and
going as you would like to.
Good question.
OK.
So we've seen how to design
some databases, which hopefully
will be helpful to you not just
this week, but in future weeks
as you design your
very own final project.
I want to make sure we get to
actually querying on our database
and using some of our SQL syntax
to ask and answer questions
about some pieces of data.
So why don't we go ahead and look
at one of the very first problems
in this week's problem
set, which is called songs.
And in songs, you're
given a list of the 100
I believe most popular
songs in 2018 or so.
And your job is to answer some
questions about those particular songs.
So to begin, why don't we actually
go to the specification page
and see what we're trying to do here.
So when I download the distribution
code for this particular problem,
I get a few different things.
I get a file called songs dot dB.
And I also get a bunch of dot SQL files.
So I can write some queries
to use on my database.
Now songs dot DB is the database.
It has all the information on the songs.
And here these dot SQL
files they allow me
to keep track of the queries I'm
writing to answer these questions here.
So let me go ahead and actually get
my songs dot dB into my code space.
And to do that, I need to
first leave SQLite here.
So to leave SQLite, you can
type dot quit, dot quit,
and you'll leave SQLite and be brought
back to your terminal prompt here.
Now if I type LS, I should see
I already have songs downloaded.
You can do the same on
the problem set page.
I'll go CD songs to change
directory into songs.
Now if I type Ls to list my files,
I should see I have my dot SQL files
and my songs dot dB as well
as this answers dot txt
that I'll use at the
very end if I'd like to.
So let's actually open up songs
dot DB and see what's inside.
I'll type SQLite 3 songs dot dB to
open up this database using SQLite 3.
Now I'll clear my screen
and I will type dot schema.
Schema alone tells me
what kinds of tables
are in this database and the
create table statements that
were used to create them.
So I'll hit Enter.
And here I'll see, how
many tables do we have?
How many tables do we see?
We see two.
So there are two create
table statements.
It looks like one of these tables
is called songs and another of these
is called artists.
The songs table has several columns.
It seems to have the ID, the name,
the artist ID, danceability, energy,
loudness, [INAUDIBLE].
There's a lot of information
about these songs
here that we could use to ask and
answer questions about these songs.
In the meantime, the artists table does
have an ID column and a name column.
So pretty straightforward here.
And notice that for the sake
of simplicity in this problem,
we haven't actually defined the
primary keys, the foreign keys.
Although if you were working
on your own you probably
should define these particular features
data of your actual database tables.
So to get a sense of what we're
working with here one thing to do
is to just select and see
what we actually have.
So I could try this query.
Select star from the,
let's say, the songs table.
Remember, select means
give me some data back.
It's a tool for reading some data.
Star is this idea that says,
give me back all the columns.
I don't really care which ones.
I want all the columns
from this particular table.
And from says, where are we
actually getting the data from?
Which table do you want to query?
In this case songs.
So I'll hit Enter here and I'll get
back, if I zoom out, a lot of songs
in this particular database.
In fact, there are 100 total, because
we have 100 at the very bottom here.
So often though, if you're working
with much bigger databases,
you don't want to just print
out everything to your screen.
A good way to actually get a peek
at what's inside is to do this.
Maybe select a particular column.
I'll say select title.
Select title from songs.
But then I only want the first,
let's say, five titles just
to see what's inside here.
Take a literal peek at our data set.
Limit five.
Hit Enter.
Oops.
Is there no column title?
Let me do dot schema songs.
And it's not called title
but it is called name.
So I will go ahead
and change this query.
I'll say select name from songs.
And limit five.
So now I see, these are the first five
songs on this list of the top 100 songs
in 2018, at least in the US.
So now I can figure
out, OK, how do I start
answering these next particular
questions in this songs problem?
So I'll go back to the specification.
And I'll look at this
very first question here.
In one dot SQL, write
a SQL query to list
the names of all songs in the database.
So let me ask you all, which
column should we be querying?
If our goal is to list the names
of all songs in the database,
which column should we be selecting?
Probably name if you just
want the names of all songs.
So I'll go back and I'll select name.
Now this in itself is not quite enough.
I need to say, where am
I selecting name from?
Like where does the
name column come from?
Well, it comes from the songs table.
So I'll say select name from songs.
Hit Enter.
And that is our query.
Notice how we got back all 100,
all 100 names from this table.
So now that I think I've
solved this first question,
Why don't I go ahead and try to write
that query inside of one dot SQL.
I'll make myself a new terminal.
I'll hit this plus button here.
Now I'm back at my bash prompt.
And this is kind of handy.
I can have SQLite open in one and my
other bash prompt open in the other.
I could then type LS CD into songs.
And now I could code one
dot SQL to open it up.
And I have a blank SQL file here.
But to keep track of this
query, what I could do
is say select name from songs,
that same query we used before.
And now I have it documented for
myself inside of one dot SQL.
Let's say I also want to maybe
not just keep track of it,
but run what I write in one dot SQL.
Well, I could use a SQLite keyword.
This one called dot read.
So I could say dot read one dot SQL.
And that will see whatever
is inside one dot SQL
and read it into SQLite, running
any SQL statements it sees.
So I'll hit Enter here.
And notice how I got
the very same results.
So dot read one dot SQL simply executes
the query I wrote in one dot SQL.
Enter again just to show you
I can use dot read as well.
So questions on this very first bit
of querying with our songs database?
Any questions?
Oh good question.
So how would you specify
what data you want, and how
would you get multiple pieces of
data from multiple different tables?
So two questions here.
How do you specify what data you want?
So for that, you often have to
use a select keyword in SQL.
Select allows you to select certain
columns from individual tables.
So we could say select name or
select author id or so on, and then
from some particular table.
If though, you want to query
multiple tables at once,
like look at data in the
artist table and look
at data in the songs table, that
would require more advanced techniques
we'll see a little later, either
called a subquery or a join so more
on that in just a bit.
But to more formally introduce
some of these tools in your toolkit
as you answer these
questions, I want to show you
some keywords you might want to be
familiar with as you work on songs.
So, once you open up SQLite3 with
your database name, you might go ahead
and type SQLite3 songs dot dB.
You could then type your query here.
And then you could do dot tables
to see the tables involved.
And you can kind of visualize
songs dot dB like this.
It's having both songs
and artist tables.
And each of course,
has different schema,
like schema songs as we saw
before or select star from songs
limit 3 to find those top few rows.
And you get back something like this.
You can do the same for
artists a bit like that.
And as you go ahead and solve some of
these, like queries one through five,
these are the kinds
of keywords you might
want to be familiar with as you work.
So select where, like and
order by to begin with.
So select, we saw helps us
select certain rows from our--
or select certain columns from our
table, where it lets us actually
filter to only certain rows.
So let's try our next query.
This one is listing names of all
songs in increasing order of tempo.
So for that, we might want
to actually use order by.
Order by lets us change the order of
certain rows as they return to us.
So let me go ahead and go
back to my SQLite prompt.
And now I want to list the names of
all songs in increasing order of tempo.
So to begin, all SQL
statements begin with a select.
Let me ask you, what should we
be selecting here, which column?
Probably selecting the names of songs.
We could say select name to begin with.
And then of course from the songs table.
Now, as my queries
get longer, it's often
good to not include them
all on the same line,
but to break them up
into individual lines.
So I'll select name.
Hit Enter from songs.
Hit Enter again.
And there's one final
piece of this query.
I've selected the name
column from the table,
but now I want the songs in
increasing order of tempo.
So to do that, I could use order by.
Order by often comes at
the end of a statement
to tell me what order my
results are given back to me.
So I'll say order by, order
by tempo, in this case.
Semicolon and Enter.
So now I should see that I have these
songs in a slightly different order,
in this case by tempo.
And to prove it, why don't I
go ahead and modify this query.
I'll say select name, not
just name, but tempo as well.
So now I'm selecting two columns
name comma tempo from songs.
I'll order by tempo.
Hit Enter.
And now I should see that
I have these songs ordered
by tempo in increasing order, so
smallest to largest, just like that.
Now once this particular
query is done, why don't I
go ahead and add it into two dot SQL.
I'll say code two dot SQL.
And I will then say
select name from songs.
Order by tempo like this.
So now I've used order by.
Let's take a look at our next one.
So three dot SQL.
The names of the top five
longest songs in descending order
of length, the top five longest
songs in descending order of length.
So here, I think we can
reuse this idea of order by.
We're trying to figure out
the top five longest songs.
And they should be in some particular
order, descending order of length.
So maybe I'll go back
to my SQLite prompt.
And I want to again select names.
Select name from songs.
But which column should
I be ordering on?
Any ideas?
The top five longest songs.
Let's go ahead and type dot
schema, dot schema songs.
Do any of these columns seem to
specify the length of a song?
So I'm seeing duration, so
duration in milliseconds.
So this is like, how long
that song actually is.
So I could order by that
particular column there.
So I'll try select name from
songs and order by duration ms.
Now the problem here is I want the
songs in decreasing order of length,
descending order of length.
Notice how before,
when we used order by,
we went in increasing order
from lowest to highest.
But here I want highest to lowest.
So to change this, I
could modify order by.
And I could say desc or asc
for ascending or descending.
So descending or desc means give
me the largest values first,
and then give me the smaller ones
as you go down this particular list.
So once I have that, I'll hit Enter.
And I've gotten the songs, I think
in decreasing order of duration.
I could say select name
duration ms from songs, order
by duration ms in descending order.
I think I've ordered them
properly, based on what I see here.
But how could I find only the top five?
What can I add on to my query?
A limit 5 is what I'm seeing.
So I'll go ahead and try that.
I will go here, scroll
down, and I'll say,
let's select name
again from songs, order
by duration ms in descending order.
And now, limit myself
to the top five results.
Now in general, as you're working
with SQL syntax like this,
knowing the ordering that these
statements go in is often helpful.
So to give you a guide, often select
goes first, followed by an order
by, trying to order the result
in some particular order.
Then at the very end of your
query, do you have limit.
So limit tells me, give me
back all of the results,
but only take those top five.
I'll hit Enter here.
And now I'll see these are
the top five songs in terms
of duration, the longest
five songs to be exact.
So I'll go back to my other
terminal, type code three dot SQL.
Let me just document this query here.
I'll say select name from songs, order
by duration ms in descending order.
And then I'll limit myself
to the top five songs.
So this is that particular
query now done for me here.
Let's keep going.
Let's see four dot SQL.
So four dot SQL lists the names of any
songs that have a danceability energy
and valence greater than 0.75.
Well, let's take a peek at
what that actually means.
So, I'll go back to my database.
And why don't I just select the
title or the name of a song.
And then why don't I also select the
danceability, energy, and valence,
see what those numbers are.
Select name, danceability, energy,
and valence, all in one go from songs.
And I'll just take the top
song here to see what it is.
Hit Enter.
So it seems like the very
first song is called God's Plan
and the danceability of it is 0.754.
The energy is 0.449.
And the valence is 0.357.
So if you're not familiar, this
data actually comes from Spotify.
And Spotify has various metrics
they make to help characterize
certain songs on a zero to one scale.
So danceability is how danceable
that song is, how much you
can kind of jive to the beat.
Energy here is like how
much intensity it has.
Is it something you kind of mellow
out to or like play at a club?
And then valence is like how
happy is this song, where one is
like it's a happy, very positive song.
Zero is kind of like a minor
key, kind of dark kind of song.
So it's like a way of characterizing the
song in terms of actual numeric output,
which is kind of cool.
So our goal here is to find
generally, those songs that
are pretty danceable, pretty energetic,
and pretty happy, it seems like.
So we're going to try to find the
titles of those particular songs.
So I again want to list
the names of songs.
Maybe I'll go back to my SQLite prompt.
I'll say select name from songs.
But here's where I get into trouble.
How do I exclude certain
songs and only include
those that have a danceability,
energy, and valence greater than 0.75?
Which keyword do you think
we should probably use here?
I'm seeing where.
So often, when you want to filter
the rows, you're going to use where.
Where often comes immediately
after you use a select and a from.
So I'll say select name from songs.
And now I'll have my condition.
Well, where, first part of my
condition is the danceability
should be greater than 0.75.
So it should be a pretty danceable song.
I'll go and say where,
danceability is greater than 0.75.
But that's not the only condition here.
I also want to make sure that
the energy and the valence
are similarly at least that big.
So if I want to add on more
conditions, I can use and.
I could say and the energy
is greater than 0.75.
And let's say, the valence
I could also use or, capital O, capital
R to say either this or that as well.
But I'll take this.
And I think this should
satisfy my query.
Any songs that danceability, energy,
and valence greater than 0.75.
I'll hit Enter.
And I should see that
there are about, let's see,
five songs that are pretty danceable,
pretty energetic, and pretty happy,
according to Spotify at least.
So I'll go back to my other terminal.
And I'll say code, what was this?
This was four dot SQL.
Code four dot SQL.
And now I'll type in that very same
query, which was selecting names
from songs where the danceability
was greater than 0.75 and the energy
was greater than 0.75 and the
valence was greater than 0.75.
And that was my entire query.
All right.
Questions, then, on
what we've seen so far?
What questions do you have?
All right, seeing none for right now.
So let's keep going and do
something a little more interesting.
Our next question asks us
to return the average energy
of all the songs, the average energy.
So this is a little bit
different, because I
don't think I can select any particular
row and get back the average energy.
Because if I go ahead and I do
something like select energy from songs,
like this, I get back all the
values in the energy column.
So I need something a little
special to answer this question.
That is what we call in SQLite,
this idea of an aggregate function.
So an aggregate function
takes in something.
Let me try to find this slide here.
An aggregate function takes
in lots of data and spits
out one particular number.
So you can take a whole
column of data and give you
one summary number, if you will.
Now there are a few of these.
And you could use them like this.
Where you often have a query, it looks
a bit like select column from name
or some condition is true, you could
say select count of the values there.
How many values do we
have that are not null?
You could select the
average of those numbers,
like what is the average number across
all these in a particular column?
You could select the minimum,
the maximum, and so on.
So we'll actually use
these for queries, five
through seven in the songs problem.
But often you simply use them
by taking your column name
and sticking it inside some parentheses
after your aggregate function
in particular.
So like average count min or so on.
So why don't I try average.
Select AVG for average.
Select average energy from songs.
Hit Enter.
And now I see that the average
energy is about a 0.65906 out of one.
Now there's a bit of a bonus here.
I don't quite care if
it's like 906 at the end.
It could be 0.65.
So to adjust this, I could try
select but say the rounded average.
I could around the average energy
to two decimal places from songs.
From songs.
And now I get back just the rounded
version to two decimal places
if I'd like.
So round is one other function you
can use, not an aggregate function,
but it does let you round your
results from a particular column.
In this case though, we want
the non-rounded version.
So I'll go to my terminal.
I'll type code five dot SQL.
And now I'll say select the
average energy from songs.
And that should answer the
question for five dot SQL.
All right.
Questions on aggregate functions here?
Not seeing any.
Now I think we'll go back to
another question, which said,
how do we get data from multiple tables.
And we'll see a few approaches
actually here today.
So in six dot SQL,
it's asking us to write
a SQL query that lists the names
of songs that are by Post Malone.
So Post Malone in the US
is an artist and a rapper.
So how could we find the
songs by Post Malone?
Well, if I type dot schema songs.
Oops.
This is my SQLite prompt.
If I type dot schema songs.
Do I see any information
about the authors here
or the artists of this song?
What information do I have to work with?
I see artist ID.
So I could probably filter these songs
using where to a particular artist ID.
But then the next question is,
well, which ID should I be using?
Like I don't quite know
right now Post Malone's ID.
So how could I filter the songs to
those that have Post Malone's ID?
Well, there's probably a few
ways I could go about this.
And I want to show you one visualization
and one example of how you can actually
use this technique not just for this
scenario, but for other ones too.
So go back to some slides.
And let's go ahead and take a
look at how we can solve ways to--
queries that ask us to combine tables
and gather data from multiple sources.
So in general, there
are two ways to do this.
One is to use subqueries.
And one is to actually
join those tables together.
We'll focus here first on
using this idea of a subquery.
So to motivate them, I think it's worth
going through a particular example,
where maybe I now have two tables,
one for movies and one for ratings.
And let's say I want to
find the rating of Cars
3, my own personal favorite movie.
Where could I find the rating of Cars 3?
Well, it seems like it's
in the ratings table.
But if I were to just query movies, I
wouldn't actually see the rating there.
So you need to reference
both tables to figure out
what is the rating of Cars 3?
Now let me ask you, what do you
notice about these two tables?
What allows me to reference
data between them?
What could I do?
So the ID column in movies and the
movie ID column and ratings, those
seem to correspond.
In fact, the movie ID column seems
to be a foreign key referencing
the primary key ID in movies.
So notice here, these two kind of align.
They reference each other.
So I could use this to my advantage.
Maybe I could do in
SQLite, I could do this.
I could say, why don't I find the ID
for Cars 3, where the title is Cars 3.
And that would give me back 3606752.
OK.
That's helpful for me.
Maybe my next query then could be this.
Select rating from ratings where
the movie ID equals 3606752.
And that would give me
back the rating for Cars 3.
But what could I be doing better, or at
least what seems annoying about this?
Any ideas?
I would just think about, would
you want to type this query?
I mean it's kind of like, the
idea is just kind of long to type.
I don't want to have to do
that really multiple times.
And let's say the ID of Cars changes.
Like that is not something I
want to actually keep track of.
So there's probably a
better way to do this
that actually allows me to
abstract away or not even
think about the ID of what
Cars 3-- of Cars 3 at all.
So why don't I reformulate my query.
And why don't I try this.
Select rating from ratings where
the movie ID equals something,
but I don't know what yet.
There's a question mark there.
I need to figure out, well,
what is the ID of Cars 3?
And to fill in that question mark,
I could use some other SQL query.
I could organize it like this.
And now I could say, why don't I
put in this query that finds me
that ID for Cars 3.
In this case, I'll say select ID from
movies where the title equals Cars 3.
OK.
So now I'm trying to build up a
single query that doesn't even
care what the ID of Cars is.
I'm now able to just
find the rating from it.
And as a bit of a side note
here, I think, let me check.
Yes.
So this particular quote, these
quotes here, double quotes.
Don't do what I did.
That's not good.
Only use single quotes.
So this is often hard to keep
track of as evidenced here.
But you should only
be using single quotes
when you actually use strings in SQL.
So my bad.
But don't use double quotes.
All right, so let's say we
have this inner query here.
Select ID from movies
where title equals Cars 3.
First, that query will run and
return to us the ID of Cars 3.
So whatever is the innermost query
in parentheses will run first.
And in that case we'll get
back, let's say, 3606752.
And our query kind of
becomes this query here.
Select rating from ratings where the
movie ID equals that ID for Cars.
And of course, we can then get back
the rating we're looking for all along.
So let's try this with, let's
say, this idea of Post Malone.
So I want to find the
songs by Post Malone.
Well I know first I want to
select, select names from songs.
And I want to do so where the
artist ID equals, equals something.
I don't quite know what yet.
So I might write a subquery.
I could say, let's
have some parentheses.
And I'll hit Enter and indent
four times for style's sake.
Now I'm trying to answer that question,
like what is Post Malone's artist ID?
Any ideas for how I could get
access to that particular ID?
What kind of query could I use
here to find the ID of Post Malone?
Probably want to select.
I want to select the ID column,
probably from the artist table.
So I'll say select ID from
artists and you could probably
find this if you went back and checked
the schema of the artist table too.
Select ID from artists.
And now I want to only
get one ID, which is
the ID of the artist where
their name equals Post
Malone with single quotes importantly.
Now I'll hit Enter.
And that is my entire subquery.
And parentheses, semicolon, hit Enter.
And now I see these are the
six songs Post Malone had
in the top 100 list in 2018.
So questions then on subqueries.
And now we're using them here.
Why single quotes?
So you could use double
quotes if you wanted to.
I think it would still work.
Technically in SQLite, single quotes
are used for strings like Post Malone.
And double quotes are
used for identifiers,
like table names and column names.
You don't have to use them.
Here I'm not using them as you'll see.
But it's good not to mix those up.
So in general, strings like Post
Malone, single quotes, column names,
table names, double quotes
are what you would use there
if you are using quotes at all.
Good questions.
Can you show data from both
tables with the queries?
What an excellent question.
So can you show data
with both tables from--
show data from both
tables with the queries?
You absolutely can.
That would require you,
though, to use a join.
So subqueries are great when you
want to filter your data based
on something in another table.
If you want to actually see column from
multiple tables all together in one,
you want to join those tables together.
So more on that in just a bit.
Actually, why don't we go
ahead and turn to it right now?
So our next query is seven dot SQL.
And here, we're trying to return
the average energy of songs
that are by Drake.
Average energy of songs
Well, what could we do?
Well first we probably have
to find what is Drake's ID.
And we could simply
use our subquery again.
That would work perfectly fine.
But let's say we want to see, not
just the average energy of songs
that are by Drake, but also maybe
Drake's name somewhere in there too.
So I want to kind of join my
tables together a bit like this.
And let me actually
give you a visualization
for what that could look like.
Go back to my slides here.
Let's focus now on joining
up our tables and trying
to answer that same question
we did earlier about what
is the rating of Cars 3, the movie.
So here again I have my
movies and ratings tables.
And we noticed earlier that these
two columns had a relationship.
That is the movie ID column
was the foreign key referencing
the primary key called ID in movies.
So now I could answer
this question the same way
I did before, or maybe
even more simply, I
could try to push these tables
together so that I align the movie's ID
column with the values of
the ratings movie ID column.
So I could visually do this.
And notice here how I'm
matching up rows based
on where the ID column in movies
and the movie ID column in ratings
are the same value.
To visualize again, I know I should put
this rating 8.3, 8.3, next to Toy Story
because movie ID 114709 matches
the ID column movies 114709.
So when I join these tables,
those will be the rows I match up.
Same thing for Cars.
And now I have a single
table here that shows
me the title, Cars 3, and the rating.
So I could abstract away
this movie ID column.
And now I'm left with basically a
single table that has IDs for movies
but now also has some additional
data like the ratings piece as well.
So this is how we could solve
this problem using join.
Let's try it now to figure
out, what is the average energy
of songs that are by Drake?
Well, to actually
implement a join, I need
to actually type this join keyword.
So why don't I try this?
I'll say select, the name
energy and let's say artist.
Let's see, actually let
me see what is the--
if I use dot schema artist, the name.
So notice how artists has a name column.
I want to, let's say get
back the name of Drake
songs, the energy associated
with them, and the name of Drake.
So I can actually see in
one table, like, whatever
Drake's song name is the energy
of that song and then the name
Drake right next to it.
So I could say select name
from, let's say, the song table.
Select energy as well.
And now select well, the
name column from artist.
So why might this be a little confusing?
I have two columns named
name in two different tables.
So, I probably want to specify
where I'm getting which one.
And to do this, if you have this
problem, you could do the following.
I could say, not just
name, but songs dot name,
or for instance, artists dot name.
This allows me to say,
I want in particular
the name column from songs and
the name column from artists.
And now, why don't I say from, let's
go ahead and say from the songs table.
But the songs table, of course, doesn't
have the name column in artists.
So I need to join that table in.
I'll say from songs join artists.
And now I have to specify which
two columns should SQLite use
to know which rows to put
together across these two tables.
So I'll say join artists
on, in this case,
I know I should use
the artists.id column
and set that, that should be the
same as the songs dot artist,
ID column, like this.
So I'm telling SQLite,
when you join these tables,
make sure that the ID column in artists
matches the artist ID column in songs.
Now I'll hit Enter.
And why don't I try specify, where
artists dot name equals Drake.
And hopefully, fingers
crossed, I'll hit Enter here.
This is all improvised.
I should see that the I have the names
of Drake songs and the energy of them,
and of course, Drake's
name right next to them.
So questions on these joins then?
What questions do we have?
So we saw in lecture that
joins can be pretty slow.
Why is that the case?
Let's see, in general, joins don't
need to be any slower than subqueries.
What can seem slow off the bat is
when you have many joins all together,
because it takes a lot of work for
SQLite to go through and figure out,
how do these rows match up across
all these different tables.
It can speed up joins if you
have the right kinds of indexes.
In lecture, we saw this idea
of an index that speeds up
queries on a particular column.
So if you have the right
indexes, joins aren't necessarily
any slower than subqueries.
It just turns out in lecture, we
didn't have the right kinds of indexes
to make that particular query
very fast with those joins.
Can you join more than two tables?
You certainly can.
You can join as many tables to your
heart's content as you would like.
Just keep in mind performance as well.
And if you're doing
more than three or four,
I'd question why you're doing
that in the first place.
You need to, if you need to.
When joining tables, does order matter?
It can.
Very unlikely that it
would in particular.
If you have a particular
ordering, you want the rows in,
it might vary that order.
But that's why, at the
very end of your query,
you can use order by to set the
order you get those things back in.
And if you are feeling more
comfortable with these kinds of things,
I want to propose that you could learn
a bit more about how SQLite is doing
or learn more about what SQLite is doing
underneath the hood, by typing this.
Let's say, explain query plan.
Hit Enter.
And now I'll try joining again.
I'll say I want to select, lets go for
songs dot name, and artists dot name.
And then I'll join, or from
songs join artists on artists
dot ID equals songs dot artist ID.
So I'm basically telling SQLite, I
want you to join these two tables.
But the very first thing
I said is, explain to me
how you're going to do this.
Explain to me how you're going to
join these two tables together.
I'll hit semicolon Enter here.
And this tells me exactly how it is
planning to join these tables together.
If you want to, you can
learn more about this.
If you don't want to, totally OK.
But if you are feeling
more comfortable, you
could learn about what SQULite
is doing underneath the hood,
if that makes sense.
All right.
So let's finish up our Drake query here.
We said we would select the average
energy of songs that are by Drake.
So to finish this out, I could say
select average energy from songs.
And maybe I'll join, join,
the artists table on artist
dot ID equals songs dot artist ID.
And then I could say where the artist
or the name well, or the artist name,
artist dot name is Drake.
Like this.
Hit Enter.
Oh.
It's artist, isn't it?
OK.
So, case in point, it's
not artist, it's artists.
So I'll say select
average energy from songs.
Join.
And then where artists
dot name is Drake.
And we find that Drake's songs
have an average energy of 0.599.
All right.
Now our one final query
here before we wrap up.
This is going to ask us to
find all the names of songs
that feature other artists.
So notice how songs feature others will
include the word feet in the title.
So to figure out this one, we
should introduce this idea of like.
And like, as we saw in lecture
allows us to specify a pattern
to match in our text.
So I want to figure out if feet is
anywhere in some particular song title.
I can use like similar to where.
But it allows me to specify something
like, not just particularly equal to,
but matching some particular pattern.
So I will find the names of
songs to feature other artists.
I'll say select name from songs
and then where, let's say,
let's say where the name is not equal
to something, but is like some pattern.
And in this case, I could say
percent feet percent to say,
I want to match any name that
has feet somewhere in its name.
If I wanted to say feet only at the
end, I could omit this percent sign
and say percent feet.
If I wanted to find feet
at the very beginning,
I could say feet and then
percent at the end here.
Basically, this percent sign allows me
to say, you can match any characters,
any characters at all,
but make sure it has feet
somewhere in this particular title.
So I'll hit Enter here.
And I should see, I get back all
the names of songs that in this case
have feet in the title.
All right.
The questions then on
these past few queries.
A good question.
Is all the syntax and keywords common
to all of SQL software or do they only
work in SQLite?
So there are a few things
that only work in SQLite.
I don't know off the top of my head.
In general, SQLite is
very cross compatible.
So you could use the same
kinds of things in SQLite
that you would be able to use in
things like MySQL or PostgreSQL.
A question about, how
do you find the mode
of artists, such the top artists
that appears in the table?
We didn't see this here today.
We did see it briefly in lecture.
There's this idea of group by.
Let's say you want to figure out
how many times some artist appears
in the table.
Well, I could try to
find that out for you.
I could say, let's try
to find the artist name.
Well, how should I do this?
I want to find artists dot name.
And I also want to select the count
of times that artist dot name appears.
I want to select that from the
songs table, but joining let's say,
the artist table on artists dot
id equals songs dot artist id
And I want to in the end,
do what we call a group by.
So I'll group by artist dot name.
And what this will do for me is this.
So we saw earlier that this join
allows me to think of my two tables
as one table.
Basically I'm now able to see
songs and their artist names.
Once I have that, I want to select the
name column from the artists table.
And then I want to
select the count of times
that artist name appears in the table.
But in order to make this work, I
want to group by artist dot name.
So when I type count here,
I'm going to figure out
how many times does
each artist name appear,
and not just how many times this artist
name happened in general, if that makes
sense.
I'll hit Enter and see what I get.
I'll see here.
That seems to have worked.
Five Seconds of Summer appears one time.
Ed Sheeran appears three times.
And so on.
So if you want to learn
more about group by,
I'd encourage you to try to just
do a bit of googling around,
see some visualizations.
Or actually rewatch part of lecture
you can see David talk more about group
by too.
Let's see.
How would you find all the songs
that have a specific word for them?
You could use like for that.
So like is good for often trying
to match patterns of text.
And the question, so join
joins artists to songs.
It does.
In this case, we could specify,
we are starting with songs
and joining in artists.
And then question about
SQLite type of entities.
We use text here because you use
char or varchar instead of text.
So char and varchar are
particular to MySQL or Postgres.
They aren't part of SQLite in
this case, but good question.
All right, so I think what we'll do
is go ahead and wrap officially here.
We've gone through how
to design our databases,
how to solve particular songs problem,
and if any of this interested you,
I'd encourage you to
go ahead and check out
one of our very own
courses, Our Introduction
to Databases with SQL, which you can
find more about at this URL down here.
Let's take you into a
deep dive with databases
and designing your
very own final project,
focused on databases in particular.
So with that, we'll end
our week seven section.
And I hope to see you next time.