SPEAKER: In speller,
your task is going to be
to write a spell checker that can take
a text and take every word in that text
and check to see if the word
is spelled correctly or not
and, importantly, to do
so as quickly as possible.
How are you going to do that?
Well, let's first take a
look at the distribution code
that you'll be given in this problem.
We're going to give you
a file called speller.c,
which contains the code that
will do the spell checking
calling upon some functions that are
going to be declared in dictionary.h.
So if you open up dictionary.h,
you'll see the function prototypes
for five functions that you're
going to implement in this problem.
In dictionary.c is where you
are actually going to write
the implementations of these functions.
Makefile is going to
contain some commands that
will compile all our files
together into a finished program.
And then we've given you three
directories, or folders--
a dictionaries/ directory, which
will contain both a large and small
dictionary of words, a text/ directory
that will contain some sample files,
so you can run your
spell checker against,
and we'll give you a keys/ directory,
which will contain the solutions,
the list of words that are misspelled
in each of the sample texts that we
provide to you.
So let's take a closer
look at dictionary.c
because dictionary.c is the file that
you'll have to edit in this problem
in order to make this
spell checker work.
What are the five functions that you'll
need to implement in dictionary.c?
Well, the first is called load,
which is responsible for loading
all of the words in the dictionary
into some sort of data structure,
like a hash table.
Next up is a function called hash,
which is going to take a word
and run a hash function on
it, returning some number that
corresponds to that word.
Next up is size, which
is just going to return
how many words are in your dictionary.
Next is check, which will take a
word and answer the question of,
is this word in the dictionary or not?
In other words, is it
correctly spelled or not?
And finally, we'll be unload,
where any of the memory that you've
had to allocate in order to store
data inside of your data structure,
you'll now need to free up
and give back to the computer.
So these are the five steps for speller.
And we'll take a look at each of them
one at a time so that by the end of it,
you'll have a working spell checker.