BRIAN: In substitution,
your task is going
to be to implement a substitution
cipher where you'll encrypt or encipher
some plain text by taking every
alphabetic character in that plain text
and replacing it with another character.
What might that actually look like?
Well, let's take a look at a sample key.
Here, we have the plain
text letters of the alphabet
from A all the way through Z.
And in a substitution cipher,
we're going to replace each
of those plain text characters
with a cipher text character.
For example, here is a mapping
that maps the plain text character
A to the letter J, maps the letter
B to T, maps the letter C to R,
so on and so forth.
How do we actually use
this inside of a cipher?
Well, if the plain text is the word
hello, then using this substitution
cipher, we would end up with the cipher
text VKXXN because H in plain text maps
to V in the cipher text.
E maps to K both of the Ls map
to the letter X. And of course,
O maps to the letter N, which gives
us that resulting cipher text.
Your task is going to be to write a
program in C that is going to implement
such a substitution cipher.
How does the program work?
Well, you'll run the program by
calling dot slash substitution followed
by a 26-character-long key that's
going to describe how you're
going to map each of the
alphabetic characters
into other alphabetic characters where
here, the first character is what
we map A to, the second character is
what we might B to, so on and so forth.
Your program should then prompt the
user to type in some plain text.
And if the user types
in ABC, for example,
then your program should
output cipher text
followed by the enciphered version of
that plain text-- in this case, J, T,
and then R. So if we were to
call that same substitution
cipher passing in hello as the plain
text, then the output is VKXXN.
Of course, your program should be able
to support plain text that isn't just
uppercase characters.
So if we were to instead call dot slash
substitution followed by the same key
and the plain text were hello
in all lowercase letters,
then the output should still be vkxxn
but the characters should be lowercase.
The case of the plain
text should be preserved.
And if our plain text was a little
more complicated, for example,
if we called dot slash
substitution on the same key
but this time the plain
text were this is CS50,
then this is what the
cipher text would look like.
Notice in particular
that the characters that
were originally uppercase
in the plain text
are still uppercase in the cipher
text, and the characters that
were originally lowercase
in the plain text
are still lowercase in the cipher text.
Any character that isn't
a letter, like the space
or the digits or the punctuation,
those haven't been changed at all.
And they're the same in both the
plain text and the cipher text.
In addition, the key that your program
takes as a command line argument
should be case insensitive.
Here, for example, the key
is all uppercase letters.
But the program should
behave exactly the same
if, for example, the key
were all lowercase letters
or if there was a mix of uppercase and
lowercase letters inside of the key.
However, not every key that's
provided as a command line argument
is necessarily going to be
a valid substitution cipher.
So there's some additional
work you'll need
to do in order to validate the key
to make sure it is indeed valid.
For example, if a user were
to call dot slash substitution
but not provide a key at
all, then your program
should remind the user of how to
use the program by calling dot slash
substitution followed by a key.
What else might count as an invalid key?
Well, if a user were to call dot slash
substitution and provide a key that's
fewer than 26 characters,
then we're not going
to know how to map every
single alphabetic character
to another character.
So in this case, your program,
rather than prompting the user
to type in any plain text
should instead report
that the key must contain
26 characters and then
return with a status code
of one to indicate an error.
What else might be
considered an invalid key?
Well, if the user were to run dot
slash substitution and then provide
this key, which is 26 characters
but the last character
is the number two instead
of an alphabetic character,
this key is not valid because
in a valid substitution cipher,
every letter should be
substituted for another letter.
So if any character in the key that
is provided as a command line argument
is not an alphabetic
character, then your program
should report that error,
reporting to the user
that the key must only
contain alphabetic characters
and then returning one,
for example, to indicate
that there was, in fact, an error.
And finally, if the user were to run
dot slash substitution and then provide
this key, where notice that
the first character of the key
is the letter J and the last character
of the key is also the letter J,
this too is not a valid substitution.
And your program should
report to the user
that the key should not
contain repeated characters,
and your program should, again,
exit with a return code of one.
So in summary what do you
need to do in this problem?
Well, you'll first need to get the key.
Then you'll need to validate
the key to make sure
that it's a valid substitution.
Then you'll need to prompt the
user to type in some plain text.
Then you'll need to encipher that
plain text using your substitution key.
And then finally, you'll need
to print out that cipher text.
How are you going to get the key?
Well, recall that the key is going to
be provided as a command line argument.
The user is going to run your program by
running dot slash substitution followed
by the key.
How do you extract that
command line argument?
Well, you can structure your
main function as something
like this, taking two
arguments, one of which
is an int argc representing the
number of command line arguments,
and one of which is an array of strings,
argv, representing all of the command
line arguments that were provided.
Once you've collected the
command line arguments,
the next step is going to be validating
the key to make sure that it's valid.
And here, you should
check the key length
to make sure that it is,
in fact, 26 characters.
You should also check to make sure that
there are no non-alphabetic characters
inside of the key, and you should
also check for repeated characters
because every letter of the alphabet
should appear once and only once
in the key, regardless of whether
it's uppercase or lowercase.
After you've validated
the key, then you can
start to prompt the user to type in
some input by asking for plain text.
Here, you can use the
function get_string,
declared in the CS50 library,
as a way of getting input
from the user as a string.
After you've gotten the string,
then you can encipher the text
where for each alphabetic
character you'll need to determine,
based on the substitution cipher that
you've collected as a command line
argument input, what character
should this alphabetic character
map to, making sure to preserve case
so that uppercase characters stay
uppercase and lowercase
characters stay lowercase.
If there are any non-alphabetic
characters like spaces or punctuation
or numbers, those
characters should be left
as is and unchanged between the
plain text and the cipher text.
Finally, after all of
that, you should be
able to print out the
cipher text to the user
so that they see the enciphered
version of their original message.
You can test your code by running
dot slash substitution followed
by a valid 26-character substitution
key, then typing in some plain text
and making sure the cipher text
is the result of substituting
all of the alphabetic
characters for the characters
that are mapped to by the key.
My name is Brian, and
this was substitution.