BRIAN YU: In filter, your task
is going to be to take an image
and apply a number of different image
filtering algorithms to that image.
What sort of filters could
you apply to this image?
Well, you'll, first, create a grayscale
filter that will take this image
and convert it to black and white.
Next, you'll implement a reflection
filter that will take an image
and get the mirror image or the
reflection of that image instead.
Next, you'll implement a blur
filter that will take an image
and soften it a little bit, so the
edges are a little bit less sharp.
And finally, you'll implement
an edge-detection filter
that will take an image
and highlight where
all the boundaries between
objects are inside of that image.
So these are the four parts of
the filter assignment-- grayscale,
reflect, blur, and then finally, edges.
But how do you go about applying
filters to images at all?
Well, every image,
remember, is just a sequence
of individual pixels arranged
into a particular grid.
And how do we represent a pixel?
Well, on a computer screen,
every pixel has three values,
which we might call channels--
a red channel, a green channel, and
a blue channel where those values
range from 0, meaning none,
to 255, meaning the maximum.
If we set the red
value to a small value,
you'll see that we have a
little bit of red in the pixel.
A higher red value means
more red in the pixel.
And 255 means we have as much red as we
possibly can in this particular pixel.
We set it back to 0, and the
pixel goes back to black.
Why is it that each channel
value goes from 0 to 255?
Well, 0, represented in binary,
is just 0, as you might imagine.
And 255 represented in
binary is eight 1's,
which means that for each color value,
we can use one byte or eight bits
for each color-- red, green, and blue.
And since we have three of those, we
can use 3 bytes or 24 bits per pixel.
So if you've ever heard
the term 24-bit color,
that's what this is referring to.
So we can use the red channel to
control how much red is in this pixel.
We can use the green channel to
control how much green is in the pixel.
And we can use the blue channel to
control how much blue is in the pixel.
But, of course, we don't need to just
use one of the channels at a time.
We can use them in combination to
create any number of different colors.
If we have a lot of red
and a little bit of blue,
we have a color that looks a
little something like this.
And if we have a lot of green and a lot
of blue but just a little bit of red,
then we get a turquoise color that
looks a little something like this.
And if we set each of the
channel values of red, green,
and blue to the maximum value
of 255, well, that pixel
is just going to be a pure white pixel.
If we take enough of these pixels,
set them to the right color value,
and arrange them in
the appropriate order,
the result is that we can
actually see an image that
looks like something by arranging
colors in the correct position.
So what files do you actually
need to work with in this problem?
Well, there's bmp.h, which is going to
store information about bitmap images.
It's going to store some
of the structs that you're
going to need to deal with in
order to complete this assignment.
We've also given you filter.c,
which is the program you'll
run to actually run these
filters, which is going
to take care of the logic of
reading the file from memory,
calling a function to apply a filter,
and then writing the new image to disk
as a brand new file.
Helpers.c is the file
that actually contains
all of the functions that
are going to implement each
of the filters for this assignment.
Helpers.h is the header
file that's going
to declare all of the functions that
show up in helpers.c, telling you
what the return type of
the function is and what
all of the types of the
arguments to the functions are.
Finally, we've given you a
Makefile, which when you run make
is going to take all of these
files and combine them together
into an executable that you can run to
actually apply these filters to images
of your very own.
We've completed all of the
files except for helpers.c,
and that's where you come.
In.
So how are you actually going to write
the code to implement these filters?
Well, in bmp.h, we've
defined a struct for you
called RGBTRIPLE, which is
going to represent a pixel that
has a red, green, and blue value.
You'll notice that this
struct has three fields,
a field called rgbtBlue representing
the amount of blue in the triple,
a field called rgbtGreen
representing the amount of green,
and a field called rgbtRed
representing the amount of red.
Each field stores a byte
worth of information,
remembering that a byte
is really just 8 bits.
Your task is going to be to implement
the four functions in helpers.c--
grayscale, reflect, blur, and edges.
Each of these functions
takes three arguments,
an integer called height,
an integer called width,
and a two-dimensional
array of RGBTRIPLES,
a 2D array of pixels where there
are height rows and width columns.
So your image might
look a little something
like this, a two-dimensional array
which has a particular height, which
will be an argument to your function,
and it has a particular width,
which will also be an argument.
So if we have an image, which
is a two-dimensional array,
image 0 is going to represent
the first row of that image.
Image 1 represents the second row.
Image 2 represents the third
row so on and so forth.
How, for example, would you
get the last row in the image?
Well, if there are height
many rows in the image
and we start counting from row
0, then the last row in the image
is going to be image height
minus for 1, for example.
So that's how you get
a row of the image.
But how do you get it at a very
particular pixel in that image?
Well, image 0 is a row of the image,
which itself is just an array.
So if image 0 is the
first row of the image,
image 0 0 is going to be the
first pixel in that first row.
Image 0 1 is the second
pixel in the row.
Image 0 2 is the third pixel
in the row so on and so forth.
And we can use this notation to
access any pixel in the image.
Image 2 3, for example,
is the pixel in row 2
and column 3 of this particular image.
So if we have a pixel,
how do we actually
modify the pixel to
change its color values?
Well, recall that every pixel is
really just a struct that has values
rgbtRed, rgbtGreen, and rgbtBlue.
So to access the
properties of a struct, we
can use dot notation
using image 2 3.rgbtRed
to set the red value of the
pixel equal to something
and doing the same for the green
and the blue values, for example.
If we set the red, green,
and blue values all to 0,
then we're going to
turn this pixel black
because black is the color
represented by values of 0
for each of red, green, and blue.
Your task in each of
these functions is going
to be to take the image as input,
as this two-dimensional array
and modify the two-dimensional array
changing the individual pixels in order
to create the effect that you would
get by applying one of these filters.