INSTRUCTOR: The next filter that
you'll implement is called blur.
In blur, your task is going
to be to take an image
and blur it by creating a softer,
less sharp version of the same image.
Let's zoom in to this image a little bit
to see what this actually looks like.
Notice that if this
is the original image,
this is what the blurred
image looks like.
Notice that the details
are a little bit softer,
and it's a bit tougher to make out.
So what does that algorithm
actually look like?
How do we take an image
and blur it, so to speak?
Well, let's look at this
image, a simple 6-by-6 image
where we have red and blue.
And what would it look like
if we were to blur the image?
Well, the blurred image
might look a little something
like this, where the
details are a bit softer,
and you can't quite make out the
lines as crisply or as sharply
as you could before.
You can look at them side by side here.
On the left is the original
image, and on the right
is the blurred version
of the same image.
You'll notice that the pixels have
changed their color values slightly.
The pixels that were originally just
pure red now look a little more blue,
and the pixels that were originally
blue now look a little more red.
So how do we actually do this?
Well, the type of blur we're going
to do is what's called a box blur.
And to implement a box blur, we're going
to compute the new value for a pixel
by taking the average of the old
color values of all of the nine pixels
that form a grid around
that original pixel--
in other words, all of the
pixels that are within one row
and one column of the original pixel.
What does that mean
for an image like this?
Well, if we take this
pixel, for example,
and we want to compute its new
color value in the blurred image,
we're going to do that by looking at
the original color values of these nine
pixels, the pixels that are within
one row and one column of that pixel.
Likewise, to determine the
blurred version of this pixel,
we're going to take the average of the
original color values of these nine
pixels.
Of course, not every pixel
in our image has nine pixels
that form a 3-by-3 grid around it.
Let's consider an edge case,
for example, like this pixel.
What happens now?
Well, instead of averaging nine
pixels to get the new color
value for this pixel,
we're instead going
to average these six color
values because these six
pixels are the only ones within one row
and one column of that original pixel.
And likewise, if we look at
this pixel down in the corner,
we're going to compute its new value
by taking the average of these four
pixels, the only pixels that
are within one row and one
column of this particular pixel.
So let's take a look at an example in
a little more detail by calculating
the new value for this pixel if we
were to try and blur this image.
In order to do so, we need to
look not just at this pixel,
but in all of the pixels within
one row and one column of it, which
would be this grid of nine pixels.
Let's take a look at
them in more detail.
Notice that the blue pixels
have a blue value of 255,
and our red and green value of 0.
And the red pixels, of which there are
five of them, have a red value of 255
and a green and blue value of 0.
So what are we going to do to
filter the pixel in the middle here?
Well, what we're going to do is
calculate the average amount of red,
the average amount of green,
and the average amount of blue.
The average amount of red across
all nine of these pixels is 142.
Five of the pixels have the maximum
amount of red, and four of them
have no red.
As for green, none of these
pixels have any green at all,
so the average amount of green is 0,
and the average amount of blue is 113--
again, all of these rounded
to the nearest integer.
So what that means is that the blurred
version for this new middle pixel
is going to be based on the average
of the original color values
for all nine of these
pixels, which means
it's going to now have a red
value of 142, a green value of 0,
and a blue value of 113.
If we do that same process for each
of the pixels in the original image,
determining the new color values
for each of red, green, and blue
by taking the average of the original
color values for all of the pixels
that are within one row and
one column of that pixel,
the end result is an image that
looks like this, a blurred version
of that original image.
And once you've done that
for every pixel in the image,
you can test this by running ./filter,
passing in -b to specify that you want
to run the blur filter, then specifying
the input file that you'd like to use
as a source, and of
course, the output file.
Once you've done that, you should
be able to take the original image
and create a blurred
version of the same thing.
My name is Brian, and this was blur.