SPEAKER 1: Let's dive into filter.
In filter, your task is going
to be to take a bitmap image
and apply some number of
different filters to that image.
You'll apply a filter to take an
image and convert it into grayscale,
making it black and white.
You'll take the image and
apply a filter to turn it
into sepia, giving everything a
reddish brown, old time feel to it.
You'll take the image and
reflect it, getting the mirror
image of the original picture.
And finally, you'll apply a blur
filter that will take the image
and soften it so the details
are a little bit less clear.
So these are the four
parts of this project.
Grayscale, sepia, reflect, and blur.
But how do you go about applying
filters to images at all?
Well, every image,
remember, is just a sequence
of individual pixels arranged
into a particular grid.
And how do we represent a pixel?
Well, on a computer screen,
every pixel has three values,
which we might call channels.
A red channel, a green
channel, and a blue channel,
where those values range from 0--
meaning none-- to 255--
meaning the maximum.
If we set the red
value to a small value,
you'll see that we have a
little bit of red in the pixel.
A higher red value means
more red in the pixel.
And 255 means we have as much red as we
possibly can in this particular pixel.
We set it back to 0, and the
pixel goes back to black.
Why is it that each channel
value goes from 0 to 255?
Well, 0 represented in binary
is just 0, as you might imagine.
And 255 represented
in binary is eight 1s,
which means that for each color
value, we can use one byte or 8 bits
for each color-- red, green, and blue.
And since we have three of those, we can
use three bytes or 24 bits per pixel.
So if you've ever heard
the term 24-bit color,
that's what this is referring to.
So we can use the red channel to
control how much red is in this pixel.
We can use the green channel to
control how much green is in the pixel.
And we can use the blue channel to
control how much blue is in the pixel.
But of course, we don't need to just
use one of the channels at a time.
We can use them in combination to
create any number of different colors.
If we have a lot of red
and a little bit of blue,
we have a color that looks a
little something like this.
And if we have a lot of green and a lot
of blue but just a little bit of red,
then we get a turquoise color that
looks a little something like this.
And if we set each of the
channel values of red, green,
and blue to the maximum value
of 255, well, that pixel
is just going to be a pure white pixel.
If we take enough of these pixels,
set them to the right color value,
and arrange them in
the appropriate order,
the result is that we can
actually see an image that
looks like something by arranging
colors in the correct position.
So what files do you actually
need to work with in this problem?
Well, there's bmp.h, which is going to
store information about bitmap images.
It's going to store some
of the structs that you're
going to need to deal with in
order to complete this assignment.
We've also given you filter.c,
which is the program you'll
run to actually run these
filters, which is going
to take care of the logic of
reading the file from memory,
calling a function to apply a filter,
and then writing the new image to disk
as a brand new file.
Helpers.c is the file
that actually contains
all of the functions that
are going to implement
each of the filters for this
assignment-- blur, reflection, sepia,
grayscale.
Helpers.h is the header
file that's going
to declare all of the functions that
show up in helpers.c, telling you
what the return type of
the function is and what
all of the types of the
arguments for the functions are.
Finally, we've given you a
makefile, which when you run make
is going to take all of these
files and combine them together
into an executable that you can run to
actually apply these filters to images
of your very own.
We've completed all of the
files except for helpers.c,
and that's where you come in.
So how are you actually going to write
the code to implement these filters?
Well, in bmp.h, we've
defined a struct for you
called RGBTRIPLE, which is
going to represent a pixel that
has a red, green, and blue value.
You'll notice that this
struct has three fields.
A field called rgbtBlue representing
the amount of blue in the triple,
a field called rgbtGreen
representing the amount of green,
and a field called rgbtRed
representing the amount of red.
Each field stores a byte worth
of information-- remembering
that a byte is really just 8 bits.
Your task is going to be to implement
the four functions in helpers.c;
grayscale, sepia, reflect, and blur.
Each of these functions
takes three arguments.
An integer called height, an integer
called width, and a two dimensional
array of RGBTRIPLES--
a 2D array of pixels where there
are height rows and width columns.
So your image might look a
little something like this.
A two dimensional array which
has a particular height, which
will be an argument to your function,
and has a particular width, which
will also be an argument.
So if we have an image which
is a two dimensional array,
image[0] is going to represent
the first row of that image.
Image[1] represents the second row.
Image[2] represents the third row.
So on and so forth.
How, for example would you
get the last row in the image?
Well, if there are height many rows in
the image and we start counting from
row 0, then the last row in the
image is going to be image[height-1],
for example.
So that's how you get
a row of the image.
But how do you get at a very
particular pixel in that image?
Well, image[0] is a row of the
image, which itself is just an array.
So if image[0] is the
first row of the image,
image[0][0] is going to be the
first pixel in that first row.
Image[0][1] is the
second pixel in the row.
Image[0][2] is the
third pixel in the row.
So on and so forth.
And we can use this notation to
access any pixel in the image.
Image[2][3], for example, is the
pixel in row 2 and column 3 of this
particular image.
So if we have a pixel,
how do we actually
modify the pixel to
change its color values?
Well, recall that every pixel is
really just a struct that has values
rgbtRed, rgbtGreen, and rgbtBlue.
So to access the properties of a
struct, we can use dot notation.
Using image[2][3].rgbtRed to set the red
value of the pixel equal to something.
And doing the same for the green
and the blue values, for example.
If we set the red, green,
and blue values all to 0,
then we're going to
turn this pixel black
because black is the color
represented by values of 0
for each of red, green, and blue.
Your task in each of these functions--
grayscale, sepia, reflect, and blur--
is going to be to take the image as
input, as this two dimensional array,
and modify the two dimensional array,
changing the individual pixels in order
to create the effect that you would
get by applying one of these filters.