SPEAKER 1: In this
problem, your task is going
to be to design a web
application that allows
users to manage a portfolio of stocks.
In order to do so,
you'll need to implement
a variety of different features.
First, you'll need to make sure that
every user can register for an account.
Once they register
for an account, a user
should have the ability
to look up a stock quote,
buy a stock if they want
to, see an index page that
shows them all of the stocks
the current user is bought,
then the user should be able to sell any
of the stocks that they currently own,
and see a history of all
of their transactions.
And finally, once you've
implemented all of these features,
you'll implement a personal touch of
your very own to add to this website
application.
But before we dive into the features
that you're going to implement,
let's start by taking a look at
the distribution code that will
provide to you as a starting point.
For this problem, the
distribution code for this problem
comes in a number of different parts.
We'll give you a few Python files,
app.py, and helpers.py, in addition to
a SQLite database called finance.db.
In addition, we'll also give you
a folder filled with templates.
And we'll walk through each of
these parts of the distribution code
one file at a time.
Let's start with app.py, which is where
you'll write most of your Python code
for this web application.
App.py defines a Flask web
application, and also defines
a variable called db, which will allow
you to connect to a SQL database.
In particular, you can use
the function db.execute
to execute a SQL statement
on your SQL database.
Later in app.py, you'll
also see definitions
for each of the routes inside
of your web application.
Each of which will start
with the syntax @app.route.
These routes can take a variety
of different request methods.
Most notably for getting the
contents of a page and post
generally used if you're submitting
data to a particular route.
There are some routes that
have already been implemented
for you, such as log in and log out.
And let's now take an opportunity to
look at one of these routes, the login
route, just to get a sense
for how routes in Flask
this web framework actually work.
So here is the login
route, and it begins
with this syntax, @app.route
with slash login being the route
that users can use to access this
part of your web application.
This particular route accepts two
different methods, GET and POST.
And it's associated with
this function called login.
Because the login route accepts
to request methods, GET and POST,
and we need to make different
decisions based on that request method,
one of the first things we'll need to
do is check what the request method is.
If the request method is POST,
that means the user has just
submitted the login form.
And if the user has just
submitted the login form,
then we'll need to access whatever
data the user typed into that form.
In order to do that, we can use this
syntax here, reques.form.getusername,
to get whatever the current username is
that the user typed in into that form.
And if the user didn't
provide a username,
well then we should render an apology.
An error message to the
user to let them know
that they need to provide a username.
Likewise, just as we make sure that
the user has typed in a username,
we also need to make sure that
the user has typed in a password.
And if the user didn't
type in a password,
then we should render
an apology as well.
After that, once we're
sure that the user has
typed in both a username
and a password, we
need to now look them up inside
of our finance.db database
to make sure that this is a valid
username and password combination.
So we'll use db.execute to run a
select query on our existing database,
and do a SELECT to try and find the
user whose username is equal to whatever
it is the user typed in into the form.
We won't know what the user
name is until the user actually
types in their username and clicks
the button to submit the form.
And so here, we're
using a question mark,
where the question mark is acting as a
placeholder for whatever the user typed
into the form, which
again, we can access
via this syntax, request.form.get.
Whenever we run the execute
function on a select query running
on our database, what we'll get
back is a list of all of the rows
that matched our SELECT query.
So the next thing we should do is
check to make sure that what we got
back is exactly one row
representing that particular user,
and we should check to make sure
that their password was correct.
If either of those isn't true, if
the user is not in the database,
or they typed in their
password wrong, well then
we should return an error back to
the user using that apology function
to let the user know that this was
an invalid username and password
combination.
And if we made it
through all of that, that
means the user has typed in
a username and a password,
and we verified that this is a
valid username password combination.
And if that's the case, then
the next thing we should do
is actually log the user in.
How do we do that,
we'll recall that we can
use the session variable to keep track
of information about the current user.
So we'll store inside of session
bracket user ID, the current user's ID
that we got from the database.
And after we've signed
the user in, we'll
go ahead and redirect the
user back to the home page.
So that they can now go
ahead and look up stocks
buy stocks or sell stocks
if they would like to.
And finally, at the very
end of the function,
we need to take care of
the other request method.
All of that code we just took a look
at was if the request method was POST.
The user actually
submitted the login form.
But if instead the
request method is GET,
that means the user just clicked on
a button to access the login form.
And in order to do
that, what we'll do is
return a template back to
the user rendering the login
form so the user can go ahead and
type in their username and password.
In addition to app.py,
we also provide you
with helpers.py, which is a Python file
that contains some useful functions
that you might take
advantage of as you're
building the various features
of this web application.
We'll give you a function
called apology that
displays an error message to the user.
Login required can be used
above any of your functions
to require that a user log in before
they're able to access a given route.
For example, you might want to make sure
that a user is logged in before they're
able to buy or sell stocks.
The lookup function, meanwhile, uses
a stocks API to get the current stock
quote for a particular stock symbol.
So you can look up a
stock buy it's symbol
and figure out what the current
quote for that stock is.
And finally, we give you a function
called USD that takes a number
and formats it as US dollars.
With a dollar sign, some number of
dollars, and some number of cents.
Next in the distribution
code is finance.db
and this is the SQLite database that is
going to store all of the application
data for your web application.
So far in financ.db will
give you a user's table.
And inside of this user's
table, you'll find columns
for keeping track of each
user's ID, their username,
a hash of their password, and
how much cash that user has.
But you'll likely need to add
new tables into this database
to finish implementing all of the
features of the web application.
And you can do that using the
CREATE TABLE syntax in SQL.
Finally, in this
distribution code, we also
give you a folder of templates
that contains HTML templates that
can be rendered to the user depending
on what part of the web application
they're trying to access.
There's a file inside of your
templates folder called layout.HTML
that defines the general HTML
structure for all of your pages,
and then the rest of your
HTML pages can use the syntax
to extend layout.HTML to
use that existing layout
and add to it a title for the page
and the main body content of each
of your other HTML pages.
Now that we've taken a look
at the distribution code that
will provide to you for this
problem, let's now turn our attention
to each of the different
features that you'll
need to implement to make this
web application fully functional.
The first thing you'll
need to do is make sure
that each user has the ability to
register for your finance application.
In order to do that, your register route
should accept two different request
methods, GET and POST.
If the user tries to access the register
route using the GET request method,
then you should just
display a form to the user.
So that they can register
for a new account.
Once the user submits that form,
accessing your register route
via the POST request method, what you
should do is check for possible errors.
And if there are no errors, then you
can insert the new user into the user's
table and log the user in after that.
So let's start with
that registration form.
How will you display a
registration form to the user?
Well in order to do
that, you'll likely need
to create a new template that contains
the HTML for that registration form.
And recall that you can find
all of your templates inside
of that templates folder
in your finance directory.
You can use the login.HTML
template that we've already
provided to you as inspiration for
what this new template might look like.
And remember, the HTML
form that you create
should contain input fields that
allow the user to choose a username,
choose a password, and then verify that
they typed in their password correctly.
Once the user types in information
into that registration form
and submits it to your
website application,
your Python code is going to need to
access whatever it is the user typed
in to that registration form.
In order to do that, you can
use some syntax like this.
If you have an input field
inside of your HTML code
with an attribute that says name
equals password, for example.
Well then inside of
your Flask application,
inside of your Python code,
you can use this syntax here,
request.form.get, and then the name
of that input field, in this case,
password.
And that will allow
you to access whatever
it is the user typed
into the form, and then
submitted via the POST request method.
You can do that for the
password, for the confirmation,
and for the user's username as well.
Inside of your route, you'll also
want to check for possible errors.
What might go wrong when the user is
trying to register for a new account
Well, if any field is left blank, if
the user didn't type in a username,
didn't provide a password, or
didn't confirm their password,
you should return an apology, letting
the user know that each of those fields
was required.
If the two passwords don't
match with each other,
you should also let the
user know that as well.
And finally, if the user name is
already taken by some other user
already inside of your database,
you should apologize to the user
and let them know about that as well.
Once you've confirmed that there are
no errors with what the user provided
to you, you'll want to add the user
to the user's table of your database,
but you should keep security
in mind as you do so.
In particular, remember the databases
should never store plaintext passwords.
Instead, you should
first generate a hash
of the user's password using
the Generate password hash
function provided to you.
And then store the hash of the
password inside of the database instead
of the plaintext password itself.
Once you've generated
a hash of the password,
then you can add all of this
information into the database
by using db.execute in order
to run an insert statement
to add a new row into the user's table.
And remember again, you can
use the question mark symbol
to stand in as a placeholder for a value
that you might not know yet at the time
that you're writing this code.
Once the user has been
added into the user's table,
then you can log the user in.
Setting session, bracket user ID,
equal to the new ID for whatever user
you've just added to the database.
Once the user has been able
to register for an account,
next, you'll want to allow the
user to look up stock quotes.
In your quote route, you should
also accept to request methods,
GET and POST.
If a user tries to access
your quote route via GET,
you should display a form that lets
the user request a stock that they
would like to look up.
And when the form is submitted
via POST, then your application
should look up that stock symbol
by calling the lookup function
and display the results
back to the user.
How does the lookup function work?
Will recall that lookup
is a function that we have
defined for you inside of helper.py.
And it takes a stock symbol
and returns a stock quote.
If lookup was able to successfully
look up the stock quote,
then the function is going to
return a dictionary back to you
with fields to represent the name of
the stock, the symbol for that stock,
and what the stock's current price is.
But it's also possible that the
lookup will not be successful.
If for example, the user tries to type
in a stock symbol that doesn't exist.
In that case, you
should return an apology
to the user letting them know that
particular stock symbol doesn't exist.
But if the lookup is
successful, what you'll
want to do is display an HTML page
to the user that contains information
about the stock, the name
of the stock, and what
the current price of that stock is.
In order to do so, you'll need to pass
in values into your HTML template.
And how might you do that?
Well, in your Python code, you can
use the render template function
to render an HTML
template, but you can also
provide variables into this template
that's known as a jinja template.
For example, in this code
here, I'm rendering Hello.HTML,
but giving this template
access to a variable
called name, which in this
case is equal to Brian.
And then inside of my jinja template,
I can use double curly braces
around the variable name.
In this case, name, in
order to display whatever
was passed in from the render template
function here inside of my HTML.
Likewise, you could do something
like this as well in order
to display the current price of whatever
stock the user has just looked up.
In addition to allowing users
to look up a stock quote,
we also want to allow
users to buy a new stock.
In order to do that, your buyer out
will also accept to request methods GET,
and POST.
Where when the user gets
this page they should
be shown a form that allows
the user to buy a stock.
And when the user submits that form,
you should purchase the stock as long
as the user can actually afford it.
Your HTML form should allow the
user to type in what stock symbol
they would like to buy, in addition to
how many shares they would like to buy.
Once the user submits the form, you'll
want to check it for valid input.
For example, a user shouldn't be allowed
to by a negative number of shares.
And you'll also want to make sure that
the stock symbol is actually valid.
But before you can add this
data into your database,
you'll likely need to create
one or more new tables
to keep track of this new information.
Right now the finance.db
database we provide
to you includes a table
for keeping track of users
and how much cash they
have but doesn't include
any tables for keeping track of
what stocks each of those users
actually owns.
So you'll first want to give some
thought as to what new tables
you'll want to add to
this database, and what
fields that table or tables will have.
You can use the CREATE TABLE statement
to add a new table to the database,
and you'll want to be sure to use
appropriate SQL types as you do so.
There are multiple correct
ways to implement this.
So decide for yourself what
kind of database design
makes the most sense to you and is
most logical for this particular web
application.
Once you're happy with the
tables inside of your database,
you'll want to add this new stock
purchase to the user's portfolio.
First, remember that you'll need to
make sure the user has enough cash
to afford the stock.
If the user can't afford the
number of shares of the stock
that they're trying to purchase,
you should return an apology
to the user letting them
know that they don't
have enough cash for this purchase.
But assuming the user does have
enough cash for the purchase,
you should run whatever SQL
statement you need on your database
to purchase that stock, and also be sure
to update that user's cash to reflect
the purchase that they've just made.
Once you've implemented
this feature, users
should be able to log into your
web application and buy new stocks.
But once users have bought those
new stocks it would be nice
if there was a place where users
could view all of the stocks
they've already bought, and that's
what you'll do in this next feature.
The index page of your application
should display an HTML table
with all of the information
about all of the stocks
that the current user owns,
how many shares of each stock
the user owns, the current
price of each of those stocks,
as well as the total value
for each of those holdings.
For example, if the user has
multiple of a certain stock,
their total value for
that stock will be higher.
You should also display the user
current cash balance on this page,
as well as their grand
total of the combination
of the value of all of
their stocks and whatever
cash they happen to have on hand.
As you create this HTML table,
you'll realize that there's
some HTML that you're going to repeat.
For example, you might
have one row for one stock,
and a very similar
row for another stock.
And again and again for each of the
stocks that the user currently owns.
In order to render
this as HTML, it might
be nice to have some
kind of a loop where
you're looping over all of the stocks,
adding 1 row of the table for each
of the stocks the user currently owns.
And it turns out we can use loops
like this inside of a jinja template.
In this example, we return
render template Hello.HTML,
and then also pass into that HTML
template a list of Python dictionaries.
Then inside of our jinja
template we're able to loop over
each one of those dictionaries
for contact in contacts
and then use dot notation
inside of the template to access
any of the fields of that dictionary.
Dot name or dot house, in
this particular example.
And you might imagine doing something
similar in your own index page.
First, using the database
and the lookup function
to look up all of the information
you need about the stocks
that the current user has, and
then looping over all of them
inside of your HTML template displaying
one row of a table for each stock
that the user currently owns.
Users now have the
ability to buy new stocks
and see an index of all of
the stocks they currently own.
So next, let's give users
the ability to sell a stock.
When the user tries to request
your cell route via GET,
you should display a form that allows
the user to choose which of the stocks
they currently own that
they would like to sell,
and how many shares of that
stock they would like to sell.
And when the user submits
that form via POST,
you should check for
possible errors, and then
sell the specified number
of shares of that stock,
and update the user's cash
balance to reflect that sale.
What kind of errors might come up?
Well for example, you want to
make sure that the user actually
has the number of shares of
stock they're trying to sell,
and you want to make sure that the user
can't sell a negative number of shares.
With all of these features,
users now have the ability
to buy and sell stocks.
But let's now give
users the ability to see
a history of all of their previous
transactions on your application.
When the user accesses
the history route,
you should display to
the user in HTML table
with all of their previous
transactions, with one row for every buy
or sell including information about
what stock was bought or sold,
how many shares of that
stock were bought or sold,
and when that transaction
actually took place.
How you implement the history
functionality in your web application
will depend on how you've designed
your database, what tables there are,
and what columns each table has.
And it's possible that you
might need to revisit and revise
your existing database structure to
allow for this new history feature.
Once you've implemented all of those
features, the last thing you'll do
is add a personal touch to
your website application
by deciding a new feature of your
own that you'd like to implement
and adding it to CS 50 finance.
For example, you might allow
users to change their password,
or you might allow users to add new cash
into their account,m or you can choose
something else entirely.
Deciding on a feature you would like
for this web application to have
and designing new route,
templates, or tables as
needed to make that
functionality possible.
Once you've completed that you'll
have a fully functional web
application, allowing users to
register, sign into their account,
buy and sell stocks, and see a
history of all of their transactions.
My name is Brian, and
this was CS 50 finance.