[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right, this is CS50.
And this is week 3.
And as promised, we thought we'd take a
bit of a break on new syntax this week
and focus a lot more on
algorithms and implementation
thereof because over the past few
weeks, besides Scratch, we've now had C.
And you have a lot of vocabulary now.
Even if it might not
seem yet that you fully
grasp all of the functionality of this
particular language, with practice,
it'll get easier and easier.
But today, we'd focus instead
on ideas and ultimately on this,
how to think algorithmically, and so
to take problems in the real world
and try to quantize them in a
way that you can map those puzzle
pieces from week 0 or all of this
new syntax from weeks 1 and 2
on to actually writing code
to solve those problems.
To contextualize this,
though, we thought
we'd remind you of this
here chart from week zero.
And recall that in week zero,
we painted this picture where
on the x-axis on the horizontal
was the size of the problem.
And the number of phone
book pages increased
as you went from left to right.
And then on the vertical axis
or y-axis, we had time to solve.
So this was like how many
seconds, how many page turns,
how many units of measure--
whatever you're using.
We might actually describe
the solution there too.
And the first algorithm we had
in week 0 for the phone book
was, like, one page at a time.
So we plotted it with this 1 to 1 slope.
The second algorithm, we
started doing two pages
at a time, which did risk a bug.
I might have to double back one page.
But it was still going for
the most part twice as fast.
So it was still a slow but sort of
a 2 to 1 slope instead of 1 to 1.
But the third and final
algorithm, recall,
was sort of fundamentally different.
And it was this logarithmic
curve, so to speak,
whereby it kept increasing, increasing,
increasing but very, very slowly.
So even if you, like, doubled
the size of the phone book,
as by having Cambridge and Allston here
in Massachusetts merge, no big deal.
It was just one more page turn,
not another 500 or another 1,000.
So think back today on that particular
idea of how we began to divide
and conquer the problem.
And that sort of gave us a
fundamentally better advantage.
So we thought we'd see if we can
apply this lesson learned as follows.
If I were to take, like, attendance
today sort of here on stage,
I could do it old school, like,
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, and so
forth, so one step at a time.
I could also double the speed--
2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12,
14, 16, and so forth.
But I dare say we can
learn a bit from week zero.
And if you'll indulge me
right in place, could everyone
stand up and think of the number one.
So right where you are,
just stand up if you could.
Stand up.
And think of the number one.
So at this point, hopefully, everyone's
literally thinking of the number one.
And the second step of this algorithm,
which I claim ultimately theoretically
should be much faster than
either my one person at a time
or two people at a
time, step two is this.
Pair off with someone standing.
And add their number to yours.
And remember the sum.
Person can be in front of,
behind, left, or right of you.
All right most likely most
everyone in the room assuming you
found someone is thinking
of the number two
now unless you're sort of an
odd person out in the row.
And that's fine.
If you're still one, that's fine.
But most of you are probably two.
Next step is that one of you
in those pairs should sit down.
OK, so many of you tried to sit down
as quickly as possible we noticed.
But so next step now, at this
point, rather, most of you
are thinking of the number two.
A few of you are thinking
of the number one.
And that's OK.
The next step, and notice we're about
to induce a loop, so the rest of this
is on you, if still standing,
go back to step two.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
DAVID MALAN: If still standing,
notice that this is a loop.
So keep going.
Keep going if still standing.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
DAVID MALAN: There?
How about there?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
DAVID MALAN: That's OK.
But now keep going.
Keep going.
Keep pairing off, so maybe you two.
All right, a few more seconds.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
DAVID MALAN: So step two, still.
All right, keep pairing
if you're standing.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
All right, so theoretically, there's
only one person standing left.
But clearly, that's not the case.
That's fine.
I will help with the pairing
because some of you are far away.
So let's see.
What's your number here?
Sorry?
What's your number?
Eight.
OK, go ahead and sit down.
How about in back?
What's your number?
46.
Nice.
OK, go ahead and sit down.
Who else is standing?
Over here, what's your number?
You're 16?
OK, so go ahead and sit down.
And behind you?
48.
OK, go ahead and sit down.
Is anyone still standing?
Yeah?
32.
Nice.
Still standing over here.
43.
OK, nice.
Sit down.
And anyone else still standing here?
22.
Go ahead and sit down.
Is anyone still standing
and participating?
Yeah, where-- oh, yeah.
16.
OK, go ahead and sit down.
Anyone else still standing?
OK, so theoretically,
everyone's paired off.
You were the last person standing.
So when I hit Enter here,
having just greased the wheels
to do all of the remaining
additions myself,
we should have the total
count of people in the room.
And recognize that unlike
my algorithm, which
would have required pointing
at each and every person
or my second algorithm, which would
mean pointing at every two people
twice as fast, theoretically, the
algorithm you all just executed,
I daresay, should've been
fundamentally faster.
Why?
Because no matter how many
people in the room-- maybe, like,
if there were 1,000
people in the room, there
would then have been 500, just as
there would be 500 pages in week zero.
Then from 500, there'd be 250--
125.
Why?
Because on each step of
the algorithm, half of you
theoretically were sitting down,
sitting down, sitting down, dividing
and conquering that problem.
So the total number of people in the
room as of now according to your count
is 231.
As a backup, though, Carter kindly
did it the old-fashioned way,
one person at a time.
And Carter, the actual number
of people in the room is?
[LAUGHS]
OK, so our first real
world bug to be fair.
So theoretically, that
should have worked.
But clearly, we lost some
numbers along the way, so a bug
that we can fix today.
But remember that really,
this is just similar in spirit
to that algorithm we
indeed did in week zero.
It's the same as the phone book example.
It went off the rails in this case.
But it's the same idea, ultimately
dividing and conquering.
And any time you have this
halving, halving, halving,
there's going to be a
logarithm involved there,
even if you're a little
rusty on your math.
And that's fundamentally faster
than just doing something n times
or even n divided by 2 times where n
is the number of people in the room
or in week zero, the number
of pages in the phone book.
So even when you're using your iPhone
or Android device later today, like,
if you search for a
contact using autocomplete,
it is that so-called divide
and conquer algorithm that's
finding people in your address book.
It's not starting top
to bottom or bottom up.
It's probably going
roughly to the middle
and then doing the top half or the
bottom half, repeating again and again.
So these ideas are everywhere.
And hopefully, you end
up finding just the one
person you're looking
for or in your case,
the one person last standing
who should have theoretically
had the count of everyone because if
each of you started by representing 1,
effectively handed off your
number, handed off your number,
handed off your number, it
theoretically should have coalesced
in that final person standing.
So let's consider the
connection now between this idea
and what we introduced last week,
which was this idea of very simple data
structures in your computer's memory--
like, actually using this memory as
though it's kind of a grid of bytes.
Each one of these squares, recall,
represents 1 byte or 8 bits.
And we can get rid of
the hardware and sort
of abstract it away as just this
grid of memory or this canvas.
And then we introduced arrays last week.
And what was the key
definition of an array?
How would you describe an array?
What is it, anyone?
What's an array?
Yeah, in the middle.
A collection.
And I don't love data types only because
in C, it tends to be the same type.
So a collection of data.
I do like that.
But there's one other
key characteristic.
Do you want to be more precise?
It's not just a collection--
something about where it is.
Potentially strings.
But strings are just an example
of putting char, char, char, char.
It could certainly be integers
or floating point values.
Another characteristic?
Sorry?
It's not necessarily ordered.
Actually, we'll come back to that today.
It could be in any order.
And certainly a string isn't
necessarily in sorted order.
It's in whatever the word is.
It's a list in concept.
But there was something key about
where we put things in memory.
Yeah?
Consecutive-- the memory is
consecutive, a.k.a., contiguous.
An array is important in C because,
yes, it's a list of values.
Yes, it's a collection of values.
But the real key distinction in an
array in C is that it's contiguous.
The bytes are back to back to back
somewhere in the computer's memory,
at least for any given data type, be
it an int, a float, a bigger string.
All of the characters are back to
back to back in the computer's memory,
not spread all out, even if
you have space elsewhere.
So with that said, we can actually start
to solve problems with that mindset.
And for instance, if I kind of pare this
down to just an abstract array of size
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7,
for instance, suppose
that there are these numbers
inside of this array of memory.
So here are seven integers or
ints in C. I have in this case
sorted them just to make the numbers pop
out as obviously smallest to largest.
But the catch with C is
that if I were to ask you
or if you were to ask the computer
through code to find you the number 50,
well, obviously, every
human in this room
just found it obviously right there
because we kind of have this bird's eye
view of the whole memory at once.
But the computer
ironically does not have
that bird's eye view of its own memory.
It can only look at each
location one at a time.
So if you really were to do this like
a computer, you would kind of have to,
like, shield your eye and only look
at one number at a time from left
to right, from right to
left, or in any order
in order to find is
the 50 actually there.
You can't just take a step back.
And boom, it pops out at you.
So this is kind of
analogous, this array,
to being like a set of
gym lockers or school
lockers like this where the doors
are actually closed by default.
The numbers are in there.
But the doors are closed,
which is to say the computer
and we can't actually look.
So we couldn't find yellow lockers.
But we did find red lockers here.
And so I propose that you think
of these lockers on the stage
here of which there are seven as
well as representing an array.
And just so we have some terminology,
notice that I've labeled these bracket
0, bracket 1, bracket 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6.
And the bracket notation
recalls the new syntax
from last week that
lets you index into--
go to a specific spot
inside of an array.
And notice that even though
there are seven lockers,
I only counted as high as six.
But again, that's just a side effect
of our generally counting from 0.
So 0 through 6 or 0 through n minus 1
because if there are n equal 7 lockers,
n minus 1 is 6.
So that's the left bound and
the right bound respectively.
So suppose that we were to use these
lockers as representing a problem,
like we want to find an actual
number behind these doors.
So this is actually a very
common problem in the real world.
And you and I take for granted every
day that big companies like Google
and Microsoft and others,
like, do this for us
constantly, not to mention AI
doing something similar nowadays,
searching for information.
And we'll focus on
some basics first that
will lead us to more sophisticated
algorithms ultimately.
But all we're going to
talk about fundamentally
is this same picture from week zero
and from week one and from week two
where here is a problem to be solved.
So if for instance, the input to
this problem is an array of numbers--
an array of seven numbers--
I can't see them all at once-- but I'm
looking for something like the number
50--
ultimately, I want to get back out.
I claim true or false.
Like, the number 50 is there.
Or it is not.
That's one way of thinking
about the search problem.
Find me some piece of
data if it's there.
Otherwise, tell me that it's
not-- true or false, respectively.
So the algorithm inside
of this black box,
though, is where we're going to
actually have to do some thinking
and actually figure out how best to find
the number or the data we care about.
And even though we'll use numbers
to keep things simple today,
you could certainly generalize
this to web pages or contacts
or any other type of information that
are in some computer or database more
generally.
So maybe to keep things
interesting, could we
get-- how about two volunteers?
Wow, that was fast.
OK, come on down.
And how about one other volunteer?
I'll go over here.
OK, how about you?
Come on down.
Sure, round of applause
for our volunteers.
[APPLAUSE]
OK, welcome.
Come on over.
Do you want to introduce
yourself to the group?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Like a few seconds is fine.
AUDIENCE: Hi, I'm Sam.
I am not a CS concentration.
DAVID MALAN: [LAUGHS] So what are you?
Do you know yet?
AUDIENCE: Applied math.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
Nice.
Nice to meet you.
Welcome.
And?
AUDIENCE: Hi, I'm Louis.
I'm from first year, Matthews.
And I'm going to do Econ with Stats.
DAVID MALAN: Oh, you're in Matthews too?
OK.
[CHUCKLES] I was in Matthews
too, so Matthews South?
Oh, wow.
Oh, my god.
I was room 201.
AUDIENCE: 103.
DAVID MALAN: Fifth floor--
all right, so anyhow.
And so we have Louis and your name?
AUDIENCE: Sam.
DAVID MALAN: Sam.
Louis and Sam.
So Louis and I are going to step off to
the side for just a moment because Sam,
we have a problem for you to solve.
This feels a little bit
like Price Is Right.
But behind you are these seven lockers.
And we'd like you to just
find us the number 50.
That's all the information you get.
But we'd like you to then explain
how you go about finding it.
AUDIENCE: Wait, are they
in order or anything?
Or [INAUDIBLE] it just
kind of [INAUDIBLE]??
DAVID MALAN: Find us the number 50.
And then tell us how you found it.
OK, what was in there,
just so the audience knows.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yes.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: It was $10, a
very, very big $10 bill.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
AUDIENCE: Fake money.
AUDIENCE: That was $100.
$1.
$5.
OK, I'm not lucky.
Oh, I found it.
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
Take it out and so people can believe.
All right, wonderful.
So you found the 50.
[APPLAUSE]
And now if you could explain.
I'll take that.
If you could explain,
what was your algorithm?
What was the step-by-step
approach you took?
AUDIENCE: I didn't really have one.
I just started on one end.
And I went down because it
wasn't in order or anything.
So I just kept going until I found it.
DAVID MALAN: OK, so that's
actually pretty fair.
And in fact, let's step forward here.
Carter's going to very secretly
kind of shuffle the numbers
in a particular new arrangement here.
And so you really went
from right to left.
And I dare say maybe going from
left to right might be equivalent.
But could she have done better?
Could she have done better, because
that took 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 steps?
Could Sam have done better?
Sure.
How?
OK, so you got lucky.
You could have found
the number in one step.
Although, luck isn't
really an algorithm.
It really isn't a step-by-step approach.
So another thought?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] dollar bills--
sort them in order?
DAVID MALAN: Oh, interesting.
So you could have taken out all
of the dollar bills, sorted them,
put them back in, and then you
probably could have done something
like the divide and conquer approach.
AUDIENCE: I didn't know
I was allowed to do that.
DAVID MALAN: No, you weren't allowed to.
So that's fine.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: But that
would be a valid algorithm.
Although, it sounds very
inefficient to do all this work just
to find the number 50
because in doing that work,
she would've found the 50 once.
But that might actually
be a reasonable solution
if she plans to search again and again
and again, not just for seven numbers
but maybe a lot of numbers.
Maybe you do want to incur some
cost up front and all the data
so as to find it faster.
But let's do this a
little more methodically.
We'll step off to the side once more.
And just by convention, if you want
to go ahead and-- do we need this?
OK.
AUDIENCE: Got it.
DAVID MALAN: OK, let's
go from left to right.
Yep.
And go ahead and show
everyone the numbers just
to prove that there's
no funny business here.
AUDIENCE: 20.
DAVID MALAN: [LAUGHS]
AUDIENCE: Oh, OK.
500.
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
AUDIENCE: 10.
DAVID MALAN: Mm-hm.
So it doesn't sound like it's
sorted, either, this time.
AUDIENCE: Five.
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
And?
AUDIENCE: 100.
DAVID MALAN: Oh, so close.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: I know.
Now we're just messing with you.
AUDIENCE: 1.
DAVID MALAN: OK, and lastly?
AUDIENCE: [GASPS] 50.
DAVID MALAN: Very well done.
OK, so nicely done.
[APPLAUSE]
And so thank you.
So this is a say whether she goes
from left to right or right to left,
like, the performance of that
algorithm just going linearly
from side to side really depends
on where the number ends up being.
And it kind of does boil down to luck.
And so that was kind of the best
you could do because I dare say,
had you gone linearly from right
to left-- and go ahead to reset--
had you gone from right to left, that
time you would have gotten lucky.
So on average, it might
just kind of work out.
And so half the time, it takes
you maybe half as many steps--
half the number of lockers
to find it on average
because sometimes it's in the one end.
Sometimes it's on the other end.
Sometimes it's smack dab in the middle.
But we're going to give
you the option now,
Louis, of knowing that it's sorted.
So we're going to take away
the microphone from you.
But stay on up here with us.
And you are now given the
assumption that the numbers
are this time sorted from smallest
to largest, left to right.
And might you want to take more of
a divide and conquer approach here?
Wait a minute.
AUDIENCE: [LAUGHS]
DAVID MALAN: What might you
do as your algorithm, Louis?
AUDIENCE: Well, I think I
know all the numbers, right?
It's 1, 5--
DAVID MALAN: Oh, damn it.
AUDIENCE: 10, 20, 50.
DAVID MALAN: OK, so Louis has
some memory, as we'll say.
OK.
AUDIENCE: But assuming
if I didn't have memory.
DAVID MALAN: OK, assuming
if you didn't have
memory, where would you start first?
AUDIENCE: I would probably
start in the middle.
DAVID MALAN: OK, go ahead.
Go in the middle.
And what do you see?
AUDIENCE: 20.
DAVID MALAN: 20.
OK, what does that mean now for you?
AUDIENCE: So now that means that since4
I know there's some numbers bigger,
I'll go to the right.
DAVID MALAN: Good.
So you can tear the problem
in half, so to speak.
As per week zero, skip all
of the lockers on the left.
And now go where
relative to these three?
AUDIENCE: Relative to the middle.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
AUDIENCE: So maybe [? you ?] don't
know what's on the right-hand side.
And so now it's 100.
DAVID MALAN: OK, nice.
AUDIENCE: So the 50 must
be between 20 and 100.
So it must be this one.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
So a round of applause for Louis
for getting this right this time.
[APPLAUSE]
We have some lovely parting gifts,
since we're using monopoly money.
So it's not actual money.
But this is the Cambridge edition
Harvard Square and all for both of you.
So welcome.
Thank you so much.
[APPLAUSE]
So Louis was actually getting
particularly clever there
when his first instinct
was to just remember
what were all the numbers
and then sort of deduce
where the 50 must obviously be.
So that's on us.
Like, ideally, we would have
completely changed the dollar amount so
that he couldn't use that information.
But it turns out Louie's instinct there
to figure out where the number should
be and jump right there--
index into that exact location--
is actually a technique.
And it's a technique we'll
talk about in future classes
where you actually do take
into account the information
and go right where you want.
It's an example of what we'll
eventually call hashing, so to speak,
in a concept called hash tables.
But for now, let's try to
formalize the algorithms
that both of these volunteers
kind of intuitively
came up with, first and second.
And we'll slap some names on them.
So the first, and I've hinted at this,
is what we would call linear search.
Anytime you search from left
to right or from right to left,
it's generally called linear search.
Why?
Because you're kind of walking in
a line, no matter which direction
you're going.
But now for today's purposes,
let's see if we can't truly
formalize what our volunteers'
algorithms were by translating them,
not necessarily to code
yet, but pseudocode.
See if we can't map it to English-like
syntax that gets the ideas across.
So I dare say, the first algorithm,
even though she went from right to left,
then from left to right,
might look like this.
For each door from left to right,
she checked if 50 is behind the door
as by looking at it.
If it was behind the door,
then she returned true.
Like, yes, this is the 50.
That didn't happen on the
first iteration, though.
So she moved on again and again.
And now notice the
indentation here is just
as important as it was in week zero.
Notice that only at the very
bottom of this algorithm
do I propose returning false.
But it's not indented
inside of this pseudocode.
Why?
Well, because if I had
changed it to be this,
what would be the logical bug in
this version of that algorithm?
Yeah?
Exactly.
If she had opened the first door, found
it to be the wrong number if it says
else-- if it's not behind
the door, then return false--
that would erroneously
conclude the 50's not there,
even though it could certainly
be among those other doors.
So this first version of the
code where the return false is
sort of left indented, so to
speak, and the very last thing
you do if you don't previously
return true, that just
makes sure that we're
handling all possible cases.
But let's make this maybe
a little more technical.
This is how a computer
scientist or a programmer
would likely express this instead.
Instead of just drawing
it in broad strokes,
it's actually fine to kind of steal
some of the syntax from languages like C
and actually use some of the indices
or indexes like 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
to represent the pieces
of data we care about.
So this is a little more precise.
For i-- like a variable i--
from the value 0 to n minus 1,
so in the case of seven doors, this
is like saying, for i starting at 0,
going up to 6, do the following.
If the number 50 is
behind the doors array--
so I'm using array syntax, even though
this is technically still pseudocode--
if the ith location of my doors
array has the number 50, return true.
Otherwise, if you do that
again and again and again--
n total times-- and you still don't
find it, you want to return false.
So we introduced this.
This is just an example of how you can
start to borrow ideas from actual code
to paint the picture even
more precisely of what
it is you want a
colleague to do, what it
is you want your code to
do, ultimately, by sort
of borrowing these ideas from code and
incorporating it into our pseudocode.
But what about the
second algorithm here,
the second algorithm, whereby he
took a divide and conquer approach,
starting in the middle and then
going right and then going left.
Well, it turns out this is
generally called binary search.
Bi implying two, because
you're either going
with the left half or the
right half again and again.
This is literally what we've been
talking about since week zero
when I searched the phone book.
That too was binary search, dividing and
dividing and dividing in half and half.
So if we were to draw
some pseudocode for this,
I would propose that we
could do something like this.
If 50 is behind the middle
door, then we got lucky.
Just return true.
Else if the 50 is less than
the value at the middle door--
so if it's smaller
than the middle door--
I want to search to the left.
So I can say search left half.
Else if 50 is greater than the middle
door, I want to search to the right.
And I think that's
almost everything, right?
Is there a fourth possible case?
What else could happen?
Good.
So taking into account that if
there are no doors left or no doors
to begin with, we
better handle that case
so that we don't induce one
of those spinning beach balls,
so that the computer
doesn't freeze or crash.
There's really four possible scenarios
in searching for information.
It's either in the middle or
to the left or to the right.
Or it's just not there at all.
And so I sort of slip that in at the end
because technically, that's a question
you should ask first because if there's
no doors, there's no work to be done.
But logically, this is the juicy
part-- the other three questions
that you might ask yourself.
So this then might be the
pseudocode for binary search.
And we could make it more technical.
And this is where it kind of
escalates quickly syntactically.
But I'm just using the
same kind of syntax.
If doors in my pseudocode
represents an array of doors,
well, then doors bracket middle
is just a pseudocode-like way
of saying go to the
middle door in that array.
And then notice, else if 50 is
less than-- that middle value--
then search doors bracket
0, so the leftmost one--
through doors middle minus 1.
So you don't need to waste time
researching the middle door.
So I say middle minus 1 so that I scooch
over slightly to the left, so to speak.
Else if 50 is greater than
the value at the middle door,
then you want to search
1 over to the right,
so middle plus 1 among those doors,
through the last door, which is not n,
because we start counting
at 0, but n minus 1.
And the rest of the
algorithm is the same.
This is just a little more precise.
And I dare say, when writing a
program in C or any language,
like, honestly, starting in pseudocode
like this will generally make it
much easier to write the actual code.
So in fact, in this and future
problem sets, do get into the habit,
especially if you're struggling
getting started-- just
write things out in English
and maybe high level
English a little more like this.
Then as a version two, go in with
your keyboard or paper, pencil.
And make it a little more precise
using some code-like syntax.
And then I dare say in
version 3, you can now
translate this pretty
much verbatim to C code.
The only headache is going
to be rounding issues
with integers because if you divide
an integer and you a fraction,
it's going to truncate, so
all that kind of headache.
But you can work through
that by just thinking
through what's going
to get truncated when
you round down or up as a solution.
Any questions, though,
on this pseudocode
for either linear or binary
search as we've defined them--
linear or binary search--
no?
All right, well, let's
consider then a bit more
formally a question that we'll come
back to in the future in future classes
as well.
What is the running time
of these algorithms?
What is, that is to say, the
efficiency of these algorithms?
And how do we actually measure
the efficiency of an algorithm?
Is it with a stopwatch or
with some other mechanism?
Well, I propose that we
think back to this picture
here, whereby this, again, was
representative of both the phone book
example from week zero and
theoretically, bug aside,
the attendance counting algorithm
from earlier today, whereby
this same green line theoretically
represents how much time it should have
taken us as a group to count ourselves.
Why?
Because if maybe another
class comes in and doubles
the size of the number of humans
in this room, no big deal.
That's just one more step or
one more iteration of the loop
because half of the people
would anyway sit down.
So this green algorithm still represents
the faster theoretical algorithm today.
And so recall that we described these
things more mathematically as n.
So this was one page at a
time or one person at a time.
This was two people or
two pages at a time.
So it's twice as fast, so if n
is the number of people or pages
and divided by 2 is the
total number of steps.
And then this one got a little
mathy, but log base 2 of n.
And log base 2 of n just means what is
the value when you take n and divide it
in two by 2 again and
again and again and again
until you're left with just one
page or one person standing.
But in the world of running times,
it turns out that being this precise
is not that intellectually interesting.
And it sort of devolves
into lower level math.
It's just not necessary
when having discussions
about the efficiency of an algorithm
or even code that you've written.
So generally, a computer
scientist, when asked
what's the running
time of your algorithm
or what's the efficiency
of your algorithm or more
generally how good or
bad is your algorithm,
they'll talk about it being on
the order of some number of steps.
This is a phrase you'll hear
increasingly in computer science
where you can kind of
wave your hand at it.
Like, oh, the lower level
details don't matter that much.
All you care about in broad
strokes are certain numbers
that will add up the most.
And in fact, when
computer scientists talk
about the efficiency of
algorithms, they tend
to throw away constant factors,
so literally, numbers like 2
that might be dividing
here or a base here.
So for instance, these two
algorithms to a computer scientist
would sort be the same.
Like, yeah, it's
technically twice as fast.
But look at the lines.
I mean, they're practically the same and
this one here too, log base 2-- sure.
But if you remember from math class,
you can change the base of any logarithm
from one number to
another pretty easily.
So ah, let's just
generalize it as log of n.
It doesn't really matter fundamentally
what the numbers actually are.
And honestly, if we zoom out slightly
so that the y-axis and the x-axis
get even bigger, honestly,
these first two algorithms
really do start to resemble
each other closer and closer.
And I daresay in your mind's eye,
imagine zooming further and further
and further out.
Like, that red and yellow line are
pretty much-- once n is large enough--
going to be functionally the same.
Like, they're practically
the same algorithm.
But this one is still doing
amazingly because it's
a fundamentally different shape.
So this is to say when a computer
scientist talks about, thinks
about the efficiency of algorithms,
we just throw away the constant terms
that when n gets really large
just don't seem to matter as much.
They don't add up as
much or fundamentally
change the picture in a case like this.
So what I'm describing here with this
capital letter O has a technical term.
This is called big O notation.
And this is omnipresent
in computer science
and often rears its head
even in programming,
specifically when talking about
the design of some algorithm.
And this is a little cheat
sheet here on the screen now.
Very often, algorithms
that you write or you
use will be describable as being on the
order of one of these running times.
So n is just representative of the
number of things-- number of people,
number of pages--
whatever it is you're
actually doing in code.
So the mathematical formulas
inside of the parentheses
describe as a function
of the size of that input
how fast or slow the
algorithm's going to be.
So this algorithm in the middle
here, big O of n, so to speak,
means that it takes linear
time, in other words.
So my first algorithm--
1, 2, 3, 4--
or my first algorithm in week zero--
1, 2, 3, 4.
That was a linear search.
The number of steps it takes is on the
order of n because if there's n pages,
in the worst case, like, John Harvard's
all the way at the end of the phone
book, so it takes me n steps.
In this case, it's always going to
take me n steps to count you all
because if I want to point
at each and every one of you,
that is always going to take me n steps.
So big O represents an upper
bound on the number of steps
that you might be counting.
And so we often use it to consider
the worst case and the worst
case, John Harvard, or whoever might
be all the way at the end of the phone
book.
So that linear search
is on the order of n.
But what about n squared?
This means n people doing n things.
So for instance, and
we won't do this today,
but if we were to ask you
again to stand up and shake
everyone's hand in the room--
not good for health nowadays-- but
shake everyone's hand in the room,
how many handshakes would there be?
Well, if there's n of you and you've
got to shake everyone else's hand,
that's technically n times n minus 1.
Let's throw away the minus 1.
That's n times n or
n squared handshakes.
That's a lot of handshakes.
And so the running time
of shaking everyone's hand
in the room to introduce yourself
would be on the order of n squared.
At the other end of the spectrum,
the faster end, big O of 1
doesn't mean that the algorithm
takes literally one step.
It could take two steps or
three or even 1,000 steps.
But what it means is it's
a constant number of steps.
So it doesn't matter how
many people are in the room,
this describes something
taking just one step total
or a constant number of steps total.
So for instance, earlier when
everyone stood up at the same time,
that was constant time because
if we had twice as many people
come into the room, it's not going
to take us twice as long to stand up
if everyone stands up at the same time.
That would be a constant time algorithm.
So this is linear.
This is constant.
If you want to get
fancy, this is quadratic.
This is logarithmic.
And this is n log n.
Or there's other fancier terms we
can give it as well, but for now,
just a common list of running times that
we might apply to certain algorithms.
So linear search, I
claim, is in big O of n
because it's going to take
in the worst case n steps.
What about binary search?
How many steps does binary
search take on the order of
according to this chart?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Log n.
DAVID MALAN: Log n.
Yeah, because no matter what with
binary search, you're dividing in half,
half, half.
But in the worst case, it might
be in the last door you check.
But you only took log
n steps to get there.
But it still might be
the last one you check.
So binary search indeed would
be on the order of log n.
But sometimes, you do get lucky.
And we saw with our volunteers
that sometimes you can get lucky
and just find things quicker.
So we don't always want to talk about
things in terms of an upper bound,
like how many steps in the worst
case might this algorithm take.
Sometimes it's useful
to know in the best case
how few steps might an algorithm take.
So for that, we have this
capital Greek omega, which
is another symbol in computer science.
And whereas big O represents upper
bound, omega represents lower bound.
And it's the exact same idea.
It's just a different
symbol to represent
a different idea, the
opposite, in this case.
So here's a similar cheat sheet here.
But when you use the
omega symbol, that just
means that this algorithm might
take as few as this many steps,
for instance, in the very best case.
So by that logic, if I
ask about linear search,
our first demonstration with the
lockers, let's consider the best case.
How many steps might it
take to search n lockers
using linear search in the best case?
You get lucky.
So I heard it.
Yeah, just one step.
So we could say that linear search
is an omega of 1, so to speak.
What about binary search?
If you've got n lockers,
in the best case, though,
how few steps might it take us?
Again, one, because we
might just get lucky.
And boom, it happens to be
right there in the middle.
So you could say that both linear search
and binary search are an omega of 1.
Now, by contrast, my attendance
algorithm, the first one I proposed--
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, I claimed a
moment ago that that's in big O of n
because if there's n people in the
room, I've got to point at everyone.
But equivalently, if
there's n people in the room
and I have to point at everyone,
what's the fewest number of steps
it could take me to take attendance
using this linear approach?
So still n, right, unless I
guess, which is not an algorithm.
Like, unless I guess, I'm not
going to get the right answer,
so I kind of have to point at everyone.
So in both the best
case and the worst case,
some algorithms still take n steps.
And for this, we have what we'll
call theta notation, whereby
if big O and omega happen to be the
same, which is not always the case
but can be, then you can say that
algorithm is in theta of such and such.
So my attendance-taking algorithm,
the very first, 1, 2, 3, 4,
all the way on up to n
would be in theta of n
because in both the best
case and the worst case,
it takes the same number of steps
as per my big O and omega analysis.
Now, there is a more formal mathematical
definition for both of these.
And if you take higher
level computer science,
you'll go more into the
weeds of these ideas.
But for now, big O, upper bound.
Omega, lower bound.
Questions on this symbology?
It'll be a tool in our tool kit.
No?
OK, so with that said, let's see how
we might translate this to actual code
in something that makes sense
now using C and not so much
new syntax but applications of
similar ideas from last time.
So for instance, let me actually go over
to search dot C. And in search dot C,
I'm going to go ahead and implement
the idea of linear search,
very simply, using integers initially.
So to do this, let me go ahead and
give myself the familiar CS50 dot h
so that I can ask the human
what number to search for.
Then let me go ahead and
include standard io.h
so that I can use printf and the like.
Then I'm going to go ahead and do int
main void without any command line
arguments because I'm not going to need
any for this particular demonstration.
And someone asked about
this a while back.
If I want to declare an
array of values but I
know in advance what the values are,
there is a special syntax I can use,
which is this.
If I want a whole bunch of numbers
but I want those numbers to be stored
in an array, I can store them in--
using these curly braces.
And I'm going to use the same
numbers as the monopoly denominations
that we've been playing with.
And I'm just going to put
them in sort of random order.
But I'm going to deliberately
put the 50 all the way at the end
just so that I know that it's going to
try all possible steps, so big O of n,
ultimately.
Now let's go ahead and ask
the user for a value n.
And we'll use get int.
And just ask the user for a number to
search for, be it 50 or something else.
And then here's how I might
implement in code now linear search,
translating effectively the
pseudocode from last time.
For int i equals 0.
i is less than 7. i plus plus.
And then inside of this
loop, I can ask a question.
If the ith number in the numbers array--
so numbers bracket i--
equals, equals the number n
that I care about, well, this is
where I could just declare return true
or return false.
Here, I'm going to go ahead and
just use a printf statement.
And I'm going to say found,
backslash n, just to know visually
that I found the number.
And else I might do something like this.
Else if that's not the
case, I'll go ahead
and print out not found backslash n.
All right, so let me zoom
out for just a moment.
Here's all of my code.
Any concerns with this implementation
of what I claim is now linear search?
Any concerns with what I
claim is linear search?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
If I search the first number and it's
not found, it's going to say not found.
But it's going to keep saying
not found, not found, not found,
which might be fine.
But it's a little stupid.
I probably want to know
if it's found or not.
So I've made that same mistake
that I called out earlier.
Like, the else is not the
alternative to not finding
the number in that first location.
It's the final decision to make when
I haven't actually found the value.
So I think what I want to do
is get rid of this else clause.
And then at the outside
of this loop, I think
I want to conclude printf not found.
But here too there's a
new bug that's arisen.
There's a new bug, even though I fixed
the logical error you just described.
What symptom are we still going to see?
Yeah, now it's going to
always print not found,
even when I have found it
because even once I've found it
and I finished going through
the array, it's still going
to assume that I got to the bottom.
And therefore, it's not found.
So I need to somehow exit out of
main prematurely, if you will.
And recall that last week,
we also introduced the idea
that main all this time does
actually return a value, an integer.
By default, it's secretly been zero.
Anytime a program exits, it just
returns zero, an exit status of zero.
But we do now have control over that.
And so a convention in
C would be that when
you want your main function
to end prematurely if so,
you can literally just return a value.
And even though this feels a little
backwards, this is just the way it is.
You return zero to indicate success.
And you return any other
integer to indicate failure.
So by convention, people go
to 1 and then 2 and then 3.
They don't think too hard
about what numbers to use.
But in this case, I'm going
to go ahead and return 1
if I do get to the bottom of this file.
So now if I open back up my
terminal window, I run make search.
No syntax errors-- dot slash search.
I'm going to be prompted for a number.
Let's go ahead and
search for the number 50.
And I should see found.
Meanwhile, if I run it
again-- dot slash search--
I search for the number 13,
that should be not found.
So I claim that this is now a correct
implementation of linear search
that's gone from left to right, looking
for a number that may or may not
be there.
Any questions on this
version of the code here?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Return
zero indicates success
when doing it from main in particular.
And that's backwards only in the
sense that generally 0 is false.
And 1 is true.
But the logic here is that if the
program works correctly, that's zero.
But there's an infinite number
of things that can go wrong.
And that's why we need 1 and 2
and 3 and 4 and all the way up.
Other questions?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yes.
DAVID MALAN: Correct.
When you return zero or return any value
from main wherever it is in your code,
the program will effectively
terminate right then and there.
No additional code will get executed
at the bottom of the function.
You'll effectively exit out.
Just like in a normal function that
isn't main, when you return a value,
it immediately exits that
function and hands back the value.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: So return
1 is just me being
pedantic at this point because I'm
frankly not going to really care what
the exit status is of this program.
But once I've introduced the idea of
manually returning 0 on this line 14
to indicate success, it stands
to reason that I should also
return a different value when
I want to indicate failure.
And so even though this
does not functionally
change the program-- it will
still work-- it will still
print the same things correctly--
it's a lower level detail
that programmers, teaching
assistants, testing software,
might appreciate, knowing
what actually happened
in the program underneath the hood.
All right, so what about strings?
So it turns out with
strings, we're going
to have to think a little harder
about how best to do this.
So let me actually go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and get rid of
much of this code but transition
to a different type of array,
this time an array of strings.
And I'm going to call the array strings
itself plural, just to make clear
what's in it instead of numbers.
I'm going to use the square
bracket notation, which
just means I don't know at the moment
how many elements it's going to have.
But the compiler can
figure it out for me.
And in the spirit of Monopoly,
let's go ahead in our curly braces,
do something like this.
Battleship is going to
be one of the strings.
Boot is going to be another.
Cannon is going to be a third.
Iron is going to be the fourth.
Thimble-- and if you've
ever played Monopoly,
you know where these are coming
from-- and top hat, for instance.
So this gives me 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
I could write the number 6 here.
And the compiler would appreciate it.
But it doesn't matter.
The compiler can figure it out on its
own just based on the number of commas.
And this also ensures that I
don't write one number to the left
and then miscount on the right.
So omitting it is probably
in everyone's benefit.
Now let's do this.
Let's ask the user for a string
using get string instead of get int
for some string to search for.
Then let's go ahead and
do the exact same thing.
For i int i equals 0.
i is less than 6, which is
technically a magic number.
But let's focus on the
searching algorithm for now.
i plus plus.
And then inside of this
loop, let's do this.
If strings bracket i equals
equals, s, then let's go ahead
and print out just as before, quote,
unquote, found-- backslash n--
and proactively return zero this time.
And if we don't find it
anywhere in the loop,
let's go ahead and return
1 at the very bottom,
before which we will print
not found backslash n.
So it's the exact same
logic at the moment,
even though I've changed
my ints to strings.
Let me go ahead and open
up my terminal window now.
Do make search again and
see, OK, so far, so good.
Let me now go ahead and
do dot slash search.
And let's go ahead and search
for-- how about top hat.
So we should see found.
Huh.
All right, not found.
All right, well, let's do
dot slash search again.
How about thimble?
Maybe it's because it's just two words.
No, thimble's not found, either.
Dot slash search-- let's search
for the first one, battleship.
Enter-- still not found.
Let's search for
something else like cat.
Not found.
What is going on because I'm pretty
sure the logic is exactly the same?
Well, it turns out in C, this
line here, currently line 11,
is not how you compare strings.
If you want to compare strings in C,
you don't do it like you did integers.
You actually need another
technique altogether.
And for that, we're going to need
to revisit one of our friends, which
is string.h, which is one of the
header files for the string library
that we introduced last week
that has in addition to functions
like strlen, which gives you the
length of a string, it also gives us,
as per the documentation here,
another function that we'll
start to find useful here, succinctly
named strcmp, for string compare.
And string compare will actually tell
us if two strings are the same or not.
It will indeed compare them.
And if I use this now,
let me go back to my code
here and see what I might do differently
if I go back into my code here
and change this value.
Instead of using strings bracket i
equals, equals s, let's do str compare.
And I read the documentation earlier.
So I know that it takes two arguments,
the first and the second string
that you want to compare, so
strings bracket i and then s,
which is the string
that the human typed in.
But somewhat weirdly,
what I want to check for
is that str compare returns zero.
So if str compare when given two strings
is input, strings bracket i and s,
returns an integer 0, that actually
means the strings are the same.
So let's try this.
Let me do make search again.
Huh.
What did I do wrong here?
A whole bunch of errors popped out.
What did I do wrong?
Yeah?
Yeah, so I didn't include the very
header file we're talking about.
So again, it doesn't necessarily
mean a logical error.
It just means a stupid error on my part.
I didn't actually
include the header file.
So let me go back and actually do that.
Up at the top in addition
to cs50.h and standard io,
let's also include string.h.
Let me clear my terminal
and do make search again.
Crossing my fingers.
That time it worked.
And now if I do dot slash search
and search for top hat like before,
now, thankfully, it is, in fact, found.
If I do it once more and search for
battleship, now it's, in fact, found.
cat, which should not be in there,
that is not, in fact, found.
So now just intuitively, even if
you've never done this before,
why might it be valuable for
this function called strcmp
to return zero if the
strings are equal as opposed
to a simple Boolean like true or false,
which might have been your intuition?
When you compare two strings,
what are the possible takeaways
you might have from
comparing two strings?
It's not just that they're equal or not.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, so maybe if the
ASCII values are the same, that
might imply, indeed, literal equality.
But something else.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] about how
similar these things are [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Ah, nice.
Like, you and I in English,
certainly, are very much
in the habit of sorting
information, whether it's
in a dictionary, in our contacts, in
a phone book, in any such technology.
And so it's often useful to be able to
know, does this string equal another?
Sure.
But does this string come before
another alphabetically or maybe
after another alphabetically?
So sometimes, you want functions
to give you back three answers.
But equals, equals alone can only
give you true or false, yes or no.
And that might not be
useful enough when you're
trying to solve some
problem involving strings.
So it turns out str compare actually
compares the two strings for equality
but also for what's called,
playfully, ASCII-betical order.
So not alphabetical order, per
se, but ASCII-betical order
where it actually compares the
integer values of the letters.
So if you're comparing
the letter A, It's
going to compare 65 against some
other letter's integer value-- hence
ASCII-betical value.
So we're not doing any
form of sorting here.
So it's sort of immaterial.
But as per the documentation,
I do know that str compare
returns zero if two strings are equal.
And a little teaser for next week, it
turns out when I was only using equals,
equals to compare
strings bracket i and s,
I was not comparing the strings in
the way that you might have thought.
And if you have programmed in Java
or Python before, equals, equals
is actually doing something
different in those languages
than it is actually doing in
C. But more on that next week.
For now, just take on faith
that str compare is indeed
how you compare two strings.
So let's actually put this into play
with some actual additional code.
Let me propose that we implement a very
simplistic phone book, for instance.
Let me go ahead and implement here--
how about in a new file.
Instead of search dot C, let's
actually do phone book dot c.
And in this phone book, I'm going to go
ahead and include the same header file,
so cs50.h, so I can get input--
standard io.h, so I can use printf--
string.h so that I can use str compare.
Let me give myself a main function again
without command line arguments for now.
And let me go ahead now and
store a proper phone book, which
has some names and some actual numbers.
So let's store the names first.
So string-- names is going
to be the name of my array.
And let's go ahead and
store Carter's name,
how about my name, and maybe John
Harvard for phone book throwback.
Then let's go ahead and give me another
array called numbers wherein I'll put
our phone number, so
617-495-1000 for Carter--
617-495-1000 for me-- technically,
directory assistance here.
And then for John, we'll
give him an actual one.
So it's actually going
to be 949-468-2750.
You're welcome to text or
call John when you want.
Whoops.
And just for good measure, let's
go ahead and put our country codes
in here plus 1, even though at the
end of the day, these are strings.
So indeed notice I'm not using
an integer for these values.
I kind of sort of should.
But here's where data types
in C and programming more
generally might sometimes mislead you.
Even though we call it,
obviously, a phone number.
It's probably best to represent
it generally as strings, in fact,
so that you can have the pluses-- you
can have the dashes so that it doesn't
get too big and overflow an integer.
Maybe it's an international number
for which there's even more digits.
You don't want to risk
overflowing a value.
And in general, the rule
of thumb in programming
is even if in English we
call something a number,
if you wouldn't do math on it ever,
you should probably be storing it
as a string, not as an integer.
And it makes no logical sense to
do math on phone numbers, per se.
So those are best
instinctively left as strings.
And in this case, even
more simply, this ensures
that we have pluses and dashes
stored inside of the string.
All right, so now that I have these
two arrays in parallel, if you will.
Like, I'm assuming that
Carter's name is first.
So his number is first.
David's name is second.
So his number is second.
John's is third and thus third.
So let's actually search this.
Let's ask the user for--
how about a name using get string.
And this will be a name to
search for in the phone book
just like we did in week zero.
Let's do for int i
equals 0, i less than 3.
Again, the 3 is bad practice.
I should probably store
that in a constant.
But let's keep the focus for
today on the algorithm alone--
i plus, plus.
Then in here, let's do if--
how about names bracket i
equals, equals name typed in.
But wait a minute.
I'm screwing this up again.
What should I be using here?
str compare again-- so let's do
str compare, names bracket i comma,
name, which came from the user.
And if that return value is
zero, then let's go ahead
and print out, just like
before, found backslash n.
But you know what?
We can do something more interesting.
Let's actually print out the number.
So I didn't just find something.
I found the name.
So let's actually plug in that
person's corresponding number.
So now it's a more useful
phonebook or contacts app
where I'm going to show
the human not just found
but found this specific number.
Then I'm going to go ahead as before
and return 0 to indicate success.
And if we get all the way down here,
I'm going to go ahead and say not found
and not print out any number because
I obviously haven't found one,
and return one by convention
to indicate failure.
So let me open my terminal window.
Let me do make phone book-- enter.
So far, so good-- dot slash phone book.
Let's search for Carter--
enter-- found his number.
Let's do it again.
Dot slash phone book--
David-- found it.
Let's do it one more time for John--
found it.
And just for good measure, let's
do one other here like Eli--
enter-- not found in this case.
All right, so it seems to be
working based on this example here.
But now we've actually implemented the
idea of, like, a proper phone book.
But does any aspect of
the design of this code,
even if you've never
programmed before CS50,
does anything rub you wrong about
how we're storing our data--
the phone book itself--
these names and numbers?
Does anything rub you the wrong way?
Yeah, in back.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah,
really good observation.
I'm separating the
names and the numbers,
which indeed, it looks
a little bit weird.
And there's actually this technical
term in the world of programming,
which is code smell, where, like--
[SNIFFING]---- something smells a little
off about this code in the sense that,
like, this probably
doesn't end well, right?
If I add a fourth name, a fourth
number, a fifth name, a fiftieth name
and number, like, at some
point, they're probably
going to get out of sync, right?
So, like, there's something
awry about this design
that I shouldn't decouple
the names from the numbers.
So something kind of smells
about this code, so to speak.
And any time you perceive
that in your code,
it's probably an opportunity to
go about improving it somehow.
But to do that, we actually need
another tool in the toolkit.
And that is, again, this term
that I've used a couple of times--
data structures.
Like, arrays have been the
first of our data structures.
And they're so simplistic.
It just means storing things back to
back to back contiguously in memory.
But it turns out C--
and a little bit of new syntax-- but
it's not a lot of new syntax today--
a little bit of new
syntax today will allow
us to create our own data structures,
our own types of variables,
largely using syntax
we've seen thus far.
So to do this, let me
propose that in order
to represent a person in
a phone book-- well, let's
not just implement them as a list
of names and a list of numbers.
Wouldn't it be nice if C had a
data type actually called person?
Because if it did, then I could go
about creating an array called--
using the pluralized form-- people--
containing my people in my phone book.
And maybe a person has
both a name and a number.
And therefore, we can kind
of keep everything together.
So how can I do this?
Well, what is a person?
Well, a person, really, in this
story is a person has a name.
And a person has a number.
So can we create a new data type that
maybe has both of these together?
Well, we actually can by
using one piece of new syntax
today, which is just this here.
Using what's called a struct, we
can create our own data structure
that actually has some structure in it.
It's not just one thing
like a string or an int.
Maybe it's two strings.
Maybe it's two ints.
Maybe it's one of each.
So a structure can be a variable that
contains any number of other variables,
so to speak.
And typedef is a cryptic
keyword that just
means define the following type--
invent the following data type for me.
And the syntax is a little weird.
But you say typedef struct curly brace.
Inside of the curly braces,
you put all of the types
of variables you want to
associate with this new data type.
And then after the curly
brace, you invent the name
that you want to give it.
And this will create a new
data type in C called person,
even though no one
thought of this decades
ago when C was created alongside of
the ints and the floats and so forth.
So how can I actually use this?
Well, it turns out that
once you have this building
block of creating your very own data
structures, I can go back into my code
and improve it as follows in
direct response to your concern
about it seeming not ideal that we're
decoupling the names and the numbers.
Now, it's going to look a little
more complicated at first.
But it will scale better over time.
So within my code here,
I'm going to go ahead
and essentially type out
exactly that same data type.
So define a structure that has inside
of it a string called name and a string
called number.
And let's call this thing a person.
So these new lines copied and pasted
from the slide a moment ago just
invent the data type called person.
So the only thing we need
today is the syntax via which
we can set a person's name and number--
like, how can we access those values.
So to do this, I'm going to go ahead
and erase the hard-coded arrays
that I had before.
And I'm going to give myself one
array of type person called people
with room for three people.
So this seems like a bit of a mouthful.
But the new data type is called person.
The array name is called people,
which in English is weird.
I mean, it could call it persons
to make it a little more parallel.
But we call them people, generally.
And I want three such
people in my phone book.
Now, how do I actually
initialize those people?
Well, previously, I did something
like this-- names, bracket, 0.
And then I did numbers, bracket, 0.
Well, it's a similar idea.
I do people, bracket, 0.
But if I want to set this person's
name, the one new piece of syntax today
is a period, a literal dot operator,
that says go inside of this person
and access their name field
or their name attribute.
And set it equal to,
quote, unquote, "Carter."
Then go into that same person.
But go into their number field.
And set that equal to
plus 1, 617-495-1000.
Then-- and I'll just
separate it with white space
for readability-- go
into people bracket 1.
Set their name into mine, David.
Let's go into people bracket 1 number.
Set that equal to the same, since we're
both available through the directory,
so 617-495-1000.
And then lastly, let's go ahead and
do people bracket 2 dot name equals,
quote, unquote, "John," and then people
bracket 2 dot number equals, quote,
unquote, "plus 1, 949-468-2750--
let me fix my dash--
semicolon.
And now I think I can mostly keep
the rest of the code the same
because if I'm searching
for this person's name,
I think the only thing I want to change
is this because I don't have a names
array anymore.
So what should I change this
highlighted phrase to in order
to search the ith person's name?
What should this be?
Yeah?
People bracket i dash name because
the whole point of this loop
is to iterate over each of
these people one at a time.
So people bracket i gives me the ith
person-- first [INAUDIBLE] people 0,
people 1, people 2.
But if on each iteration, I
want to check that person's name
and compare it against
whatever the human typed in,
now I can do exactly that.
But I have to change the output
to be people bracket i dot number,
in this case.
So I've added a little
bit of complexity.
And granted, this is not going to be the
way long term you create a phone book.
Odds are, we're going to get the
phone book with a loop of some sort.
We're going to use a constant, so I
know how many people I have room for.
For demonstration sake, I'm just
typing everything out manually.
But I think logically now,
we've achieved the same thing.
So let me do make phone
book for this new version--
no syntax errors-- dot slash phone book.
Let's search for Carter-- enter.
And there indeed is his number.
Let's go ahead and search for David.
There's my number.
And lastly, let's search for John--
his number.
And again, we'll search for
someone we know is not there--
Eli.
And Eli is not found.
So what we've done is try to solve this
problem of introducing a brand new data
type that allows us to represent
this custom data that you and I just
created.
And that is by using the struct keyword
to cluster these things together
and the typedef keyword to give it
a brand new name that we might like.
Now, as an aside, when it
comes to styling your code,
you'll actually see that style50
and similar tools will actually
put the name of the data type on the
same line as the closing curly brace,
just sort of a curiosity.
That's fine.
Even though I wrote it the
first way for consistency
with Scratch and our prior examples,
this is the right way in styling it.
Any questions now on this data type?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: The
question is, do you have
to assign both the name and the
number when creating a person?
Or can you only get away
with assigning one of them?
You can.
But that's going to be one of those
so-called garbage values, typically.
And so there's just going
to be some bogus data there.
And unless you are so careful as to
never touch that field thereafter,
you probably run the risk of some kind
of bug, even a crash in your code,
if you try to access that value
later, even though you've never
initialized it.
So yes, it's possible.
But no, do not do that.
Other questions?
No?
All right, well, now
that we have the ability
to sort of represent more
interesting structures, up until now,
we've sort of assumed that in
order to get to binary search,
we have a phone book that
someone already sorted for us.
For our second demonstration
with our volunteers,
we assumed that someone,
Carter in that case,
had already sorted the
information for us.
It was proposed by the
audience that, well,
what if we sort the information
first and then go find the number 50?
That invited the question even early
on-- well, how expensive is it to sort?
How much time and money and inefficiency
do Google and Microsoft and others
spend to keep their data
and our data sorted?
Well, let's consider what
the problem really is.
If this is how we represent
any problem, the unsorted data
that we might consume by typing
things in randomly to a search engine
or crawling the internet or just adding
context in any old order to our phone
is arguably unsorted.
It's certainly not
alphabetically sorted by default.
But we want to get it sorted.
And so somewhere in here in this
black box, we need a set of algorithms
for actually sorting
information as well.
For instance, if we have
these integers here unsorted--
72541603-- effectively random,
the problem of sorting, of course,
is to turn it into 01234567 instead.
And there's a bunch of
different ways to do this.
But before we do that, I think it's
probably time for some brownies.
So let's go ahead and
take a 10-minute break.
And we'll see you in 10.
All right, we are back.
And where we left off
was this cliffhanger.
We've got some unsorted numbers.
We want to make them sorted.
How do we do this?
And at the risk of one
too many volunteers,
could we get eight more volunteers?
Wow, OK, overwhelming.
OK, how about 1, 2, 3, 4.
How about all three of you?
OK, 5, 6, 7--
OK, 8.
Come on.
All right, one from each section--
all right, come on down.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
DAVID MALAN: All right, come on down.
Thank you.
And if you all could grab a number here.
So you'll be 7.
Stand on the left there if you could.
All right, you'll be number 2.
Stand to his left.
OK, keep coming.
OK, yeah.
OK, here we go.
There you go.
OK, [INAUDIBLE] 0 and 3.
OK, so let's just make sure
they match what we've got there.
Good so far.
OK, so we have eight volunteers here,
an array of volunteers, if you would.
This time, we've used
eight rather than seven.
We deliberately had seven lockers
just so that the divide by 2 math
worked out.
That was very deliberate that there
was always a [INAUDIBLE] a middle,
a middle, a middle.
In this case, it doesn't matter because
we're going to focus on sorting.
But first, how about some
introductions from each group?
AUDIENCE: I'm Rebecca.
I'm a first year in Pennypacker.
And I'm thinking about
studying environmental science
and public policy.
[CHEERING]
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
[APPLAUSE]
AUDIENCE: I'm [? Mariella. ?]
I'm also in Pennypacker.
I'm a first year.
And I'm thinking of
studying bioengineering.
DAVID MALAN: Wonderful.
AUDIENCE: My name's [? Haron ?]
[? Li. ?] I'm a freshman in Matthews.
I'm planning on studying
applied mathematics.
DAVID MALAN: Nice-- Matthews.
AUDIENCE: My name is Emily.
I'm a first year in Canada.
And I'm still deciding what to study.
DAVID MALAN: Fair.
AUDIENCE: My name's [? Tanai. ?]
I'm a first year from Toronto.
And I'm planning on
studying ECON and CS.
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
AUDIENCE: My name is Teddy.
I'm a first year in Hurlbut.
And I'm planning on concentrating in
computer science with linguistics.
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
AUDIENCE: Yeah!
[APPLAUSE]
AUDIENCE: My name's [? Lenny. ?]
I'm a first year in Matthews.
And I'm planning on
concentrating in gov and CS.
DAVID MALAN: Ah, nice.
[CHEERING]
[APPLAUSE]
And?
AUDIENCE: My name is Eli.
I'm a first year in Hollis.
And I plan on concentrating in CS.
DAVID MALAN: Eli, we keep
looking for you today.
OK, so if you guys could scooch
a little bit this way just
to be a little more centered.
Notice that this array of
volunteers is entirely unsorted.
So we thought we'd do
three passes at this.
Could you all sort yourselves
from smallest to largest?
Go.
All right, that was very good.
So yes, so, sure.
OK.
[CHEERING]
[APPLAUSE]
And let's see.
What was your algorithm?
AUDIENCE: I just kind
of found the person that
was, like, one lower or one higher.
So I looked at him.
He had 2.
So I knew I had to be on his left.
And then she had 3.
So I told her to come to my right.
And then I knew he had 5.
DAVID MALAN: OK, nice-- pretty clever.
And how about your algorithm?
AUDIENCE: Same thing-- looked for
the number that was lower and higher
and found the middle.
DAVID MALAN: OK, interesting, because
I think from the outside view,
it all seemed very organic.
And things just kind of worked
themselves out, which is fine.
But I dare say what you guys did
was probably a little hard for me
to translate into code.
So let me propose that we
take two passes at this.
If you could reset yourselves
to be in that order from left
to right, which is just the exact
same sequence, just so that we're
starting from the same point each time.
[INAUDIBLE]
Very good.
All right, so let me propose this.
We can approach sorting in
a couple of different ways.
But it needs to be methodical.
Like, it needs to translate ideally
to pseudocode and eventually code.
So as much as we can quantize
things to be step by step,
I think the better this
will scale overall,
especially when there's not eight people
but maybe there's 80 people or 800.
Because I dare say that if we had
everyone in the room sort themselves--
if they were all handling a number--
like, that probably wouldn't
have worked out very well.
It probably would have taken forever
because there's just so much more data.
So let's be a little more methodical.
So for instance, I don't have a
bird's eye view of the numbers
just as before because
even though we don't
have doors in front of our volunteers,
they're effectively lockers too.
And the computer or the human in my case
can only look at one door at a time.
So if I want to find the
smallest number and put it
where it should go on
the left, I can't just
take a step back and be like,
OK, obviously, there's the one.
I have to do it more methodically.
So I'm going to check here--
7.
At the moment, this is actually
the smallest number I've seen.
So I'm going to make mental note of it.
OK, 2 I see now.
I can forget about the 7
because 2 is clearly smaller.
5-- I don't need to remember it.
4-- I don't need to remember it.
1-- OK, that's clearly smaller.
Have I found my smallest number?
Not even because there actually is a 0.
So I should go through the whole list.
But I will remember that my
smallest element is now 1.
6 is not smaller-- oh, 0 is
smaller, so I'll remember this.
3 is not smaller.
And so now, our volunteer
for 0-- what was your name?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Mariana, and where
should we put you clearly?
So there.
But what's your name again?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Eli's in the way.
So we could have Mary Ellen?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: [? Mariella ?]
just go to the right of Eli.
But that's kind of cheating, right?
Because if this is an array,
recall that they are contiguous.
But there could be other stuff in
memory to the left and to the right.
So that's not quite fair.
We can't just have the luxury of
putting things wherever we want.
But Eli, you're not even
in the right order, anyway.
So why don't we just swap you two.
So [? Mariella ?] and Eli swap.
But now I've taken one
bite out of this problem.
I've coincidentally
made it a little better
by moving Eli closer to where he is.
But you know what?
He was in a random location, anyway.
So I don't think I made the
problem any worse, fundamentally.
Now I can do this again.
And I can shave a little
bit of time off of it
because I don't need to revisit
[? Mariella ?] because if she
was the smaller and I've already
selected her from the array,
I can just move on and take one
fewer bites this time around.
So 2 is the smallest
number, not 5, not 4.
OK, 1 is the smallest number.
So I'm going to remember that as
with a mental variable- 6, 7, 3.
OK, 1 is the smallest.
So let me select number 1.
And we're going to have
to evict you, which
is making the problem slightly worse.
But I think it'll average out.
And now 0 and 1 are in the right place.
So now let me do this again but faster.
So 5-- OK, 4--
2 is the smallest--
6, 7, 3.
OK, 2, let's put you where
you belong, evicting 5.
Now I can skip all three
of these volunteers.
OK, 4, is the smallest.
Nope.
3, you're the smallest.
Let me evict 4.
All right, and now let me move
in front of these volunteers.
5, 6, 7, 4, come on back.
All right, and now let's select 6, 7, 5.
OK, come on back.
Oh, no, no cheating, Eli.
OK, and then let's see.
5, 7, 6-- OK, 6, come on back.
OK, now you have to move.
OK, and now we've selected in turn
all of the numbers from left to right.
And even though that did feel slower--
I was doing it a little more
verbally as I stepped through it--
but I dare say we could translate
that probably more to code.
Why?
Because there's a lot of,
like, looping through it
and probably a lot of conditionals
just asking the question,
is this number smaller than this one or
conversely greater than this other one.
All right, let's do this one more time.
If you guys could reset
yourselves to this ordering.
All right, so we again have 72541603.
Good.
So how about this?
I liked the intuition
that they originally
had, funny enough, whereby
they just kind of organically
looked to the person to
the left and to the right
and kind of fixed the problem.
So if they were out of order, they
just kind of swapped locally adjacent
to each other.
So let's try this.
So 7 and 2, you're clearly out of order.
So let's swap just you two.
7 and 5, you're out of order.
Let's swap you two.
7 and 4, let's swap you two.
7 and 1, let's swap you two.
7 and 6, let's swap you two.
7 and 0, swap you two.
7 and 3, swap you two.
OK, that was a lot of swapping.
But notice what happened.
I'm not done, clearly.
It's not sorted yet.
But I have improved the situation.
How?
Who is now definitely
in the right place?
So, 7-- or Eli has wonderfully bubbled
all the way up to the top of the list,
so to speak.
Now I can actually skip
him moving forward.
So that takes one bite
out of the problem.
Let's do this again.
2 and 5 are OK.
5 and 4, let's swap.
No, over there.
[LAUGHS] Thank you.
5 and 1, let's swap.
5 and 6 are good.
6 and 0, let's swap.
6 and 3, let's swap.
And we don't have to worry about Eli.
And now, what's your name again?
AUDIENCE: [? Haron. ?]
DAVID MALAN: [? Haron-- ?] we don't
have to worry about him either as well.
So now I can go back to the beginning.
And even though it feels like
I'm going back and forth a lot,
that's OK because the problem's
still getting better and better.
I'm taking a bite out of it each time.
2 and 4 are good.
4 and 1, let's swap.
4 and 5 are good.
5 and 0, swap.
5 and 3, swap.
And now these three
are in the right place.
Let's do it again.
2 and 1-- ah, here we go.
Let's swap.
2 and 4 are OK.
4 and 0, swap.
4 and 3, swap.
Now, these four are OK.
1 and 2, you're good.
2 and 0, swap.
2 and 3, you're good.
You're good.
OK, now 1 and 0, swap--
1 and 2 and now 0 and 1.
A round of applause if we
could for our volunteers.
[APPLAUSE]
[CHEERING]
So if you want to put your
numbers on the tray there,
we have some lovely Super
Mario Oreos today, which
maybe drives a lot of the volunteerism.
But here we go.
Thank you all so much.
And maybe, Carter, if you
can help with the reset?
All right, here we go.
[INAUDIBLE] yes, all set.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thank you, guys.
Thank you, yes.
To recap, let's actually formalize
a little more algorithmically
what we did.
And I deliberately kind
of orchestrated things
there to show two fundamentally
different approaches, one
where I kind of selected the
element I wanted again and again
on the basis of how small it was.
I looked for the smallest, then
the next smallest, and so forth.
The second time around, I
took a different approach
by just fixing local problems.
But I did it again and
again and again until I
fixed all of the minor problems.
And frankly, what they did
organically at the beginning
was probably closer to the
second algorithm than the first,
even though I'm not sure they would
write down the same pseudocode for it.
The first algorithm we executed
is actually called selection sort.
And I deliberately used
that vernacular of selecting
the smallest element again and again
to evoke this name of the algorithm.
So for instance, when we had these
numbers here initially unsorted,
I kept looking again and again and
again for the smallest element.
And I don't know a priori what
the smallest number is until I
go through the list at least once.
Then I can pluck out the 0.
I then go through the list a second
time to pluck out the 1, a third time
to pluck out the 2.
Now, this assumes that I don't
have an infinite amount of memory
because even though I kept repeating
myself looking for the next smallest
element, next smallest
element, I propose that I only
keep track of one number at a time,
one variable in my mind, which
was the smallest element
I have seen thus far.
If I used more memory, I could
probably remember from the first pass
where the 2 is, where the 3 is.
But that's a different algorithm.
And it would take more
space, more memory.
I was confining myself to just
one variable in my approach.
So here might be the pseudocode
for what we'd call selection
sort, the very first algorithm that
we all did together, not organically,
but more methodically as a group.
I would propose that we use some syntax
from C when we talk about the loop
and say for i from 0 to n minus 1.
Now, why is that?
Well, if there were n
people or 8, 0 through 7
are the indexes or indices of those
humans on stage from left to right.
So what did I have myself do?
Find the smallest number between
numbers bracket i and numbers bracket
n minus 1.
So when the loop starts
at 0, this is literally
saying between numbers bracket
0 and numbers bracket n minus 1.
So from the far left to the far
right, find me the smallest number.
Then swap that number
with numbers bracket i.
So that's why we evicted
the person all the way
over to the right or your
left the very first time,
and then the next person, and
the next person, and so forth.
So this is an algorithm that has us
go back and forth, back and forth,
iteratively selecting
the smallest element.
So if we generalize this now, not away
from eight people to, like, n people,
you can think of them as
representing an array, a.k.a.
doors like this where the leftmost one
is 0, the rightmost one is n minus 1,
second to last is n minus 2, and
so forth if we don't know or care
what n specifically is.
So how many total steps does
selection sort perhaps take?
And let's make this a
little more real here.
Let me actually open up, for
instance, a quick visualization here.
And on the screen here,
you'll just see now
an artist's rendition of an array
of values whereby tall purple bars
represent big integers.
And short purple bars
represent small integers.
So the idea of any sorting
algorithm here as visualized
is to get the small bars on the
left and the big bars on the right.
And this is a nice handy tool
that lets you play around
with different algorithms.
So here is selection sort
that I've just clicked.
In pink again and
again is the equivalent
of me walking through the volunteers
looking for the next smallest element.
And as soon as I found them, I swapped
them into their leftmost location,
evicting whoever's there
in order to gradually sort
this list from left to right.
And so as you can see here,
it holds very briefly in pink
whatever the currently smallest
element it has found is.
That's the analog of, like,
me pointing to my head
whereby it's constantly
comparing, comparing, comparing,
looking for the next smallest element.
Now, I'm kind of stalling because
I'm running out of intelligent words
to say.
But that is to say, this
algorithm feels kind of slow.
Like, it seems to be
doing a lot of work.
Where is the work coming in?
Like, what is it doing
a lot of specifically?
Yeah?
Yeah, it keeps going back
and forth and back and forth.
And even though it's shaving
a little bit of time,
right, because it doesn't have
to stupidly go all the way back
to the beginning, and I was
saving myself a few steps,
like, it's a lot of cyclicity
again and again and again.
And put another way, it's a lot
of comparisons again and again.
And some of those comparisons
you're doing multiple times
because I only remembered one
element at a time in my head.
So I have to kind of remind
myself on every pass which
is smallest, which is smallest.
So this invites the question how
fast or how slow or equivalently
how efficient or inefficient
is something like bubble--
selection sort.
Well, let's actually consider how
we could analyze this as follows.
So if we have n numbers
that we want to sort,
how many comparisons do
we do the first time?
Well, if there's n numbers, you can
only make n minus 1 comparisons.
Why?
Because if we have
eight people here and we
started with whoever's
all the way over here,
we compare this person against
seven others-- n minus 1 if n is 8.
So the first pass through the
list, I made n minus 1 comparisons.
But that put the smallest
number 0 in place.
The second time I walked
across our eight volunteers,
I didn't need to walk
in front of all eight.
I could shave off a little
bit and do seven of them,
then six, then five, then four.
So if I were to write this
out roughly mathematically,
I could do this-- n minus 1 plus
n minus 2 plus n minus 3 plus
dot, dot, dot, all the way
down to my very last comparison
at the end of the list.
Now, this is the kind of thing
that typically in high school
you'd look at the back of
the math book or physics book
that's got a little cheat sheet for
all of the formulas that add up.
This series here, let me just
stipulate, adds up to this-- n times
n minus 1 divided by 2.
So no matter what n is, this
formula captures that series,
that summation of all of those values.
So that is how many steps
I took again and again
and again when implementing
selection sort for eight people.
So of course, let's multiply this out.
So this is like n squared
minus n all divided by 2.
Let's do it out a little bit more.
That's n squared divided
by 2 minus n over 2.
And now we're back into the
territory of running times.
Like, how many steps
does this algorithm take?
How many comparisons are we making?
Now, n squared seems
like the biggest term.
It's the dominant term.
In other words, as n gets
large-- not eight but 80 or 800
or 8,000 or 8 million-- squaring that
is going to make a way bigger difference
than just doing, like, n divided
by 2 and subtracting that off.
Similarly, just dividing even
this quadratic formula by 2,
like, yes, it's going
to halve it literally.
But that's kind of a drop in the bucket.
As n gets larger and
larger and larger, it's
still going to be a crazy big number.
So computer scientists would typically
wrap this in some big O notation
and say, OK, OK, selection sort
is on the order of n squared.
That's not a precise measurement.
But it's on the order of
n squared because it's
making so many darn comparisons, not
unlike everyone shaking everyone else's
hand like I proposed verbally earlier.
It's a lot of work to get that done.
So selection sort is on the
order of n squared steps.
And that's kind of a slow one.
That's what was at the
top of my cheat sheet
earlier when I proposed a ranking
of some common running times.
There's an infinite number of them.
But those are some of the common ones.
So can we do actually better?
Well, if bubble sort then is in big O--
sorry.
Sorry-- spoiler.
If selection sort is in
the order of n squared,
could we maybe get lucky sometimes?
Like, with selection sort, what
would the best case scenario be?
Well, the best case would be,
like, everyone is already sorted,
0 through 7.
And we just get lucky.
But does bubble sort--
[SIGHS]---- does selection
sort appreciate that?
Does selection sort take into account
whether the list is already sorted?
Not necessarily, because if you
look at the pseudocode even,
there's no special conditional in here
that says, if it's already sorted,
exit early.
It's just going to blindly
do this this many times.
And you can actually see
pseudocode-wise the n squared.
Notice that this line of pseudocode here
is essentially telling me to do what?
Do something n times
from 0 to n minus 1,
or equivalently, if you prefer
the real world, from 1 to n.
That's n times total.
But what are you doing
inside of this loop?
Well, every time you're
inside of this loop,
you're looking for the smallest element,
looking for the smallest element.
And that might take
you as many as n steps.
So another way to think about the
running time of this algorithm
selection sort is this loop is
telling you to do something n times.
This line is telling you to
do something n times as well.
And that's roughly n
times n or n squared.
It's not precise.
But it's on the order of n squared.
Unfortunately, if you're just
blindly doing that much work always,
even if you have any
number of doors, this
is going to end up being in
omega of n squared as well,
because even in the best case where
all of the numbers are already sorted,
there is nothing about the algorithm
called selection sort or even
my implementation thereof that would
have said, wait a minute-- like, I'm
done, and exit prematurely.
So selection sort is
in big O of and omega
of n squared as we've designed it.
And by coincidence, because
those boundaries are the same,
you can also say that it's
in theta of n squared.
No matter what, you're going to spend n
squared steps or n squared comparisons.
But that second algorithm that I
keep teasing called bubble sort,
and I deliberately used the word
bubble in my description of what
was happening because Eli, I
think was our first volunteer, who
kind of bubbled his way up all
the way to the end of the list.
Then number 6 did, then 5,
then 4, then 3, then 2, then 1.
All of the numbers kind
of bubbled their way up
being the bigger values to the right.
So bubble sort just does
something again and again
by comparing adjacencies,
comparing, comparing, comparing.
And then it does it again
and again and again.
So let's analyze bubble sort.
If, for instance, this was the original
array that we tried sorting before--
same exact numbers--
I was doing things like flipping the
7 and the 2, and then the 7 and the 5,
and then the 7 and the 4.
But that would only fix
minimally one number.
I then had to repeat
again and again and again.
So that one too felt like
it was taking some time.
So here's one way of
thinking about bubble sort.
Bubble sort pseudocode could say this.
Repeat the following n times.
And that's why I kept going
through the list again and again--
for i from 0 to n minus 2.
Now, this is a little weird, but
we'll get back to this-- from i
from 0 to n minus 2.
If the number at location i and
the number at location i plus 1
are out of order, swap them.
And then just repeat, repeat, repeat.
But we've never seen n minus
2 in pseudocode before.
Why is it n minus 2 and
not the usual n minus 1?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly,
because we're taking a number
and comparing it to the next one.
So you better not go
all the way to the end
and expect there to be a next
one at the end of the list.
So if we use these same numbers
here, even though they're
in a different order,
if this is location 0,
and this is location n
minus 1 always, if you think
of i as being my left hand, it's
pointing from 0 to 1 to 2 to 3
to 4 to 5 to 6 to 7.
If you get to the end, you
don't want to look at i plus 1
because that's pointing to
no man's land over here.
And you can't go beyond the
boundaries of your array.
But n minus 2 would be the second
to last element, as you know.
And that makes sure that
my left hand and right
hand stay within the
boundaries of the array
if left hand represents i and
right hand represents i plus 1.
So it's just to make sure
we don't screw up and go
too far past the boundary of the array.
But as implemented here, this too does
not take into account whether or not
the array is already sorted.
So technically, we can actually
do this n minus 1 times
because the last one you get for free.
It ends up being in place.
But even still, let's do
a quick analysis here.
If we've got n doors in total
from 0 on up to n minus 1,
bubble sort's analysis looks
a little bit like this.
Do the following-- n minus
1 times n minus 1 times.
Well, how did we get from that?
Let me back up to the pseudocode.
If this is the pseudocode
as I originally put it,
I then propose verbally a refinement.
You don't need to repeat yourself n
times again and again because again,
the last one bubbles up.
But by process of elimination,
it's in the right place.
So you can think of it
as just n minus 1 times.
How many times can you
compare i and i plus 1?
Well, you're iterating
from 0 to n minus 2.
And this is where the math
is going to get weird.
But that is n minus 1 steps also.
Why?
Because if you do it in the
real world starting at one,
this is saying from i
from 1 to n minus 1.
And then maybe it pops
a little more obviously.
This inner loop is
repeating n minus 1 times.
So outer loop says do the
following n minus 1 times.
Inner loop says do this
now n minus 1 times.
Mathematically, then, that's
n minus 1 times n minus 1.
Now we've got our old FOIL method.
So n squared minus n minus n plus 1.
Combine like terms gives us
n squared minus 2n plus 1.
But now let's think like
a computer scientist.
When n gets really large, we
definitely don't care about the plus 1.
When n gets really large, we probably
don't even care about the minus 2n.
It will make a mathematical
difference but a drop in the bucket
once n gets to be in the
millions or billions.
So this would be on the
order of what, similarly?
On the order of n squared as well.
So algorithmically, and actually,
we'll use a different term
now-- asymptotically-- asymptotic
notation is the fancy term
to describe big O and omega and theta
notation-- asymptotically bubble
sort is, quote, unquote,
"the same" as selection sort
in terms of its upper bound.
It's not 100% exactly the same.
If we get into the weeds of the math,
there are obviously different formulas.
But when n gets really large and
you plot the pictures on a chart,
they're going to look almost
the same because they're going
to be fundamentally the same shape.
So in our cheat sheet here, bubble
sort now is in big O of n squared.
But let me propose that
we make an improvement.
Here's our pseudocode earlier.
When might it make sense
to abort bubble sort early?
Like, when could you logically
conclude that I do not need
to make another pass again and again?
And remember what I did from left
to right over our volunteers.
I was comparing, comparing, comparing,
comparing and maybe swapping
people who were out of order.
So what could I do to
short circuit this?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
If I compare through the whole list
left to right and I make no swaps,
it stands to reason that
they're already ordered.
Otherwise, I would have swapped them.
And therefore, I would be crazy to
do that again and again and again.
Because if I didn't swap
them the first time around,
why would I swap them the second
time around if no one's moving.
So I can terminate the algorithm early.
So in pseudocode, I could
say something like this.
If no swaps, quit.
And I can do that inside
of the inner loop.
So once I make a pass through the people
and I say, hm, did I make any swaps?
If no, just quit because
they're not going
to move any further if they
didn't just move already.
So bubble sort then might
arguably be an omega of what?
In the best case, how few steps could
we get away with with bubble sort?
OK, it's not one.
But it is n.
Why?
Because I minimally need to go
through the whole list to decide,
did I make any swaps.
And logically-- and this will come up
a lot in the analysis of algorithms--
any question like, is this list sorted,
cannot possibly take only one step
if you've got n elements.
Why?
Because then you're just guessing.
Like, if you don't at least take
the time to look at every element,
how in the world can you conclude
logically that they're sorted or not?
Like, you minimally have to meet
us halfway and check every element.
So it's minimally in omega of n.
Constant time wouldn't even give
you time to look at the whole list
if there's n elements.
So that's the intuition there.
So we can't say anything about
theta notation for bubble sort
because it's different,
upper and lower bounds.
But we seem to have done better
asymptotically than selection sort.
In the worst case, they're just as bad.
They're super slow.
But in the best case, bubble
sort with that tweak--
that conditional about swapping--
might actually be faster for us.
And you'd want Google, Microsoft, your
phone, to use that kind of algorithm.
Let me go back to the sorting
demonstration earlier.
Let me re-randomize the array.
Small bars is small number.
Big bars is big number.
And let me click bubble sort this time.
And you'll see again, the
pink represents comparisons.
But now the comparisons are always
adjacent from left to right.
So this is pretty much doing with more
bars what I did with eight people here.
And you'll see that the
biggest elements, Eli
being the first one of
the humans, bubbled up
all the way to the right, followed
by the next largest, next largest,
next largest.
But here again you can visually see.
And with the number of words
I'm using to kind of stall here,
you can [? hear ?] that
this is kind of slow
because you're doing a lot of
comparisons again and again and again.
And you're making improvements.
So you're taking bites
out of the problem
but really only one bite at a time.
So I kind of feel this is going
to be like holding in a sneeze
if we don't finish this.
So I feel like we should
give you emotional closure
with getting this to finish.
Any questions in the meantime because
there's going to be no surprise.
It's going to be sorted.
This is bubble sort.
No?
All right, we're almost there.
It's going faster because the list
is effectively getting shorter.
And-- oh, OK, so that
then was bubble sort.
But both of these, I claim now,
are actually pretty inefficient.
They're pretty slow.
And my god, that was only
eight humans on the stage.
That was only, like, what,
40 or 50 bars on the screen.
What if we start talking about hundreds
or thousands or millions of inputs?
Like, those algorithms are
probably going to take crazy
long because n squared gets really big.
So can we do better than n squared?
Well, we can.
But let me propose that we introduce
a new problem-solving technique
that we've actually been using
already, just not by name.
In programming and in mathematics,
there's this idea of recursion.
And recursion is a description
for a function that calls itself.
A function that calls
itself is recursive.
So what do we mean by this?
Well, we've actually seen this already.
Here's the same pseudocode
for binary search earlier.
And binary search--
bi implying two-- went
either left or right or left
or right, halving each time.
So that was the division and conquering.
So this is the same pseudocode.
But notice that in my
pseudocode earlier,
I literally used the keyword search
inside of my definition of search.
So this is sort of one of those,
like, circular definitions.
Like, if this is a search
algorithm, how am I
getting away with using the word
search in the definition of search?
It's kind of when you get
reprimanded for using a word
to define a vocabulary word.
This is kind of like that because
this algorithm is calling itself.
This search function is calling itself.
Now, normally, if you were to
have a function call itself,
call itself, call itself, call itself,
it would just do that infinitely.
And presumably, it would go on forever.
Or the program or
computer would probably
crash because out of memory or something
like that-- more on that next week.
But there's a key detail,
a key characteristic
about this algorithm that makes
sure that doing the same thing again
and again is not crazy.
It's actually going to
lead us to a solution.
Even though I'm using
search here or search here,
what's happening to the size of the
problem for each of these lines?
What's happening?
Yeah?
It's being cut in half.
So even though I'm doing the exact same
thing algorithmically again and again,
I'm doing it on a smaller,
smaller, smaller input--
fewer, fewer, fewer doors--
fewer, fewer, fewer people.
And so even though I'm
doing it again and again,
so long as I have this so-called
base case, as we'll call it,
that just makes sure if there's
no doors-- you're done--
I can break out of what would
otherwise be an infinite loop of sorts.
All right, so those two lines
we've already kind of seen.
And actually, we saw this in week zero.
So this is the pseudocode for the
phone book example from week zero.
And you might recall that we
had these lines of code here.
And this is very procedural
or iterative where I literally
told you go back to line 3.
And we did that today when we
took attendance, so to speak.
With that third algorithm, you went
back to step 2 again and again.
That's a very iterative
loop-based approach.
But you know what?
I could be a little more
clever here too in week zero.
We just didn't want to get
too far ahead of ourselves.
Let me actually change these highlighted
lines to be more, succinctly,
search left half book,
search right half of book.
I can now tighten the code up.
So it's kind of a shorter algorithm.
But it's the exact same idea.
But on week zero, I very methodically
told you what I want you to do next.
But here, I'm sort of
recognizing that, wait a minute,
I just spent the past six lines
telling you how to search.
So go do more of that.
You have all of the logic you need.
So this too is recursive in the sense
that if this is a search algorithm,
the search algorithm is using a
search algorithm inside of it.
But here too, the phone book
was getting divided and divided
and divided in half again and again.
So recursion doesn't just
describe mathematical formulas.
It doesn't just describe pseudocode
or code-- even physical structures.
So we deliberately brought
back these bricks here today,
which are reminiscent, of course,
from Mario and Super Mario Brothers.
That pyramid, especially if
we get rid of the distractions
of the ground and the
mountains and so forth,
is itself recursive as a structure.
Now, why is that?
Well, here you can kind
of play verbal games.
If this is a pyramid of height 4--
and ask the question, well, what is
that-- what is a pyramid of height 4--
I could kind of be difficult
and say, well, it's just
a pyramid of height 3 plus 1 other row.
All right, well, what's
a pyramid of height 3?
You could be difficult and say,
well, it's just a pyramid of height 2
plus 1 more row.
What's a pyramid of height 2?
Well, it's this plus 1 more row.
I might have skipped a step there.
What's a pyramid of height 2?
Well, it's a pyramid of
height 1 plus 1 more row.
What's a pyramid of height 1?
Well, it's nothing plus 1 more row.
Or at this point, you can
just say it's a single brick.
You can have a base case that just
says, like, the buck stops here.
Stop asking me these questions.
I can special case or hard code my
answer to the very tiniest of problems.
So even those bricks then are sort of--
the pyramid is recursively defined.
And we can actually
implement this even in code
if we want in a couple of
different ways to make this clear.
So let me go back over to VS Code here.
And let me propose that we do one
old-school iterative example with
this--
code iteration dot C.
And iteration just means
to loop again and again.
An iteration is a pass through the code.
And let me go ahead and
whip this up as follows.
Let's include the CS50 library.
So we have our get int function.
Let's include standard io
so that we have printf.
Let's go ahead and create main with
no command line arguments today.
Let's go ahead and create
a variable of type int set
equal to the return
value of get int asking
the user for the height of the pyramid.
And then let me assume
for the sake of discussion
that there is a function now that
will draw a pyramid of that height.
All right, now let's actually implement
that function as a helper function,
so to speak.
So if I have a function called draw,
it's going to clearly take an integer.
And I'll call it, maybe, n as input.
And it doesn't need to return anything.
So I'm going to say that
this is a void function.
It doesn't return a value.
It just has a side effect of
printing bricks on the screen.
How can I go about doing
a pyramid of height n?
Well, I'm going to do this one, which
looks like this-- one at a time,
then two, then three, then four.
And this is a little
easier, for instance,
than problem set one, which had the
pyramid flipped around the other way.
So this one's a little
easier to do deliberately.
So if I go back to my code, I could say
something like this-- for int i gets 0.
i is less than, let's say,
n, which is the height--
i plus, plus.
That's going to essentially iterate over
every row of the pyramid top to bottom.
This might feel similar--
reminiscent-- to problem set one.
Then in my inner loop,
I'm going to do four.
int j gets 0.
j is less than i plus 1 j plus, plus.
And we'll see why this
works in a moment.
And then let's go ahead and print
out a single hash, no new line.
But at the very bottom of this row,
let's print out just a new line
to move the cursor down a line.
Now, I'm not done yet.
Let me hide my terminal for a second.
I need the prototype.
So I'm going to copy this, paste
it up here with a semicolon.
And I think now the code is correct.
Now, why is this correct?
Because on my outer loop, I'm
iterating n times starting at 0.
My inner loop-- realize I want
to have at least one hash,
then two, then three, then four.
So I can't start my
number of hashes at 0.
And that's why I'm doing j all the way
up to i plus 1 so that when i is 0,
I'm actually still printing one hash,
and then two hashes, and then three.
Otherwise, I would start
with 0, which is not my goal.
Let me go in and do make
iteration to compile this--
dot slash iteration.
And let me go ahead and
make my terminal bigger--
enter.
The height will be, for instance, 4.
And indeed, it's not quite to scale
because these are a little more
vertical than they are horizontal.
But it essentially
looks like that pyramid.
And I can do this even larger.
Let's do this again
after clearing my screen.
Let's do like 10 of these.
And it gets bigger.
Let's do, like, 50 of these.
And it gets even bigger.
It doesn't even fit on the screen.
But it works.
And that's an iterative
approach, 100% correct,
and similar to what you might
have done already for something
like week zero or week one.
But it turns out if
we leverage recursion,
we can be a little more clever, in fact.
Let me go ahead and do this.
Let me minimize my terminal window.
And let me go back into my code here.
And let me propose to implement the
exact same program recursively instead.
And let me go ahead and do this.
I'm going to leave main--
let's see-- exactly as is.
And I'm going to go ahead and change
my draw function to work as follows.
Let me delete all of these
loops because loops are sort
of an indication of using iteration.
And I'm instead going to do this.
What is a pyramid of height 4?
I said it's a pyramid of
height 3 plus 1 more row.
So let's take that literally.
If a pyramid of height
n needs to be drawn,
let's first draw a pyramid of n minus 1.
And then how do I go about
drawing one more row?
Well, this, I can use
a bit of iteration.
But I don't need a
doubly-nested loop anymore.
I can set i equal to 0, i
less than n, i plus, plus.
And this block of code
is simply going to print
one simple row of hashes again and
again followed by a new line just
to move the cursor down.
So notice this line here.
And I'll add some comments--
print pyramid of height n minus 1,
print one more row.
So I'm kind of taking a bite out
of the problem by printing one row.
But I'm deferring to, weirdly, myself,
to print the rest of the pyramid.
Now I'm going to go ahead and
try compiling this-- make--
oh.
And this is no longer iteration.
So I'm actually going to do
this-- code recursion dot c.
I'm going to paste that same
code into this new version,
just so we have a different file
without breaking the old one.
And now I'm going to do make recursion.
All right, interesting.
So Clang is yelling
at me with this error.
All paths through this
function will call itself.
So Clang is actually smart
enough to notice in my code
that no matter what, the draw function
is going to call the draw function.
And the draw function is going
to call the draw function.
And the draw function's going
Now, to be fair, n, the input to
draw, is getting smaller and smaller.
But what's going to happen
eventually to the input of draw
as I've written this code right now?
Yeah, in the back?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Remember that integers
are signed by default.
They can be both positive
or 0 or negative.
And so here, if I just
keep blindly subtracting 1,
it's going to do that seemingly
forever until I technically underflow.
But that's going to be like 2
billion rows of pyramids later.
So I think what I actually need
to do is something like this.
I need to ask the
question, if n equals 0--
or heck, just to be super safe, let's
say if n is less than or equal to 0,
just to make sure it never goes
negative, let's just go ahead
and return without doing anything.
So I'm going to comment this as,
like, if nothing to draw, well, then
don't blindly call draw again.
So this is that so-called base case.
This is analogous to saying, like,
if John Harvard not in phone book
or if no lockers or doors left, then
just exit or return in this case.
So now I'll never call draw
a negative number of times
or zero number of times.
I will only do it so
long as n is positive.
So now if I make my terminal bigger,
make recursion again does compile fine.
Dot slash recursion-- let's
do the same input for.
And I get the exact
same number of bricks.
Let's go ahead and do
it again with maybe 10.
That seems to work too.
Let's do it again with 50.
And I can go a little crazy.
I can do, like, 5,000.
This is still going to work.
It's just not going to fit on my screen.
But it is doing a valiant attempt
to print all of those out.
Now, it turns out that
could get us in trouble
if we start poking around in the--
now, maybe not 5,000 but 500,000 or 5
million or beyond.
But for now, we'll just assume that
this is just a slow process at that.
But if we go back to the goal,
which was to print this thing here,
this too is a recursive structure
that we're just now translating
the ideas of recursive code to.
And actually, if you've
never discovered this,
we would be remiss in
not doing this for you.
If I go into a browser here.
And suppose that I'm not
using any AI fancy technology.
I'm just going to Google.com.
And I search for recursion because
I'm curious to see what it means.
Google for years has had this little
Easter egg for computer scientists.
It's not a typo.
Get it?
Ha, ha, kind of funny.
Yeah?
OK, like, see?
Recursion-- so if you click
recursion, OK, now we're
in night mode for some reason.
But OK, like, so it just
does this endlessly.
OK, so programmers with too
much free time or too much
control over Google's
own servers to do that.
So it turns out, yes, if you
search for recursion on Google,
this is a long-standing
Easter egg in this case.
But the point of
introducing recursion is
that, one, it's actually going to be a
very powerful problem-solving technique
because honestly, it, one, we've
seen in pseudocode already,
it kind of tightens up the amount
of code or the amount of lines
that you need to write
to convey an algorithm.
And two, it will actually
allow us to solve
problems in a
fundamentally different way
by using computer's memory
in an interesting way.
And so toward that end, we wanted to
introduce one final sort today, which
we won't use humans to demonstrate
but just numbers instead, namely
something called merge sort.
And merge sort is an algorithm
for sorting n numbers that I claim
is going to be better than
selection sort and bubble sort.
It's got to be better because
that n squared was killing us.
We want to get something
lower than n squared.
So merge sort's pseudocode
essentially looks like this.
And this is it.
Merge sort says, if you've got n
numbers or an array of numbers,
sort the left half of them,
sort the right half of them.
And then merge the sorted halves.
And we'll see what this
means in just a moment.
But if there's only
one number, just quit.
So this is my base case
because this is recursive.
Because if this is a sorting
algorithm called merge sort,
I'm kind of cheating by using the
verb sort in the sorting algorithm.
But that just makes it recursive.
It doesn't make it wrong.
So what do I mean by merging?
Just to make this clear, here among
these numbers are two lists of size 4.
And I'm going to scooch them
over to the left and the right
just to make clear that on the
left is one half that is sorted--
1346 from smallest to largest.
On the right is a second
half that's also sorted 0257.
So for the sake of
discussion, suppose that I'm
partway through this
algorithm called merge sort.
And I've sorted the left
half already, clearly.
I've sorted the right
Now I need to merge the sorted halves.
What do we mean by that?
Well, that means to
essentially, conceptually,
point your left hand at
the first at the left half.
Point your right hand at the right half.
And then decide which of these
numbers should come first
in order to merge or kind of
stitch these two lists together
in sorted order.
Well, which is smaller?
Obviously, 0.
So that last step, merge sorted
halves, would have me take this number
and put it in an extra
empty array up here.
Now I move my right hand to the
next number in the right half.
And I compare the 1 and the 2.
Obviously, 1 comes next.
So I put this now up here.
Now I compare the 3 and the 2.
Obviously, the 2 comes next.
And so I put this up here--
3 and 5-- obviously, 3--
4 and 5-- obviously, 4--
6 and 5-- obviously, 5--
and 6 and 7-- obviously, 6.
And I didn't leave quite enough
room for 7, perhaps, and lastly, 7.
So that's all we mean by
merging two lists together.
If they're already sorted,
you just kind of stitch them
together by plucking from one
or the other the next number
that you actually want.
And that's it.
And even though I picked up
partway through this algorithm,
those three steps alone
would seem to work.
So long as you can sort the left
half and sort the right half,
you can surely then
merge the sorted halves.
Now I'll go ahead and do this digitally
rather than use the physical numbers
because clearly, it's a little
involved moving them up and down.
But this rack here, this
shelving, essentially
represents one array with
maybe a second array here.
And heck, if I really want it,
a third and a fourth array.
It turns out that with
selection sort and bubble sort,
we've really been tying
our hands because I only
allowed myself a constant amount of
memory, just one variable in my head,
for instance, with selection
sort that let me keep
track of who was the smallest element.
And when we did bubble sort,
the only number I kept in mind
was i, like i and i plus 1.
I didn't allow myself
any additional memory.
But it turns out in
programming and in CS, you
can trade off one resource for another.
So if you want to spend
less time solving a problem,
you've got to throw space at it.
You've got to spend more
space, spend more money,
in order to give yourself more
space to reduce your time.
Conversely, if you're fine with
things being slow in terms of time,
then you can get away
with very little space.
So it's kind of like
this balance whereby
you have to decide which is
more important to you, which
is more expensive for you, or the like.
So let's go ahead then and consider
exactly this algorithm as follows.
So suppose that these are
the numbers in question.
So here is our array.
It's clearly unsorted.
I'd like to sort this.
I could use selection sort.
But selection sort was not great
because it's big O of n squared.
And it's omega of n squared,
so sort of damned if you do.
Damned if you don't.
Bubble sort was a little better.
It was still big O of n squared.
But sometimes, we could get
lucky and shave some time off.
So it was omega of only n.
Let's see if merge sort
is fundamentally better.
And let's do so by trying to reduce the
number of comparisons-- no more looping
back and forth and back and forth
and back and forth endlessly.
So here's how we can draw inspiration
from the idea of recursion and divide
and conquer as per week zero.
Let's first think of these
numbers as indeed in an array
contiguously from left to right.
Let's then go ahead
and sort the left half.
Because again, the
pseudocode that you have
to remember throughout this whole
algorithm has just three real steps.
Sort the left half.
Sort the right half.
Merge the sorted halves.
And then this is sort
of a one-off thing.
But it's important.
But this is the juicy part.
Sort left half.
Sort right half.
Merge the sorted halves.
So if we go back to this array on the
top shelf, here's the original array.
Let's go ahead and sort the left half.
And I'm going to do so by sort
of stealing some more memory,
so I can sort of work on a second
shelf with just these numbers.
So 6341 is now an array
of size 4, essentially.
How do I sort an array of size 4?
Well, I've got an algorithm
for that-- selection sort.
But we decided that's slow.
Bubble sort-- that's slow.
Wait a minute.
I'm in the middle of
defining merge sort.
Let's recursively use the
same algorithm by just
sorting the left half of the left half.
So if you've got an array of size 4,
it's only three steps to solve it.
Sort left half.
Sort right half.
Merge.
So let's do that.
Let's sort the left half.
OK, wait a minute.
How do you sort an array of size 2?
I've got an algorithm for that.
Sort the left half.
Sort the right half.
Merge the two halves.
All right, let's sort the left half.
What now?
So 6 is a list of size 1.
What was that special base case then?
So it was quit or just return.
Like, I'm already done.
So this list of size 1 is sort
of weirdly already sorted.
So I'm making progress.
Meanwhile, what's the next step
after sorting this left half?
Sort the right half.
Done.
This is already sorted.
But here's the magic.
What's the third step for these numbers?
Merge them.
So this is like the left
hand, right hand thing.
Which one comes first?
Obviously, 3 and then 6.
And now we are making progress because
now the list of size 2 is sorted.
So what have I just done?
I've just finished sorting the
left half of the left half.
So after I've sorted the left half,
what comes next if you rewind in time?
Sort the right half of that left half.
So now I take the right half.
And how do I sort this
right half of size 2?
Well, sort its left half.
Done.
Sort its right half.
Now merge them together.
And obviously, the 1
comes first, then the 4.
Now where are we?
We're at the point in the story
where we have a left left half
sorted and a right left half sorted.
So what comes next now narratively?
Merge the two together, so
left hand, right hand, so 1346.
And where are we now in the story?
We're sort of at the beginning
because I've now sorted the left half.
And you recall the demo
I did physically, this
is how I had the left half was
already sorted on the second shelf.
But now that I've sorted the left
half of the original array, what's
the original second step?
Sort the right half.
So it's the same idea.
So I'm borrowing some extra memory here.
And now I've got an array of size 4.
How do I sort an array of size 4?
Sort the left half.
All right, how do I
sort an array of size 2?
Sort the left half.
Done.
Sort the right half.
Now what?
Merge the two together.
And of course, it's 2 and 5.
Now what do I do?
I've sorted the left
half of the right half.
So now I sort the right
How do I sort a list of size 2?
Well, sort the left half.
Done.
Sort the right half.
Merge them together-- 0 and 7.
Where am I in the story?
I've sorted the left half and the
right half of the original right half.
So I merge these two together--
0 and then 2 and then 5 and then 7.
Whew.
Where are we?
We're at exactly the point in the
story where we had the numbers
originally on the second shelf.
We had a list that's sorted on the
left, a list that's sorted on the right.
And what I demoed physically
was merging those two together.
So what happens now?
01234567.
And it seems kind of magical and kind
of weird in that I kind of cheated.
And when I had these leaves--
these leaf nodes, so to
speak-- these singletons--
I was, like, sorted.
I wasn't really doing anything.
But it's that merging that
seems to really be doing
the magic of sorting things for us.
So that felt like a mouthful.
And recursion in general
is the kind of thing
that will, like, bend
your brain a little bit.
And if that went over your
head, like, that's fine.
It takes time and time
and time and practice.
But what there was not a lot of with
this algorithm was again and again
and again and again.
I was kind of only doing things once.
And then once I fixed a
number, I moved on to the next.
And that's sort of the essence
of this algorithm here.
If it helps you to see
it in another visual way,
let me go back to our
previous visualization here.
Let me re-randomize the
array and click merge sort.
And this time, notice that
merge sort is using more space.
Technically, I was
using 1, 2, 3 shelves.
But you can actually be slightly
more intelligent about it
and actually just go back and forth
and back and forth between two shelves
just to save a little space.
So you're still using
twice as much space.
But you don't need four times
as much space as the diagrams
or as the shelves might imply.
So here is merge sort.
And you'll notice that we're sort
of working in halves-- sometimes
big halves, sometimes smaller halves.
But you can see as the
two halves are merged,
things seem to happen very quickly.
And so notice that this is the
same number of bars as before.
But that was way faster, right?
I don't need to stall nearly
as much as I have in the past.
So why is that?
Well, if we go back to
the diagram in question,
here's the array that's already sorted.
And if we consider now
exactly how much work is done,
I'll stipulate already it's not
n squared. n squared was slow.
And merge sort is actually
much better than that.
Let's see how much better it is.
So here is the original list--
63415270.
And here are all of the remnants of
that algorithm, all of the states
that we were in at some point-- sort of
leaving a whole bunch of breadcrumbs.
How many pieces of work did I do?
Well, like, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9,
10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19,
20, 21, 22, 23, 24.
So I moved things around,
like, 24 times, it seems.
And how do I actually reason about that?
Well, these are the numbers.
This is like my
temporary workspace here.
And 24 is the literal number.
But let's see if we can't do
things a little more generically.
Log base 2 of n, recall,
is what refers to anything
that we're doing in half--
dividing, dividing, dividing.
And that's kind of
what I was doing here.
I took a list of size 8-- divide it
into two of size 4, then four of size 2,
then eight of size 1.
Well, how many times can you do this
if you start with eight numbers?
Well, that's log base 2 of 8.
And if we do some fancy math, that's
just log base 2 of 2 to the third.
And remember, the base and the
number here can cancel out.
So that's actually 3.
So log base 2 of 8 is 3, which
means that's how many times you
can divide a problem of size
8 in half, in half, in half.
But every time we did that per this
chart, I had to take the numbers
and merge them together, merge
them together, merge them together.
And so on every row of this
postmortem of the algorithm,
there are n steps, n steps, n steps.
So laterally, there's n steps because
I had to merge all of those things
back together.
But what is the height
of these yellow remnants?
Well, it's 3, which is log
base 2 of 8, which is 3.
So this is technically three
times 8, ergo 24 steps.
But more generally, this is log n
height and n width, so to speak.
So the total running
time I claim is actually
n log n, which it's OK if that doesn't
quite gel immediately in your mind,
especially if you're
rusty on algorithms.
But and we can throw away the base
because that's just a constant factor
and with a wave of our hand when we
talk about big O notation, merge sort,
I claim is in big O of n log
n-- that is, n times log n.
Unfortunately, it is
also in omega of n log
n, which means that, frankly, bubble
sort might sometimes outperform it,
at least when the inputs are already
sorted or certainly relatively small.
But that's probably
OK because in general,
data that we're sorting
probably isn't very sorted.
And honestly, we could
even half merge sort
to just do one pass to check
initially, is the whole thing sorted,
and then maybe terminate early.
So we can maybe massage the algorithm
a little better to be a little smarter.
But fundamentally, merge
sort is in theta of n log n,
is how you would say it.
It's on the order of
n times log n steps.
Now, in terms of that chart,
it's strictly higher than linear.
But it's strictly lower than quadratic--
n and n squared, respectively.
So it clearly seems to be faster.
So it's not as good as linear search.
And it's definitely not
as good as binary search.
But it's way better than selection
sort or bubble sort actually were.
So with that said, we
thought we'd conclude
by showing you a final
film that's just about
a minute long that compares these actual
algorithms and shows them as follows.
You'll see on the top, the middle, and
the bottom, three different algorithms.
On the top, you will see selection sort.
On the bottom, you will see bubble sort.
And in the middle, you will see and hear
an appreciation of what n log n is--
a.k.a., merge sort today.
So if we could dim the
lights dramatically,
this is n log n vis a vis n squared.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[END PLAYBACK]
All right, that's it for CS50.
We'll see you next time.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]