[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
This is CS50.
This is week 2 wherein we will
ultimately learn how to use memory,
but we thought we'd first
begin with a bit of story time.
And in fact, allow me to walk
over to our brave volunteers who
have joined us already.
First here on my left, we have who?
AKSHAYA: Hi, I'm Akshaya.
I'm a first year in
Mathews, and I'm planning
on concentrating in chemical
and physical biology and CS.
DAVID MALAN: Wonderful, welcome.
And let me have you hang
on to the microphone
first because we've asked
Akshaya to tell us a short story.
So in your envelope, you have
the beginnings of a story.
If you wouldn't mind reading it aloud.
And as she reads this, allow us
to give some thought as to what
level Akshaya reads at, so to speak.
AKSHAYA: All right, it's
a long one, get ready.
One fish, two fish, red fish, blue fish.
DAVID MALAN: All right, very well done.
What grade level would you say
she reads at if you think back
to your middle school,
grade school, when
maybe teacher said you read at this
level or maybe this level or this one
here?
So OK, no offense taken yet.
AUDIENCE: 1st grade.
DAVID MALAN: I'm sorry?
DAVID MALAN: 1st grade.
OK, so first grade is just about right.
And in fact, according to one
algorithm, this text here,
one fish, two fish, red
fish, blue fish, would indeed
be considered to actually be 1st
grade or just before first grade.
So let's-- and why is that, though?
Why did you say 1st grade?
AUDIENCE: It's very basic.
DAVID MALAN: It's very basic.
But what is it about these
words that are very basic?
Do you want to identify yourself?
AKSHAYA: Sure.
They're all one syllable and they're
very simple like colors and stuff
like that.
DAVID MALAN: Spot-on.
So like they're very short words
they're very short sentences.
And you would expect
that of a younger person.
All right, let's go ahead and hand
the mic to your next volunteer
here if you'd like to
introduce yourself.
ETHAN: Yes.
Hi, I'm Ethan.
I'm a first year in Canada, and
I'll be concentrating in economics.
DAVID MALAN: Wonderful.
And in your folder, we have
another story to share.
ETHAN: Congratulations.
Today is your day.
You're off to great places.
You're off and away.
DAVID MALAN: So this text might
sound familiar, particularly
on the heels of high school, perhaps.
What grade level might he be reading at?
So maybe 5th grade.
And why 5th grade?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK.
Yeah.
So a little more complicated.
Like the words-- we've got some more
punctuation, we have an apostrophe,
we have longer sentences.
And indeed, according to one
algorithm, not quite 5th grade,
but we would adjudicate your
reading level to be 3rd.
But let's see if we can't
do one final flourish here
if you'd like to introduce
yourself and your story.
MIKE: Hi, I'm Mike.
I'm also a first year.
I'm in Weld, and I'm
planning on concentrating
in biomedical engineering.
DAVID MALAN: Welcome.
And your tale?
MIKE: It was a bright, cold day in
April and the clocks were striking 13.
Winston Smith, his chin nuzzled
into his breast in an effort
to escape the vile wind, slipped
quickly through the glass doors
of victory mansions,
though not quickly enough
to prevent a swirl of gritty dust
from entering along with him.
DAVID MALAN: All right,
so escalated quickly.
And someone's guess
at this reading level?
AUDIENCE: 1984.
DAVID MALAN: What's that?
Oh, OK, 1984 is indeed the
text in question, and in what
grade did you perhaps read that book?
So I'm hearing 8th, I'm hearing 10th.
So indeed, 10th grade is what a
certain algorithm would actually
adjudicate that reading level to be at.
And consider now the heuristics.
So we started with very small words,
very small sentences, very easy words,
and then things sort of escalated
into more interesting, more
sophisticated English, more interesting
sentence construction and the like.
So I bet if we could somehow capture
those characteristics of text,
the length of the words and
the lengths of the sentences
and the position of the
punctuation, I daresay,
even using week 1 material
and, today, week 2 material,
we'll be able to actually write code
and implement an algorithm like that
can take these spoken
words, put them to paper,
and actually analyze roughly
what that reading level might be.
So that's just a teaser
of what lies ahead.
For now, allow us to thank
our volunteers, each of whom
gets a wonderful parting
gift here to read at home.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
And Thank you all so much.
So with that said, there's another
domain that we'll explore this week,
and indeed, what you'll
find in the coming weeks
is that beyond just focusing on some
of the fundamentals and the basics
like we've really done in the past
couple of weeks talking about loops
and conditionals and
Boolean expressions,
really building blocks or puzzle
pieces that we can assemble together,
we're going to increasingly
start talking about applications
of these ideas which, after
all, is why any field is perhaps
important and applicable.
So here, for instance, we'll consider
not only reading levels today,
and in turn, in problem set 2 this week,
but also the world of cryptography,
which is the art, the science
of scrambling, encrypting
information, and
ciphering it in such a way
that you can send a message securely
through the internet, through the air,
through any medium even though
someone might intercept it.
Ideally, thanks to
cryptography, they shouldn't
be able to decrypt it or actually
determine what it there says.
So for instance, if you were to receive
a message like this, at first glance,
it's indeed a bit cryptic.
Three words maybe, but
by day's end, we'll
have decrypted even
this message for you.
So up until now, though, we've had some
sort of conceptual training wheels on.
And I gave us this picture last week
when we introduced the tool make via
which you can make programs out of your
source code because you need to turn
that source code into machine
code, the 0's and 1's.
And in the middle here was
this thing called a compiler.
But it really has been kind
of an abstraction for us,
and we've sort of had these
metaphorical and physical training
wheels here in the sense
that we haven't really
needed to care like what the compiler
is doing, how it works and so forth.
But today, what we thought we'd do
is peel back a bit of that layer so
that even though after
today you'll continue
to be able to use commands
like make and sort of return
to the beautiful abstraction
that is not caring about some
of these lower-level
details, we'll offer you
a glimpse of how some
of these things work.
Because so that inevitably
when something goes wrong,
you've got some bug,
you're having some problem,
you'll have a bottom-up understanding
of what it could actually be.
And indeed, these basics,
you'll find, will very often
help you troubleshoot problems and
really solve problems more generally.
So here, for instance, is the
code that we keep coming back to.
And this code here is the simplest of C
programs that just says "hello, world."
This is the source code.
This, we claimed, was the
corresponding machine code.
And it was that program
called a compiler that
converted one into the other.
But let's dive a little
more deeply this week
into what we mean by compiling code.
Like what is happening
so that by day's end,
nothing really feels like magic anymore.
It's not just that it goes from
source code to machine code
and that's that, you understand
what's actually being done for you,
and frankly, what other humans
have done over the decades to make
make as beautifully abstract and as
simple as it now might seem to be.
So here are a couple
of commands that you've
been in the habit of running when
you want to first compile your code
and then execute your code.
But it turns out that make is actually
running another command for you.
The first of several white
lies we'll tell in the course
is that make itself is
not a compiler, per se.
It's actually a program that
automatically runs a compiler for you.
And by that, I mean this.
Let me go over to VS Code here and let
me create our familiar hello.c program.
And I'm going to go ahead and do include
stdio.h, int main void, and inside
of the curly braces, printf "hello,"
comma, "world," backslash n semicolon.
So that's the code that we
keep writing again and again.
And up until now, if I wanted to
compile that, I would do make hello
dot slash hello, and voila,
now my program is made
and it actually executes.
But what's actually going
on underneath the hood
there is that make is running
an actual compiler for you,
and the reveal today is that
the compiler we have been using
is something called
Clang for C language.
And this is just another
program whose purpose in life
is actually to do the conversion
of source code to machine code.
But it turns out that
Clang by itself can
be used very simply like
you see here, clang hello.c,
but it doesn't behave nearly as
user-friendly as you might like.
So in particular, let
me go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead and
remove my compiled program
by running rm for remove, which
I alluded to briefly last time.
And then I'm going to say y for
yes, remove that regular file.
And if I go ahead now and run just
clang of hello.c and hit Enter,
it seems to be successful, at least
insofar as there's no error messages.
But if I try to do dot
slash hello, Enter,
there is no such file or
directory called hello.
That is because by default,
Clang somewhat goofily like just
outputs a file name called a dot out.
Like why a?
Well, it's sort of a simple name. a dot
out, technically for assembler output,
but this just means
this is the default file
name that Clang is going to give us.
So OK, it turns out I can do dot
slash a dot out Enter, and voila,
that now is my program, but that's
just a stupid name for a program.
It's not very user-friendly.
It's certainly not an
icon you would want
to put on people's desktops or phones.
So how can we do better?
Well, it turns out, with Clang,
we can configure it using
what we'll call command line arguments.
And command line arguments are actually
something we've been using thus far,
we just didn't slap this word on
it, but command line arguments
are additional words
or shorthand notation
that you typed at your
command prompt that somehow
modify the behavior of a program.
And you can perhaps guess
where this is going.
It turns out that if I actually want
to create a program called hello--
not a.out, which is the
default, I can actually
do this-- clang, space, dash
lowercase o, space, hello,
or whatever I want to call
the thing, space, hello.c.
And now if I hit Enter,
nothing seems to happen,
but now if I do ./hello and Enter,
now I've actually got that program.
So why is make useful?
Well, it just saves us
the trouble of having
to type out this longer
line of command any time
we actually want to compile the code.
But in fact, it gets
even worse than that
with commands like clang
or compilers in general
because consider this code here.
Not just the version of "hello, world,"
but maybe the second version wherein
last week, I started to get user
input by adding the CS50 Library using
get_string and then saying,
"hello," comma, "David."
Well, if I go back to VS Code
and I modify this program
to be that same one--
so let me go ahead and
include cs50.h at the top.
Let me get rid of this simple
print line and instead give myself
a string called name equals
get_string, "What's your name?"
Question mark, just
like we did in Scratch.
Then I can do printf,
quote-unquote, "hello," comma.
And previously I typed "world."
I obviously don't want to type "David"
because I want it to be dynamic.
What did I type last week
for as a placeholder?
So yeah, just-- not Command-S,
but %S. So %S in this case,
which is a placeholder
for any such string.
Then I can still do my new line,
close, quote, comma, and then
I can substitute in something like
the value of the name variable.
All right, so if I go
ahead now and compile this,
now last week, I could just do
make hello and I'm on my way,
it worked just fine.
But if I instead do clang
manually, it turns out
that this is not going to be sufficient
now. clang -o hello, space, hello.c.
Exact same thing I typed
a moment ago, but I
think I'm going to see some errors.
So what's this error hinting at here?
Well, at the very bottom, it's
a bit arcane with its output,
and much of this you can ignore, but
there are some certain key words.
What's the first maybe keyword
you recognize in these three
lines of erroneous output?
So it mentions main.
That's not that much of a clue because
that's the only thing I wrote so far.
Second line, though, get_string.
There's some issue with an
undefined reference to get_string.
Now why might that be?
I did include cs50.h,
but that's apparently not
enough to teach the
compiler about get_string.
Well, it turns out that if you're
using a third-party library, one
that doesn't necessarily come with C
the language, something like CS50's, it
turns out that you additionally
have to tell the compiler that you
want to use that library.
And not just by including
the header file,
but by an additional command as well.
So when you run Clang, you
want to provide an additional
rather command line argument.
Literally -l for library, which
is a term I used last week, cs50.
A library is just code
that someone else wrote
that you want to use in your project.
So if I really want to compile this
version that uses the CS50 Library,
I can still do clang o hello hello.c,
but before I finish my thought,
I need to tell the compiler to link,
so to speak, in the library CS50.
And now I hit Enter, the error
message goes away, I can do ./hello,
I can type in my name, and
voila, we're back to week 1.
And this is why, suffice it
to say, we introduce make,
which is not a CS50 thing.
This is a popular tool that
real people in the real world
use to automate these
kinds of processes.
So unbeknownst to you,
make has been using
the -o for you. make, unbeknownst to
you, has been using -l cs50 for you
just because it makes our lives easier.
But today, we thought
we would deliberately
peel back this layer so
we at least understand
what's going on behind this
abstraction that is make itself
and compiling more generally.
So let me propose that compiling
itself is not quite what
we've described it to be.
Compiling is like this catch-all
phrase that apparently I claim
goes from source code to machine code.
But if we really want to get
pedantic, which we'll do briefly,
but this is not a sign of things
to come because this, too,
will be abstract away, compiling is
just one of four steps that are involved
in turning source code that you
and I write into those 0's and 1's.
But through an understanding
of these four steps
today, you'll hopefully
better understand
how to troubleshoot issues
like that and just know
what's happening because
it's not, in fact, magic.
It's just the result of years of humans
developing these four steps here.
So when you run make, what's happening?
Or in turn, when you run clang,
four different things are happening.
And the first one is
called pre-processing.
So what is this all about?
Well, let's consider this code here.
And this code is a
little bit interesting
insofar as it's one of the more
complicated examples from last week.
And you'll notice, for instance,
that I had include stdio at the top
so I could use printf.
I had main down here, whose purpose
in life was just to meow three times.
And then recall we made our own meow
function just like we did in week 0
with Scratch that just printed
out, quote-unquote, "meow."
But I also included this line
here, which we called what?
This was a prototype.
And why did I have to include it there?
Or equivalently, what would happen
if I didn't include a prototype up
at the top there?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
If I didn't include it up here, the
program, when trying to compile main,
would not know what meow is because
it's not defined until later.
So this is kind of like a
little hint of what is to come.
Alternatively, we could just move this
whole thing up at the top of the file,
but I claim that just
devolves into a big mess
eventually once you have
many different functions.
Like you can't realistically put them
all at the top to solve this problem.
So these prototypes solve that problem.
So nothing new here.
Just a reminder of what motivated
this one line of prototype.
Now let's consider this
simpler program, which
is just the one we wrote
most recently in VS Code.
This program prompts
the human for their name
and then says hello to that person.
But it has two includes
at the top of the file.
And in fact, any line of C that
starts with this hash symbol
is what we'll call now a
preprocessor directive.
It's not really a word you need
to remember in your vocabulary,
but it is a little bit different
from most every other line
because it starts with that hash.
That's a special symbol in C.
And what this means is the following.
This very first line, cs50.h, is
indeed a file that I and CS50 staff
wrote and we installed somewhere in VS
Code for you, somewhere in the cloud.
And I've claimed you need to use this
header file in order to use get_string.
So just logically, what is
probably inside of cs50.h?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Function [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Super close.
So the function called get_string
that does the getting of a string,
but it's not quite as much
as the function itself.
It's actually a little bit less than
that, but you're on the right track.
What is inside of cs50.h, presumably?
Just a what?
Just a prototype for?
Which function?
get_string.
So admittedly, there's some
other stuff in there, too,
but the important line for today's
discussion is that inside of cs50.h
is indeed one line of code that
defines what the return value, what
the name is, and what the arguments,
if any, are to get_string,
and some other stuff.
And so what happens effectively
when you compile your code,
step 1 is this pre-processing line.
And essentially, there is some
code that someone else wrote inside
of the clang compiler that looks for
a line that starts with hash include,
and when it sees that, it goes and
finds this file and effectively copies
and pastes the contents of that
file right there into your code
so that you don't have
to go find the file,
copy and paste it, and make
a mess of your own code.
So in particular, it's effectively
as though you're copying and pasting
the prototype of get_string
to the very top of your file,
thereby teaching the
compiler that it exists.
By that same logic, what
is probably in stdio.h?
The prototype for?
For printf.
And indeed, exactly that.
So this line effectively gets
replaced with the equivalent
of the prototype for printf,
which, for today's purposes,
is a bit more complicated, so let
me wave my hand at the dot-dot-dot
just because it takes a
variable number of arguments
depending on how many placeholders
or format codes you have.
But effectively, that,
too, is what's happening.
So the preprocessor
step, step 1 of 4, just
does that find and replace, if you will.
Now there's some-- again,
some other stuff in that file,
and this, too, is kind
of a white lie. printf
probably has its own file because
that's a really big library,
but the essence of it is exactly this.
So preprocessing converts
all of those hash
include lines to whatever
the underlying prototypes are
within the file plus some other stuff.
Now compiling we use it as this
catch-all phrase, but it turns out,
it has a very specific
meaning that's worth
knowing about even
though after today, you
can go back to using compiling
as the sort of catch-all phrase.
So when you've got this same code
here after the pre-processing step
has happened.
So this is essentially happening
in the computer's memory.
It's not changing your hello.c file
permanently or anything like that.
This code gets, quote-unquote,
"compiled" into something
that looks more like this.
And this is a scarier language
that we won't spend time
on in this particular class.
This is what's known
as assembly language.
And back in the day,
before there was C, humans
wrote this to program their computers.
Similarly, before there was
assembly code back in the day,
humans very initially used what instead?
AUDIENCE: 0's and 1's.
DAVID MALAN: So 0's and 1's-- like
they actually wrote the machine code
painfully, be it in code or be it
in punch cards like physical objects
or the like.
So again, these are
sort of abstractions,
but we're rewinding for today in time.
But what this compiler for
C is doing is converting C
into this other language
called assembly language.
And even though this
looks very esoteric,
there's at least some
juicy things in here.
If I highlight get_string,
it's mentioned in this code.
printf is mentioned in this code.
And even some of these
keywords here that
are spelled a bit weirdly, this
relates to subtracting and moving
something in memory and calling
a function, calling a function.
So there's some semantics
that are probably
somewhat familiar even though this
is not code we ourselves will write.
But unfortunately, this
is not yet machine code,
and that's where step 3 comes in.
So step 3 of this four-step process
is technically called assembling.
And assembling just takes that assembly
code and converts it, thankfully,
to the thing we do care
about, the 0's and 1's.
So assembling takes assembly
code converts it to 0's and 1's.
As an aside, and I
alluded to this earlier,
the reason that Clang names its files
a.out by default, assembler output,
is a side effect of that being
one of the steps in this process,
dealing with assembly language
and its subsequent output.
All right, so here are some 0's
and 1's, but unfortunately, there's
still that fourth and final step, which
is a word that I also used earlier,
namely linking.
So let me take a step back
and look at this code here.
And even though this code is exactly
as I wrote in VS Code in hello.c--
so no copying and pasting,
no prototypes have
been plugged in here, this is
my code, technically, there's
three different files involved in
compiling even something relatively
simple like this.
There's obviously this thing
itself, hello.c, which I wrote.
There's apparently cs50.h, and
there's apparently stdio.h.
But technically-- and you don't have to
know this file name, per se, somewhere
else on the computer's
hard drive, so to speak,
is a cs50.c file,
which actually contains
the staff's implementation of
get_string and get_int and get_float
and all of those other functions.
Somewhere on the server's
hard drive is stdio.c
that implements printf and all
of these other functions as well.
So the dot c is just
inferred from the dot h here.
You don't ever mention the dot c file,
but someone else wrote those files,
someone else stored them
in the server for you--
CS50 staff in this case.
So technically, even when compiling
a relatively short program like this,
you're really combining three files
at least at the end of the day.
And I'll write them from
left to right. hello.c,
which I wrote, cs50.c, which the
staff wrote, and then stdio.c as well.
So somewhere there's these three files.
And Clang, our compiler,
needs to compile each of these
into the corresponding 0's and 1's.
Lastly, this is not yet sufficient
because these 0's and 1's haven't
been linked together.
I mean, I deliberately left a
gap here to imply that these
are three separately-compiled files.
So that fourth and final
step called linking
takes all of these 0's and
1's and an intelligent way
combines them into just one final
file named hello, named a.out,
whatever the file name is of choice.
So what you and I for the past week
have just been calling compiling--
and that's what a normal
person will use henceforth
to describe this whole
process, technically, there's
these four different steps
underneath the hood, each of which
is sort of a representative of an
evolution of technology over the years.
And nowadays, if we
fast forward a few weeks
in class, when we start
talking about Python, which
is another more modern language, that,
too, is going to be conceptually even
higher level, even though
underneath the hood,
there's going to be some
lower-level principles at work.
So any questions on just terminology
or these processes known as compiling?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: I didn't really
understand what compiling means.
[INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
Compiling, if I rewind, is the process
of taking your source code, which
looks like this, recall-- whoops, this,
and converting it into assembly code.
So preprocessing just
converts all of those hash
include lines and a few
others to their equivalents.
So that's step 1.
Compiling converts the C code
into the underlying assembly code.
The assembling step, step 3, converts
the assembly code to 0's and 1's.
And then the fourth
step, linking, combines
all of the 0's and 1's from the one,
the two, the three or more files
that are involved in your
project and links them
all together for you magically.
But at the end of the day, all of this
is happening automatically for you.
If I jump now to the end
here, whereby just by running
make, which, in turn, runs
clang for you, like all of this
is abstracted away.
But the key here is that even with
these commands that we've been running,
be it the make command
or the clang command,
everything should be explainable
what you are typing at the prompt
ultimately.
Each of those things has a purpose.
So any questions, then,
on what we've just
now called compiling even though
it's only when you take another CS
course that you might
spend more time on assembly
language or these lower-level details?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: A good question.
Are there other types of compilers?
Yes.
Back when I took CS50, I used a popular
compiler called GCC, the GNU Compiler
Collection, which still exists
actually in the code space
that you're using for CS50.
Clang is somewhat more recent.
It's gaining popularity.
And frankly, we use it in large
part because it's error messages
are slightly more user-friendly.
You might not believe us because if you
encountered some errors with your code
this past week, they were probably just
as arcane as the error messages I saw,
but it's better than
it was some years ago.
And there's alternatives
to compiling, too,
but more on that when we
get to Python as well.
Other questions?
No?
All right.
Well, what are the implications of the
fact that we're going from source code
to machine code?
Well, it stands to reason
that if you can compile code,
maybe you can decompile it-- that
is, go in the reverse direction.
Go from 0's and 1's
to actual source code.
Now that would be handy if you want
to go in as a programmer and change
something in a program that you
or someone else already wrote.
It's maybe not ideal for
your intellectual property,
though, if you are the person who
wrote that program in the first place.
If you are Microsoft and you
wrote Microsoft Word or Excel
that people with Macs and PCs and
phones have installed on their devices,
it doesn't actually sound very
appealing if any old customer
can take those 0's and 1's and
reverse them, reverse engineer them,
so to speak, into the
original source code
because then they can have their
own version of Microsoft Word
and make changes to it without
really having put in all of the R&D
that it might have taken to
build the first version thereof.
But it turns out that
reverse engineering--
so doing things in the
opposite direction-- is easier
said than done because there are
multiple ways, as you've seen already,
to implement programs.
Like loops alone, you can use for
loops, while loops, even do-while loops.
And so there's other ways--
there's multiple ways
to solve the same problem.
So even if you try to
reverse engineer a program
and convert machine code
back to source code,
there's not necessarily going
to be an obvious way to do so.
And the reality is, that it
ends up being such a mess
because you lose the
variable names typically,
you lose the function names typically,
that what you end up looking at
might very well be C code, but
it's completely difficult for you,
even a good programmer, to read.
And generally, the mindset is,
if you're really good enough
to decompile code in that
way and read it subsequently
even without good variable
names, good function
names, good documentation and the like,
could probably have just implemented
the program in the first place yourself
without jumping through those hoops.
So there's some
practicality pushing back
on what are otherwise potential threats
to, say, your intellectual property.
But that's not going to be the
case later on in the term when
we do get to languages like Python
to some extent, other languages
like JavaScript.
Some of those are actually
going to be readable by anyone.
Any of your customers,
any of your friends,
and your family that
actually use your programs.
So with that said, let's introduce
now another tool to our toolkit
that will hopefully
make some of the pain
from this past week
when you did encounter
bugs a little more manageable.
And indeed, part of the process
of writing code to this day
is debugging it.
And it is a rare thing
to write a program,
be it in C or any other language,
and get it 100% right the first time.
I mean, to this day, I still, 20-plus
years later, still write buggy code.
Hopefully a little bit less of it, but
any time you're adding a new feature,
any time you're doing
something for the first time,
you're not necessarily going to
see all of the possible mistakes.
So even in industry, bugs are
omnipresent, which is really to say,
having techniques to debug
code-- that is, eliminate bugs,
is super compelling.
Now just for a bit of history,
here is Admiral Grace Hopper,
who was actually in
not only the military,
but also on the faculty
of Harvard years ago
and worked on a Harvard
computer called the Harvard Mark
I, which is actually on display at
the School of Engineering and Applied
Sciences if you take a
tour over there sometime.
But also when working
on the Harvard Mark II,
she is known for having at least
popularized the phrase "bug" to mean
a mistake in a computer's program--
a mistake in a computer's code.
And the etymology of this
supposedly is this here logbook
wherein she and her colleagues were
documenting processes being computed
on computers, that a
moth actually got stuck
in one of the relays, one of the
mechanical-- the electric relays inside
of the very old now computer,
and someone very cleverly
wrote, "First actual
case of bug being found."
So it wasn't she who
actually discovered it,
but this was a story she was thereafter
fond of telling as a famed computer
scientist thereafter.
We now know bugs to be all too familiar
when it comes to writing our own code,
and I thought I would deliberately
write some buggy code based
on some of the programs with
which we experimented last week.
So let me go back over
to VS Code here and let
me propose that I do something somewhat
simplistic just like this to print out
a column of bricks of height 3.
So I'm going into VS Code and I'm
going to deliberately call this program
buggy.c because I intend
to do this poorly.
I'm going to include stdio.h as
before, int main void as before.
And in here, if I want to
print a pyramid of height 3,
I'm going to do 4 int i gets--
all right, I'm still new
to programming in my mind
here, so I know I'm supposed
to start counting at 0, OK.
And I want to do this until I count
up to 3, so I'm going to do that.
And then i++ I remember
from class in this way.
And now I might go ahead and print
out just a hash mark, backslash n,
which I do want because I want to
move this cursor to the next line
to make this vertical.
But of course, if you've noticed with
your eye already, when I do make buggy,
it compiles OK.
So no typos, no syntactical errors.
But when I run this, I'm
going to see how many bricks.
So four in this case.
Now this is meant to
be a simplistic example
so that we don't spend time trying to
figure out what the bug is, but rather,
focus on techniques for
actually identifying the bug.
So-- finding, rather, the bug.
So what's one of the first
tools in your toolkit?
Literally one you have
already. printf is your friend.
And it is a very quick and
dirty tool for just seeing
what's going on inside
of the computer when
you don't have more sophisticated
tools or even the time to use them.
And so in this case, for instance,
what I'd propose is that--
all right, I'm obviously
seeing four hashes.
And let me play a little slow here.
It'd be helpful for me to understand why
logically I'm ending up with four, even
though I'm starting at 0 like I remember
from class and I'm going up to 3
as we did in class, like I'm just not
seeing it in this particular story.
So what I would commonly do is go
into my code and just help me see
what's going on, and I might literally
write a printf line like, i is %i,
backslash n, comma, and then
just print out the value of i.
I just want to see on
every iteration, what
is i, what is i, what is i just to help
me see what the computer already knows.
So let me go ahead and recompile
buggy, let me rerun buggy,
and then let me make my
terminal window bigger
just to make clear what's going on.
And now it's a little more pedantic.
Now i is 0, I get a hash. i is 1,
I get a hash. i is 2, I get a hash.
Wait a minute. i is 3, I get a hash.
So clearly now, it should be
maybe more obvious to you,
especially if the syntax
itself is unfamiliar,
I certainly don't want
this last one printing,
or maybe equivalently, I don't
want the first one printing.
So I can fix this in a couple
of ways, but the solution,
the most canonical solution is
probably to do what with my code?
To change to what to what?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So change the less than or equal
sign to just a less than sign.
So even though this is like counting
from 0 to 3 instead of 1 through 3,
it's the more typical programmatic
way to write code like this.
And now, of course, if I do make buggy--
and I'll increase my terminal
window again, ./buggy,
now I see what's going
on inside of the code.
Now it matches my expectations,
and so now the bug is gone.
Now of course, if I'm
submitting this or shipping it,
I should delete the temporary printf.
And let me disclaim that using
printf in this way just to help you
see what's going on is
generally a good thing,
but generally adding a printf and a
printf and a printf and a printf--
like it starts to devolve into
just trial and error and you
have no idea what's going on, so
you're just printing out everything.
Let me propose that if you ever
find yourself slipping down
that hill into just trying
this, trying this, trying this,
you need a better tool,
not just doing printf.
And frankly, it's annoying to use printf
because every time you add a printf,
you have to recompile
the code, rerun the code.
It's just adding to the number of steps.
So let me propose
instead that we do this.
I'm going to go back
into VS Code here and I'm
going to write a different
program that actually
has a helper function, so to speak.
A second function whose
purpose in life is maybe just
to print that column for me.
So I'm going to say
this-- void print_column,
though I could call it anything
I want, and this function
is going to take a argument
or a parameter called
height which will tell it
how many bricks to print,
how many vertical bricks.
I'm going to do the same kind
of logic. for int i equals 0.
i is less than--
I'm going to make the same mistake
again-- less than or equal to height,
i++.
And then inside of this for loop, let
me go ahead and print out the hash mark.
So I've made the same
mistake, but I've made it
in the context now of a helper
function only because in main,
what I'd like to do now, just to be a
little more sophisticated is get int
from the user for the height.
And when I do get that int, I want
to store it in a variable called n,
but I do need to give that
variable a type like last week.
So I'll say that it's an integer.
And now, lastly, I can print_column,
passing in-- actually, I'll
call it h just because height is h.
Print column h, semicolon.
OK, so it's the exact same program
except I'm getting user input now.
So it's not just going to be 3,
it's going to be a variable height,
but I've done something stupid.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: I've done
two stupid things.
So this, of course, is not supposed
to be there, so I'll fix that.
And someone else.
What else have I done?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
I'm missing the prototype.
And this is, let me reiterate, probably
the only time where copy-paste is OK.
Once you've implemented
the function, you
can copy paste its first
line at a semicolon
so that it teaches the compiler
that this function will exist.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Three stupid things.
OK.
Thank you.
So, good.
Include cs50.h.
And now, anyone want to go for four?
No?
All right.
Slightly unintended here.
So let's see. make buggy.
OK, no syntax errors thanks to you all.
So the code compiles, but
of course, when I run buggy
and I type in something like 3 manually,
I'm still going to get 1, 2, 3 4 out.
So let me now introduce
a more powerful tool
that's generally known as a debugger.
And within the VS Code
environment that you're using,
we actually have a command that makes
it a little easier to use this tool,
but we didn't write the tool itself.
You are about to see a very graphical,
a very popular industry standard
tool called a debugger, but we'll start
the debugger using a CS50-specific
command called debug50, which just
makes it easier with a single command
to start the debugger without
having to configure a text
file with all of your preferred
settings and all of that.
It's just an annoying hoop
otherwise to jump through.
So what I'm going to do is
go back to my code here.
I have already compiled it,
but just for good measure,
I'll make buggy again because
the debugger needs your code
to be compiled.
It's not going to help
with syntax errors
like the stupid mistakes I
just made unintentionally,
it will help you though with
programmatic errors, logical errors
in your code once your code is running.
So to run debug50, I'm going to
do this. debug50, space, and then
the exact same command I would normally
run to just run the program itself.
So ./buggy.
So exact same thing, ./buggy,
but I prefix it now with debug50.
When I hit Enter, a whole bunch of--
another error is going to
pop up on the screen, which
is a good reminder because this
will happen to you, too, invariably.
It's reminding me that I have to
set what's called a breakpoint.
And as that word
suggests, it is the point
at which you want your code to break.
Not break in make the situation
worse sense, but rather,
where do you want to pause?
Execution, break, execution--
like hitting the brakes on a car
so the program doesn't run all at once.
And you can put this
any number of places,
and you might have
done this accidentally
if you've ever hovered
over the gutter of VS Code,
the left-hand side next
to your line numbers.
See the little red dot that appears?
If I click on any of these lines, that's
going to set a breakpoint, so to speak.
And I want to break execution at main.
So I'm just going to click to
the left of line 6 in this case.
That makes it a darker
red circle, a stop sign
of sorts that tells the debugger
to pause execution on that line,
though I could put it
elsewhere if I so choose.
Let me go ahead and rerun
debug50 ./buggy, Enter,
and now a bunch of things are
going to happen on the screen.
It's going to look a little
overwhelming perhaps at first glance,
but there's some useful
stuff that just happened.
So one, my code is still here, but the
line that I set the breakpoint on is--
rather, the first line
of actual executable
code at or below the breakpoint I set
is highlighted in this yellowish green
here, which says, this line of
code has not yet been executed.
We broke at this point, but if I
click a button, this line of code
will be executed.
Because up until now, every C program
you write runs as fast as that.
I want to pump the
brakes and pause here.
But notice a few other
aspects of the window here.
So notice that up here some weirdness.
There's mentions of variables
and we're familiar with these.
Local is a term we'll use this week.
But there's this variable
h, which weirdly,
where did the value 21912 come from?
So it turns out, in C, before you
initialize a variable with a value
by literally typing the number 3,
or by using a function like get_int,
it often contains what's
called a garbage value.
More on those in a couple of weeks.
But a garbage value
is you can think of it
as like remnants of whatever
was in the computer's memory
before you ran your program.
And that's a bit of
a oversimplification,
but you cannot trust that a variable
will have a certain value in this case
if you did not put one there yourself.
So for now, h is nonsensical.
It's a garbage value it means nothing.
But once I execute this line, it should
contain whatever the human types in.
All right.
Down here, there's a watch section,
which is a more sophisticated feature.
Down here is what's
called the call stack.
More on that in the future.
But what this means for now is that
I'm executing the main function, not,
for instance, print_column.
So notice up here, these are the most
useful controls within the interface.
If I hit this Play
button, it's just going
to actually run my program to the end
of it without bothering me further.
However, I can actually step over
this line of code and execute it,
or I can step into this
line of code and actually
poke around the contents of get_int
if it's available on the system.
So conceptually you can
either execute this line
or you can dive down conceptually deeper
and see what's inside of that function.
Lastly, this will let
you step out, this will
allow you to restart the whole process,
and this will just stop the debugger.
So these buttons are
going to be our friends.
And the one I'll click first
is the first one I described,
which is step over.
So step over doesn't mean, skip
this step, it just means execute it,
but don't bother me by going into the
weeds of what is on the specific line,
namely get_int.
So when I click this
button in a moment, you'll
see that my terminal, which is still
at the bottom, prompts me for a height.
I'm going to go ahead and type 3.
As soon as I hit Enter,
what part of the screen
probably will change
based on what I've said?
So h, the variable h should
hopefully take on the number 3.
And I'll probably see a
different line of code
highlighted, probably line 9 next
once I'm done executing line 8.
So let me go ahead and hit Enter and
watch the top-left of the screen.
And voila, h now has the value 3, and
execution has now paused on line 9
because the debugger is allowing me
to step through my code line by line.
Now let me go ahead and print out-- let
me go ahead and just say, all right,
I'm done with this.
Let's go ahead and run
the rest of the program.
It clearly got the value 3.
But wait a minute--
oh, and at this point,
it closed the window
in which I would have seen the output,
I would have still seen four hashes.
So let me actually do this again.
Let me go back into debug50 by
running the exact same command again.
It's going to think for a moment,
it's going to reconfigure the screen.
I'm going to do the exact same thing.
I'm going to step over
this line, but I'd
like to actually see what's going on
inside of my print_column function.
So this time, instead of
just saying run to the end
and close all the windows
on me, let me go ahead
and step into my print_column function.
So don't step over, step into.
Because if I step over--
and now this is what I
meant to show earlier,
you can see that it's
still printing out 4.
So in fact, let me undo this,
let me just stop the whole thing.
Let me rerun the command a final time.
So it goes back to
where we began before.
It's going to prompt me again once I
step over line 8 for a number like 3.
But this time, instead of stepping
over line 9, let's poke around.
I wrote print_column, so let's
look at print_column step by step,
step into it, and watch what
happens to the yellow highlight.
It now jumps logically to
the inside of print_column,
thereby letting me
walk through this code.
And now I can just step over each
of these lines one at a time.
So stepping over.
OK, so what did it do?
It did that whole narrative
that I did verbally last week
where it compared i against height.
It then went inside of the loop.
When I click Step Over, watch what
happens in my terminal-- one hash
prints out.
Now line 14 is highlighted again.
It's comparing per the
Boolean expression, i,
is it less than or equal to height?
If so, it's going to go
ahead and print out the hash.
It's going to do this
again, print out the hash.
But notice at the top-left
of the screen, height
is still the same, it's still 3, but
what has been changing, apparently?
i on each iteration.
So the debugger is letting me see what's
going on slowly inside of this loop
because i keeps getting incremented.
So if I step over this line now,
notice that I've now printed 3.
So ideally I want this loop to end,
but if I click Step Over once more,
notice that the value
of i at top-left is 3,
but 3 is less than or equal to height--
oh, now I get it, if I play along here.
Now I see why less than or equals to,
mathematically, is clearly incorrect.
And as soon as that light bulb
goes off, you can just sort of
bail out, click the red Stop
button to turn the debugger off,
go back in, fix your code,
and voila, recompile, run it,
and you're back in business.
So the takeaways here really
are just what tools now exist?
Printf is your friend, but only for
quick-and-dirty debugging techniques.
Get into the habit now of using debug50,
and in turn, VS Code's debugger.
You will invariably not
take this advice, say,
for problem set 2 as you
first begin because it's
going to feel easier and quicker just
to use printf, just to use printf,
just to use printf.
And the problem with
that logic is that you
begin to build up like
technical debt, so to speak,
where you really should
have learned it earlier,
you really should have
learned it earlier,
you really should have learned
it earlier, at which point,
you end up spending more
time wasted using printf
and doing things manually than
if you had just spent 10 minutes,
30 minutes just learning
the user interface
and the buttons of a proper debugger.
So please take that advice
because it will save you
significant amounts of time over time.
Questions on printf or
debugging in this way?
Any questions on this?
No?
OK.
So let me give you a third and final
technique for debugging, which has been
looming over us here for some time.
So there is actually this technique
known as rubber duck debugging.
And in the absence of a roommate who
is taking CS50 or who has taken CS50
or knows how to program, in the
absence of having a TF or TA or CA
sitting next to you, in the absence of
having a family member available to ask
questions of, if you have simply
an inanimate object on your desk,
goes the tradition, just talk
to that inanimate object.
Better yet, if it's an adorable
rubber duck in this way.
And the idea of rubber duck
debugging is that simply
by verbalizing literally out
loud to this inanimate object--
probably with the door
closed and no one knowing
that you're talking to this
rubber duck, you invariably
end up hearing any illogic in
your own thoughts, at which point
the proverbial light bulb tends to go
off and you're like, oh, I'm an idiot.
It's supposed to be less than,
not less than or equal to.
So literally just explaining to a
duck or any inanimate object what's
going on in your code
will quite frequently just
help you see in your mind's eye
what it is you've been doing wrong.
So rubber duck debugging is
indeed a very effective technique
even if you don't happen to have
a small or large rubber duck.
Of course, you're also welcome
to use the CS50 Duck who
lives at cs50.ai, and also within
a pane in VS Code at cs50.dev.
You can ask the CS50 Duck about
concepts you don't understand,
or you can even copy paste
certain lines of code
with which you might be having trouble
and ask the duck for its own advice.
All right.
So, with those tools in our toolkit,
let me propose now that we do--
that we introduce now a few
lower-level features of C
itself and better understand how we can
start solving some of those problems
like the readability of text
or the encryption of data.
These were our so-called
types last week when
we introduced at least a subset of
them or used them just to store data
in a certain format, so to speak.
Like in week 0, we said that
everything at the end of the day
is just 0's and 1's, binary.
And I claimed conceptually that how
a computer knows if a set of bits
is a number versus a letter versus a
color or a sound or an image or a video
is just context-dependent,
like you're using Photoshop
or you're using Microsoft
Word or something else.
But last week, we saw a little
more precisely that it's
not quite as broad strokes as that.
It's more about what the
programmer has told the software is
being stored in a given variable.
Is it an integer?
Is it a char, a character?
Is it a whole string?
Is it a longer integer or the like?
So you now have this control.
The catch, though, recall, though,
is that each of these types
has only a finite amount
of space allocated to it.
So for instance, an integer
is typically 4 bytes,
and 4 bytes is 32 bits
because it's 8 times 4.
32 bits, we claimed,
is roughly 4 billion,
but if you want to represent
negative and positive numbers,
the biggest integer you can
store is like 2 billion.
Now that's really big for
a lot of applications,
but years ago, Facebook,
for instance, was
rumored to be using integers
when they had fewer users.
But now that they have
billions of users--
3-plus billion users, an integer is no
longer big enough for the Facebooks,
the Googles, the Microsofts
and so forth of the world.
So we also have longs, which use
twice as many bytes, but exponentially
bigger range of values.
Meanwhile, a bool,
interestingly, is a byte, which
is kind of bad design in what sense?
Why might that be bad design?
It's only-- it should only be 2--
1 bit, rather, because
a 0 or 1 should suffice.
Turns out, it's just
easier to use a whole byte
even though we're wasting
seven of those bits,
but bools are represented
nonetheless with 1 byte.
Chars are going to be 1 byte.
Floats tend to be 4 bytes.
Doubles tend to be 8 bytes.
Some of this is system-dependent,
but nowadays on modern computers,
this tends to be a useful rule of thumb.
The only one I can't
commit to here is a string
because a string, recall,
is a sequence of text.
And maybe it has no characters,
one character, two, 10, 100.
So it's a variable number
of bytes presumably
where each byte represents
a given character.
So with that said, how do we
get from an actual computer
to information being
represented therein?
Well, let me remind us that this is
what's inside of our Macs, PCs, phones.
Even though this isn't a scale and
it might not be the same shape,
this is memory, random access memory.
And on these black chips,
on the circuit board
here, are the bytes that
we keep talking about.
In fact, let's go ahead and
zoom in on one of these chips,
fill the screen here.
And just for an artist's
depiction's sake,
let me propose that if
you've got, I don't know,
a megabyte, a gigabyte-- like a lot of
bytes packed into this chip nowadays,
it stands to reason that no
matter how many of them you have,
we could just number
them from top to bottom
and we could say that this
is byte 1, or you know what?
This is byte 0, 1, 2, 3, and this is
maybe byte 1 billion or whatever it is.
So you can think of
memory as having addresses
or just locations, numeric indices
that identify each of those bytes
individually.
Why a byte?
Individual bits are not that
useful, so 8, again, 1 byte
tends to be the de facto standard.
Let me-- so, for instance, if you're
storing just a single character,
a char, it might be stored literally
in this top-left corner, so to speak,
of the chip of memory.
If you're storing maybe
an integer, 4 bytes,
it might take up that many bytes.
If you're storing a long, it might
take up that many bytes instead.
Now we don't have to dwell on the
particulars of the circuit board
and these traces and all the
connections, so let me just abstract
this away and claim that what
your computer's memory really
is is just kind of this canvas, I
mean kind of in the Photoshop sense.
If you've ever made
pictures, it's just a grid
of pixels, up, down, left, right,
that's really all your memory is.
It's this canvas that you can manipulate
the bits on to store numbers anywhere
you want in the computer's memory.
So in fact, let's zoom in
here and let's consider
how your computer is actually storing
information using just these bytes.
At the end of the day, no
matter how sophisticated
your Mac, your PC, your
phone is, like this is all
it has access to for
storing information.
It's a canvas of bytes,
and what you do with this
now really invites design decisions.
So let's consider this.
Here is an excerpt from a
program wherein maybe I'm
prompting the user for three scores.
Like three test, scores, exam
scores, something like that.
And the purpose in life
of this program is maybe
to average those three
scores together if you
want to get a sense of where
you stand in some class.
So we can certainly whip
up some code like this.
And in just a moment, let me go
ahead and flip over to VS Code here.
And I'll write up a new
program called scores.c.
And in this, let me go ahead
and first include stdio.h,
int main void at the top.
And in here, let me go
ahead and assume that, eh,
it's not been the greatest semester.
So my first score, which
I'll call score1, was a 72,
my second score was a 73, but my
third score, score3, was like a 33.
Now you might remember these
numbers in another context,
they might spell a message, but
in this case, it's just integers.
It's just numbers because I'm telling
the computer to treat these as ints.
Now if I want to figure out what my
average is, I can do a bit of math.
So let me just print
out that my average is--
and I don't want to shortchange myself.
I'm not going to use %i because I
don't want to lose even anything after
the decimal point.
So we're going to use a float instead.
And my average i claim will be
score1 plus score2 plus score3
divided by 3, semicolon.
With parentheses, because
just like grade school math,
like order of operations, I
parenthesize the numerator,
so I can divide the whole thing by 3.
But I have screwed up already.
I am going to shortchange myself
and not give myself as high a grade
as I deserve, but this one's subtle.
What have I done wrong?
Yeah, I might want to cast
these scores to floats
because if you do integral math, divide
an integer or the sum of an integers--
some integers by an integer, it's
going to be an integer as the result,
so it's going to throw away
anything after the decimal point.
Even if it's something-point-1,
something-point-5, something-point-9,
that fraction is going
to be thrown away.
There's a bunch of ways to fix this.
I could just use floats or
doubles for all of these.
I could cast score1, score2,
or score3 as you propose.
Frankly, the simplest way is
just change the denominator
because so long as I've got
one float involved in the math,
this will promote the whole arithmetic
expression to being floating point
math instead of integer math.
So let me go ahead now
and do make scores, Enter.
So far, so good. ./scores, and
my average seems to be not great,
but 59.33333--
so in the third.
But I would have lost
that third if I hadn't
used a float in this particular way.
Well, let's consider now what's
actually going on inside of the computer
when I store these three variables.
So, back to the grid here,
just my canvas of memory.
It doesn't really matter
where things end up.
I might put it here,
I might put it there,
the computer makes these decisions.
But for the artist's sake, I'm going
to put it at the top left-hand corner
here.
So, score1 is containing the integer 72.
Why is it taking up
four squares, though?
Because?
It's an integer.
And on this system,
an integer is 4 bytes.
So I've drawn it to scale, if you
will. score2 is the number 73,
it also takes 4 bytes.
By coincidence, but
also by convention, it
will likely end up next
to the first integer
in memory because I've only got
three variables going on anyway,
so the computer quite likely will
store them back to back to back.
And indeed, by that logic,
score3, containing the number 33,
is going to fill in this space here.
We'll consider down
the road what happens
if things get fragmented--
something's here,
something's here, something's
here, but for now, we
can assume that this is probably
contiguous, though not necessarily so.
All right, so that's
pretty straightforward,
but what's really going on?
Well, these are just bytes of memory--
that is, bits of memory times 8.
And so what's really
going on is this pattern
of 0's and 1's is being
stored to represent 72.
This pattern of 0's
and 1's is being stored
to represent 73, and similarly, 33.
But that's a very low level detail
that we don't really care about,
so we'll generally just think about
these as numbers like 72, 73, 33.
All right.
So if we go back to the
actual code, though, here, I
wonder if this is the best idea.
These three lines of code are correct.
I got my 59 and 1/3 for
my average, which I claim
is correct, but code-wise, this
should maybe rub you the wrong way.
Even if you hadn't
programmed before CS50,
why might this not be the best
approach to storing things
like scores in a program?
How might this get us in trouble?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
It's not the best because
you have to use a whole bunch
of different variables for each score.
They're almost identically
named, though, but just imagine
in almost any question involving the
design of your code, what happens is n,
the number of things
involved, gets larger?
Am I really going to start writing
code that has score4, score5, score6,
score10, score20?
I mean, your code is just going to look
like this mess of mostly copy-paste
except that the number at the
end of the variable is changing.
Like that should make you cringe
a little bit because it's not
going to end well eventually.
And typographical errors are going
to get in the way most likely
because we'll make mistakes.
So how can we do a little
bit better than that?
Well, let me propose that we introduce
what we're going to now call an array.
An array is a sequence of values
back to back to back in memory.
So an array is just a chunk of memory
storing values back to back to back.
So no gaps, no fragmentation.
From left to right, top to
bottom, just as I already drew.
But these arrays in
C, at least, are going
to give a slightly new syntax that
addresses exactly your concern.
So here instead is I would propose
how you define a one variable--
not three, one variable called
scores, plural, each of whose values
is going to be an int, and you
want three integers tucked away
in that variable.
So now I can pluralize
the name of my variable
because by using square brackets and
the number 3, I'm telling the compiler,
give me enough room for not one, not
two, but three integers in total.
And the computer is going to do
me a favor by storing them back
to back to back in
the computer's memory.
Now assigning values to these
variables is almost the same,
but the syntax looks like this.
To assign the first value, I do
scores, bracket, 0 equals whatever, 72.
scores, bracket, 1 equals 73;
scores, bracket, 2 equals 33.
And it's square brackets consistently.
And notice, this is a feature--
or a downside of C.
We very frequently use the same
syntax for slightly different ideas.
This first line tells the computer,
give me an array of size 3.
These next three lines mean, go
into this array at location 0
and put this value there.
Location 1, put this value there;
location 2, put this value there.
So same syntax, but different meaning
depending on the context here.
But the equal sign indeed means
that this is assignment from right
to left just like last week.
So what does this mean
in the computer's memory?
Well, in this case here, we now have a
slightly different way of doing this.
And actually, let me
do it first in code.
Let me go back to VS
Code here, and let me
propose that instead of having
these three separate variables,
let me give myself an int,
scores variable of size 3,
and then do scores, bracket, 0 equals
72; scores, bracket, 1 equals 73;
scores, bracket, 2 equals 33.
And now I have to change this
syntax slightly, but same idea.
scores, bracket, 0; scores, bracket,
1; and lastly, scores, bracket, 2.
So a couple of key details.
I started counting at 0.
Why?
That's just the way it is with arrays.
You must start counting at 0 unless
you want to waste one of those spaces.
And what you definitely
don't want to do is
go into scores, bracket,
3 because I only
ask the computer for three integers.
If I blindly do something like
this, you're going too far.
You're going beyond the
end of the chunk of memory
and bad things will often happen.
So we won't do that just yet.
But for now, 0, 1, and 2 are the
first, second, and third locations.
So if I recompile this code-- so
make scores seems OK. ./scores,
and I get the exact same answer there.
But let me make it more
dynamic because this
is a little stupid that I'm compiling
a program with my scores hardcoded.
What if I have a fourth exam
tomorrow or something like that?
So let's make it more
dynamic and I think
the syntax will start to
make a little more sense.
Let's go ahead and use get_int
and ask the user for a score.
Let's go ahead and get_int and
ask the user for another score.
ask the user for a third score,
now storing the return values
in each of those variables.
If I now do make scores--
oh, darn it.
a mistake.
Similar to one I've made before, but we
didn't see the error message last time.
What'd I do wrong?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK.
What did I do wrong--
how about over here?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So I'm missing the CS50 header file.
So how do you know that?
Well, implicit declaration
of function get_int.
So it just doesn't know what get_int is.
Well, who does know what get_int is?
The CS50 Library, that should
be your first instinct.
All right.
Let me go to the top here and let me go
ahead and squeeze in the CS50 Library
like this.
Now let me clear my terminal.
make scores again.
We're back in business.
And notice, I don't need to do -l cs50.
make is doing that for me for clang, but
we don't even see clang being executed,
but it is being executed
underneath the hood, so to speak.
All right, so ./scores, here we go.
72, 73, 33.
Math is still the same, but now
the program is more interactive.
Now this, too, hopefully
should rub you the wrong way.
This is correct, I would
claim, but bad design still.
Reeks of week 0 inefficiencies.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK.
So I could ask the human how
many scores do you want to input?
Let's come back to that.
But I think even in this
construct, what better could I do?
Use a loop, right?
Because I'm literally doing
the same thing again and again.
And notice, this number
is just changing slightly.
I would think that a little plus-plus
could help there. get_int Score,
get_int Score, get_int Score--
that's the exact same thing.
So a loop is a perfect solution here.
So let me go over into this code
here, and I can still for now
declare it to be of
size 3, but I think I
could do something like this--
for int i get 0, i is less than 3,
so I'm not going to make the same
buggy mistake as I made earlier.
I++.
Inside of the loop now, I can
do scores, bracket, i, and now
arrays are getting really
interesting because you
can use and reuse them, but
dynamically go to a specific location.
Equals get_int, quote-unquote, "Score."
Now I can type that phrase just
once and this loop ultimately
will do the same thing,
but it's getting better.
The code is getting better
designed because it's more compact
and I'm not repeating myself.
72, 73, 33.
Still works the same, but we're
iteratively improving the code here.
Now how else-- there's one design
flaw here that I still don't love
it's a little more subtle.
Any observations?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Ah, interesting.
So instead of dividing by
3.0, maybe I should divide it
by the array size, which at the
moment is technically still 3,
but I do concur that that is worrisome
because they could get out of sync.
But there's something else
that still isn't quite right.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: I'm OK moving
to this zero-indexed model.
So this is a new term of art.
To index into an array means
to go to a specific location.
So here, I'm indexing into
location i, but i is going
to start at 0 and then 1 and then 2.
I'm actually OK with that.
Even though in common day life we
would say score1, score2, score3,
as a programmer, I just
have to get into the habit
of saying score0, score1, score2 now.
But something else.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: I could compute the average.
DAVID MALAN: I could also
compute the average in a loop
because indeed, this is only going--
so solving the problem halfway.
I'm gathering the
information in the loop,
but then I'm manually
writing it all out.
So it does feel like there
should be a better solution here.
But let me also identify one
other issue I really don't like,
and this is, indeed, subtle.
I've got 3 here, I've got 3 here,
and I essentially have 3 here,
albeit a floating point version.
This is just ripe for me making a
mistake eventually and changing one
of those values, but not the other two?
So how might I fix this?
I might at least do something like this.
I could say integer maybe n for
scores, I'll set that equal to 3.
I could then use n here,
I could use n here.
I could use n here, but
that's a step backwards
because I don't want an int because I'm
going to run into the same math issue
as before, but I could convert
it-- that is, cast it to a float,
and we did that briefly last week.
But there's one other thing I could do
here that we did introduced last week.
This is better because I don't
have a magic number floating around
in multiple places.
Yeah, if I really want to
be proper, I should probably
say this should be a constant integer.
Why?
Because I don't want to
accidentally change it myself.
I don't want to be
collaborating with a colleague
and they foolishly change it on me.
This just sends a stronger signal to the
compiler, do not let the humans change
this value.
And now just to point out
one other feature of C,
if you have a number like
this, like the number 3,
I've deliberately capitalized
this variable name really
for the first time.
Any time you have a constant,
it tends to be a convention
to capitalize it just to
draw your attention to it.
It doesn't mean anything technically.
Capitalizing a variable
does nothing to it,
but it draws attention
visually to it to the human.
So if you declare
something as a constant,
it's commonplace to
capitalize it just because.
Moreover, if you have a constant that
you might want to occasionally modify--
maybe next semester when there's four
exams or five exams instead of three,
it actually is OK
sometimes to define what
might be called a global
variable, a variable that is not
inside of curly braces, it's literally
at the top of the file outside of main,
and despite what I said
about scope last week,
a global variable like this
on line 4 will be in scope
to every function in this file.
So it's actually a way
of sharing a variable
across multiple functions, which
is generally fine if you're
using a constant.
If you intend to change it,
there's probably a better way
than actually using a global
variable, but this is just
in contrast to what I
previously did, which I would
call, by contrast, a local variable.
But again, I'm just trying to reduce
the probability of making mistakes
somewhere in the code.
And I do agree.
I don't like that I'm still
adding all of these scores
manually even though clearly
I had a loop a moment ago.
But for now, let's at
least consider what's
been going on inside of
the computer's memory.
So with this array, I now have not
three variables, score1, score2, score3.
I have one variable, an array
variable, called scores, plural.
And if I want to access the first
element, its scores, bracket, 0.
If I want to access the second
element, its scores, bracket, 1.
If I want to access the third
element, it's scores, bracket, 2.
If I were to make a mistake
and do scores, bracket, 3,
which is the fourth element, I'd
end up in no man's land here,
and worst case, your program could
crash or something weird will happen,
spinning beach balls,
those kinds of things.
Just don't make those mistakes.
And C makes it easy to
make those mistakes,
so the onus is really
on you programmatically.
Questions on this use of arrays?
Question on this use of arrays?
Yeah, in back.
AUDIENCE: Is there any way [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
Is there any way to create an
array just by using syntax alone
without prompting the human for it?
Short answer, yes.
If you want to have an array of
integers called, for instance, array,
you could actually do like 13,
42, 50, something like this,
would give you an array
if you use this syntax.
This would give you an array of size
3 where the three values by default
are 13, 42 and 50.
It's not syntax we'll use for now,
but there is syntax like that.
It's not quite as user-friendly,
though, as other languages
if you've indeed programmed before.
Other questions on this use of arrays?
Yeah, in front.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Is there
a way to copy what?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Oh, is there a way to
calculate the length of an array?
Short answer, no, and I'm about to
show you one demonstration of this.
Those of you who have programmed
before in Java, in JavaScript,
in certain other languages, it's very
easy to get the length of an array.
You essentially just ask the
array, what's its length?
C does not give you that capability.
The onus is entirely on you and me to
remember, s as with another variable,
like n, how long the array is.
And so in fact, let me
go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead and open
up a baking style, a program
that I wrote in advance here
which kind of escalates quickly,
but there's not really too many
new ideas here except for the array
specifics.
So this is scores.c premade this time.
And notice what I have.
One, I've included cs50.h and stdio.h
at the top, so that's the same.
I have declared a constant
called n, set it equal to 3.
That is now the same as
of my most recent change.
I did introduce an average function,
which was one of the remaining concerns
that I could compute the average
with some kind of loop, too.
That average function is going
to return a float, which is what.
I want my average to be a
float with the fraction.
But notice this.
In answer to your question,
if I want a function called
average to do something iterate
over an array step by step by step,
add up all the numbers, and divide
by the total number of numbers,
I need to give it the array of numbers,
and I need to tell it how many of those
numbers are.
So I literally have
to pass in two values.
Meanwhile, this code is the
same as before inside of main.
I'm declaring a variable
called scores of size n.
I'm iterating from i to n.
And actually-- yep.
And then in this loop, I'm assigning
each of the scores a return
value of get_int.
The last line of main is this--
print out the average with f,
but don't just do it manually by
adding and dividing with parentheses.
Call the average function, pass in
the length of the array and the array
itself, and hope that it returns a float
that then gets plugged into percent f
So I would claim that pretty much
all of this, even though it's a lot,
should be familiar.
There's no real new ideas except for
this use of the global variable now
and this average function.
So let me scroll down
to the average function
because this is the takeaway
from this final example.
In this example here--
let me scroll up to
the average function,
copy-pasted the prototype
for the very first line.
And here's how I'm
computing the average.
There's different ways of doing
this, but here's an accumulator way.
On line 28, I'm declaring a variable
inside of the average function called
sum, and I'm just initializing it to 0.
Why?
Mentally I want to add up
all of the person scores
and then I want to divide by the total
and that's my mathematical average.
So here's my loop where I'm
iterating from 0 up to, but not
through the length-- so
that should be three times.
I am adding to the sum variable whatever
is at the i-th location, so to speak,
of the array.
So this is array, bracket 0;
array, bracket, 1; array, bracket,
2 on each iteration.
And then the last thing I'm
doing is a nice one-liner.
I'm dividing the sum, which is an
int, which is the sum of 72, 73, 33,
divided by the length, which is 3, but 3
is not a float, so I cast it to a float
so that the end value, hopefully, is
going to be 59.33333 and so forth.
So the only thing that's weird
syntactically is this, though.
When you define a function in C that
takes an argument that isn't just
a simple char, isn't just a simple
integer, it's actually an array,
you don't have to know the
array's length in advance.
You can just put square brackets
after the name you give it.
And I don't have to call it array.
I could call it x or y
or z or anything else.
I called it array just to
make clear that it's an array,
but you do need to know
the length somehow.
OK.
Questions on combining those
ideas in that there way?
Any questions?
No?
All right.
Well, we've only dealt
with numbers thus far.
It would be nice to actually deal
with letters and words and paragraphs
and the like, much like
our readability example,
but I think first, some snacks and
some fruit are served in the transept.
So we'll see you in 10.
See you in 10.
All right.
So we're back.
And up until now,
we've been representing
just numbers underneath
the hood, but we've
introduced arrays, which
gave us this ability, recall,
to store numbers back to back to back.
So it turns out, you actually
had this capability for the past
week even though you might
not have realized it.
And let me propose that we first
consider very simple example of three
chars instead of three integers.
And for simplistically, I'm
going to call them c1, c2,
and c3 just for the sake of discussion.
But I'm going to put our
familiar characters, "HI!"
in those variables using
single quotes because again.
That's what you do when
using individual chars
to make the point that I can store
three chars in three separate variables.
So let me go ahead
and go over to VS Code
here and let me create
something called hi.c.
And in this program, I'll first include
stdio.h, int main void as before.
And then inside of main,
let's just do exactly that.
Char c1 equals, quote-unquote,
capital H. Char C2 equals,
quote-unquote, capital
I. Char C3 equals,
quote-unquote, exclamation point.
So clearly not the best approach,
but just for demonstration's sake.
And here now that you
understand hopefully
from week 1 that really number--
and really, from week 0,
that numbers are just letters,
which can be something more, too.
We can really just use our
basic understanding of C
to tinker with these ideas
now and see them such
that there is indeed going to be no
magic happening for us ultimately.
So let me go ahead and print out three
characters-- %c, %c, %c, backslash n.
And then print out c1, c2, c3.
So I've got three separate placeholders.
And we haven't really had occasion to
use %c, but it means put char here,
unlike %s, which is put a whole
string here, or %i, put an integer.
Let me go ahead and make
hi, no syntax errors, ./hi,
and it should print out "HI!"
in exclamation points
because I'm printing out
just three simple characters.
But per our discussion
as far back as week 0,
letters are just numbers and
numbers are just letters,
it just depends on the
context in which we use them.
So let me change this %c to an i.
And I'm going to add a space
just so that you can obviously
separate one number from another.
Change this to i, change this to
i, but still print out c1, c2, c3.
So no integers, per se.
Let me just print out those chars.
Let me do make hi, no errors,
./hi, and now I see 72, 73, 33.
So in the case of chars and ints, you
can actually treat one as the other
so long as you have enough
bits to fit one in the other.
You don't have to cast even
or do anything explicitly.
You do have to cast one of--
converting an integer to a float
to make clear to the compiler
that you really intend
to do this because that
could be destructive if it can't quite
represent the number as you intend.
But in this case here, I think we're
OK just poking around and seeing
what's going on underneath the hood.
Well, what is going on
underneath the hood memory-wise?
Well, something very similar.
Here's that canvas of memory.
And maybe we got lucky and it's
in the top left-hand corner
like this-- c1, c2, c3.
But these are just three
individual characters,
but we're getting awfully close
to what we last week called
a string, which are just
characters, a sequence of characters
from left to right.
And in fact, I think if we combine
this revelation that these are just
numbers underneath the hood
back to back to back combined
with the idea of an array
from earlier, we can
start to see what's really going on.
Because indeed, underneath the hood,
this is just a number, 72, 73, 33.
And really, if we go
lower level than that,
it's these three
patterns of 0's and 1's.
That's all that's going
on inside of the computer,
but it's our use of int that
shows it to us as an integer.
It's our use of char that makes it
clear that it's a char, or equivalently,
%i and %c respectively.
But what exactly is a string?
Well, it's really just a
sequence of characters,
and so why don't we go there?
Let me propose that we actually
give ourselves an actual string,
call it s-- we'll use
double quotes this time.
So if I go back to VS Code here,
let me shorten this program
and just give myself a single
string s, set it equal to "HI!"
in double quotes.
And then below that, let's go ahead
and print out %s, backslash n,
and then s itself.
And then, turns out,
for reasons we'll soon
see, I do need to include
the CS50 Library so as
to use the actual keyword string here
even though I'm not using get_string,
but more on that another time.
But if I now do make hi, it does compile
./hi and it still prints out the exact
same thing.
But what's going on inside
of the computer's memory
when I use a string called s
instead of three chars, well,
you can think of the string as
taking up at least three bytes, H,
I, exclamation point.
But it's not three separate
variables, it's one variable.
But what does this really
look like now, especially
if I add back the yellow lines?
s is really just an array of characters.
So we called it a string
last week, and I claim today
that this is an abstraction in the CS50
library that's giving us this string,
but it's really just an
array of size at least 3
here where s, bracket, 0 presumably
gives me the H, s, bracket,
1 is the I, s, bracket, 2
is the exclamation point.
But just by saying string, all
of that happens automatically.
I don't even need to tell the
computer how many chars are
going to be in this string all at once.
So in fact, let me go over to
maybe a variant of this program
and we can see this syntactically.
So instead of printing out
the whole string with %s,
let me actually be a little
curious and print out %c, %c, %c,
and then change s to s, bracket,
0, s, bracket, 1, s, bracket, 2.
Which is not better in any sense.
This is way more
tedious now, but it does
demonstrate that I can
treat here in week 2
as though it's an array, which means
even in week 1 it was an array,
we just didn't know it.
We didn't have the syntax
with which to express that.
So if I now do make hi,
still compiles ./hi.
Same exact output, but I'm
now just kind of manipulating
the string in these
different ways because I
a string is just an array
of characters, so I can
treat with the square bracket notation.
But how do I know-- how does
the computer know where hi ends?
And this is where strings
get a little dangerous.
Like a char is 1 byte no matter what.
1 char, 1 character, that's it.
But a string, recall my
question mark from earlier,
could be null bytes if it's--
you would think could be 0 bytes if you
have nothing in it inside the quotes.
It could be one character,
two, 10, 100 like I claimed,
but how does the computer
know where strings end?
Like how does the computer not
know that the string is not
the whole row of memory here?
How does it know that it ends here?
Well, it turns out, all this time,
when we've been using, quote-unquote,
string and using get_string
from the CS50 library,
there's actually a
special sentinel value
at the end of every string
in a computer's memory
that tells the computer
string, stops here.
And the sentinel value--
and by sentinel, I
just mean special value that the world
decided on decades ago, is all 0 bits.
If you have a byte with all 0 bits
in it, that means string ends here.
So the implication is that the computer
now, using a loop or something,
can print out char,
char, char-- oh, done,
because it sees this special value.
If it didn't have that, it might
blindly go char, char, char, char char--
printing out values of memory that
don't belong to that given string.
So I was correcting myself
verbally a moment ago
because I said that this string is of
length 3, it's 3 bytes, but it's not.
Every string in the world,
both last week and now, this
is actually n plus 1 bytes where
n is the actual human length
that you care about, H-I,
exclamation point, or 3,
but it's always going to use one extra
byte for this so-called zero value
at the end.
And this 0 value is very
tedious to write a 0--
as 8 0 bits.
So we would actually typically
just write it as a 0.
But you don't want to confuse a 0
on the screen-- it's actually being
like the number 0 on the keyboard.
And so we would actually typically
write this symbol with a backslash 0.
So this is the char-based
representation of 0.
So it means the exact
same thing, this is just
C notation that indicates
that this is 8 0 bits,
but just makes clear that
it's not literally the number
0 that you want to see on the
screen, it's a sentinel value
that is terminating this here string.
So now what can I do once
I know this information?
Well, I can actually even see
this let me go back to this code
here in VS Code.
Let me change these %c's
to %i's just like before.
And now, we'll see again those
same numbers, make hi, ./hi,
there are the three.
I can technically poke around a
little bit further, %i one more,
and let's look at s, bracket, 3.
I was not exaggerating
earlier when I said,
in general, if you go past the end
of an array, bad things can happen.
But in this case, I know that there is
one more thing at the end of this array
because this is how strings are
built. This is not a CS50 thing,
this is a thing in C. Every string
in the world in double quotes
ends with a backslash
0-- that is 8 0 bits.
So if I really want, I can see
this by printing out s, bracket, 3,
which is the fourth and final location.
If I recompile my code now, make hi
./hi, I should see 72, 73, 33, and 0.
That's always been there.
So I'm always using 4 bytes, somewhat
wastefully, but somewhat necessarily
so that the computer actually
knows where that string ends.
So if we go back to the memory
representation of this here,
it's just as though you have an array of
integers being stored contiguously back
to back to back, the last one of which
means this is the end of the array
of characters, but because I'm
using, quote-unquote, "string,"
because I'm using %s and %c, I'm
not seeing these numbers by default,
I'm seeing H-I, exclamation point unless
I explicitly tell printf, no, no, no,
no, show me with %i
these actual integers.
This, then, is how you can
think about the string.
Like you don't really
need to think about
it as being individual characters.
This is just s, and it
has some length here,
but it does not necessarily an array
that you yourself have to create,
you get it automatically
just by using a string.
Now there's just-- not
to add on to the jargon.
This backslash 0,
these 8 0 bits, there's
actually a technical term for them.
You can call them NUL.
It's typically written in all
caps like this, confusingly.
In a couple of weeks, we're going
to see another word pronounced null,
but spelled N-U-L-L. Left hand wasn't
talking to right hand years ago,
but N-U-L means this is the 0
byte that terminates strings,
that indicate the end of a string.
And fun fact, you've actually seen this
before even though we glossed over it.
Here's that ASCII chart from last time.
If I focus on the leftmost column,
guess what is the 0 ASCII character?
NUL.
You never see null on the screen,
it's just how you pronounce 8 0 bits.
Whew!
questions on this
representation of strings?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Are strings [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID MALAN: Are string structured
differently in other languages?
Yes.
They are more powerful
in other languages.
In C, you have to build
them yourself in this way.
More on that when we get to Python.
Other questions.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
Does that mean we don't have a
function to get the length of a string?
Do we have to create it?
Short answer, there is a function,
but you have to-- someone
had to write code for it.
You can't just ask the string itself
like you can in JavaScript or Java.
What is the--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, you can.
It's actually more similar to Python
than it is to JavaScript or Java,
but we'll see that in just
a few minutes, in fact.
So let's introduce maybe
a couple of strings.
So here's two strings in
the abstract called s and t,
and I've initialized them
arbitrarily to "HI!" and "BYE!"
just so we can explore what's going to
actually happen underneath the hood.
So let me go back to VS Code.
Let me just completely change
this program to be that instead.
So string equals, quote-unquote, "HI!"
String t equals, quote-unquote, "BYE!"
in all caps.
And then let's print them both out
very simply. %s backslash n, s.
Print out %s backslash n, t just
so we can see what's going on.
If I do make hi ./hi, I should,
of course, see these two strings.
But what's going on inside
of the computer's memory?
Well, in this computer's
memory, assuming
these are the only two variables
involved and assuming the computer
is just doing things
top to bottom, "HI!"
is probably going to be stored somewhere
like this on my canvas of memory,
"BYE!"
is probably going to be stored there.
And it's wrapping around, but that's
just an artist's representation.
But notice that it is
now really important
that there is this NUL byte
at the end of each string
because that's how the computer
is going to know where "HI!"
ends and where "BYE!"
begins, otherwise you might see "HI!"
"BYE!"
all on the screen at once if there
weren't the sentinel value indicating
to printf, stop at this character.
But that's all that's
going on in your program
when you have two variables in this way.
And in fact, what's really going on and
things get a little more interesting
here, if I were to want
two of these things,
notice that I could refer
to them two as arrays.
So s, bracket, 0, 1, 2, and even 3.
t, bracket, 0, 1, 2, and even 3 and 4.
But if I want to actually
really blend some ideas,
just playing around with
these basic principles now,
notice what I can do in this version.
If I know I've got
two arrays in VS Code,
I don't strictly need to
do string s and t and u
and v. That's devolving back into the
scores1, scores2, scores3 mantra where
I had multiple variables
almost the same name
even though I'm using different
letters of the alphabet.
What if I want--
what if I do this?
string words, and if I want to store two
words in the computer's memory, fine.
Create an array of two strings.
But what is a string?
A string is an array of characters, so
it's getting a little bit trippy here,
but the ideas are still going
to be the same. words, bracket,
0 could certainly equal "HI!"
words, bracket, 1 can certainly equal
"BYE!" just like the scores example.
And then if I want to print these
things with %s, I can print out words,
bracket, 0.
And then I can print out %s
backslash n words bracket 1.
And the example is not going to be
any different in terms of its output,
but I've now avoided s and t, I now
just have one variable called words
containing both of these here things.
And if I really want
to poke around, here's
where things get even more
visually overwhelming,
but just the logical
extension of these same ideas.
Right now is the previous version
where I had two variables, s and t.
If I now use this new version where
I have one variable called words,
just like this here, the picture
should follow logically like this.
words, bracket, 0 is this string;
words, bracket, 1 is this string;
but what is each string?
It's an array of characters.
And so you can also think of it like
this, where this H is words, bracket,
0, bracket, 0.
So the 0-th character of the 0-th word.
And this is words, bracket, 0, 1; words,
bracket, 0, 2; words, bracket, 0, 3.
And then words, bracket, 1, 0.
So it's kind of like a
two-dimensional array, almost.
And you can think about
it that way if helpful.
But for now, it's just applying
the same principles to the code.
So if I go to my code here and
I've got my "HI!" and my "BYE!"--
this is going to look a little stupid,
but let me change this %s to %c, %c,
%c, and print out words, bracket, 0.
words, bracket, 0, bracket 1.
words, bracket, 0, bracket, 2 to
print out that three-letter word.
And now down here, let
me print out %c, %c, %c,
%c because it's four letters
in BYE, exclamation point.
This is words, bracket, 1, but the
first character; words, bracket, 1,
the second character; words,
bracket, 1, the third character;
and words, bracket, 1,
the fourth character.
It's hard to say when you're
typing a different number,
but that's what we get by using
zero indexing, so to speak.
make hi.
Whew!
No mistakes.
"HI!"
Says the same thing.
So again, there's no magic.
Like you are fully in
control over what's going
on inside of the computer's memory.
And now that we have this array
syntax with square brackets,
you can both create these things and
then manipulate them or access them
however you so choose.
Whew!
Questions on arrays or
strings in this way?
Yeah, over here.
AUDIENCE: Can you have any array
that has multiple data types in it?
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
Can you have an array with
multiple different data types?
Short answer, no;
longer answer, sort of,
but not in nearly the same
user-friendly way as with languages
like Python or JavaScript or others.
So assume for now arrays should be
the same type in C. Other questions?
Yeah, over here.
AUDIENCE: When you
talk about [INAUDIBLE]??
DAVID MALAN: Oh, a really good question.
It will-- so for those
who couldn't hear,
if you were to look past
the end of one array,
would you start to see the
beginning of the second?
In this case, maybe the word "BYE!"
Could depend on the particulars
of your code in the computer.
Let's try this.
So let's get a little greedy here and
go one past H-I, exclamation point,
null character by looking
at words, bracket, 0, 3,
which should actually be our null
character, so that's going to be there.
And actually, let's see.
Let's go ahead and do this.
Make hi ./hi.
Still works as expected, but
let me change this to integer,
integer so we can actually
see what's going on.
Integer.
And now, if I recompile make
hi, I should see the same thing,
but numerically.
And now what I think you're
proposing is let's get a little crazy
and go even past that to
what could be location 4,
but we know semantically doesn't exist,
but maybe is bumping up against "BYE!"
So make hi ./hi.
And guess what 66 is.
Well, just the B, but yes.
66, recall, is capital B because
in week 0, capital A was 65.
So indeed, now we're
really poking around.
And you can get crazy.
Like, what's 400 characters away
and see what's going on there.
Eventually your program
will probably crash,
and so don't poke around too much, but
more on that in the coming days, too.
All right, well how about some other
revelations and problem-solving?
Now coming back to the question
about strings length earlier,
and we'll see if we can then tie
this all together to something
like cryptography in the
end and manipulating strings
for the purpose of
sending them securely.
So let me propose that we go into
VS Code here again in a moment.
And I'm going to create
a program called length.
Let's actually figure out ourselves
the length of a string initially.
So I'm going to go
ahead and code length.c.
I'm going to go ahead
and include cs50.h.
I'm going to include
stdio.h, int main void.
And then inside of main, I'm going
to prompt the user for their name.
get_string, quote-unquote, "Name."
And then I'm going to
go ahead and I want
to count the length of this string.
But I know what a string is now.
It's char, char, char, char, and
then eventually the null character.
So I can look for that.
And I can write this in
a few different ways.
I know a bunch of different
types of loops now,
but I'm going to go with a while
loop by first declaring a variable n,
for number of characters,
set it equal to 0.
It's like starting to count
with your fingers all down,
and I want to do the equivalent of
this, counting each of the letters
that I type in.
So I can do that as follows.
While the name variable at
location n does not equal,
quote-unquote, backslash
0, which looks weird,
but it's just asking the
question, is the character
at that location equal to
the so-called null character?
Which is written with single quotes
and backslash 0 by convention.
And what I want to do, while
that is true, is just add 1 to n.
And then at the very bottom here, let's
just go ahead and print out with %i
the value of n because presumably
if I type in HI, exclamation point,
I'm starting at 0 and I'm going
to have H, I, exclamation point,
null character so I don't
increment n a fourth time.
So let's go ahead and run down here.
make length ./length, Enter.
Well, I guess I'm asking for
name, so I'll do my name for real.
David, five characters,
and I indeed get 5.
If I used a for loop, I
could do something similar,
but I think this while loop approach,
much like our counter from the past,
is fairly straightforward.
But what if I want to do this?
What if I want to make
another function for this?
Well, I could do that.
Let me--
All right, let's do this.
Let's write a quick function
called string_length.
It's going to take a string
called s or whatever as input.
And then you know what?
Let's just do this in that function.
I'm going to borrow my
code from a moment ago.
I'm going to paste it
into this function.
But I'm not going to
print out the length,
I'm going to return the length n.
So I have a helper
function of sorts that's
going to hand me back
the length of the string,
and that's why this returns an int,
but takes a string as its argument.
How do I use this?
Well, first, I do need
to copy the prototype
so I don't get into trouble as before.
Semicolon.
And then in my main function,
what I think I can do now
is something like this.
I can do int length equals the
string length of the name variable
that was just typed in.
And now using printf %i,
print out length, semicolon.
So exact same logic.
The only thing I've done that's
different this time is I've
added a helper function
just to demonstrate
how I can take some pretty
basic functionality,
find the length of a
string, and modularize it
into a function abstract it
away so I never again have
to copy-paste that for loop.
I now have a function
called string_length
that will solve this problem for me.
Whoops, wrong program. make length.
Huh.
Use of undeclared identifier 'name.'
What did I do wrong?
Apparently on line 16 of length.c,
what did I do wrong here?
Yeah, in front.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Good.
Perfect terminology.
So name is local to main.
The scope of name is main, though
sounds similar, but different words.
And so I'm actually
should be calling this
s because s is the name of the local
variable being passed in even though it
happens to be 1 and the same
as name because on line 9,
I'm indeed passing in
name as the argument.
All right.
So this is where, again, copy-paste
can sometimes get you into trouble.
Let's try to make length again.
Now it works. ./length, D-A-V-I-D, and
now we have a function that seems to be
working.
But this is such like
commodity functionality.
Like my God, like
surely someone before us
has written a function to get
the length of a string before,
and indeed, other people have.
So it turns out that in C, just
as you have the stdio library,
you also have a string library whose
header file is called, appropriately,
string.h.
In fact CS50 has documentation,
therefore, in its own manual pages,
so to speak, along with
some sample usage thereof.
But it turns out, in the
string library, there
is a very popular function
analogous to the Python one
that you asked about
earlier called strlen
where strlen, one word,
no underscores, just
figures out the length of a string.
And honestly, I've never
looked at its source code,
but it probably uses a while
loop, maybe it uses a for loop,
but it certainly uses the same
idea of just iterating-- that is,
walking from left to
right over a variable
in order to figure out what the
length of a given string is.
So how do we use this?
Well if I go back to VS
Code here, I can throw away
the entirety of my
string length function,
I can throw away the
prototype, therefore,
and I can include a third
header file, string.h, inside
of which I claim now is
this function called strlen
that I can just now use
out of the box for free
because someone else wrote
this function for me.
And string.h will teach the
compiler that it exists.
So if I now do make length and ./length,
now I have a similarly working program
that doesn't bother having
me write unnecessary code.
So this is another example of a library.
The string library is just going to
make our lives easier by not having to--
for us not having to
reinvent some wheel.
All right, well where else
does this get interesting?
How about something like this?
Let me go back into VS Code here.
Let's create a program called string.c--
we'll play around with our own strings--
that's going to start similarly.
So let's include cs50.h,
let's include stdio.h,
let's include string.h so we can
use that same strlen function.
int main void.
And inside of this, let's do this.
Let's get a string s and prompt the
user for any old string as input.
All right.
And then let's go ahead and maybe
print out, quote-unquote, "Output."
And I'm just going to line up my spaces
just right because these words are
slightly different lengths, but
we'll see why I'm doing this.
It's just for aesthetics'
sake in a moment.
And let's go ahead now and do this.
If I want to print out every character
in a string, how can I now do this?
Well, this is actually
a pretty common task
even though this version, thereof,
will seem pointless. for int i gets 0,
i is less than the length of s.
i++ is just the conventional way to
start a loop that iterates from left
to right over a string of that length.
And then let's go ahead and
print out each character, %c,
printing out the string at location
i using our fancy new array syntax.
And at the very end of
this program, let's just
print out a new line character just
to move the cursor to the bottom
like we've done in the past.
So this is kind of a stupid program
like I am reinventing the wheel that is
the %s format code.
I already know that printf
can print out a whole string.
Suppose it didn't.
Suppose I forgot about %s
and I only knew about %c,
these lines of code here collectively
will print out the entirety of a string
character by character
based on its length.
So if I compile this program, make
string ./string and type in my name--
for instance, David,
the output is D-A-V-I-D,
and here's why I hit the
spacebar an extra time,
because I wanted input and output to
line up nicely so we could see that
they're, in fact, the same length.
So let me just stipulate.
This code is correct, but there is an
inefficiency with this line of code.
Let's talk about design instinctively.
What is maybe bad about
this line of code 9--
line 9 that I've highlighted?
This one is subtle.
Let's go over here.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
I'm calling strlen inside of the
loop again and again and again.
Why?
Well, recall how for loops worked.
When we walked through it last
week, that middle part of for loop
in between the semicolons keeps
getting checked, keeps getting checked,
keeps getting checked.
And so if you put a function call there,
which is totally fine syntactically,
you're asking the same damn
question again and again and again.
And the length of David,
D-A-V-I-D, is never changing.
So strlen, implemented decades
ago by some other human,
has some kind of loop in
it, and you're literally
making that code run again
and again and again just
to get the same answer
5 again and again.
So I think your instinct is right.
I could come up with another
variable outside of the loop.
I could do something like this.
int length equals strlen of s, and
then I could just plug that in.
But there's a slightly more elegant way.
If you like doing things
with slightly less code,
this is correct as I've now written it.
It's less efficient-- it's
more efficient because I'm only
calling strlen once
now on this new line 9,
but a more common way to
write this would typically
be to do something like this.
After initializing i, you can also
initialize something else like length.
And you can set length equal to
strlen of s, then your semicolon,
and now you can say while
i is less than that length.
Or I can tighten this up further.
If it's just a number and it's a super
short loop, might as well just call it
n.
So this now would be a canonical way
of implementing the exact same idea,
but without the inefficiency
because now you're
calling strlen in the
initialization part of for loop,
not inside of the Boolean expression
that gets checked and executed
again and again.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Correct.
Well, I'm declaring i as an
int, but by way of the comma,
I am also declaring n as an int.
So they've got to be the same
type for this trick to work.
Good observation.
Other questions on this one here?
No?
All right.
Well, let's play around further here.
Let me propose that there's
other libraries and header files
as well that you might find useful.
There's also something called
ctype, which relates to types
and c's that's got a
bunch of useful functions
that we can actually see if we
visit the documentation here.
But before we get there,
let me actually whip up
a program that maybe does something
a little bit fun, albeit low level,
like forcing some string to uppercase
if the human types it in lowercase.
So let me go ahead and write
a program called uppercase.c.
Let me go ahead and give
myself the same header files.
Include cs50.h, include stdio.h.
And for now, let's include
string.h for the length.
And let's go ahead and have
int main void as before.
And inside of main, let's
give myself a string
s equaling get_string "Before," just
so I know what the string is initially.
Now I'm going to print out
proactively "After" with two spaces
just so that things line up
aesthetically on the screen
because "After" is
one character shorter.
And now I'm going to do the
same technique as before.
for int i equals 0, n equals the string
length of s, i is less than n, i++.
And then inside of this loop,
what do I want to do logically?
I want to force these characters
to uppercase if they are, in fact,
lowercase.
And so how might I do this?
Well, there's a bunch
of ways to express this,
but I'm going to do it maybe
the most straightforward way
even if you've not seen this before.
If the current letter in
the string at location i,
because I'm in a loop starting
from 0 all the way up to, but not
through the string
length, is greater than
or equal to a lowercase a, in single
quotes, and that letter is less than
or equal to a lowercase z.
What does this mean in English?
Well, this essentially
means if lowercase--
logically, if it's greater than
or equal to little a and less than
or equal to little z, it's somewhere
between and z in lowercase.
What do I want to do?
Well, I want to force it to uppercase.
So I want to print out a
character without a new line yet
that prints out the current
character, but force it to uppercase.
Well, how can I do this?
Well, this is where this gets
into some low-level hacking,
but notice the same ASCII chart.
Here's our uppercase
letters from last time.
Here's our lowercase characters,
and let me highlight those.
Does anyone notice a relationship
between capital A and lowercase a
that happens to be the same
for capital B and lowercase b?
AUDIENCE: Capital A [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Like this pattern is true.
So 97 minus 65 is 32, and that's true
for every lowercase and uppercase
letter respectively.
So I can leverage that.
And this is not a CS50 thing.
Like this is ASCII.
This is, in turn, Unicode.
This is how modern computers work.
So if I go back to VS Code
here, you know what I could do.
Let's just literally subtract 32.
But because I'm displaying
this as a char, not as an int,
I'm going to see the lowercase letter
seemingly become an uppercase instead.
Else, if it's not lowercase--
maybe it's already uppercase,
maybe it is punctuation, let's
just go ahead and print out with %c
the original character unaltered.
And then at the very
end of this program,
let's print a new line just to
move the cursor to the next line.
All right, so let's do make uppercase.
And let me type ./uppercase.
And I'll type in D-A-V-I-D,
all lowercase, and now,
you'll see it's in all caps.
If, though, I type in maybe my last
name but capitalized M, that's OK,
the rest of it will still
be capitalized for me.
Now I don't love this technique.
It's a little bit fragile
because I had to do some math.
I had to check my reference sheet and
then incorporate it into my program.
Even though it will be correct,
I could be a little more clever.
I could actually do something like this.
Well, whatever the
value of lowercase is--
lowercase a is minus whatever
the value of capital A is,
and I could actually do it
arithmetically even though that, too,
is somewhat inefficient in that
it's asking the same question again
and again, but the compiler is
probably smart enough to optimize that.
And frankly, for those more
comfortable, a good compiler
will also notice, no,
no, no, no, you don't
want to call strlen again and again.
The compiler can do some of
these optimizations for you,
but it's still good practice
to get into yourself.
But there's probably a better way.
Instead of rolling
this solution ourselves
and subtracting 32 or
doing any arithmetic,
let's use that ctype library.
Let me go back up to my header files.
Let's additionally include ctype.h.
Let's pretend like I read the
documentation in advance, which I did,
in fact.
And let's instead of
doing any math here,
let's use a function that exists
in that library called toupper
and pass to it whatever the current
character is in s at location i.
Otherwise, I still print
out the unchanged character.
And let me go ahead and do
make uppercase ./uppercase.
And now without any math, no
subtracting 32, that, too, also works.
But it gets better.
If you read the
documentation for toupper,
it turns out its documentation tells
you, if C is already uppercase,
it just passes it through for you.
So you don't even need to ask
this conditional question.
I can actually cut this to my
clipboard, get rid of all of this,
and just replace that
one line only and just
let toupper handle the situation for
me because again, its documentation
has assured me that if
it's already uppercase,
it's just going to return
the original value.
So if I make uppercase,
this time, ./uppercase,
now it works and now things
are getting kind of fun.
I mean, these are mundane
tasks, admittedly,
but at least I'm standing on
the shoulders of smart people
who came before me who implemented the
string library, the ctype library--
heck, even the CS50 Library so I don't
need to reinvent any of those wheels.
Questions on any of
these library techniques?
It's all still arrays, it's
all still strings and chars,
but now we're leveraging libraries
to solve some of our problems for us.
All right.
So let's come full
circle to where we began,
where and I mentioned
that some programs include
support for command line arguments.
Like Clang takes command line
arguments words after the word clang.
CD, which you've used in Linux,
takes command line arguments.
If you type cd, space,
pset1 or cd, space,
mario in order to change
directories into another folder.
If you do rm like I did
earlier, you can remove a file
by using a command line
argument, a second word that
tells the computer what to remove.
Well, it turns out that
you, too, can write
code that takes words at the command
prompt and uses them as input.
Up until now, you and I have only gotten
user input via get_string, get_int,
get_float, and functions like that.
You, too, can write code that
take command line arguments which,
frankly, just save the human time.
They can type their entire thought at
the command line, hit Enter, and boom,
the program can complete without
prompting them and re-prompting them
again.
So here's where we can now start to
take off some more training wheels.
Up until now, we've just put void
inside of the parentheses here any time
we implement main.
It turns out that you can put
something else in parentheses
when using C. It's a mouthful,
but you can replace void
with this bigger expression.
But it's two things.
int, called argc by
convention, and a string,
but not a string, actually an
array of strings called argv.
And these terms are a little
arcane, but argc means
argument count-- how many words
did the human type at the prompt?
Argv stands for argument
vector, which is generally
another term for an array--
you've heard it perhaps
from mathematics.
It's like a list of values, or in this
case, a list of command line arguments.
So C is special.
If you declare main as not taking void
inside of parentheses, but rather,
an int and an array of
strings, C will figure out
whatever the human typed at
the prompt and hand it to you
as an array and the length thereof.
So if I want to leverage
this, I can start
to implement some programs of my own
that actually incorporate command line
arguments.
For instance, let me go back
in a moment here to VS Code.
Let me create a program,
for instance, called greet.c
that's just going to greet the
user in a few different ways.
So let me first do it
the old way. cs50.h.
Let me include stdio.h.
Let me do int main void still.
So the old way.
And if I want to greet myself or
Carter or Yulie or anyone else,
I could do, old fashioned now, get
the answer from the user, get_string.
Let's prompt for "What's
your name?" question mark,
just like we did in Scratch.
And then do printf, "Hello,"
comma, %s backslash n, answer.
So we've done this many
times now this week and last.
This is the old school way
now of getting command line--
of getting user input by
prompting them for it.
So if I do make greet /greet, there's
no command line arguments at the prompt,
I'm literally just running
the program's name.
If I hit Enter, though, now get_string
kicks in, asks me for my name,
and the program then greets me.
But I can do--
otherwise, I could do
something like this instead.
First, answer's a little
generic, so let's first change
this back to name and back to name,
but that's a minor improvement there
just stylistically.
Let's, though, introduce
now a command line argument
so that I can just greet myself by
running the program, hitting Enter,
and being done, no more get_string.
So I'm going to go ahead and
change void to int argc, string
argv with square brackets.
string means-- the square
brackets means it's an array;
string means it's an array
of strings; and argc, again,
is just an integer of the
number of words typed.
Now I'm going to somewhat
dangerously going to do this.
I'm going to get rid of my
use of get_string altogether,
and I'm going to change this line to
be not name, which no longer exists,
but I'm going to go into
this array called argv
and I'm going to go into location 1.
So I'm doing this on faith.
I haven't explained what I'm doing yet,
but I'm going to do make greet ./greet,
and now I'm going to type my name at
the command line just like with rm,
with clang, with cd.
With any of the commands you've
written with multiple words,
I'm going to greet literally David.
So I hit Enter, and voila,
I've somehow gotten access
to what I typed at the prompt by
accessing this special parameter called
argv.
Technically you could call it anything
you want, but the convention is
argv and argc from right to left here.
Just a guess, then.
What if I change this to print out
bracket 0 and recompile the code?
And I run ./greet David?
What might it say instinctively?
Any hunches?
Yeah.
So it's going to say hello, ./greet.
So it turns out, you get one for free.
Whatever the name of
your program is always
accessible in argv at location 0.
That's just because.
It's a handy feature.
In case there's an error or you need to
tell the user how to use the program,
you know what the command is
that they ran, but at location 1,
maybe 2, maybe 3 are
the additional words
that the human might have typed in.
Well, let's do something a
little smarter than this.
Let me go back to version 1.
Let me recompile it, make greet.
Let me rerun ./greet David,
and this seems to work fine.
What if I get a little curious
and print out location 2?
Let me recompile the code, make greet
./greet David, Enter, OK, there's null.
And I mentioned we'd see N-U-L-L,
and here's one incarnation thereof,
but this is clearly wrong.
So I probably don't want to even
let the user do this because I
don't want them to see bogus output.
Like this is arguably
the a bug in the code
that it even bothered to show this by
default. So what could I do instead?
Well, what if I do this?
If argc equals equals 2,
then go ahead and comfortably
say printf "hello," argv, bracket, 1.
Else, if the human did not give
exactly two arguments at the prompt,
let's just print out some
default value like "hello, world"
like from last week.
In other words now I'm doing this
error checking with a conditional,
making sure with this
Boolean expression only
if argc equals equals 2, and
therefore has two words in argv
do you want to proceed.
And so now if I do make greet again,
./greet David, this now works.
But if I don't cooperate and I
just run greet, what should it say?
Just hello, world.
If I run David Malan as two
words, what should it say?
hello, world, because that's
not exactly equal to 2.
Again, the first word in argv
is always the program's name.
The second word is whatever
the human, then, has typed.
Now if we don't even know in advance
how many words they're going to be,
we can combine today's ideas.
This is going to look a little weird,
but it's the same thing as before.
for int i gets 0, i is less than--
how about argc i++?
And then inside of this loop, I can
print out %s, maybe backslash n, comma,
and then print out argv, bracket, i.
So I can have a loop that
iterates argc number of times,
once for every word at the prompt.
I can print out argv, bracket, i,
which is the i-th word in that array
from left to right.
And so if I now run make
greet and I do ./greet alone,
I just see the program's name.
If I do ./greet David, I see,
those two, one after the other.
If I do David Malan, I
get those three words.
If I keep going, I'll
get more and more words.
So using just the length of the
array and the name of the array,
I can actually do quite a bit there.
Now there's actually some fun
things you can do with this,
and this is sort of beside
the point, but there's
this thing in the world
called ASCII art, which
is making pictures and beautiful
things just using ASCII or maybe
nowadays Unicode characters,
but without using emoji.
Like emoji kind of make
this a little too easy.
But if all you have are
traditional largely English letters
and punctuation, you can actually
do some interesting things.
On Linux systems-- for instance,
if I go back to VS Code here,
let me increase the size
of my terminal window here.
And it turns out that we've
pre-installed-- really,
for no compelling reason, but just
for fun, a program called cowsay,
which has a cow say something.
So if I want to have a cow say
"moo" in ASCII art, I can do this,
and you get an adorable cow saying
something like "moo" on the screen.
But moo is a command line
argument that is clearly
modifying the output of this
program because I could also
change it to say hello,
comma, world, and now the cow
is going to say that instead.
So it takes multiple command
line arguments, if you will.
But it also takes what are called flags
or switches whereby any command line
argument that starts with a dash is
usually like a special configuration
option that you would only know
exists by reading the documentation
or seeing a demonstration.
And if I have my syntax right, if
I do cowsay -f, and maybe I'll do--
let's see.
Instead of this cow say, how
about I'll do -f for file,
and I'm going to change
it into duck mode.
And I'm going to have this version
of the ASCII art say quack.
So it's a tiny little duck
there, but it's saying quack.
And you can kind of waste
a lot of time doing this.
I can do cowsay -f dragon
and say something like, RAWR,
and this is just amazing.
Again, not really
academically compelling,
but it does demonstrate, again, command
line arguments, which are everywhere,
and you've indeed been
using them already.
But there's one other feature
we wanted to introduce you
to today, which will be a useful
building block, which will also
reveal one other thing about the
code that we've been writing.
It turns out that all of the programs
we've been writing thus far, eventually
obviously exit because
you see your prompt again
unless you have an infinite
loop such that it never ends.
But eventually they exit.
And secretly, every program
we've written thus far actually
has what's called an exit status.
It's like a special return
value from the program
itself that by default is always 0.
0 as a number in the world
generally means everything's OK.
The flip side of that is because
the world tends to use integers
and you've got four
billion possibilities,
like every other number in the world
when it comes to our program's exit
status is bad.
If it's 1, it's probably bad.
If it's negative 1, it's bad.
And in fact, you've probably
seen this in the real world.
If you've ever had like a random
error message on the screen--
here's a screenshot
of Zoom, for instance.
And that screenshot, somewhat
confusingly or unknowingly,
has an error code like
1132, that probably
means that the Zoom software that some
other humans wrote incorrectly somehow
had an error and it did not exit with
status 0, it exited with status 1132.
And somewhere at Zoom,
there's probably a file
or a book that tells the programmers
what this error code actually means.
This is not useful for you and me.
There's some programmer at Zoom
who would probably be like,
oh, I know what I did or my
colleague did wrong in this case.
You've seen this elsewhere even though
this is not quite the same thing,
but we'll talk about
this in a few weeks.
If you've ever seen 404, like numbers
are everywhere, and on the web,
404 means like file not found.
It means you made a typo, the web server
deleted a file, or something like that,
but this is just to say numbers are
so often used to signify or represent
errors.
Even though that's not
an exit status, per se,
that's an HTTP status
code, which we'll soon see.
But you have access to
exit statuses as it relates
to command line software already.
Up until now, this is how
we've been writing main, now
with command line
arguments, but we've also
been writing main with
an int return value.
And you've never used this-- we
didn't talk about this last week.
I just ask that you trust me and
just keep copying and pasting this.
But that int means
that even your programs
can return values which can be useful
even if you don't use command line
arguments and we just go back to
the original version like void.
So for instance, if I go ahead and
open up, for instance, VS Code again,
I'll get rid of the dragon.
And let's do one other program
here called status just
to play around with the idea of
these so-called exit statuses.
Let me just demonstrate the idea
with an include cs50.h, include
stdio.h, int main, and here
I'll do int argc, string argv.
And then inside of main,
let's do a similar program
to before like the hello, world.
So printf "hello,"
comma, %s backslash n.
Then let's print out argv 1.
But I only want to execute that line
if the human gave me a command line
argument.
Otherwise I don't want to even say
some default like hello, world.
I just want to abort early and just
exit the program, no output whatsoever.
So I could do this.
If argc does not equal 2--
and it's a single equals, but
it's a bang, an exclamation point,
means not equal.
So this is the opposite
of equals equals.
Then previously I would have
just printed hello, world,
but now I want to print
out an error message
like, "Missing command-line
argument" just to explain to the user
why the program is about to
terminate, and then I can return 1.
It's kind of arbitrary.
I could also return 1132,
but why start there?
This is the only possible error
that could go wrong in my program.
So I'm going to start at 1.
Zoom clearly has 1,000-plus
possible things that can go wrong
in their source code, which is
why the number got as big as 1132,
but I'm just going to arbitrarily,
but conventionally return 1.
But if everything is OK and I do-- it is
not the case that argc does not equal 2
and I actually get to line 11, I'm going
to return 0 because 0, again, I claim,
signifies success.
And all of this time, every program
we've written-- you've written
has secretly exited with
0 by default. But now
that our programs are
getting more sophisticated,
when something goes
wrong, it turns out it's
useful to have the power to just
return some other value even
though the user is not going to see it.
Even though the Zoom user
shouldn't see it, it's still there.
It's diagnostically useful to
you, or in the case of a class,
to your TF or TA or CA.
So if I do make status now to compile
this program and run ./status and type
my first name I think this is a success.
It should say hello, David
and secretly exit with 0.
If you really want to see the 0, there's
this arcane command you can type.
You can literally type
at your prompt echo $?.
It's weird symbology, but it's
what the humans chose decades ago.
This will just show you what did the
most recently-run program secretly exit
with.
So if I do this in VS Code,
I can do exit $?, Enter,
and there's that secret 0.
I could have been doing this
week and last week, it's
just not that interesting.
But it is interesting, or at least
marginally so, if I rerun status
and maybe I don't provide a command
line argument or I provide too many.
So argc does not equal 2.
And I hit Enter, I get yelled
at with the error message,
but I can see the secret status
code, which is, indeed, 1.
And so now if you're ever in the
habit in either a class like this
or in the real world where you're
automatically testing your code,
be it with check50 or in the
real world, things called
unit tests and other
third-party software,
those tests can actually detect
these status code-- exit statuses
and know that your code
succeed or fail, 0 or 1.
And if there's different types
of failures it can detect--
status 2, status 3, status 1132, it's
just one other tool in your toolkit.
But all of that is terribly
low level, and really,
the goal of this week-- and really,
today, and really, code more generally,
is to solve problems.
So let's consider an
increasingly important one, which
is the ability to send
information securely,
whether it is in file format,
wirelessly, or any other.
Cryptography is the art and
the science of encrypting.
Scrambling information.
So that even if I write
a secret message to you
and I send it through this open
audience with so many nosey eyes
who could look at the message, if I've
encrypted this message, none of them
should be able to read it,
only you, whoever you are,
to whom I intended that message.
In the world of
cryptography, then encryption
means scrambling the information
so that only you and the recipient
can receive it.
So if we consider our black
box like in week 0 and 1,
here is the problem to be solved.
And let me propose a couple
of pieces of vocabulary.
Plaintext is any message written
in English or any human language
that you want to send
and write yourself.
Ciphertext is what
you want to convert it
to before you just hand it off
to a bunch of random strangers
in the audience or a bunch
of servers on the internet,
any one of whom could
look at your message.
So in the black box is
what we're going to call
a cipher, an algorithm for
encrypting or scrambling information
in a reversible way.
It doesn't suffice to just
scramble the information randomly,
otherwise the recipient
can't do anything with it.
It's an algorithm, a cipher
that encrypts it in such a way
that someone else can decrypt it.
And here's a common way.
Most ciphers take as input not only
the plaintext message in English
or whatever else, but also a key.
And it's metaphorically
like a key to open a lock,
but it's technically generally a
number, like a really big number made up
of lots of bits.
And not even 32, not even 64,
sometimes 1,024 bits, which is crazy
unpronounceable large,
but the probability
that someone is going to guess
your key is just so, so small
that for all intents and purposes,
you are, in fact, secure.
So what's an example
of this, for instance?
Suppose the secret message I want
to send is innocuously just "HI!"
Well, it'd be pretty stupid to
write "HI!" on a piece of paper,
hand it to someone in
the audience, and expect
it to get all the way to the back
without someone like glancing at it
and obviously seeing and
reading the plaintext.
So what if I, though, agree with
someone in back, for instance,
that our secret is going to be 1?
And we have to agree upon
that secret in advance,
but 1 just means that is my key.
And let me propose that
according to one popular cipher,
if I want to send "HI!", change the
H to an I and the I to a J-- that is,
increment effectively every
letter of the alphabet by one,
and if you get to a Z, wrap
back around to A, for instance.
So shift the alphabet by
one place in this case
and send this message now instead.
So is that secure?
Well, if one of you kind of nosily
looks at this sheet of paper,
you won't see "HI!"
You will see some information
leak in this algorithm.
You'll see an exclamation point, so
I'm enthusiastically saying something,
but you won't know what the
message is unless you decrypt it.
Now that said, is this very
secure, really, in practice?
I mean, not really.
Like, if you know I'm just using a key
and I'm using the English alphabet,
you could probably brute
force your way to a solution
by just trying 1, trying
2, trying 3, trying 25,
go through all the
possibilities tediously,
but eventually it's
probably going to pop out.
This is actually known,
though, as the Caesar cipher.
And back in the day, before anyone else
knew about or had invented encryption,
Caesar, Julius Caesar, was
known to use a cipher like this
using a key of three, literally.
And I guess it works OK if you're
literally the first human in the world
by lore to have thought of this idea,
but of course, anyone who intercepts it
could attack it nonetheless and figure
things out a bit mathematically.
13 is more common.
This is called ROT13 on the internet for
rotate the letters of the alphabet 13.
That changes "HI!" to "UV!"
You might think what's better than 13?
Well, let's double the security.
ROT26.
Why is this stupid?
I mean, there's like 26 letters in
the alphabet, so like A becomes A. So
that doesn't really help-- oh, wait.
Oh, I'm pointing at something
that's not on the screen, dammit.
Suppose the message is more lovingly,
"I LOVE YOU," instead of just "HI!"
Same exact approach, whether or not
there's punctuation, "I LOVE YOU,"
with an input of 13
might now become this.
And now it's getting a little less
obvious what the ciphertext actually
represents.
And now, what's twice as secure is 13?
Well, 26 is surely better, but of
course, if you rotate 26 places,
that, of course, just
gives you the same thing.
So there's a limit to
this, but again, that just
speaks to the cipher being
used, which is very simple.
There is much, much better, more
sophisticated mathematical ciphers
that are used.
We're just starting with
something simple here.
As for decryption, if I'm using a key
of 1, how do I reverse the process?
Yeah, so I just minus 1.
So B becomes A, C becomes B,
A becomes Z. And if it's 13,
I subtract 13 instead or whatever
the key is, so long as sender
and receiver actually know it.
So in this case here, this is actually
the message with which we began class.
If we have this message here and
I used a key of 1 to encrypt it,
well, decrypting, it might
involve doing something like this.
Here's those same letters on the
screen, and I think in a moment
before we adjourn, I'll
mention too that we
might have encrypted a
message in eight characters
this whole day, so if
any of you took the time
and procrastinated and figured
out what the light bulb spelled
and they didn't seem to
spell anything in English,
well, here now is the
solution for cracking it.
This, if I subtract 1, becomes what?
U becomes T. And this is obviously--
see where we're going with this?
And if we keep going, subtracting 1--
so indeed, we're at the end of class
now because this was CS50.
And the last thing we have to say is we
have hundreds of ducks waiting for you
outside.
So on the way out, grab
your own rubber duck.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]