[MUSIC PLAYING]
SPEAKER 1: All right.
So this is CS50, and this is week four.
And this is actually
one of the weeks that
really makes CS50,
CS50, insofar as we'll
take an even lower level
look at how computers work,
and in turn, what it is you're
doing when you write code
toward an end of really giving you
a complete mental model of what's
going on inside, so that when you run
to solve some problem, when you want
to fix, solve some problem, when
you want to write some code,
you actually know what those building
blocks inside of the computer
itself actually are.
We'll, ultimately, too, take
off some of the training wheels
that we've had on for the past
few weeks, particularly in C,
and we'll also introduce
more familiar media types.
So files, like images
are sort of everywhere.
And we'll introduce
you to exactly what's
going on when you just look
at a photograph, or a GIF,
or a PNG, or any kind of image on
your screen like this one here.
And it will become clear that,
unlike Hollywood TV shows and movies,
if you try to enhance
a picture like this
to look closer, and closer, and
closer, in the movies typically
trying to figure out who the bad
guy is, for instance, eventually,
you run out of information because
there's only a finite number of bits
or bytes that compose these files.
So any time you've seen
computers that you just
hit a button, and boom, it's enhanced,
and all of a sudden the suspect
is clear, that's a lot more Hollywood
than it is computer science.
But with that said,
later in the term, we
will talk about artificial intelligence.
And even though there might
not be that information there,
through statistical reasoning,
and modeling, and predictions,
can computers increasingly
actually create
information, where perhaps
there was none, just based
on what's most likely to be there?
So more on that before long, too.
But you'll see that all of these dots
on the screen, all of these pixels,
so to speak, are just a grid
up, down, left, right that
compose these pictures.
And we're fortunate to have
three volunteers on stage who
kindly, just before the lecture began,
created their own pixel artwork,
so to speak, on this here easel.
If you guys would like
to spin this around,
let's see what it is
you've been working on.
And if you'd like to introduce
yourselves as our three artists
today, first.
SPEAKER 2: Yes, I'm Talia.
I'm a junior at the college studying
economics with a possible computer
science secondary.
SPEAKER 3: Hi.
My name is Bulut.
I'm from BU.
SPEAKER 1: Welcome.
SPEAKER 4: I'm a Assalo Caesar,
self-taught computer science student.
I've been working as a
software engineer since age 16.
SPEAKER 1: Nice.
Well, welcome to you all.
And if you would like to give
us a description of what it
is that you built out of pixels here.
SPEAKER 2: So we built a firework.
SPEAKER 1: OK, nice.
And it's very blocky
because what we've given
them is post-it notes, each of which
represents one of these pixels or dots.
Now, typically, it
might be black or white,
but the post-it notes we
have here are pink or blue.
So each of these represents
a dot on the screen.
And I gather you did
one other that actually
conveys maybe a bit more information,
if you want to reveal version two.
And thus we have yet more pixel art.
So maybe round of applause for what
our volunteers were able to do using
pixels alone.
Thank you.
We have, as always, limited supply
of delicious Super Mario Brothers
Oreos for each of you.
Thank you so much for coming up.
But thank you.
But the point here,
really, is that there's
only so much you can do when you
just have dots on the screen.
Now, of course, the image that
we saw a moment ago of these
here stress balls is
much higher quality.
It's much higher fidelity, or more
specifically, much higher resolution.
And resolution just refers to how
many dots or pixels are on the screen.
And the smaller they
are, and the more you
cram in on the screen, the clearer,
and clearer the images are.
But at the end of the day,
even this here pixel art
represents what's going on your phone,
your laptop, your desktop, your TV
nowadays, because all it
is this grid of pixels.
Now, before we can actually write
code that actually manipulates
these kinds of images,
we need to understand,
and we need to have some new
syntax for navigating files.
So not just text, but files
stored somewhere on the computer,
somewhere on the server.
But let's consider how we might
store even information like this.
But we'll make it simpler.
Here is a grid of zeros
and ones, clearly.
But I would argue that each of
these might as well represent
a pixel, an individual dot.
And if that dot is a zero, it's
representing the color black.
If that dot is a one, it's
representing the color white.
Given that, can anyone see
what this grid is a picture of,
even though it's using zeros and ones
and not post-it notes, like this here?
Yeah, in the back?
It's a smiley face.
How do you see that?
Well, in a moment it's
going to be super obvious.
But if I actually get rid of the
ones, leaving just the zeros,
there you have the zeros that
were there just a moment ago.
So what this translates
to, typically on a screen,
is not a pattern of zeros and
ones literally on the screen,
but a pattern of dots.
So again, white might be
one, and black might be--
one might be white.
Zero might be black.
But we picture it, of course, on
our screens as this actual grid.
But that's really all we need.
Inside of a file to store
something like an image,
we just need a pattern
of zeros and ones.
But of course, having more
colors would be more interesting.
And if you actually have a larger grid,
you can do even more with pixel art.
And in fact for fun, at the
beginning of the semester,
we have a staff training with all of
the teaching fellows, course assistants,
teaching assistants, and we gave
them all this Google spreadsheet.
And we sort of resized all
of the rows and columns
to just be squares instead
of the default rectangles.
And then we encouraged them to
create something out of this.
And in fact, just a few weeks ago,
here are some of this year's creations,
creating, essentially, images
using Google Spreadsheets
by treating each of the cells
as just a dot on the screen.
So here, we have a team
who in a few minutes
made a Super Mario World,
a bigger canvas, of course,
than this here easel.
Here we have a pixel
based version of Scratch.
Here, we had an homage to the
Harvard-Yale football competition.
And then here, we had a
character of some sort.
So this is what the team here did.
And actually, if you'd
like to play along at home
at the risk of distracting
you the entirety of lecture,
if you go to this URL here,
it'll actually give you
a copy of that same blank spreadsheet.
But let's talk about representing,
not just zeros and ones,
and black and white, but actual colors.
And so recall from week
zero when we talked
about how to represent
information, colors among,
them we introduced RGB, which
stands for red, green, blue.
And it's just this kind of convention
of using some amount of red,
some amount of green, and some amount
of blue mixed together to give you
the actual color that you want.
Well, it turns out in
the world of computers,
there's a standard way for describing
those amounts of red, green, and blue.
At the end of the day,
it's of course just bits.
And equivalently, it's
just numbers, like 72, 73,
33 was the arbitrary example we used
in week zero for the color yellow.
But there actually tends to be a
different notation by convention
for representing colors that
we'll actually see today, too,
as we explore the world of memory.
So here's a screenshot of Photoshop.
If you've never used it before,
this is like the color picker
that you can pull up, just to pick
any number of millions of colors
by clicking and dragging,
or typing in numbers.
But notice down here.
We've picked at the moment
the color black by moving
the slider all the way down here
to the bottom left hand corner.
And what this user
interface is telling us
is that there's zero red,
zero green, zero blue.
And a conventional way of
writing this on a screen
would be, literally, a hash symbol,
and then three pairs of digits.
zero, zero for red, zero, zero
for green, zero, zero for blue.
If by contrast, you were to pick
the color, say, white in Photoshop,
it gets a little weird.
Now it's a lot of red, a lot of green,
a lot of blue, as you might expect,
cranking all of those values up.
But the way you write it
conventionally is not using decimal,
but using letters of the
alphabet, it would seem here.
So FF for red, FF, for
Green, FF for blue.
More on that in a moment.
When it comes to representing
red, here's a lot of red, 255.
Zero green, zero blue.
And so the pattern is now FF0000.
Before I reveal what green is,
what probably should it be?
What pattern?
Yeah.
Close.
Not 0000FF, but 00FF00 because it seems
to be following this pattern, indeed,
from left to right of red, green, blue.
So zero red, 255 green,
zero blue, and thus 00FF00.
And then lastly, if we do solid
blue, it's zero red, zero green,
a lot of blue, and thus 0000FF.
So somehow or other, FF is apparently
representing the number 255.
And we'll see why in just a moment.
But recall that in the
world of computers,
they just speak zeros and ones.
And we've seen that already
in black and white form.
We of course, in the real world, tend
to use decimal instead of binary.
So we have 10 digits at our
disposal, zero through nine.
But it turns out that in the
world of graphics and colors,
turns out in the world
of computer memory,
it tends to be convenient not to use
binary, per se, not to use decimal,
per se, but to use something
called hexadecimal,
where as soon as you need
more than 10 digits total,
you start stealing from
the English alphabet.
So the next few numbers,
or digits rather,
are A, B, C, D, E, F. And
there's other systems that
use even more letters of the
alphabet, but this is probably
the last we'll discuss in any detail.
So in this case, we have a total of
10 plus one, two, three, four, five,
six, so 16 total, a.k.a.
hexadecimal, or what
we might call base 16.
And the capitalization
actually doesn't matter.
It's conventional to use
uppercase or lowercase,
so long as you're generally consistent.
So hexa, implying 16, decimal.
So hexadecimal notation here,
or otherwise known as base 16,
for mathematical reasons that go
back to our discussion in week zero.
So here's some of that same
reasoning from week zero.
How might we go about
representing using two
digits in hexadecimal, different
numbers that you and I know as decimal?
Well, if we consider this as being
the 16 to the zeros place, 16
to the ones place, and if we
do out that math, of course,
that gives us the ones place
and the sixteens place.
So we've only changed the base,
not the story from week zero.
So if we were to start representing
actual values in hexadecimal,
here are two zeros.
So that's 1 times 0 plus 16 times
0, which, of course, gives us
the number you and I know is zero.
So in hexadecimal, and in
binary, and in decimal, it's
the same way to represent the
number you and I know as zero.
But here now is the
number one in hexadecimal.
Here's the number two.
Here's the number three, four,
five, six, seven, eight, nine.
So it's identical up until this
point to our world of decimal.
But how do I count up to what you
and I would call 10 in decimal,
according to what we're
seeing here thus far?
Yeah.
So now it goes up to A,
because A would, apparently,
represent what you and I know as 10.
B represents 11.
C represents 12, 13, 14, 15.
How, though, do I count up to 16?
Yeah.
Exactly.
So not 10, quote unquote,
but one, zero because the one
in the second column here to the left
actually represents the sixteens place.
So it's 16 times 1 gives you 16, plus
1 times 0 gives you 0, so 16 in total.
So this now is the way the number
you and I would think of as 17,
18, 19, 20, 21, dot, dot, dot.
And if we go all the
way up, as high up as we
can count, well, what's the largest
digit, apparently, in hexadecimal?
The smallest is clearly zero,
and the biggest I said was F.
So once you get to FF, the
math gets a little annoying.
But this is now 16 times
15 plus 1 times 15.
And what that gives us, actually,
is the number you and I know as 255.
So we saw it in Photoshop.
We've seen it now in hexadecimal.
This is not math that you
would ever do frequently,
but indeed, it's the exact
same system as week zero,
just with a different base.
But why all of this
additional complexity?
Why are we jumping through these
hoops introducing yet another one
to give us just some
pattern like this of FF?
Well, it turns out that
hexadecimal is just convenient.
Why?
Well, if you have 16
digits in your alphabet,
zero through F, how many
bits, how many zeros and ones
do you need to represent
16 different values?
It's four, right?
Because if you've got four bits, that's
two possibilities for the first times
2, times 2, times 2.
So that's 16 possibilities.
2 to the fourth power.
And if you've got four bits
represented by a single digit,
it's just convenient in practice for
computer scientists and programmers.
So F might indeed represent 1111.
But that's not a full
byte, which is eight bits.
And no one counts in units
of four in computing.
It's always in units of, like, eight,
or 16, or 32, or 64, or the like.
So it turns out, though,
because hexadecimal lends itself
to representing four bits at a time,
well, if you just use two of them,
you can represent eight bits at a time.
And eight bits is a byte, which
is a common unit of measure.
And this is why even Photoshop uses
this convention, as do color programs,
as does web development, more generally,
of using two hexadecimal digits just
to represent single bytes.
Because the one on the left represents
the first bits, the first four bits.
The one on the right represents
the second four bits.
So it's not a big deal, per se.
It's just convenient, even though this
might feel like a lot all at once.
Any questions then on hexadecimal?
Yeah, in the middle.
No.
OK, no.
Questions on hexadecimal.
All right.
So with this system in mind, let's go
about considering where else we might
see this in the computing world.
And I would propose that we
consider, as we've done in the past,
that our computer is really just
this grid of memory, for instance,
where each of these squares
represents a single byte.
And I proposed a couple of
times already that, when
we talk about a
computer's memory, we can
think of them as each of these squares
as having an individual location.
Like, I spitballed back in the day
that maybe this is the first byte,
the second byte, the third byte.
Maybe this is the billionth
byte, so we can number
of the bytes inside of a computer.
Well, it turns out, as
we'll see today in code,
computers typically use
numbers, indeed, to represent
all of the bytes in their
memory, and they typically
use hexadecimal notation
for such by convention.
So what do I mean by that?
Technically, if we were
to start numbering these
and count at zero, as
most programmers would,
this is byte zero, one,
two, three, dot, dot, dot.
This is byte 15.
But if I wanted to keep going,
it would be then 16, 17, 18,
but that's not the true in hexadecimal.
So instead in hexadecimal,
once you hit the nine,
you'd actually use A through
F, just as I've proposed.
Meanwhile, if you kept going
thereafter, you would have one zero.
But as you noted, this is not 10.
This is 16 here, 17, 18, 19.
And so here's where
things get a little weird.
I'm saying 16.
I'm saying 17, and you're obviously
seeing what any reasonable person would
read as 10 and 11.
So there's this dichotomy,
and so we need some convention
for making clear to the reader that
these are hexadecimal numbers, not
decimal.
Otherwise, it's completely ambiguous.
And the convention there, which you
might have seen in the real world,
even though it's a bit weird, is just to
prefix hexadecimal numbers with zero X.
It's not doing anything mathematically.
It's not multiplication
or anything like that.
Just zero X means, here comes a
hexadecimal number hereafter, just
to distinguish it from decimal.
And you can see that, even though we
don't have enough room for 255 bytes,
you start to see patterns
that we haven't even
talked about yet because we're just
using those two columns as the ones
place, the 16th place, and so forth.
Capital or uppercase is fine.
All right.
So with that said, let's actually do
things more technically interesting,
like looking back at some
code that we've already seen
and seeing what we can actually glean
from this newfound representation
of memory location.
So I'm going to go over to VS Code here,
where I've opened my terminal window,
but no code file yet.
And I'm going to go ahead and
create a file called addresses.c
because I want to start playing around
now with the addresses of information
in my computer.
And to do this, let me do
something super simple first.
Let me include standard io.h.
Let me do an int main void,
no command line arguments.
And then in here, let me do exactly
the line of code we just saw.
Declare an int called n, set it
equal to a default value of 50.
And just so that the program
does something noteworthy,
let's have it actually
print out %i backslash n,
and plug-in that value of n.
So this is, like, week one
stuff, just creating a variable,
and printing out its value, just to
make sure that we're on the same page.
So let me do make addresses
in my terminal window, enter.
And when I do dot slash
addresses, no surprise.
I should indeed see the number 50.
But let's consider what that
actually does inside of the computer
now by flipping over, for instance,
to this same line of code,
and translating it into this same grid.
So here's a grid of memory,
and I don't necessarily
know where in the computer's
memory it's going to end up.
So I'm picking spots arbitrarily.
But I know that an int, typically,
is four bytes on most systems.
And so I've used one,
two, three, four squares.
And the first four that I assume
are available are down here,
and I'm calling this n, and
I'm putting the value 50 in it.
So literally, when you write that line
of code, int n equals 50 semicolon,
the computer's doing something
like this underneath the hood.
Might be over here, might be over there,
but I've drawn it simply down there.
But that means that that
50 and that variable n,
in particular, live somewhere
in the computer's memory.
And where might it live?
Well, I don't really know.
And frankly, I'm not going to
care, ultimately, after today.
But let me propose that, if all of these
bytes are numbered from zero on down,
maybe this is address OX123,
for the sake of discussion.
So it's a hexadecimal
number, one, two, three.
It's not 123.
It's one, two, three,
but in hexadecimal,
just because it's a little easy to say.
But that variable n clearly
must live at some address.
So can we maybe see this?
Well, it turns out that in C, there is
a bit more syntax we can introduce today
that actually gives you access
to the locations of variables
inside of the computer's memory.
The first of these is
literally an ampersand,
and you might pronounce that
the address of operator.
Using a single ampersand, you
can actually ask the computer
at what address is this variable.
And then the asterisk
here might be known
as the dereference operator, which
allows you to take an address
and go to it, kind of
like following a map.
X marks the spot.
The star will take you to
that location in memory,
so you can see what's actually there.
So what do I mean by that?
Well, let me go back over to VS
Code here, and let me go ahead
and change my program to be ever
so slightly different, as follows.
I'm going to still declare n, just
as before, to have the value of 50.
But instead of printing
out an integer, per se,
I'm going to print out an address.
And it turns out the format code
for that, using printf, is %p.
And if I want to print
out now the address of n,
recall that I have these two new
capabilities, the first of which
is germane.
The ampersand will get
me the address of n.
So let me go back now to VS
Code, and let me make a change,
whereby I'm going to
change the %i to %p,
which is going to show me an address,
as opposed to an integer, per se.
But I need to tell printf what address
to show, so I don't want to print out n
because that's literally the number 50.
I want to print out the address
of n, like, where is it in memory.
So here I prefix it with an ampersand.
And now if I go back into my terminal
window, make addresses again,
dot slash addresses.
I'm not going to get as lucky
as seeing OX123, probably,
because I got even more memory
than that in this computer.
But when I hit enter, I do
indeed see OX something.
And if I zoom in here,
enhance, if you will,
it happens to be at this moment in
time, on this server, OX7FFC3A7CFFBC.
So it's a big address.
That's a really big number if
we actually did all of the math.
But who really cares?
Just the fact that it exists
somewhere is the only point for now.
So this %p symbol that we're passing
into printf as a format code is
leveraging the fact that C supports
what are known as pointers.
So a pointer is really just an
address, the address of some variable
that you can even store in another
variable called itself a pointer.
So what do I mean by this?
Well, if a pointer is an address, we
can start to tinker with this same idea
as follows.
Let me actually go back
to VS Code once more
and play around with syntax like this.
So let me still declare a variable
called n and set it equal to 50.
But let's actually
create an actual pointer,
a variable whose purpose in life is
not to store a boring number like 50,
but the address of some value.
And so the syntax for
that is admittedly weird.
If you want p to be a pointer, a
variable that stores an address,
you literally say int star
for reasons we'll sort of see.
And this is different from the star
I mentioned earlier for reasons
we'll also see soon.
But int star p means,
hey compiler, give me
a variable called p, inside of which
I can store the address of an integer.
What address do you
want to put in there?
Well, now I can borrow that
same syntax from a moment ago.
I can use ampersand n, which is going
to say, hey compiler, give me-- or hey
computer, give me the
address of n itself.
Previously, I didn't
bother with a variable.
I just sent the address
of n into printf directly.
But I can now play with it as follows.
Let me go back to VS Code here.
I'll clear my terminal window.
And let's just play
around with two variables.
So int star p-- so it's an asterisk,
but most people would say star--
equals the address of n.
And now, I can just tweak
line seven ever so slightly.
Instead of printing out
in duplicate ampersand n,
I can literally just
pass in p for pointer.
So I've not done anything really that
interesting, other than add a variable,
but just to show you
the syntax via which
you can create a variable
whose purpose in life
is to store one of these addresses.
So let me go ahead and now and
do make addresses once more.
Dot slash addresses.
And we should see, indeed, pretty
much the same idea, the address
at which n happens to be, now that I've
recompiled and actually run my code.
But it gets a little more
interesting than that.
I can do one more thing when it
comes to my computer's memory.
In VS Code here, let me clear my
terminal again, and let me see
if I can perhaps reverse this process.
If n is 50, and p is
storing the address of n,
wouldn't it be interesting if I could
somehow express, go to the address of n
and tell me what is there.
So to do that, I'm just kind of
undoing all of the intellectual work
I'm doing here.
But if I want to print out an integer
at some location, I can go back to %i,
just print an integer as always.
But p now is storing the
address of someplace.
It is the treasure map, so to speak.
So if I want to go
where X marks the spot,
the syntax for that I claimed
a moment ago is star p.
So star p means go to that address.
Don't print the address,
go to that address,
and show me what's inside of
the computer's memory there.
So now, if I go into my
terminal and do make addresses,
and do dot slash addresses, what should
I see on the screen when I hit enter?
50.
So I indeed see now 50.
Now, here's where it's an
unfortunate choice of syntax
from the authors of C decades ago.
Clearly, I'm using star in
two different locations.
And suffice it to say, it
doesn't represent multiplication
in either of them.
It's being used to
represent addresses somehow.
When, on line six, I specify
a data type like int,
and then I have a star, and
then the name of a variable,
that is the syntax for declaring
a pointer, for declaring
a variable that will store an address.
What address?
Well, ampersand n, whatever
that is, OX something.
When you do a star and then the name
of a pointer without specifying a type,
this just means, go there.
So the star clearly is
related to addresses.
It's unfortunate that
it's the same symbol.
It would have been nice if they
picked maybe a different symbol
of punctuation.
But they mean slightly different
things in that context.
On line six, we're
declaring the pointer,
declaring a variable called p that's
going to point to an integers location.
But when I say star p, that
means go to that actual location.
So just try to keep that in mind, even
though it's ever so slightly subtly
different.
So what's going on then inside
of the computer's actual memory?
Well, let's consider that
in pictorial form again.
So even though I've written
the pointer in this way,
int then a space, then star p
equals ampersand n semicolon, that
is the conventional way.
That's how you'll see it on
most websites, most textbooks.
Technically speaking, I will
admit that it might actually
be easier to understand
if you actually move
the asterisk a little to the left,
because this makes, visually,
I think, it even more clear that int
star is the type of the variable p, as
opposed to the star being somehow
attached to the variable name itself.
However, you might also see it written
with a space on either side, which
I don't think really helps anyone.
But the point is that white space
does not matter in this context.
And the conventional way
is to do it by prefixing
the variable's name with the star.
And this avoids getting
into trouble when you
declare multiple variables at a time.
But if it helps you to think about
it, you can think of it as int star
as being the type.
It's not just an int, per se.
So with that said, let's consider now
the canvas of computer's memory inside
of which we're storing n, and now, p.
So previously, I proposed
that n is maybe, yeah,
maybe it's done in the bottom
right hand corner of the screen.
So n is storing the number 50 here.
But technically, n lives somewhere.
And for simplicity, I'm going to claim
it's at OX123, rather than the bigger
actual address we just saw.
But what about p?
Well, p itself is another variable
that I declared separately,
so it's got to live somewhere
in the computer's memory.
And it turns out, by convention,
pointers take up more space.
They typically use eight bytes
nowadays, rather than just four.
Why is that?
Well, if you've got eight bytes,
you can count even higher.
You can have even more addresses.
You can have more memory in
your Mac, your PC, and phone.
That's a good thing.
So pointers tend to
be eight bytes, which
is why I've used eight
squares on the screen here.
But what is actually p storing?
Well, it's just storing a number.
Yes, it's technically an
integer, but that integer
is itself should be thought of as
the address of some other value.
So n is down here at OX123. p is
up here at who knows what address.
Doesn't matter for the
sake of discussion,
but its value, what it's storing
with its pattern of 64 bits
is apparently OX123.
So how does this help us?
Well, if you think about this
a little more abstractly, who
cares about what else is going
on in the computer's memory?
It actually tends to be helpful
to think about this pictorially
as being a little something like this.
At the end of the day,
you and I, even when
we start writing code
in C that uses pointers,
generally, you and I are never going
to care about the actual addresses.
Even though I showed you
OX7 something, that's
not generally useful information.
It's suffices to know
that it exists somewhere,
and let the computer figure
out how to get there.
And so very often when talking about
pointers and addresses more generally,
people actually abstract
them away, so to speak.
So instead of literally
writing on the screen
or the whiteboard when discussing this,
OX123, what the actual address is,
who cares what it is?
It suffices that it's a value
that leads me to the other value
that I care about, sort of the treasure
map, as I described it earlier.
So let's now connect this maybe
a little more metaphorically.
So Carter, maybe here
you might have noticed
that we've had for a while now
these two mailboxes on the stage.
So this white one here is labeled p
to represent our pointer variable.
Carter's is labeled n,
representing our actual integer.
And what's really kind
of going on here is
that, if I were to access
the value inside of p,
much like we saw it up here, that's
like opening this up and figuring out
what the actual value is.
Now, this itself is a little arcane.
OX123.
And so if we actually do this
a little more metaphorically,
we can maybe do this and point
our way, if you don't mind.
So here we have a big pointer.
Oh, forgive me.
I guess we'll use this one here.
OK.
So we have this big
pointer that's essentially
pointing at the location in memory
that we care about, be it OX123,
or something else.
And then if we dereference this,
that is, use the star notation,
star p, that's like asking
Carter to go to that location,
open up the mailbox, and voila.
What value do you have there?
Voila.
Maybe a big round of applause
for Carter for having
practiced this beforehand with me.
All right.
That was mostly just an excuse
to use the foam fingers today.
But with that said, that's
hopefully a helpful metaphor,
honestly, because these pointers,
these addresses actually
tend to be among the
more arcane topics in C
that, even if things are kind of
clicking right now, as soon as you
start writing code
involving addresses, it's
easy to get lost in some of the details.
But metaphorically,
these mailboxes are meant
to represent, really, what's going on.
Mailboxes in the physical
human world have addresses.
I can go to that address, open it up,
and then I can go to another address
by following that treasure map,
if you will, or pictorially here,
the arrow that's pointing
from one location to another.
So even though it's very weird syntax
with ampersands, and asterisks,
and the like, it's just
addresses in memory,
much like mailboxes in the real world.
So with that said, let's maybe
begin to take off certain training
wheels by revisiting what strings are,
as we've been using them thus far.
So here's a line of code in C that
we've been using since week one,
really, where I declare a string
variable called s, and set it equal to,
quote unquote, hi.
Now, technically "hi" is three letters,
or two letters in a punctuation symbol.
But how many bytes is
that string taking up?
Is it one, two, three, or was it--
I'm seeing it here.
It's four.
Why?
Yeah, there's always a null character
that, even though you don't see it
on the screen, that is what terminates
every string, we claimed, a while back.
So if I were to draw
this maybe "hi" ends up
in the computer's memory down
here, bottom right hand corner.
But it is indeed four
bytes, not just three
because, secretly, there's
always been that null character,
even though we as
programmers don't often
have to type it explicitly ourselves.
That's what the double quotes do for us.
It terminates the string
with that null character.
Now, recall from week two
when we talked about arrays,
we started playing around
with strings as really
just being arrays of characters.
So we call them a string, but we
could treat them as arrays of char,
so to speak.
So if the string was called s, s bracket
zero would give us the first char,
s bracket one the second,
s bracket two the third.
And if you're really
curious, s bracket three
would give you the last
hidden null character,
which we saw on the
screen as just a zero
when we printed it out, while
tinkering with some actual code.
But technically, today,
logically, it would
seem that it's also true
that H-I exclamation
point and the null character must
clearly live at some address.
They must clearly live in
their own mailbox, so to speak.
So maybe, for the sake of
discussion, this H today is at OX123.
But recall that arrays are characterized
by contiguousness from left to right.
So if H is at OX123, it must be the
case that I is at OX124, I is at 125,
and the null character is at OX126
because those are one byte apart.
And I deliberately chose
numbers here where,
whether it's decimal or
hexadecimal, it doesn't matter.
These differ by just
one byte themselves.
So that's what implies
that they're indeed
adjacent, or contiguous in memory.
But what is s then?
When I declared s to
be a string, what is
it that's been going
in s all of this time
if, clearly, s is
actually this thing here?
Well, strings have kind of been
a white lie for a few weeks
because s itself,
technically, is a pointer.
s is the address of this string.
So the string is
somewhere in memory, but s
itself is a separate
variable that gives you
a clue as how to find all of
those characters in memory.
So if you had to guess
just intuitively now,
if this is the string actually
in memory, that is, this
is the array of chars in
memory, what would logically
make sense to put as the value of s?
A pointer.
Specifically?
A pointer to h.
And how would I express that?
What's the actual value?
OX123 might very well suffice
as the value here of s.
Now, why might that be?
Well, that essentially
gives you enough information
to find the beginning of the
string, "hi" in this case.
Now, you might think,
well, wait a minute.
How does it know about the second
character and the third character?
But now, if you kind of rewind
in time, oh, wait a minute,
maybe now the null character actually
makes even more sense from week two.
Why?
Because if s technically
storing the location
of the beginning of
the string, someone's
got to keep track of where
the string ends, presumably.
And that's effectively the string itself
because humans decided decades ago,
let's just null terminate
every string with a special
so character, zero, all zero bits,
eight zero bits, specifically.
But and that's enough information.
The sort of treasure map leads you
to the beginning of the string,
and then you can use a
for loop, a while loop,
or whatever to walk through the
string, and that's what printf does.
And you just stop as soon as
you see that null character.
So this then is what
a string actually is.
s is and has always been, since
week one, a pointer, so to speak,
that actually refers to the start
of that array of characters.
And frankly, again, who cares
about the OX123 specifics?
We can abstract that away
and actually just treat
s as, literally, an arrow that points
to the beginning of that string
because it will be rare that we
actually care about where this thing
physically is in the computer's memory.
Now, before we see this in code,
any questions on this revelation?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Have pointers gotten
larger as computer memories
have increased over the decades?
SPEAKER 1: Yes.
Have pointers gotten larger as computers
memory has increased over the decades?
Short answer, yes.
Like, back in my day, we were
limited to, like, two gigabytes
of memory total.
Well, why two?
Well, if you had 32-bit
memory, or if you use 32 bits
to represent addresses, a.k.a.
four bytes, as was conventional,
you can count recall as
high as 4 billion values.
But generally, numbers are both negative
and positive, so that halves it.
So the reason decades
ago, computers, PCs, Macs
could have no more than two gigabytes
of memory was because, literally,
the integers being used,
the pointers being used
were only four bits, that is 32 bits.
Sorry, four bytes,
that is, 32 bits long.
And so you literally
could buy more memory.
You could buy a third
gigabyte, a fourth gigabyte,
but you literally had
no way mathematically
to express all of
those bigger locations.
So it was effectively
useless, in that case.
In more modern times, computers
tend now to use 64 bits, which
allows you to count crazy high.
And that's more than enough to
address bigger chunks of memory.
Really good question.
Others on memory thus far.
No, all right.
Well, let's translate this a bit to
code by going back over to VS Code here.
And let me propose now that we
revisit maybe a simpler string
example, as opposed to these integers.
So let me go ahead and throw away
all of this integer related code.
Let me go ahead and, for
the moment, include CS50.h
so that we have access to string
and other things as in week one.
And let me do a string s equals
quote unquote "HI" in all caps.
And let me do a simple safety
check %s backslash n s,
just to make sure everything
works as it did in week one.
So make addresses, dot slash
addresses, and I should indeed
see "HI" on the screen.
Well, let's now kind of tinker with
what's going on underneath the hood.
And now, things can get a
little more memory specific.
So I'm still going to declare
s as a string up here.
But you know what?
Instead of printing
out the string itself,
let me actually treat s as
the pointer I claim it is.
I claim a string is just an address,
so I have this new syntax today,
%p to print out pointers,
to print out addresses.
Let's see what s actually is.
Let me do make addresses again, dot
slash addresses, and there it is.
It's not as simple as OX123, but
it is at location OX55C670878004.
All right.
Who really cares, specifically?
But if we poke around a bit more,
things might make a bit more sense.
Let's do this.
Let's also print out the address
using %p of, how about the very first
character of s.
So the very first character
of is known as s bracket zero.
We did that in week two,
treating a string as an array.
But how do I get the
address of a character?
Well, I have our new
symbol today, ampersand.
So even though this looks like a
mouthful, ampersand, s, square bracket,
zero, square bracket, it's
just two ideas combined.
s bracket zero gives you the
first character in the string, s.
And adding an ampersand at the beginning
says, tell me what that address is.
So if I recompile this code, make
addresses, dot slash addresses,
even if you don't remember
the value OX whatever,
what are we going to see on
the screen at a higher level?
Perhaps the same exact thing.
Why?
Well, s is just an address.
But what does that mean?
Well, it's just the address
of its first character.
And we saw that per our
picture a moment ago.
So can I see the contiguousness of this?
Well, I'm going to resort to some
copy paste just for time's sake,
even though this is going
to look a little silly,
and I could certainly
use a loop instead.
But let me print out the second
location, the third location, and heck,
even the fourth location, whoops, the
fourth location of that null character.
If I now do make addresses again and
dot slash addresses, and zoom in,
I don't really care about
what these are, specifically.
But notice the first two are indeed the
same because the first represents s.
The first represents the
first character of s,
which now I reveal are
exactly the same idea.
And the next ones are
literally just one byte
away, ending in five, six,
and seven, respectively.
So again, the numbers
in and of themselves
are not useful, actionable
information, but it
does let us actually see what's
going on underneath the hood.
So just to rewind for a moment, let
me actually go back to the original
version, where I'm printing out
the string itself, using %s.
Let me remake addresses to make sure
that, OK, it still prints out "HI".
But what has been going
on now all this time?
Well, let me go back to
our simple line of code
that we've been using
since week one, which
gave us a string called s, setting
it equal to the value of "HI".
Let me propose now that strings
were indeed this white lie.
And if I can unnecessarily
dramatically say,
here we take the training
wheels off and reveal
that, all this time, string, string is
probably, actually, what, technically?
Yeah.
A char star.
That was amazing.
Thank you for that.
So yeah.
So it's a char star, which
admittedly at first glance,
just makes a simple idea look
unnecessarily complicated.
And that's why in week one, we indeed
introduced these training wheels,
whereby we, CS50, invented the datatype
called string, just to kind of hide
this lower level detail.
If you will, string for
us is an abstraction.
Now, that is to say string
is not a CS50 specific word.
Every programmer in the
world knows what a string is.
It is a sequence of characters.
It is an array of characters.
But in C, technically, decades
ago when it was invented,
they didn't think, they didn't decide
to create an actual data type called
string because, especially if they
were among those more comfortable,
char star is equivalent, and it
achieves the exact same thing,
even though at a glance, we didn't want
to start week one with that lower level
detail.
Question here in front.
Sure.
Can I clarify how the
star makes it a string?
So we've, up until now, been
just calling it a string
so that's s is a string.
And that's a sufficient mental model.
But technically, what is a string?
I claimed pictorially
with my grid of memory
that a string is really just an address.
It's really just the address
of its first character.
I then tried to demonstrate as
much in code by using percent p
and showing you, literally, s
is a value, like, OX something.
And literally, its first character is
at that same address, OX something.
So here, when I claim that
string has never really existed,
except within the confines of CS50,
technically, the data type of a string
is best expressed as char star.
Why?
Well, a string clearly can't just be
a char because a char, by definition,
is a single character.
A string, we already know,
is a sequence of characters.
But how can you represent
a sequence of characters?
You can call it a char star, which
is a different data type that we're
introducing today for the first time.
And the star just means
that s itself is not a char.
The star means that s is
the address of a char.
And by convention, it's the address
of the first char in a string.
So with that said, if I go back
to my actual VS Code over here,
I can change, literally,
char string to char star s.
I can get rid of the CS50 library,
our so-called training wheels,
which has been the goal for the past
few weeks, to put them on initially
and then take them off quite quickly.
So now this is the same program, and %s
is still the same. s is still the same.
Everything else is still the same.
All I've done is change,
quote unquote, string to,
quote unquote, char star, which
obviates the need for the CS50 library.
And if I now do make addresses
and dot slash addresses,
"HI" behaves exactly as it would.
So this is now raw native C code
without any training wheels,
without any CS50 scaffolding, that
just uses these basic building
blocks and primitives.
Other questions on this?
AUDIENCE: Could you please clarify why
we don't use the end symbol for that
s, as opposed to the other ones?
SPEAKER 1: Correct.
Why don't we use the ampersand symbol
for this, though we did earlier?
So in this case, there's
no reason for an ampersand
because the ampersand tells you
what the address of a variable is.
I'll concede that it probably
would be a little more
consistent for us to do this, which
is maybe where your mind is going.
Now, never mind the fact that looks
even worse, I think, syntactically.
It's a reasonable
instinct, but it turns out
that two is what the double
quotes are doing for you.
The C compiler, called
Clang, is smart enough
to realize that when it sees double
quotes around a sequence of characters,
it wants to put the address of that
first char in the variable for you.
But when we had a variable
like n, which we created,
you have to distinguish
n from its address.
So that's why we prefixed
n with an ampersand.
But the double quotes
take care of it for you.
Other questions on these here addresses?
No?
All right.
Well, beyond that, let me propose
that we tinker with one other idea
to see how we actually invented
this thing called a string.
Well, I claim that
string is just char star.
You've actually seen
this technique before.
It was just a week ago that we tinkered
with structures, custom data types
to represent a person.
And recall that we had a structure
of a name and a number representing
a person.
But more importantly, we
had this keyword typedef,
which defines your own type
to be whatever you want.
Now, we used it a little
more powerfully last time
to actually represent a whole
structure of a person, having a name,
and having a number.
But at the end of the day, we really
just invented our own data type
that we called, obviously, person.
But and that represented,
indeed, this structure.
But typedef was really the
enabling element there.
And so it turns out with
typedef, you can create
any number of data types of your own.
For instance, if you
just really can't get
the hang of calling
an integer an int, you
can create your own
data type called integer
that itself is a synonym for int,
because the way typedef works,
even though this one's even
simpler than the struct,
is you can read it from right to left.
This means give me a data type called
integer that is actually an int.
And that's the same thing
that happened a moment ago.
Give me a data type called person
that is actually this whole structure.
But an integer is even simpler.
Now, most people wouldn't do this.
This really doesn't create any
intellectual enhancement of the data
types, but you could do
it if you really wanted.
More commonly, and as you'll
see this in code in the future,
would be not just a typedef
something like an integer.
But it turns out, curiously,
C has no data type for a byte.
Like, there's no built in obvious
way to represent eight bits
and store whatever you want in them.
However, you can use
what's called a uint8_t, t
which is a data type that comes with
C. And frankly, those more comfortable
might simply use this
data type once you sort of
commit to memory that it exists.
But honestly, for most of us, it's a
lot more convenient to think of a byte
as being its own data type.
When you want to write code that
manipulates one or two or more bytes,
wouldn't it be nice to have
a data type called byte?
So it turns out that you can represent
a byte, which is eight bits using
an unsigned integer with 8 bits.
And this is just a data type that's
declared in some other C header file.
But long story short, you'll
see and use this before long.
But it's just a synonym to make
things a little more user friendly,
like person, like string, like byte.
So what is in the CS50 header
file, among other things?
Literally, this line of code.
This is the single line
of code that we deploy
in week one onward that teaches
Clang to think of the word string
as being synonymous with char star,
so that you all never have to type,
or know, or think about char star
until, wonderfully, today in week four,
a couple of weeks later instead.
So that's all we've been doing.
That is the technical implementation
of the training wheels.
It's just using a custom
data type in this way.
So how about one other maybe pair
of examples here with our addresses,
such that we can tinker
a little bit further?
It turns out that, once
everything in the world
is addressable using these pointers,
like using numeric addresses
to represent where things are
in memory, you can actually
do something called pointer arithmetic.
And here, too, we the
programmers generally
don't care what the specific values
are, but we care that they do exist.
And if they do exist, we can
maybe do some arithmetic on them
and add one to go to the next byte,
add two to go to the next, next byte,
add three to go to the next,
next, net byte, and so forth.
So pointer arithmetic literally
refers to doing math on addresses.
So how do we translate this
into something actionable?
Let me actually go back
to VS Code here, and let
me propose that we do
something like the following.
I'm going to throw away
my first printf here.
And I'm instead going to print out
this string character by character,
just like we did in week two.
Let me go ahead and call printf, pass
in %c for a single char, backslash n,
comma, and now I want to print
out the first character in s.
Using array notation, what do I type
to print the first character in s?
Yep, over here.
s bracket zero.
So s bracket zero gives me
the first character in s.
And let me copy paste just
for demonstration sake
here inside of my same
curly braces, and print out
the second char, and the third.
And I don't care about
the null character.
I just want to print the
string itself for now.
So even though this is jumping through
way more hoops than just using %s
and print the whole thing at once, it's
again, just demonstrating how we can,
at a lower level,
manipulate these strings.
So let me do make addresses,
dot slash addresses.
And yet again, we see,
somewhat stupidly, one
per line, H-I exclamation point.
I can, of course fix that
by getting rid of this.
I can get rid of this, and I
can leave the last backslash n.
So let's just make it a
look a little prettier.
Make addresses, dot
slash addresses, enter,
and I can print it out all on one line.
But now using pointer
notation, it turns out
we can do one other thing,
which admittedly, for now,
is going to feel like
unnecessary complexity.
But it's actually a really helpful tool
to add to our toolkit, so to speak,
whereby I could instead do this.
To print out the first character in
s, yes, I can treat it as an array
and get the zeroth index.
However, what is s? s is
just the address of a string.
What does that mean? s is the address
of the first char in the string.
So if I do star s, what's
that going to print?
Presumably h, right?
Because if the first character in s is
h, then star s will go to that address
and show me what's actually there.
And let me go ahead and do this again.
Let me copy paste twice and
then tweak this a little bit.
I want to go to the next byte over.
Well, I could do s bracket one.
All right, but I could
instead go to s plus one.
And I could instead go
to s plus two, thereby
doing what we're calling pointer
arithmetic, math on addresses.
And now, if I go ahead and rerun make
addresses, dot slash addresses, voila.
Whoops, I forgot my backslash n.
Let's fix that just to be tidy.
Dot slash addresses, voila.
There is our "HI".
Now, this is not how a normal
person would print out a string,
but it does go to show you that
there's not really been any magic.
Like, these characters are just
where we predicted they would be.
And now that you have this star
notation, the dereference operator,
which means go there, you have the
ability to access individual values.
You even have the ability to ask where
those things are by using ampersands,
as well.
But it turns out that the reason that
we introduced the array syntax first
is that the array syntax
is what the world would
call syntactic sugar for exactly this.
When you say s bracket zero, the
compiler is essentially doing star s
and saving you the trouble.
When you do s bracket one,
the compiler is essentially
saving you the trouble of doing
star, in parentheses, s plus one,
and same for the third char, as well.
So all this time, pointers have
been there underneath the hood.
They are what allow us to go to
very specific memory locations.
They are going to be what allow us
soon to start manipulating files,
whether it's photographs of stress
balls, or CSI style content.
But for now, I think we should take our
10 minute break where whoopie pies will
now be served in the transept.
See you in 10.
All right.
So we are back, and we've clearly drawn
too much attention to the stress balls
today because now we're all
out of these and whoopie pies.
But more next week.
In the meantime, though,
we thought we'd now
use some of these new building blocks,
this idea of being able to manipulate
underlying addresses, to
revisit a couple of problems
that we kind of swept
under the rug previously
by avoiding these problems altogether.
So by that, I mean this.
Let me go over to VS Code.
And let me create another
example called compare.c,
whose purpose in life in a moment
is going to be to compare values
in kind of a very weak one way, too.
So let me go ahead and include CS50.h.
Let me go ahead and
include standard io.h.
Let me do int main void,
no command line arguments.
And in here, let me just get two
integers using getint as follows.
So getint, and we'll ask for i.
Let's go ahead and
get int and ask for j,
just so that we have
two things to compare.
And then I'm going to do
something super simple.
So if i equals, equals
j, then let's print out,
as we actually did in the
past, same backslash n.
Else, if they're not the same, let's
of course, print out, for instance,
different.
So super simple program that we
used the first time around, really,
just to demonstrate conditionals.
But now, we'll use it to
tease apart some subtleties.
So let me go ahead and compile
this with make compare.
Dot slash compare.
And we'll compare one and
one for i and j respectively.
Those are, of course, the same.
Let's compare one and two.
Those are, of course, different.
So long story short, this
program seems to work,
and we won't dwell much further on it.
But let's consider for a moment what's
going on inside of the computer's
memory when that code is executed.
So here's my canvas of memory.
Maybe i ends up over here.
Maybe j ends up over here.
Each of them I've drawn as four
squares because integers are typically
four bytes, or 32 bits.
So i has the value 50
here. i has the value 50.
So I accidentally typed
one and one, but assume
that I had typed 50 in both cases.
They both live at these
two separate locations.
All right.
So that's all fine and good.
And when we compare them, of
course, 50 and 50, or one and one
are, in fact, the exact same.
But what if we actually compare
different types of values?
Let me go back into VS Code here.
And instead of integers, let's
still, using the CS50 library,
maybe use some strings instead.
So let me go ahead and change my i
and j to maybe s and t, respectively.
So string s equals getstring.
And I'll ask for s, quote unquote.
And then string t equals getstring.
And then I'll ask for t, quote unquote.
And then down here, I'll
compare s equals, equals t.
So here's the code,
almost the same logically.
I'm just getting different data types
instead, still using the CS50 library.
So let's do make compare
again, dot slash compare.
And let's type in something
like "HI" exclamation point,
"HI" exclamation point.
And that's interesting.
All right, let's maybe try it again.
So maybe lowercase "hi", "hi".
No, those are different.
Let's do it one more
time, like "hi", "bye".
OK, so it half works.
But it seems to be saying
different no matter what.
Well, why might that be?
Well, let me first
just peel back a layer.
We already know that strings
don't technically exist.
They're really char star.
And string here is char star.
So does this reveal,
perhaps implicitly, why
s and t are being thought to be
different, even though I literally
typed "hi" twice?
Yeah, on line nine here,
I'm really just comparing
the addresses that are in s and t, and
that's why I changed it to char star,
just not to change anything,
but to make it even clearer
that s and t are, in fact, addresses.
They're not strings, per se.
They're the address of the first
character in those strings.
And even though they happen to be
the same words that I typed in,
it would seem to imply that they're
ending up in different places.
So here's another canvas
of memory for this program.
And here, for instance,
might be s with enough room
for eight bytes up here as a pointer.
Here maybe is where "hi" ended
up for this particular story.
Well, what's actually going in s?
Well, if h is at OX123, i is at
OX124, and so forth, what's going in
s is OX123.
But when I use get string a
second time and type in "hi"
exclamation point, even the exact
same way, uppercase or lowercase,
t is ending up, presumably,
somewhere else in memory.
So it's maybe using these
eight bytes over here.
The same letters, coincidentally,
by nature of how getstring works,
are ending up in the computer's
memory, maybe down there, bottom right
hand corner.
Those are presumably different
addresses, OX456, 457, 458, 459.
So what's going to go in t as its value?
OX456, according to this example.
And so when you literally
compare s equals,
equals t, no, they're not the same.
They are, in fact, different,
even if what they're pointing at
happens to be the same.
So the computer's taking us literally.
If you compare s and
t respectively, it's
going to compare what
their values actually are.
And their values are the
addresses of the first letter
of this string, and the first
letter of this string, respectively.
And if those addresses
differ, which they clearly do,
they're going to be deemed different.
Now, you might wonder, well, this
just seems stupidly inefficient.
Why put the same string
in two different places?
Well, maybe the string needs
to be changed later on,
and we might want to have two
different versions thereof.
And frankly, the first time you
call getstring, it does its thing.
The second time you call
getstring, it does its own thing.
It doesn't necessarily know how many
times it's been called in the past.
And so maybe there's no
communication between those calls.
And so surely, it's going
to do the simple thing
and just create more memory, create
more memory for each of those strings,
duplicates though they may seem to be.
So what does this imply?
Well, you might recall that we
avoided this problem altogether
just a week ago by using
what solution on line nine?
I did not compare two strings
using equals, equals last time.
Exactly.
We used the strcompare function,
which is in string.h very deliberately
at the time, because I didn't want
to trip over this mistake at the time
until we were sort of ready and
had the vocabulary to discuss it.
But I did not do s equals, equals
t, even though, logically, that's
what you're trying to
do, compare for equality.
But if you know now
what a string is, it's
an array of characters
starting at some address.
You really need someone
something to do the heavy lifting
of comparing every one of
those chars from left to right.
We did it ourselves last time by just
implementing it in code two weeks ago.
But strcompare compare does it for us.
So strcompare, s comma t actually
weirdly returns three possible values,
zero if they're the same, a positive
number if one comes before the other,
or a negative number if
the opposite is true.
So strcomp, remember, can
be used for alphabetizing
things, or ascii-betizing things,
based on those Ascii values.
So this version, if I open my terminal
window now and do make compare,
dot slash compare, and type in
"hi" and "hi", now, in fact,
they're the same because
strcomp is doing the work
of comparing them char by char.
And if I do "hi" and "bye", those
are now, in fact, different.
So we avoided the problem last time
for this very reason that simply using
equals, equals would not have worked.
Yes.
AUDIENCE: Using those values?
Is it like one minus
one, or one, two, three,
depending how different they are?
SPEAKER 1: Oh, good question.
So when using strcompare,
the documentation
says that it will return zero, or a
positive number, or a negative number.
It doesn't tell you a specific number.
So the magnitude of the integer that
comes back actually has no meaning.
It might very well be one, zero, and
negative one, but there's no guarantee.
And so you can check for
equality equals, equals,
or you should check for
greater than or less
than, but not specific
to a certain number.
So it just gives you relative ordering.
It doesn't give you any
more detail than that.
All right.
So if we were to now take
this lesson a step further,
just to hammer home this point, whereby
these strings s and t must clearly
live at different addresses, let's
actually try to see this in code.
So let me go back to VS Code here.
Let me go ahead and just remove
all of the conditional code,
and instead do something old school,
like print out %s backslash n and print
out s.
Then Let's go ahead and print
out %s again, but print out t,
just to see the two strings
as being duplicative.
So here I go.
Make compare dot slash compare,
"hi" exclamation point,
"hi" exclamation point.
And of course, they're
actually the same.
But if I actually want
to see where s and t are,
I can change the % s to what?
%p, %p here.
And I don't need to use an
ampersand before the s or the t
because they are already addresses.
That was today's big reveal.
And it turns out that printf
is smart enough when you use s,
and you give it an address of s, or the
address in t, to just go there for you.
So printf has been doing
all of that for us with %s.
But %p is actually going to
print out those raw addresses.
So let me do make compare, dot slash
compare, "hi" once, "hi" twice.
And here now, we should see the
addresses at which "hi" lives.
And it's not going to be as
simplistic as OX123 and OX456.
But if I go back to my
terminal and hit enter,
indeed, I get two different
hexadecimal values
that makes clear that, if I were to
naively compare them with equals,
equals, they're always
going to be different,
even if I typed in the same words.
So there's implications now
of this, especially if we want
to start changing things in memory.
So for instance, let me create
a new program called copy.c.
And in here, we'll start
somewhat similarly with CS5o.h.
We'll start with standard io.h.
And preemptively, I'm going to go
ahead and include string.h, as well.
I'm going to declare main as not
taking any command line arguments.
And this time, I'm just going to
get one string s with getstring,
and I'll prompt the user for s.
And now, let me go ahead
and naively say this.
Let me give myself a new string
called t and just set it equal to s,
my instinct being this is how
I've copied integers before.
This is how I've copied
floating point values before.
This surely is how I copy strings,
using the assignment operator as usual.
Let me now for the sake
of discussion propose
that I want to capitalize
the first letter in t,
but not the first letter in s.
So logically, based on week two syntax,
I'm going to go into the t string,
go to location zero, and set it
equal to upper of t bracket zero.
So recall, we introduced two upper.
It's just a handy function
for capitalizing things.
There's two lower, and there's
a bunch of others, as well.
I didn't include the header file
yet, though, so I'm going to go back
and include--
anyone remember where these are?
Yeah, ctype.h.
And it's fine to look that up
in the menu if you ever need it.
So here, I am, a little naively,
capitalizing the first letter in t.
Technically speaking, I should
check what the length of t
is first, because if there's no
characters there, if it has zero chars,
there's nothing to uppercase.
But for now, I'm going to keep it
simple and just blindly do that there.
Now, let me go ahead and print
out with %s the value of s.
Now, let me go ahead and
print out with %s value of t.
And I should see one lowercase s and one
capitalized T. All right, here we go.
Make copy, dot slash copy.
And I'm going to deliberately
type it in lowercase.
"hi" exclamation point, and we should
see now they're both capitalized,
it would seem.
Intuitively, why might that be?
Exactly, the addresses are the same.
So if I do use the assignment operator
and just do t equals s semicolon,
it's going to take me literally and
copy the address in s over to t,
so that effectively, they're
pointing at the same thing.
So if we draw another picture here,
for instance, here maybe is s,
and here maybe is the lowercase
"hi" that I first type
in down here in memory.
Maybe that's at OX123 again, and
therefore that's what's in s.
When I then create the variable
t by declaring it to be a string,
as well, that gives me another
variable here called t.
But I'm just setting it equal to s.
I'm not calling getstring
again in this version of copy.
That was in compare.
In copy, I'm just
literally copying s into t.
So that literally just changes
the value to OX123, also.
And if we abstract away
all of these addresses,
that's essentially like s and t
both pointing to the same place.
So if I use s bracket zero, or t
bracket zero, they are one and the same.
So when I use t bracket
zero to use uppercase,
it's changing that
lowercase h to capital H.
But again, both strings, both pointers
are pointing at the same value.
And again, this should be
even clearer as of today.
If I go back into VS Code and, indeed,
take these training wheels off,
and treat string as what it is, char
star, which indicates that both s and t
are just addresses, which makes
even clearer, syntactically,
that this is probably the picture
that's going on underneath the hood.
Now, just to make the
code a little more robust,
let me at least be a
little careful here.
If the string length of t is greater
than zero, then and only then,
should I really blindly index into
the string and go to location zero.
That doesn't really solve
the fundamental problem,
but it at least avoids a situation
where maybe the user just hits enter,
gives me no characters,
and I try to blindly
uppercase something that's not there.
But there's still a bug.
There's still a bug.
So how do I actually solve this?
Well, it turns out we
need two other functions
that we haven't had occasion to use.
But these are perhaps the
most powerful, and they're
going to allow us to solve even
grander problems next week when
we discuss all the more,
things called data structures.
But for now, let's very simply
solve this idea of copying a string.
Let me go back into VS Code here, and
let me give myself one more header file
that's called standard
lib for standard library.
So include standard lib dot h,
in which both of these functions,
malloc and free, are declared for me.
And now, in my code, I'm going to
behave a little bit differently here.
Clearly, I got into trouble by
just blindly copying the addresses.
What I really want to do when I
copy strings, presumably, and then
uppercase one of them,
is I want to create
a duplicate string, a second
array that is identical,
but is elsewhere in memory.
So the way to do this
might be as follows.
Instead of just setting t
equal to s, I should really
call this brand new
function called malloc,
which stands for memory allocate,
and it takes a single argument,
which is just the number of bytes
you would like the operating system
to allocate for you.
So whether you're using this on
Windows, Mac OS, or Linux in our case,
this is a way I can literally
ask the operating system,
please find for me some number
of bytes in the computer's memory
that I can now use for my own purposes.
So malloc here, I technically
need at least three bytes,
but that's not going
to be enough because I
need a fourth for the null character.
So I could put four here.
But that's stupid.
I shouldn't just hardcode a
number like this we've seen.
So I could probably do strlen
of s to dynamically figure out
how many bytes I want for the copy.
But that, too, is not
enough because string length
returns the human readable
length, so H-I exclamation point.
So I think I want a
plus one in there, too.
So that just means get the length
of whatever the human typed in,
add one for the null character to make
sure that we're not undercounting.
Now, what can I then do?
Unfortunately, I need to
do a bit of work here.
So let me actually go ahead
now and do something like this.
For int i equals zero, I is less than
the string length of s, i plus, plus.
And then inside of this loop, I could
copy into the ith location of t,
whatever is in the ith location of s.
Now, this is a little buggy.
One, this is inefficient to
keep asking this question.
We talked about this in
the context of design.
I should probably improve this by
giving myself a variable like n,
set that equal to the string
length, and then do i is less than n
again, and again, just
so I'm not stupidly
calling string length four different
times, or three different times.
But this, too, is slightly buggy,
and this one's very subtle.
This does not fully copy s into t.
Does anyone see the very subtle
bug that I've introduced?
Sorry?
Yeah, I'm forgetting the backslash zero.
So even though I'm copying
H-I exclamation point,
or whatever the human typed in, I need
to go one step further deliberately
to make sure I also
copy the backslash zero,
or at least manually put it in myself.
So I could solve this by, either
doing this up to and through n,
i is less than or equal to
n, or I could plus one here.
That, too, would be fine.
Or if I really want, I could
do this, like t bracket
three equals, quote
unquote, backslash zero.
But again, I shouldn't get into
the habit of hard coding things.
I could do string length of s, and that
would give me the last location in s,
which would also work.
But that, too, is stupid.
I might as well--
or just unnecessarily complex.
Let's just do this, change
one symbol, and boom.
Now we're copying all three, and
the fourth character, as well.
All right, so with this
said, let's go ahead now
and make sure that t is indeed of
length at least greater than zero.
Then let's go ahead and capitalize t
as before and print out the results.
So let me go ahead and open my terminal
window, make copy, dot slash copy,
and I'm going to deliberately
type "hi" in lowercase.
And now we should see disparate s and t.
s is now still lowercase,
and T is now capitalized.
But why is that exactly?
Well, let me actually go into,
say, my computer's memory
again and propose that,
if what I had before
was this situation, where s is
pointing at this chunk of memory,
and t was accidentally pointing in that
same chunk of memory, what we really
want to do is have t point
at a new chunk of memory.
And malloc is what gives
us this chunk of memory.
And then using that for loop, can I copy
the H, the I, the exclamation point,
and even the backslash zero.
So now, this is a little subtle,
but malloc is what gives me
access to this new chunk of memory.
Malloc takes one argument, the number of
bytes that you want it to find for you.
Take a guess.
What value is malloc returning?
Conceptually, it's returning a chunk
of memory, but that's kind of handwavy.
What might malloc actually be returning?
AUDIENCE: Maybe the pointer
to the first character?
SPEAKER 1: Perfect.
malloc is returning the address of that
chunk of memory, not the last address.
The first address.
And here's a difference with strings.
This chunk of memory is not magically
terminated with null for you.
I had to do that with for loop. malloc,
and in turn, your operating system,
does keep track of how big
these chunks of memory are.
So even though it's only
returning the address
of the first byte of that
memory, the operating system
is going to know that it used up
four bytes here, four bytes here.
And it will keep track
of that so that it
doesn't give you an overlapping
address in the future
because that would be bad.
Your data would get corrupted.
But you, similarly, have to remember or
figure out how many bytes are available
thereafter.
It's up to you to manage it, as
by putting a null character there
yourself.
So if I go back to my
code now, let me actually
harden this code just a
little bit more as follows,
whereby I can do this a little better.
If I go back to VS Code here, it
turns out, if something goes wrong
and I'm out of memory, maybe
I've got an old computer,
or maybe I'm typing something way
bigger than three characters in,
like three billion
characters, and the computer
might genuinely run out of memory.
I actually should be in
the habit of doing this.
If t equals, equals a special
symbol called null with two Ls,
and I promised this
would eventually exist,
I should just return one now, or
return two, return negative one,
return any value other than zero,
and just abort the program early.
That means, if malloc returns null,
there's not enough memory available.
And it turns out, all this time, I'm
going to do one other crazy thing,
even though we've not expected
you to do this thus far.
Technically, when using
getstring, getstring,
if you read the documentation, the
manual, it too can return null.
Because if you type in
a crazy long string,
and the computer can't
fit it in its memory,
getstring needs to signal
that to you somehow.
And the documentation actually says
that, if getstring returns null,
then you too should
not trust what's in it.
You should just exit the program
immediately, in this case.
But there's one other
improvement we can make here.
And even though this is making the
code seem way longer than it is,
most of this I've just added
is just error checking,
just mindless error checking to make
sure that I don't treat s as being
valid, or t as being
valid when it isn't.
It turns out this is stupid.
I don't need to reinvent this wheel.
Certainly, for decades, people have
been copying strings, even in C.
So it turns out there's another fun
function called strcopy, wonderfully
enough, that takes the
destination as its first argument,
the source as its second argument.
And that will for me copy
s into t, respectively.
So that does the equivalent of that
for loop, including the backslash zero.
However, there's one other function
recall that was on our cheat sheet
a moment ago, whereby
malloc is accompanied
by one other function called Free.
So Free is the opposite of malloc.
When you're done with
your computer's memory,
you're supposed to give it back
to Windows, to Mac OS, to Linux
so it can reuse it for something else.
And frankly, if you've ever been
using your computer for hours
on end, days on end, and maybe
it's getting slower, and slower,
maybe it's Photoshop, maybe it's
a really big document, generally,
really big files consume
lots and lots of memory.
If the humans who wrote that software,
be it Photoshop or something else,
wrote buggy code and kept using
malloc, malloc, malloc, malloc, asking
for more and more memory, but they
never call the opposite function, Free,
your computer might
actually run out of memory.
And typically, the symptom
is that it gets so darn
slow it becomes annoying to use.
And frankly, the mouse starts moving
very slowly, maybe the thing freezes
altogether, the computer crashes.
Bad things happen when
you run out of memory.
So in my case here, if
I go back to VS Code,
it's actually on me in this
language called C to actually manage
the memory myself so that,
when I have called malloc,
thereafter, I had better
free that same memory.
Now, I don't want to free it right away.
I want to free it when I'm done with it.
So frankly, the very last thing
I'm going to do in my program
here is called Free on t because
t is what I malloced up here.
So at the very bottom of my
program, I should free t.
And then just to be super
nitpicky, let me return zero just
to signify success at this point.
Now, there's a slight asymmetry,
which is a little inconsistent here.
Even though getstring,
I'm going to imply,
is still allocating memory for
me, it actually does use malloc.
getstring and CS50's other
functions are special.
They manage memory for you, so
you do not and should not free
memory that getstring returns to you.
We handle all of that for you.
But that's a training wheel that's
going to be taken off as of this week
anyway, so it's kind of moot.
So not to worry.
But I'm only freeing
memory that malloced.
All right.
Null, then, means the--
what is null?
It is just an address, and it's
literally the address zero.
So there's this theme.
N-U-L recall, was the
terminating symbol,
which just means the string ends here.
N-U-L-L, which is not greatly named, but
it's what humans went with years ago,
just means that this
is the address zero.
And what your computer does is, even
though I've been playfully saying that,
oh, in the top left is address zero, and
then one, and then two, and then three,
the address zero is hands off.
It's kind of a wasted byte
that your computer should never
use because the computer uses zero
as a special sentinel value, null,
to signify error.
So we're spending one byte out of
billions nowadays just to make sure
that there's a special symbol
that's coming back that can
indicate when something has gone wrong.
All right.
That was a mouthful.
Any questions on this copying
of strings, this malloc-ing,
or this freeing?
Oh, all right.
So let me give you a tool with which
to make some of this stuff easier,
so that when you make mistakes or
have bugs, as you invariably will,
you can chase them down without
having to raise your hand,
without having to ask the duck.
You actually have more
technical tools with which
to diagnose the problem yourself.
And there's this new tool that we'll
introduce today called valgrind.
And valgrind's purpose in life is to
check your usage of memory for you.
Admittedly, it's an older program.
It's pretty arcane in
terms of its interface,
and there's just going to be a
mess of output on the screen.
But there's going to be certain
patterns of mistakes that you'll notice,
and I'll demonstrate a
couple of them now so you can
see where and how you might go wrong.
So I'm going to go over to VS Code here.
I'm going to create a program called
memory.c that is deliberately buggy,
but it's not going to be
obviously buggy at first.
So by that I mean this.
Let me do include standard io.h.
Let me also include proactively
standard lib.h so I can use malloc.
Let me declare main with
no command line arguments,
and let me do something very simple.
Instead of just declaring an int
called X, let me be a little crazy
and manually allocate
this memory myself.
So int X just gives me an integer,
and it has since week one.
But now that I have malloc, I can kind
of take control over this process.
So let me declare, not an int,
but an int star called X. So
give me the address
of an integer, and let
me store there the return value of
malloc by asking malloc for, let's say,
four bytes.
So I know that ints are four bytes.
If I want four bytes, I just
tell malloc, give me four bytes.
Now, frankly, this is a little stupid.
I shouldn't just assume
that the int is always
going to be four bytes
on everyone's computer.
So there's this function you can start
using called sizeof, or this operator,
technically, where you
can say sizeof int.
And even if you're on an older computer,
for instance, really old at this point,
sizeof int will return the
correct value, no matter what.
You don't have to assume
that it's, in fact, four.
But you know what?
I'd actually like more
than this number of ints.
Let me actually treat X
as an array of integers.
So actually, if I want an array
of integers, I could do this.
Give me three integers.
But no, no.
Let me not do week two syntax.
Let me do this myself as follows.
Let me treat this as three
times the size of an int.
So that's technically
going to give me 12 bytes.
But this makes X effectively an array.
And this is kind of deliberate
now because if an array is
just contiguous memory,
and malloc returns to you
a chunk of contiguous memory, you
can treat what comes back from malloc
as an array.
And indeed, that's what
we're doing as strings.
We're treating chunks of
memory as arrays of chars.
So let me do something arbitrary here.
Let me go to X bracket one
and set it equal to 72.
X bracket two, set it equal to 73.
X bracket three, set it equal to 33.
And we did this a couple of weeks ago.
That's "hi" but in Ascii code.
Let me go ahead and make memory,
and it seems to work fine.
Let me do dot slash
memory, and no problem.
There's no error messages
from the compiler.
There's no runtime errors
when I actually run the code.
But does anyone see any
of the bugs thus far?
What did I do wrong?
Let me look a little in the back.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Does it not
know when the array ends?
SPEAKER 1: It doesn't seem
to know when the array ends.
Or more specifically,
I'm not respecting when
the array ends because
I'm sort of stupidly
starting at one, then two then three.
But technically, if I asked
for three of these things,
I should have done bracket
zero, bracket one, bracket two.
And there's a second more subtle bug
that you would only know from today.
Yeah.
OK, I don't necessarily know when one
integer ends and the next one begins.
That's actually not a problem,
because on a given system,
integers are always the same size.
So the computer can be smart enough
to go from here, four bytes this way,
four bytes this way,
four bytes this way.
That's OK.
Strings are problematic because
who knows how big the sentence was
that the human typed in.
But there's a more subtle bug.
What have I not done?
I didn't call free.
So I didn't practice
what I just preached.
Anytime I malloc, I call free.
But again, per my terminal window,
neither of these bugs seem obvious.
You might submit this code,
or deploy it to your software,
and be none the wiser.
But a tool like valgrind can
actually help you find these things.
So let me increase the
size of my terminal window.
Let me run this command
valgrind on my program.
So dot slash memory is
how I ran it a moment ago.
Just like debug50, you type
before the name of your program.
Valgrind, you type before
the name of your program.
And the output is going to
look crazy, but this is useful.
Why?
So notice at the very top of this, we're
just seeing what version of valgrind
we're using and what command we ran.
But this starts to get juicy,
and I'll highlight this here.
Invalid write of size
four invalid write.
So writing means changing information,
like setting a value or assigning it a.
Value and this is useful here.
The problem is in memory.c at line nine.
So colon nine means line nine.
All right, so let me go back to my code,
look at line nine, and oh, interesting.
So invalid write of size four.
So it's cryptic, but size four I
know is the size of an integer.
So I'm probably doing something
stupid on line nine involving
changing an integer.
And sure enough, even though it's
not super obvious, X bracket three,
oh, obviously, this doesn't exist.
So I have to change the problem.
One and two were OK, even though
it's logically the wrong thing.
Now I think this will
get rid of this error.
So let me actually clear my terminal
window and make it bigger again.
Let me recompile my code
because I made a change.
Let me rerun valgrind
of dot slash memory.
And now, that error went away.
There's a mess of output here,
but that error went away.
But this is interesting here now.
12 bytes in one blocks are definitely
lost in loss record one of one.
So unnecessarily verbose,
but the hint here
is that I somehow lost some bytes,
otherwise known as a memory leak.
So earlier, when I described
an imaginary bad programmer
who kept calling malloc, malloc,
malloc, and never freeing,
that's what's called
a memory leak, where
you're sort of losing track of your
memory and never freeing it again.
So I've definitely lost 12 bytes
in one block, whatever a block is,
in this case.
This is a little less obvious.
It's up to us to notice that, OK, wait
a minute, memory.c line six is somehow
germane.
Let me go back to--
oh, this is where I called malloc.
And valgrind doesn't necessarily
know when I should free the memory.
That's up to me, but I should probably
free it at the end of my function
when I'm definitely done with it,
because once you free your memory,
you should not touch that variable
again, unless you actually
change what its value is.
So now, as I've done this,
and this program to be clear
does nothing useful.
This is just an intellectual
exercise, not anything productive.
Let me do make memory one last time.
Let's do valgrind, dot slash memory.
And let me grow my terminal
window again and hit enter.
And even though it's
still kind of output,
it's still kind of cryptic, at
least it says no leaks are possible.
So now this is my own sort of
teaching assistant telling me
before I submit the code,
or before I deploy it
to production in real
software, that at least there
seem to be no memory related errors.
So valgrind is not for logical bugs.
It's not for syntax errors.
It's for memory related
bugs, as of today.
Questions on any of that?
No?
OK, so what else can go wrong?
We mentioned these in the past.
It turns out that garbage
values are a thing.
And recall that, if
you declare a variable
but don't give it a
value with an equal sign,
and you just blindly start using it,
like printing it out, or doing math
on it, you might be manipulating
a garbage value, which
is some number that's essentially
remnants of your computer
having been on for a while.
Because if you're using this
canvas and reusing it again,
and again, surely there's going
to be patterns of zeros and ones
there that you didn't put there
yourself, at least in the moment.
They might be remnants of the past.
So garbage values are values of
variables that you did not proactively
set yourself as intended.
So we can actually see this.
Let me actually go ahead and whip
up a really quick program here
after shrinking my terminal window.
Let me close memory.c.
Let me go ahead and open garbage.c.
And in here, I'll do include.
How about standard io.h?
Let's include standard lib.h
Actually, we don't even
need standard lib.h.
Let's go ahead and include standard
io.h and then int main void.
And then inside of the
curly braces, let's
give me a really big array
of scores, like 1,024 scores,
like if it's a really busy semester.
And then let me go ahead and
just blindly iterate from i
equals zero on up to
i is less than 1,024.
And I'm not going to
bother with constants.
I'm just going to play around
with these numbers for a moment.
And, oh, thank you.
Oh, cookies for you.
OK.
OK, here we go.
OK, come on up.
Thank you very much.
Fair is fair.
OK.
Thank you.
OK, now everyone's
really paying attention.
All right.
So in my loop here, I'm just
going to do something stupid,
like print out all of the values in
the scores array using percent i,
even though I did not put
anything in this array.
So on line five, I'm
obviously declaring an array
of size 1,024 for that
many ints, but I'm never
actually putting values in there myself,
or with getint, or any other function.
So there's garbage values there.
There's presumably 1,024
garbage values there,
and we can now actually see them.
Let me make my terminal window bigger.
Let me make garbage, no pun
intended, dot slash garbage.
And there's going to be way more
than even fit on the screen.
But who cares?
We just need to see a few.
There are some of the
garbage values in the array.
So make super clear that when
you create variables of your own,
you do not give them values of your own.
Who knows what may be there?
In some cases, it gets automatically
initialized for you to all zeros,
but that is not always the case.
And in general, distrust the
variable unless you yourself
have put a value there.
So how now might we leverage this to--
how now might we think
about potential problems?
Well, consider this code
here, which this program, too,
is more for discussion than actual
utility, where at the top of it,
I declare a variable called
x and a variable called y,
both of type pointer.
So x and y are supposed to be
the addresses of two integers.
malloc, the size of an
int, and stored in x.
So I'm giving myself space for
x, even though, obviously, I
could have done this weeks ago
by just not using the star,
and just say give me an int x.
Now I'm doing it the low level
way, malloc-ing the x for myself.
I'm then saying go to x, go
to that address in memory,
and put the number 42 there.
I'm then saying go to y and put
the unlucky number 13 there.
But what's worrisome
about this line here?
After this line, this line, this
line, something's bad, I think.
Yeah, I never allocated memory for y.
So specifically, I never
assigned y a value,
which means it's a garbage
value, which is still a number.
Maybe it's zero.
Maybe it's a big number.
Maybe it's a negative number.
And if it's a positive number,
it could be an actual address
somewhere in the computer's memory.
But star y means go there.
Who knows what memory I'm touching?
That's how computers crash if you touch
memory that you're not supposed to.
So let me pretend that I didn't at least
do this and let me just forge ahead
and set y equal to x
so they're the same.
And I think what that would
mean is now, if I do star y
and go to the address, that's the same
thing as going to the address in x.
And I think this will have the
effect of changing the 42 to 13.
So this code is correct, so long
as I don't blindly dereference y
by using star y notation.
So this gets a little abstract, even
though this is just an exercise here.
And our friend Nick Parlante,
a professor at Stanford,
wonderfully put together
a little claymation
that's fun to take a look at, whereby
if I go ahead and open up this file,
we'll be introduced to
someone who's a little famous
in the world of computing named
Binky, if we could dim the lights
and take a look at what bad
things can happen if you
don't manage your memory properly.
SPEAKER 5: Hey, Binky.
Wake up.
It's time for pointer fun.
SPEAKER 6: What's that?
Learn about pointers?
Oh, goody.
SPEAKER 5: Well, to get started, I guess
we're going to need a couple pointers.
SPEAKER 6: OK.
This code allocates two pointers,
which can point to integers.
SPEAKER 5: OK.
Well, I see the two pointers, but they
don't seem to be pointing to anything.
SPEAKER 6: That's right.
Initially, pointers
don't point to anything.
The things they point to are called
pointees, and setting them up
is a separate step.
SPEAKER 5: Oh, right, right.
I knew that.
The pointees are separate.
So how do you allocate a pointee?
SPEAKER 6: OK.
Well, this code allocates
a new integer pointee,
and this part sets x to point to it.
SPEAKER 5: Hey, that looks better.
So make it do something.
SPEAKER 6: OK, I'll dereference
the pointer x to store the number
42 into its pointee.
For this trick, I'll need my
magic wand of dereferencing.
SPEAKER 5: Your magic
wand of dereferencing?
That's great.
SPEAKER 6: This is what
the code looks like.
I'll just set up the number and--
SPEAKER 5: Hey, look.
There it goes.
So doing a dereference
on x follows the arrow
to access its pointee, in this
case, to store 42 in there.
Hey, try using it to store the number
13 through the other pointer, y.
SPEAKER 6: OK.
I'll just go over here to y
and get the number 13 set up,
and then take the wand of
dereferencing, and just--
whoa.
SPEAKER 5: Oh, hey, that didn't work.
Say, Binky, I don't
think dereferencing y
is a good idea because setting up
the pointee is a separate step,
and I don't think we ever did it.
SPEAKER 6: Good point.
SPEAKER 5: Yeah, we
allocated the pointer y,
but we never set it
to point to a pointee.
SPEAKER 6: Very observant.
SPEAKER 5: Hey, you're
looking good there, Binky.
Can you fix it so that y points
to the same pointee as x?
SPEAKER 6: Sure.
I'll use my magic wand
of pointer assignment.
SPEAKER 5: Is that going to
be a problem like before?
SPEAKER 6: No, this
doesn't touch the pointees.
It just changes one pointer to
point to the same thing as another.
SPEAKER 5: Oh, I see.
Now y points to the same place as x.
So wait.
Now y is fixed.
It has a pointee, so you can try
the wand of dereferencing again
to send the 13 over.
SPEAKER 6: OK.
Here it goes.
SPEAKER 5: Hey, look at that.
Now dereferencing works on y.
And because the pointers are sharing
that one pointee, they both see the 13.
SPEAKER 6: Yeah, sharing.
Whatever.
So are we going to switch places now?
SPEAKER 5: Oh, look.
We're out of time.
SPEAKER 6: But--
SPEAKER 1: All right.
So our thanks to Nick.
I can only imagine how many hours
he spent making that happen.
But hopefully, it gives you more of
a visual as to what's happening when
we're dereferencing these addresses,
and going to them, and assigning values,
and as per Binky's explosion there, what
happens when you dereference values you
shouldn't.
So related thereto, let me do this.
Let me go over to VS Code
and open up now a program
I wrote in advance called swap.c.
And the purpose of this program is just
to swap the value of two variables.
So let me walk over to the code here
and point out that, in main, I've got
two variables, x and y.
No pointers, no magic there.
Just x and y are one
and two respectively.
I've got a couple of printfs here saying
x is %i, y is %i, passing in x and y,
just so we can see that x
and y are indeed one and two.
I'm then calling a
function called swap, which
presumably, should swap the two values.
And then I'm just printing
the exact same thing again,
my hoping that it's first
going to say one, two,
then it's going to say two, one, thus
achieving the idea of swapping here.
And here's swap.
Swap takes in two
integers, a and b, though I
could have called them whatever I want.
It temporarily puts a in temp.
It then changes a to b.
It then changes b to
temp, and then that's it.
It's a void function, so
it doesn't return anything,
but it does all of the
mathematical work in here.
So this is curious, though,
because when it runs,
let me open up my terminal window here.
Make swap, dot slash swap, I should
see one, two, and then two, one.
But no, even though I do think
this is logically correct.
And actually, we're almost out of stock,
but we do have another box of cookies
here.
Can we get one volunteer
to come on up here maybe?
OK, how about you?
Yes, in the pink, come on up.
A round of applause, though, really,
it's about the cookies now, I know.
OK.
And what is your name?
SPEAKER 7: My name is Caleb, and
I'm a first year concentrating
in computer science.
SPEAKER 1: All right, welcome.
Please stand behind the desk here.
No, you can stand.
It's fine.
SPEAKER 7: OK.
SPEAKER 1: We have two glasses
of water, colored, blue,
and orange, respectively.
And I would like you to swap the
values of these two variables
so that the orange liquid
goes in the blue glass,
and the blue liquid goes
in the orange glass.
SPEAKER 7: Seems like a bad idea.
SPEAKER 1: Why is that?
SPEAKER 7: Because I can't get one out
to put the other one in because there's
no third glass.
SPEAKER 1: OK correct because
we do have what we generally
call a temporary variable here.
So here, let me give you
a variable called temp.
And if I give you this, how
does that change things?
SPEAKER 7: Well, now, I can take one.
SPEAKER 1: OK.
SPEAKER 7: Very carefully.
SPEAKER 1: Nice.
SPEAKER 7: I'm trying.
SPEAKER 1: OK.
SPEAKER 7: There we go.
SPEAKER 1: And now you can
put b into a, if you will.
Nice.
And now temp goes back into that one.
All right.
That was very well done.
Maybe round of applause.
Thank you.
So this was just a cookie
based way of making clear
that the code on the
screen seems to work.
If I scroll back down
to the swap function,
it seems to do exactly what you just did
there, whereby the temporary glass is
where we put a, then we
changed a to contain b,
then we changed b to contain
what was originally an a,
but is now in the temporary glass.
And now we're done.
So it did achieve the stated goal, and
yet when I ran this code a moment ago,
it was one, two, and
then one, two again.
So why might that actually be?
Well, here we can go back to
some of today's fundamentals
to consider what it
is that's going wrong.
And in this case, it's
actually related to a concept
we introduced some time ago, whereby
there seems to be an issue of scope,
whereby sometimes when you're
manipulating variables inside
of curly braces, thus defining their
scope, it has no effect on values
elsewhere.
The variables might not even exist
elsewhere, as we saw in the past.
So what do I mean by this?
Well, with matters of scope, it
turns out that in this case, the way
I've implemented the swap
function, I'm doing something
a programmer would
call passing by value.
I'm literally passing in x and
y by their values, one and two.
Another way of putting
this is passing by copy.
So when I pass x and y
into the swap function,
it turns out swap is actually
getting copies thereof.
Now, what do I mean by this?
Well, let's go back
again to this picture
of memory representative of what's
in your Mac, your PC, or your phone.
And if we zoom in on
this chip and we treat
it more abstractly as this canvas,
get rid of the actual hardware,
and consider what's going
on inside of the computer,
it turns out that there are conventions
of how computers use this memory.
And it's worth having a general
sense of what goes where.
So generally speaking, if this is
a big rectangular region of memory,
even though this is just an
artist's depiction thereof,
it turns out that the top
of your memory, so to speak,
is where machine code goes.
The zeros and ones that you
compile get loaded into here.
So when you do dot slash something, or
on a Mac or PC, when you double click,
or on a phone, when you single tap,
that loads your program's machine code,
the app's machine code to the
top of your computer's memory.
Strictly speaking, it
doesn't have to be the top.
But for our sake, it's
in this region here.
That's how the computer can access
all of those zeros and ones quickly.
Below that, so to speak, are
where global variables go.
We haven't had many
occasions to use these.
But if you define a
variable outside of main,
and outside of every
other function in C,
it's what's called a global variable.
So those get tucked
especially up at the top
so that they're accessible
everywhere else in your program.
Then there's something called the heap.
More on that in a moment.
And it grows downward, so you have
a lot of memory available to you
here in the heap, and you can
keep getting more, and more,
and more available to you.
But at the bottom of this memory
is what's called the stack.
And the stack actually grows, curiously,
in the other direction, up, and up,
and up.
And it turns out, when you use malloc
and ask the computer for memory,
it comes from this heap
region, specifically.
When you use functions with
variables and arguments,
you're using stack memory.
Now, the astute viewer will notice that
this does not seem like a good thing
if they're about to collide eventually.
And bad things can and will happen
when one overflows the other, but more
on that, too, in a moment.
But let's focus for
the moment on a stack
when we do something
like this swap function.
So for instance, when we had
code like this, which was bad,
it did not allow us to permanently
change the values of x and y.
Why?
No pun intended.
Here on the stack is where
the very first function
goes in your computer's memory.
So main, if you have
any variables, they go
at the bottom of the computer's memory
once you've loaded that program.
So what do I mean by that?
Well, if you think back to the code a
moment ago, it was things like x and y,
and so forth.
When main calls swap, swap goes
above it on the stack, so to speak.
And each of these rectangles,
the technical term is frame.
So this is a stack frame.
This is a stack frame.
And if swap called another
function, another frame
would go on the stack this way.
And then as soon as
swap returns, though,
that memory essentially
goes away, or the computer
forgets about it, even though the
bits are obviously still there.
You still have the hardware,
but it's forgotten.
And main remains until main
finishes and exits your program.
But let's consider what's going
inside of these stack frames.
So here's main at the bottom, and
it had two variables, x and y.
Those variables were one
and two, respectively.
Main called swap, which
had two arguments, a and b,
also integers, which are
effectively local variables, also,
even though you're declaring
them in the signature,
the prototype of the function.
So when swap is called, swap is
using its frame of memory as follows.
Room for a, room for b, room for temp.
Not necessarily to scale.
I just wanted everything
to be a pretty rectangle.
What's going where?
Well, because functions in C pass by
value, that is, copy, a is a copy of x,
and b is a copy of y.
But they're separate bytes.
This is a different
memory location than this.
So we're just copying the patterns
of bits from one to the other.
This is passing by value, a.k.a.
Passing by copy.
So what then happens?
Just like our demonstration,
we used temp cleverly,
whereby with this code here, we
copied the value of a into temp.
So that puts the number one here, too.
We then changed a to equal b.
So that's what happened here.
We then changed b to equal temp,
so that changed the value there.
But then swap returned.
You went back to your seat,
leaving a and b swapped, yes.
But what was not swapped was x and y.
You did all of this work
correctly, but in the wrong scope.
You operated on copies thereof.
So this swap function,
while logically correct,
will never solve this
problem correctly as written
because we've been passing by value.
So today, we introduce
a technique, whereby
you can pass by reference
instead, pass by pointer instead,
because instead of
just passing in copies,
what if we actually tell swap where
x is and where y is, not what it is
and what it is, but where each is?
Then swap can follow the proverbial
treasure map, go to those locations,
and change them permanently.
So this was the bad
code in red, and this
is going to escalate quickly visually.
But it's just an application
of today's ideas.
This is the correct solution now.
So let me do before.
In red is bad.
Green, after, is correct.
Why?
The way you specify pass
by reference or pointer
instead is you change swap to
take, not two integers, per se,
but two addresses of integers.
And the syntax for that today
is just to add the star.
So int star, and int star.
Meanwhile, the code
down here has to change.
Temp does not have to change.
Temp is still just a variable
that's ready for some value.
But the a and the b, and the b
need to be rewritten as follows.
So star a means go to the
address a, and get its value,
and put it in temp, just like you
reached for one of the glasses
and poured it in.
Star b means, go to the
value in b and grab it.
And then go to the value at a
and change it to be that at b.
And then lastly, this is not now sweat.
This is now colored liquid.
This last line is go to the address
b, and put temp there instead.
So the picture now is
fundamentally different.
Main looks the same still.
But when swap is called, effectively,
and we won't bother with OX123 or 456.
Let's just do it with
arrows pointing at things.
a is a pointer to x,
b is a pointer to y.
So what do those lines
of code tell us to do?
Go to a.
So that means this, kind of like
the old chutes and ladders game,
if you ever played.
Follow the arrow, and that leads you to
the number one, and store it in temp.
So that one was straightforward.
Go to the value in b.
So follow the arrow.
That gives us two, and
put it at the location
in a, which means put the two there.
The very last line of code now means
get temp, which is obviously there,
and go to the address
b, and change it to one.
So now, even though we've not
changed a and b at all, per se,
we've used them as little
breadcrumbs to lead us
to the right location in
the computer's memory.
So when swap returns this time,
even though it's a void function,
it has made a difference.
And it's had this effect of swapping
the actual original values of x and y.
The code, admittedly,
is cryptic looking.
It's not the most user friendly
syntax, but this ability
now to go to locations
in memory and change
what is actually there is
what we've been given today
with this new syntax of the star
operator, and occasionally as needed,
the ampersand one, as well.
Questions on this technique, which
is, admittedly, the most sophisticated
of the examples thus far, and we'll
probably take time to get used to.
Yeah.
Say that again.
Will this work if--
AUDIENCE: Will this work if
you're swapping the value
of two strings instead of ints?
SPEAKER 1: Ah, good question.
Will this work if you're
swapping the values
of two strings instead of two ints?
Yes, if you go to the address that
the string represents and change maybe
with a loop all of the
characters one at a time.
So it's going to be more complicated
than this in green because you're
going to have to change all
of the individual characters,
probably reusing a temporary char,
instead of a temporary integer.
But you could.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
SPEAKER 1: Since integers
have a fixed number of bits,
can you ever run into a situation
where you run out of memory?
Absolutely.
Your phone, your laptop, your
desktop can only do so much,
can only count so high because
of these physical limitations.
And hopefully, it's just
never reach that limit.
But we'll talk in a couple of weeks time
when we transition to web programming
and databases, and the
Metas, the Microsofts,
the Googles of the world that
have crazy large amounts of data.
The number of bits we
use in those contexts
is actually going to matter
for exactly that reason.
If business is booming,
and if you've got
lots and lots of data,
lots and lots of users,
you need to be able to count higher.
Just so that you've seen the
code actually in operation,
here is, of course, my
swap function down below.
And if I go ahead and
change its prototype
to take in pointers to a and b, and
similarly change the prototype up here.
And if I go in and change a here to
be star a to dereference it, star
b to dereference it,
star a to dereference it,
and star b to dereference it, I claim
now that this version of the code
should now work.
In fact, let me go
ahead and do make swap.
It didn't compile.
So why might that be?
Well, let me scroll up to
see what the message is.
Incompatible integer
to pointer conversion
passing in parameter of type int star.
That's a lot to absorb.
But clearly, the issue is
with how I'm calling swap.
So why is this?
Well, notice that now that my swap
function expects as arguments pointers
to integers, I can't just blindly
pass in x and y, which are integers.
Instead, I do need to use our friend,
the new ampersand operator to pass
in the address of x
and the address of y.
So now, if I reopen my terminal window,
run make swap, and do dot slash swap,
now I see one, two, and then two, one.
So the code changes in this way.
And maybe this example
more so than others
makes clear why the star
operator lets us go somewhere,
but the ampersand effectively
does the opposite and figures out
what the address of something now is.
All right.
So what about these other
locations in memory?
Well, it turns out that, indeed,
the stack, as we've described it,
grows up, and up, and up.
And recall that stack
here in this sense is
kind of like the stack of trays and the
cafeteria or any of the dining halls.
There's one tray, another tray,
another tray, another tray.
But then you start removing
them from top down.
So there's an ordering to them that
we'll actually revisit next week.
But this is not a good
design, in general.
You shouldn't be doing things like two
trains on the tracks barreling together
toward each other in this way.
But honestly, it's kind of the
only way, because if you've only
got a finite amount of
memory, OK, sure, you
can have them both grow
in the same direction.
But they're still going to
hit some impasse eventually.
You're still going to run out of space.
So the way computers were designed years
ago is they use memory in this way,
even though bad things can happen,
if you use too much stack space,
or too much heap space.
So what do I mean by that?
Our example a moment ago just
had us call main and then swap
and that was it.
So it's like two frames no big deal.
But if you call many
functions again, and again,
and again, if you do something
recursively, where you call yourself,
you're going to pile, pile,
pile stack frames potentially.
So you could start to hit
the so-called heap area.
Meanwhile, if you call
malloc too many times,
you might be growing down,
down, down, down, down,
and then overrun some of
the stack memory, as well.
So bad things can happen when
you overrun either of these.
And those of you maybe with
prior programming experience
might have heard at least one of
these terms, heap overflow, or more
popularly, stack overflow.
Super popular website for questions
and answers about programming.
The etymology thereof is exactly
this idea of overflowing the stack
and touching memory that
you should not, whether it's
memory down here, or even
worse, memory over here,
as by something called heap overflow.
And these are specific examples of what
we'll start calling buffer overflows.
Buffer is just a chunk of memory.
And buffer overflows means overflowing,
using too much of that memory.
And buffers are everywhere.
In fact, if you've
used YouTube recently,
and maybe it's just kind of paused and
spinning, and spinning, and spinning,
maybe you're on a really bad connection.
There's no more bytes in your buffer.
There's no more video
footage in the buffer
because maybe you have
such a bad connection.
But if Google were to
make mistakes and try
to download too many bytes at a time,
they too could overflow a buffer.
And if YouTube or similar
apps have ever crashed,
it could be because they're trying
to use more memory than they actually
should be.
So these things are sort of everywhere.
Now, as for these training
wheels, we sort of took away
the mystery of what a string is.
But what about all of these
other functions we've been
taking for granted now for a few weeks?
You can and should still use them to
solve some problems because, frankly, C
does not make it easy to get user
input safely, like, period, full stop.
It is very non-trivial to get
user input without running
the risk of overflowing a buffer.
Why?
Well, you're the programmer.
How do you possibly know in
advance how big of a string
a human might type in tomorrow,
or the next week, or the next day?
You could try to be safe and
allocate a million bytes all at once.
But what if they type
in 1,000,001 characters,
or use copy paste so much
that they similarly overflow?
So getting user input is a hard problem.
So let's introduce you to
what the alternative would be
and given an appreciation for what
libraries like CS50's and others
like it are actually doing for you.
Let me go ahead and create our own
version of getint and getstring
without using the CS50
library, but using a standard C
function called scanf.
And to do that, let
me go over to VS Code.
Let me create a new file
called, for instance, get.c.
And then in get.c, let's
make a very simple program
first that just gets an integer, but
again, without using the CS50 library.
So let me go ahead and include
the standard io library.
Let me go ahead and declare
main as int main void.
And then inside of main, let me
go ahead and declare an integer n
so that we have some place
to put the integer that we're
getting from the user.
Then let me go ahead
and just prompt the user
for a value for n, so n
colon space, for instance.
Because again, I'm not using
getint, so I can't just
call it to present the
user with a prompt.
So I'm going to use printf
to create my own prompt.
And now, let me use this
function scanf as follows.
I'm going to call scanf, and
then I'm going to pass to scanf,
similar in spirit to printf,
a format code, like %i,
effectively telling scanf that what
I want it to scan, so to speak,
from the user's keyboard is
in fact a single integer.
Now, I'm going to close quotes, and I
don't need a new line because I'm not
trying to print anything.
I'm trying to get something
from the user using scanf.
But I do need to tell scanf
where to put this integer.
Now, if I want to put this
integer in the variable n,
it's not quite as
simple as just passing n
in because recall how
variables are passed.
This variable n is going
to be passed by value.
Effectively, a copy is
going to go into scanf,
and so scanf is not going to have
the ability to change that value.
But if you think back to
how we swapped two values
and passed two values into
that swap function in C,
well, if we pass those two
values in by their addresses,
so passing by reference, so
to speak, then the function,
swap in that case, scanf in this
case, can actually go to that address
and change the value.
So to summarize, I'm going to pass the
scanf one argument, which is a format
code, and a second argument, which is
the address of an integer into which
to put the user's value.
After that, I'm just going to go
ahead and print out what's happened.
So I'm going to go ahead and print out
the value of n followed by a colon,
followed by an actual
placeholder, %i backslash n.
And I'm going to pass in
now to printf the value n.
So to be clear, I'm still passing
n into printf, just like we've
been doing since week one, but I'm
passing to scanf the address of n,
so that scanf can actually go to that
address and change the value of n.
So I think this is
actually going to work,
even though I've not used getint
or any of the CS50 library.
Let me go into my
terminal, run make get.
Seems to compile OK.
Let me do dot shalsh get, and let
me type in a value like 50 for n.
And indeed, I should see spit back
at me that the value I got was 50.
So it turns out that getting
an integer from users
is relatively straightforward
just using scanf.
But of course, to use scanf, you need to
know a little something about pointers
or addresses, more generally.
That was not knowledge
we had in week one.
And so we do, indeed,
use those training wheels
of the CS50 library
for the past few weeks
so that we can get integers more easily.
And it turns out, if the user
types more than a simple integer,
or doesn't even type in an
integer, scanf isn't necessarily
going to behave as user
friendly as getint might.
So in the CS50 library, we do a bit
more error handling for you, as well.
But let's consider
now an implementation,
not of getting an integer,
but getting a string instead.
Let me clear my terminal window, and let
me go ahead and erase all of this code,
and instead focus this
time on getting a string.
Well, we know we can't use string
anymore, at least if we're not
using the CS50 library.
But not a problem because we know
that strings are now char stars.
So if I want to get a string from
the user, that's like getting,
I think, a char star.
So let me just call this
string s by default.
Let me go ahead therefore and
declare a variable s that's
going to store my string.
Let me go ahead next, as
before, and prompt the user
for the value of that variable,
just by prompting them with printf.
So nothing fancy there.
And let me try again using
scanf to scan this time
a string from the user's keyboard.
I'm going to type scanf.
I'm going to do %s instead
of %i because I, indeed,
want to scan a string in this case.
And then I'm going to go
ahead and pass in just s.
And here, at first glance, seems
to be an inconsistency because,
previously, I did ampersand n.
But that's because n was an
integer, not the address thereof.
But in the world of
strings as we now know,
a string is just the
address of its first byte.
And so if we declare s
to be a char star, a.k.a.
string, well, s is already in address.
So I can just pass in
s in this case to scanf
without actually using an ampersand.
After that, let's go ahead and print out
the result. So let's just use printf.
Let's print out a prefix, like s
colon again, %s as my placeholder,
and now backslash n because I'm
formatting it on the screen.
And then let's go ahead and
pass in s as always to printf.
So s is just a string, so I just
pass it into printf like that.
Well, let me go ahead now, and
I'm going to go ahead and compile
this an old fashioned way
because we actually protect you
from doing something like this.
But I'm going to go ahead and ignore
the warnings you would otherwise
see us make.
And I'm going to go ahead and
compile this with clang directly.
So clang-o get, because that's the
name of the program I want to output.
But I'm also going to specify dash
capital W, no, uninitialized, which
is simply another command
line argument that's
going to tell clang not to warn us about
variables that are not initialized.
Because case in point on line five,
as some of you might have noticed,
I didn't actually initialize
s to anything, even null.
But that's OK because I want to forge
ahead blindly just to make a point as
to what's going on here.
And in fact, let's go ahead and
compile this code as follows.
It does seem to compile,
even though make would
have warned us that something's awry.
Let me go ahead now and run dot slash
get, and this time, not type in 50.
But let me type in something
like our familiar "hi"
exclamation point, and hit enter.
I immediately get a
segmentation fault, which
means something has gone
wrong related to memory.
A segment of memory has been
touched that I shouldn't have.
Well, why, in fact, is this?
Well, let's consider what
it is we've been doing.
If this here is my computer's
memory, and in the first case
I was just trying to
get an integer, that
was actually pretty straightforward,
because even if this memory is filled
with a whole bunch of garbage
values, as personified here
by Oscar the Grouch, when I
declared n to be an integer before,
I just needed, on this
machine, four bytes, which
is the typical size for an int.
And I put the number 50 there.
So it doesn't matter that there
were these garbage values.
I just went to those four
bytes after declaring
a variable called n and
overwrote those bits,
with some pattern of bits
representing the number 50.
But strings we now know are
sort of fundamentally different.
If I go back to that same memory
space, and I declare s to be a pointer,
that is, a char star, well,
recall that pointers are generally
eight bytes on modern systems.
And so that's like taking eight of these
bytes from memory and calling it s.
But the catch is, if I haven't
initialized s to actually
be a valid location,
as via calling malloc,
there are still garbage values there.
That is to say, patterns
of bits that maybe
have been there always, but from
some previous function that got
called, or some other lines of code
if this program were actually bigger.
So it's just some garbage value
is filling that variable s.
The problem, though, is that in
my code now, when I call scanf
and I tell scanf to scan a string from
the user and to put it at that location
s, well, what is that location s?
It's literally a garbage value.
It's the equivalent of a foam
finger pointing there, there, there.
We just don't know because
it's not a valid address.
And so I get that segmentation
fault here in my terminal window
because I've not initialized
s to be some known value.
I get a segmentation fault
because, effectively, I've
accidentally touched memory that I
should not, in fact, have done so.
So how do we fix this?
Well clearly, I need s to point
at some valid chunk of memory,
and I could do that using malloc.
But frankly, in this case, I
could do it even more simply
by just declaring s to be
an array of characters,
as we might have in week two.
So let me go ahead and clear
my terminal window here.
Let me go into get.c, and let's
simply change what's s is.
Instead of a char star, which we
know is what a string technically is,
we can still implement strings
as arrays of characters.
That's certainly still true.
So let me go ahead and
do that, declare s to be
an array of, say, four characters.
And in this case, I should have enough
room for the H, the I, the exclamation
point, and even that null character,
the trailing backslash zero.
So now, let me go ahead and build this.
Make get.
And because I'm not, not
initializing something this time,
I can use make as usual without
getting yelled at because I'm not yet
doing anything wrong.
Now let me go ahead and
do dot slash get enter.
And in this case, it's ready to
receive my H-I exclamation point enter,
and all actually seems well.
Why?
Because in this case, I
actually had enough space for s,
because if I go back to my memory
here, because I've now redeclared s
as an actual array of
four characters, that's
like asking the operating system, for
instance, for these four chars here.
And certainly, I can fit H-I
exclamation point and the null character
into those four bytes.
So there's not a problem.
But there might be a problem if
the I, or the user, more generally,
types in too many characters.
So let me go ahead and
run dot slash get again.
Let me type H-I exclamation point.
But just to get a little aggressive, let
me highlight that and paste it again,
again, again, and again, and
really type, very excitedly,
a pretty long string that is
surely longer than four bytes.
Well unfortunately, I've only
asked the operating system
for an array of four bytes.
So what's going to happen with all
of those extra hi's, hi's, hi's?
They're just going to, by default,
remain contiguous from left to right,
top to bottom in the computer's memory.
But they're going to end up,
some of those characters,
at locations I didn't ask the
operating system for in this array.
So if I go back to VS Code here, I've
typed in a very long string, certainly
longer than four bytes in total.
Let me hit enter.
And darn it.
There is another segmentation
fault. So in short, we,
you are going to see these
segmentation faults any time
you touch segments of
memory, so to speak,
that do not belong to you, that
you didn't allocate space for, as
via an array, or even via malloc.
And this is going to be a fundamental
problem with getting strings
because I don't in advance how
long the string is going to be
that the human's going to type in.
Maybe it's four.
Maybe it's fewer characters.
Maybe it's even more.
So what's the alternative?
Well, I could go in here maybe
and allocate, I don't know,
4,000 characters for s.
But what if you type in an even longer
string that's 4,001 characters or more?
I might still have these memory related
errors, these segmentation faults.
So one of the reasons then, too, that
we provide you with the CS50 library,
and in turn, functions
like getstring, is
that getstring very, very conservatively
walks through these user's input
byte, by byte, by byte,
one character at a time.
And what the CS50 library
is doing underneath the hood
is, as soon as it realizes, oh, the
user gave us another byte, another byte,
we in the CS50 library are
constantly allocating and re
allocating more and more
memory using malloc for you,
and effectively managing the
memory required for that string.
So even though scanf exists, it's
dangerous to use with strings.
And even with integers,
it turns out it lacks
some of the error handling that the
CS50 library has thus far provided.
How do we actually go
about solving this?
The way getstring actually works in
the CS50 library is it kind of tiptoes.
It waits.
It gets one character from you and then
checks if there's another one coming.
Then it allocates more
space for a second.
If there's still a third, it allocates
more space, more space, more space.
So essentially, what getstring
does is it uses malloc again,
and again, and again, and it
kind of lays the tracks down
as you're typing in the
keystrokes and hitting enter,
so that we never assume how many
characters you're going to type in.
We dynamically allocate just enough
bytes for you, plus one extra,
for the null character.
And this is sort of a
hoop that's just not
fun to jump through when, at the
end of the day, all you want to do
is get input from the user.
So even with the training
wheels officially off,
it's going to be annoying to
get strings from users in C.
But it is easy with ints, with
floats, with other data types.
And frankly, we'll soon,
in two weeks, pivot
to Python, which takes care of
all of these problems for us
and manages our memory.
But for now, we have one
final to do beyond scanf,
which is file IO, which is a fancy
way of saying input and output.
Because now that we a
little bit of hexadecimal,
now that we know a little
bit about pointers,
we actually have some more
functions available to us
that will let us actually manipulate
files on a computer's hard drive,
like image files, or text files,
or anything else we might want.
Among the most common functions that
are related to files are these here.
fopen is going to be a function that
lets you open a file, doing in code
what you might otherwise do by going
to File, Open in a graphical program.
Fclose does the opposite.
It's the way you, in code,
click on an X and close a file.
Nothing's going to
happen visually, but it's
how you give access to a program
to the contents of a file.
fprintf, it allows you to print,
not to the screen, but to a file.
fscanf lets you read data, not from
the keyboard, but from a file. fread
and fwrite write are similarly used
to read and write data from a file,
but generally binary data,
like images, or something
that's not Ascii or Unicode text.
fseek is a function that
lets you move around
in a file left to right,
kind of like fast forwarding
or rewinding through
Netflix, or similar when
you want to jump to a different location
in a video, or in this case, a file.
And there's bunches of others, as well.
So to give you a sense of
what you can do with it when
it comes to manipulating files, let's
write just a couple of final programs,
for instance, that let us
manipulate some of this code for us.
In fact, let me go ahead and open up
here in VS Code a new file called,
say, phonebook.c.
And in phonebook.c, we're
going to implement now
a version of the phonebook
like we did in the past.
But in this case, we don't actually
have a forgetful program that
prompts the user with getstring
for a couple of names and numbers,
and then just forgets
about them altogether.
This version of the
phonebook is actually
going to go ahead and save them
persistently to a file for us.
And for this, let me go ahead and
open up just on my other screen here,
without flipping over just yet,
let me go ahead and open up--
give me just one moment.
So we have this ready to go.
Let me go ahead and create the
file, this program as follows.
I'm going to cheat and save time by
using the CS50 library because I do not
want to get into the nuances of
getting strings character by character,
which itself will escalate too quickly.
But let me go ahead and include the
CS50 library, the standard IO library,
and lastly, the string library
for this particular case.
In my main function now, I'm
going to go ahead and open up
a file called maybe phonebook.csv.
If you've ever used a CSV file,
it's like a lightweight spreadsheet
that you can open in Apple Numbers,
Google Spreadsheets, Microsoft Excel.
But CSV means that we're going to
separate all of the values by commas.
So anywhere we want a new
column, we actually use a comma,
as we'll soon see.
So how do I actually do this?
I can open a file called phonebook.csv
by literally using fopen phonebook.csv.
And I have to tell fopen
how I want to open it.
Do I want to open it for reading with R?
Do I want to open it for writing with W?
Or do I want to open
it with appending, A?
And for something like a phone book,
if I run this program again and again,
I'm going to actually do append so that
new contacts get added to the file,
and we don't overwrite it with W.
Now, what is fopen return?
It technically returns
a pointer to a file.
But this one's a little weird.
It's all capitalized, but it is a
thing in C. File in all caps star file
is going to be a pointer
to that file in memory.
So think of fopen as opening the file
and returning the address thereof
in the computer's memory.
All right.
What do I want to next do?
I want to go ahead and get two strings
from the user, like maybe someone's
name, using getstring, again,
to keep things simple for now.
Let me then go ahead
and get another one.
How about their number?
Using getstring, again,
prompting for a number.
And I don't strictly need
these training wheels.
So even though it doesn't
really make a difference,
I'm going to at least change that
to char star, even though I do
want to keep using
getstring conveniently.
And now I want to save this person's
name and number to that CSV file.
So I'm going to use,
not printf, but fprintf,
printing to that file, variable, which
is open in the computer's memory.
Now I'm going to go ahead and print
out two strings, %s comma, %s.
Then I want to go ahead and print out
the name for the first placeholder,
and the number for the
second placeholder.
And for good measure, I want to move
the cursor to the next line in the file,
so I am going to include a backslash n.
Then I'm going to go ahead and
fclose that same file with fclose.
And that's it.
No more printing to the user.
But I claim that I'm going to
be changing the file again,
and again, and again.
So let me try this.
Make phone book, OK, dot
slash phonebook, enter.
And let's type in David.
And how about +1 617-495-1000?
Enter.
OK, hopefully, it worked.
Let's do it again.
Dot slash phonebook.
Carter, we'll give him the
same number as last time.
495-1000.
And let's do, how about just those two?
So let me go ahead now
and reveal that we do have
a file in here called phonebook.csv.
So that does exist.
Let me go ahead and do this.
Let me open up my file
browser over here.
I've got a lot of files I've created.
Here's phonebook.csv.
And if I click on it, there
is the file that I just
created, separated by commas.
But even more interestingly, let me
actually right click or control click
on this, download it to
my Mac's downloads folder.
Let me go into my downloads
folder just for fun,
and I've installed in
advance Microsoft Excel.
If I go into my downloads folder
and open up phonebook.csv,
we're going to see, oh, Apple
Numbers, not Excel, opening up.
View my spreadsheets.
All right, numbers is kind of stupid.
So there we go.
No, this isn't a Mac versus PC thing.
So now we have phonebook.csv
rendered in this format here.
Numbers presumes that the top row
should be gray and not white, as well.
So the formatting looks a bit off.
Anyhow, clearly, you
could open this same file
in a spreadsheet program like
Microsoft Office, or Apple Numbers,
or of course, something
like Google Spreadsheets.
But let me do one other thing when
it comes to copying files now,
whereby besides making a phone book,
whereby I clearly have the ability now
to save strings in files.
And actually, just for good measure,
let me hammer home the point
that anytime we're dealing with
pointers now, something could go wrong.
And if you read the
documentation for fopen,
we should also check
that file could be null.
Maybe the file is not found, or
something's not working on the server.
And so just to be safe, we
should return one there.
So even not just malloc,
not just getstring.
Any time a function
returns a pointer, you
should check if it's null, because
if it is, per the documentation,
almost always means
something has gone wrong.
So you should get out, lest you
trust the return value therein.
So let me go ahead and do
one other program here.
Let me create my own copy program.
So up until now, we've used commands
like RM, and LS, and CP for copy.
I can actually create my own
version of Linux's copy program,
perhaps as follows.
Let me actually go into
cp.c, in this case.
Let me include some familiar file.
Standard io.h.
Let me include, how about one other?
Standard int.h for
reasons we'll see now,
because in standard int.h is
that uint8_type that I mentioned
earlier, which just means, give me
an eight bit value that's unsigned,
which means no negative numbers.
It's just raw data.
It's not an integer in the
positive or negative sense.
And let me just nickname
that to byte, just
to make clear that I want to
manipulate files byte at a time.
Let me now declare, for
the first time today,
a version of main that takes in
an ergc command, takes in argc,
and takes in argv, which is
for command line arguments.
Technically though, I'm not using
the CS50 library in this version,
so even that can now be changed.
And this is the canonical
way in C to declare
main when you want to get
command line arguments using
char star instead of string.
So now, I'm going to do two things.
Remember how copy works.
You specify two files,
the file you want to copy,
and the new name that you
want to give to the copy.
So it would be like CP, space, old name,
space, new name at the command line.
So accordingly, I'm going to do this.
I'm going to create one file in memory
called source, or SRC for short.
And I'm going to set that equal to
whatever is in argv one in read mode.
But just to be super specific,
I'm going to use read binary mode.
I don't want to be copying text files.
I want binary data, zeros
and ones, like images.
So I'm going to tell fopen
to expect binary data.
I'm then going to go ahead
and create a second variable
called destination, DST for short.
And I'm going to open up
whatever is in argv two,
the second file name
at the command line.
But I don't want to read this file.
I want to write to it in
binary using zeros and ones.
Now, let me do the copying
one bite at a time.
It's a little inefficient.
I should really do bunches
of bytes at a time for speed.
But let me just give myself one
byte in a variable called b.
So byte is not a thing
in C. It's literally
a synonym I created just
for the sake of discussion
because we'll do this
in the future, as well.
Now, let me go ahead and do this.
How do you copy a file from old to new?
Well, I think it would
suffice to use a loop
and just start at the
beginning of the file,
loop all the way to the end of
the file, and within the loop,
copy one byte from old to new.
So how do I do that?
I used fprintf last time to write text.
This time, I'm going to use a
different function as follows.
While there are bytes
to read from the file,
and this one's going to be a
mouthful, so let me just type it out
and then I'll explain it.
While that line is
true, go ahead and write
this line, which is similarly a
mouthful, so I'll type it first
and then explain what it does.
Then I'm going to close destination.
Whoops.
Then I'm going to close source, and I
claim, if I haven't messed anything up,
this will now copy files for me.
How?
So this is indeed a mouthful, but
there's a function called fread,
whose purpose in life is to
read one or more bytes for you.
How does it work?
Well, just like swap,
just like scanf, you
have to tell it where to
load those bytes in memory.
So if I want to put them
in the byte called b,
I can't just say b because
that's passed by value.
I need to pass by reference.
So I say the address of b
is where I want you to put
one byte from the file at a time.
How big is a byte?
Technically, I could just say one
because we all know how big a byte is.
But I'm just going to be super proper
and generalize this as size of b
so it just figures it out
for me, just in case we ever
do more than one bite at a time.
How many bytes do I
want to copy at a time?
One, just to keep it simple.
And where do I want to
read those bytes from?
The source file.
fread, if you read the
documentation, just tells you
how many bytes were successfully read.
Logically, it should
either be one was read,
or zero were read, based on
what I'm asking it to do.
I'm asking it to read one at a time, so
it's either going to succeed or fail.
So I want to do this for
as long as it succeeds
because it's going to succeed until
it gets to the end of the file,
and then there's no more bytes to read,
at which point it will return zero.
So now, I do the opposite with
fwrite, and it's almost the same line.
Where do I want to write that byte?
Well, first, I tell fwrite
where to find the byte,
go there, and get the
byte that was copied.
It's this size, which is going to
be one, but I did it generally.
One bite at a time, please.
And write it to the destination file.
So if I now open up my
terminal window, let me first
make CP to create my own copy program.
Let me actually open an
image I came with today.
Here's a happy cat from the internet.
And that's going to
be my original image.
Let me now go ahead and run this.
Dot slash CP.
I have to run dot slash because
I want my version of CP,
not the one that comes with Linux.
So dot slash CP, cat.jpeg,
and let's call it maybe
my backup cat, just in case
I ever mess up the original.
Enter.
Seems to work OK.
When I run now code of backup
dot jpeg to open the copy,
there is that same happy cat.
So it's very low level
manipulation, but it all
results from my now having
the power to express myself
in terms of locations and memory
using pointers, understanding
that strings and now files are really
just abstractions on top of these lower
level details.
And from all of that is going to come
some pretty powerful functionality.
In fact, among the things that you
can now do, as you'll soon see,
is manipulate at least simple
files, known as bitmap files.
So BMP is bitmap file, and it
essentially implements images exactly
as we began today, as just a map of
bits, a grid, xy coordinates of grids,
each of which represents
a pixel coordinate.
A bitmap is a type of file with a
dot BMP file extension on a computer
that stores images just like that.
And now that you have the ability to
not only think about images in this way,
but write code that
manipulates images, you
can do powerful things all on
Instagram, and TikTok, and Snapchat,
like filters nowadays.
So for instance, here is
an image of the bridge,
the Weeks Bridge across the river.
Here is a black and white filter that
we've applied by writing some C code,
as you soon will, to change it
from colorful to black and white.
Here's the original that
you might see every day.
Here, meanwhile, is
a reflection thereof.
If you've ever flipped an
image around on the x-axis,
this can actually rotate the image,
even though this is the other side
of the bridge over there.
Meanwhile, here is a blurred version.
If it looks a little
blurry, that's deliberate
because we've essentially smudged all
of the values by looking at every pixel,
looking up, down, left, and
right, and kind of blurring
the effect to give it this effect here.
Here is what's called
edge detection, whereby
if you're feeling more
comfortable, you can
write code that looks at
these individual pixels,
tries to figure out where the edges
are, just like a fancy computer might,
and then colorize it
in this way, as well.
And you'll be able to do all of
that because images like these
are just grids with coordinates
with lots and lots of pixels.
So what started quite simply
now is going to be something
you now have complete
control over, now that we've
taken off these training wheels.
And it's cultural
within computer science
to understand geek humor like this.
And so the last thing
we'll do today is give you
this joke to end on, which for better
or for worse, should now make sense.
And those chuckles will suffice.
This was CS50.