[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
This is CS50, and this
is finally week 6.
And this is that week we
promised, wherein we finally
transition from C, this lower-level
older language via which we explored
memory and how really computers
work underneath the hood,
to what's now called Python, which is
a more modern, higher-level language,
whereby we're still going to be able
to solve the same types of problems.
But it's going to suddenly start to
get much, much easier because what
Python offers, as do higher-level
languages more generally,
are what we might
describe as abstractions
over the very low-level ideas that
you've been implementing in sections
and problem sets and so much more.
But recall from week 0, where we began.
This was our simplest of programs
that just printed "hello, world."
Things escalated quickly
thereafter in week 1,
where, suddenly, we had
all of this new syntax.
But the idea was still the same of
just printing out "hello, world."
Well, as of today, a
lot of that distraction,
a lot of the visual
distraction, goes away entirely
such that what used to be this in C
will now be quite simply this in Python.
And that's a bit of a
head fake in that we're
going to see some other
fancier features of Python.
But you'll find that Python's
popularity in large part
derives from just how
relatively readable it is
and also, as we'll ultimately
see, just how exciting
and filled the ecosystem
among Python programmers.
That is to say there's
a lot more libraries.
There's a lot more problems that
people have solved in Python
that you can now incorporate
into your own programs
in order to stand on their shoulders
and get real work done faster.
But recall, though, from C that
we had a few steps via which
to actually compile that kind of code.
So we got into the habit of make
to make our program called hello.
And then we've been in the habit
of running it with ./hello,
the effect of which, of course, is to
feed all of the zeros and ones that
compose the hello program into the
computer's memory and, in turn,
the CPU.
We revealed that what
make is really doing
is something a little more specific,
namely running clang, the C language
compiler specifically, with some
automatic command line arguments so as
to output the name that you want,
link in the library that you want,
and so forth.
But with Python, wonderfully, we're
going to get rid of those steps,
too, and quite simply run it as follows.
Henceforth, our programs will no
longer be in files ending in .c,
suffice it to say.
Our files starting today are
going to start ending with .py,
which is an indication to the
computer-- macOS, Windows,
or Linux or anything else--
that this is a Python program.
But unlike C, wherein we've been
in the habit of compiling our code
and running it, compiling our code
and running it, any time you make
a change, with Python, those two
steps get reduced into one, such
that any time you make a change
and want to rerun your code,
you don't explicitly compile it anymore.
You instead just run a program called
python, similar in spirit to clang.
But whereas clang is a
compiler, python will
see as not only the name of the
language, but the name of a program.
And the type of that program
is that of interpreter.
An interpreter is a program that reads
your code top to bottom, left to right,
and really does what it says without
having this intermediate step of first
having to compile it in zeros and ones.
So with that said, let me do this.
Let me flip over here to VS Code.
And within VS Code, let me
write my first Python program.
And as always, I can create a new file
with the code command within VS Code.
I'm going to create this file
called hello.py, for instance.
And quite, quite simply, I'm going to
go ahead and simply do print("Hello,
world").
And if I go down to my terminal
window, instead of compiling this,
I'm instead going to interpret this
program by running python, space,
and the name of the file I want
Python to interpret, hitting Enter.
And voila.
Now you see "hello, world."
But let me go ahead and
compare this at left.
Let me also go ahead and bring
back briefly a file called hello.c.
And I'm going to do this as we
did in the very first day of C,
where I included standard io.h.
I did int main(void).
I did inside of there printf(), quote
unquote, "hello, world," backslash n,
close quote, semicolon.
And let me go ahead in VS Code.
And if you drag your file
over to the right or the left,
you can actually split-screen
things if of help.
And what I've done here is-- and
let me hide my terminal window--
I've now compared these
two files left and right.
So here's hello.c from, say, week 1.
Here's hello.py from week 6 now.
And the obvious-- the
differences are perhaps obvious.
But there's still some-- there's
a subtlety, at least one subtlety.
Beyond getting rid of
lots of syntax, what
did I apparently omit
from my Python version,
even though it didn't appear
to behave in any buggy way?
Yeah?
Sorry?
Say one more time?
AUDIENCE: The library.
DAVID MALAN: The library.
So I didn't have to include any kind of
library like the standard I/O library.
print(), apparently,
in Python, just works.
AUDIENCE: main() [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: So I don't
need to use main() anymore.
So this main() function, to be clear,
was required in C because that's what
told the compiler what the
main part of your program is.
And you can't just start
writing code otherwise.
What else do you see?
AUDIENCE: No semicolon.
DAVID MALAN: So there's no more
semicolon, wonderfully enough,
at the end of this line,
even though there was here.
And things are getting a
little more subtle now.
What else?
So the new line.
So recall that in printf(), if you
wanted to move the cursor to the next
line when you're done printing,
you had to do it yourself.
So it seems as though Python--
because when I interpreted
this program a moment ago,
the cursor did move to
the next line on its own.
They sort of reversed
the default behavior.
So those are just some of
the salient differences here.
One, you don't have to explicitly
include standard library, so to speak,
like standard I/O. You don't need
to define a main() function anymore.
You can just start writing your code.
You don't need these
parentheses, these curly braces.
printf() is now called
print(), it would seem.
And you don't need the backslash n.
Now, there is one thing
that's also a little looser,
even though I didn't do it here.
Even though in C, it was required
to use double quotes any times you--
any time you want to use a
string, a.k.a., char*, in Python,
as with a lot of languages nowadays, you
can actually get away with just using
single quotes so long
as you are consistent.
Generally speaking,
some people like this
because you don't have to hold
Shift, and therefore, you just
hit one key instead of two.
So there's an argument
in terms of efficiency.
However, if you want to use
an apostrophe in your string,
then you have to escape it.
And so in general, stylistically,
I'll use double quotes in this way.
But things are getting a
little looser now with Python,
whereby that's not
actually a requirement.
But what's especially
exciting with Python,
and, really, a lot of higher-level
languages, is just how much real work
you can get done relatively quickly.
So you've just spent
quite a bit of time,
daresay, implementing your
spell checker and implementing
your own dictionary of sorts.
Well, let me propose that
maybe we should have asked you
to do that in Python instead of C. Why?
Well, let me go ahead and do this.
Let me close these two tabs
and reopen my terminal window.
Let me go into a
directory called speller
that I downloaded in advance for class.
And if I type ls in here,
you'll notice that it's
very similar to what you spent
time on with problem set 5.
But the file extensions are different.
There's a dictionary.py
instead of dictionary.c.
There's a speller.py
instead of a speller.c.
And there's the exact same
directories, dictionaries, and texts
that we gave you for problem set 5.
So let me just stipulate that I spent
time implementing speller.c in Python.
And so I gave it a name of speller.py.
But I didn't go about really
implementing dictionary.py yet.
And so why don't we go ahead and
actually implement dictionary.py
together by doing this?
Let me clear my terminal,
do code dictionary.py.
And let me propose that we implement,
ultimately, four functions.
And what are those
functions going to be?
Well, they're going to be the check()
function, the load() function,
the size() function, and
the unload() function.
But recall that in problem set 5,
you implemented your own hash table.
And so while there isn't a
hash table data type in Python,
I'm going to go ahead and do this.
I'm going to create a variable, a
global variable in dictionary.py,
called words, and I'm
going to make it a set.
In the mathematical sense,
a set is a collection
of things that won't contain duplicates.
Any duplicates will be filtered out.
So I'm going to now, after that,
creating that one global variable,
I'm going to create a function
called check(), just as you did.
And check() takes as input a word.
And if I want to check if a
word is in that set of words,
I can simply do word.lower in words.
And that's it.
Let me now define another function
called load(), which, recall,
took an argument, which was the name
of the dictionary you want to load
into memory.
Inside of my load() function,
I'm now going to do this.
I'm going to say with open(dictionary)
as a variable called file.
And in there, I'm going to go
ahead and update the set of words
to be the updated version of whatever's
in this file as a result of reading
it and then splitting its
lines, whereby this file has
a big, long column of words, each
of which is separated by a new line,
splitline is going to split all
of those into one big collection.
And then I'm just going to
go ahead and return True.
I'm now going to go ahead and define
a size function, just as you did.
But in Python, I'm going to go ahead
and just go ahead and return the length
of that set of words, where length, or
len(), is a function itself in Python.
And I'm going to do one last function.
It turns out that in Python,
even though, for this program,
I'm going to go and implement
a function called unload,
there's not actually
anything to unload in Python,
because Python will manage
your memory for you.
malloc() is gone. free() is gone.
Pointers are gone.
It handles all of that, seemingly
magically for now, for you.
So here then is, I claim, what you
could have done with problem set 5
if implementing it in Python instead.
Let me go ahead and
open my terminal window.
Let me increase its size.
Let me run Python of speller.py, which
is the name of the actual program, not
the dictionary per se
that I implemented.
Let's run it on a file called
holmes.txt because that
was a particularly big file.
And if I hit Enter now,
we'll see, hopefully,
the same output that you saw
in C flying across the screen.
And eventually, we should see
that same summary at the bottom
as to how many words
seem to be misspelled,
how many words were in the
dictionary, and, ultimately, how
fast this whole process was.
Now, the total amount of time required
was 1.93 seconds, which was actually
longer than it seemed to take.
That's because we're
doing this in the cloud,
and it was taking some amount of time
to send all of the text to my screen.
But the code was only taking 1.93
seconds total on the actual server.
And hopefully, these same kinds
of numbers line up with your own,
the difference being what I did not have
to implement for this spell checker is
your own hash table, is your
own dictionary, literally,
beyond what I've done using Python here
with some of these built-in features.
So why, you see, why
not always use Python,
assuming that you
prefer the idea of being
able to whip up within seconds
the entirety of problem set 5?
How might you choose
now between languages?
And I apologize if you're
harboring resentment
that this wasn't a week earlier.
Why Python or why C?
Any instincts?
Any thoughts?
There's hopefully a reason?
Yeah, over here?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: I always thought that Python
was a little slower than C [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Ah, really good conjecture.
So you always thought that
Python was slower than C
and takes up more space than C.
Odds are that's, in fact, correct.
So even though, ultimately, this 1.93
seconds is still pretty darn fast,
odds are it's a little slower than
the C version would have been.
It's possible, too, that
my version in Python
actually does take up more RAM
or memory underneath the hood.
Why?
Well, because Python itself
is managing memory for you.
And it doesn't necessarily know a priori
how much memory you're going to need.
You, the programmer might, and
you, the programmer writing in C,
allocated presumably
exactly as much memory
as you might have needed
last week with problem set 5.
But Python's got to maybe
do its best effort for you
and try to manage memory for you, and
there's going to be some overhead.
The fact that I have so
many fewer lines of code,
the fact that these lines of
code solve problem set 5 for me,
means that Python, or whoever invented
Python, they wrote lines of code
to of give me this functionality.
And so if you think of Python
as a middleman of sorts,
it's doing more work for me.
It's doing more of the heavy lift.
So it might take me a bit more time.
But, my gosh, look how much
time it has saved in terms
of writing this code more quickly.
And arguably, this code
is even more readable,
or at least will be after today, week
6, once you have an eye for the syntax
and features of Python itself.
So beyond that, it turns out you can
do other things pretty easily as well.
Let me go back into my terminal window.
Let me close this dictionary.py.
Let me go into a folder
called filter, in which
I have this same bridge that we've seen
in the past across the river there.
So here's a bridge.
This is the original version
of this particular photograph.
Suppose I actually want to
write a program that blurs this.
Well, you might recall from problem set
4 you could write that same code in C
by manipulating all of the red,
the green, the blue pixels that
are ultimately composing that file.
But let me go ahead and
propose this instead.
Let me create a file called blur.py.
And in this file, let me go ahead and
just go ahead and import a library.
So from the Python image
library, PIL, let me go ahead
and import something called Image,
capital I, and Image Filter, capital
I, capital F.
So I'm going to do before
= Image.open("bridge.bmp").
Then let me go ahead and create
another variable called after
and set that equal to before.filter,
and then, in parentheses,
ImageFilter, spelled
as before, dot BoxBlur,
and then we'll give it a value of 10.
How much do I want to
blur it, for instance?
After that, I'm going to literally
call after.save, and let's
save it as a file called out.bmp.
And that's it.
I propose that this is how you can now
write code in Python to blur an image,
much like you might
have for problem set 4.
Now let me go ahead in my terminal
window and run python of blur.py.
When I hit Enter, those
four lines of code will run.
It seems to have happened quite quickly.
Let me go ahead and open now out.bmp.
And whereas the previous image looked
like this a moment ago, let me go ahead
and open out.bmp.
And hopefully, you can
indeed see that it blurred it
for me using that same code.
And if we want things to
escalate a little more quickly,
let me go ahead and do this instead.
Let me close blur.bmp.
Let me go ahead and open
a file called edges.py.
And maybe, in edges.py, we
can use this same library.
So from the Python Image Library,
import Image and import ImageFilter.
Let me go ahead and create
another variable called before,
set it equal to
Image.open("bridge.bmp"),
just like before.
Let me create another
variable called after,
set that equal to
before.filter(ImageFilter.FIND_EDGES),
which comes with this library
automatically, and lastly,
the same thing-- save this
as a file called out.bmp.
So if you struggled
perhaps with this one
previously, whereby you wrote for the
more comfortable version of problem
set 4, edge detection,
so to speak, well, you
might have then created a file
that given an input like this,
the original bridge.bmp, this new
version, out.bmp, with just four
lines of code, now looks like this.
So, again, if this is
a little frustrating
that we had to do all of
this in C, that was exactly
the point to motivate that
you now understand nonetheless
what's going on underneath the hood.
But with Python, you can
express the solutions
to problems all the more
efficiently, all the more readily.
And just one last one, too--
it's very common nowadays
in the world of photography and
social media and the like to do face
detection, for better or for worse.
And it turns out that
face detection, even
if you want to integrate it
into your own application,
is something that lots of other people
have integrated into their applications
as well.
So Python, to my point earlier of having
this very rich ecosystem of libraries
that other people wrote, you can
literally run a command like pip
install face_recognition if you want
to add support to your code space,
or to your programming and
environment more generally,
for the notion of face recognition.
In fact, this is going
to automatically install
from some server elsewhere a
library that someone else wrote
called face_recognition.
And with this library, you
can do something like this.
Let me go into a directory
that I came with in advance.
Let me go ahead and ls in there,
and you'll see four files--
detect.py and recognize.py,
which are going to detect
faces and then recognize specific
faces, respectively, and then two files
I brought from a popular
TV show, for instance.
So if I open office.jpg, here is one of
the early cast photos from the hit TV
series The Office.
And here is a photograph of someone
specific from the show, Toby.
Now, this is, of course, Toby's face.
But what is it that
makes Toby's face a face?
More generally, if I open up
office.jpg, and I asked you, the human,
to identify all of the
faces in this picture,
it wouldn't be that hard with a marker
to sort of circle all of the faces.
But how?
Why?
How do you as humans detect
faces, might you think?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: You have eyes, nose.
DAVID MALAN: Features,
yeah, like eyes, nose,
generally in a similar
orientation, even though we all
have different faces, ultimately.
But there's a pattern to the shapes
that you're seeing on the screen.
Well, it turns out this
face_recognition library
has been trained, perhaps via
artificial intelligence over time,
to recognize faces, but any
number of different faces,
perhaps among these folks here.
So if I go back into my
terminal window here,
let me go ahead and run, say,
python of detect.py, which I wrote
in advance, which uses that library.
And what that program is going to do--
it's going to think, do some thinking.
It's just found some face.
And let me go ahead now and
open a file it just created
called detected.jpg, which I didn't
have in my folder a moment ago.
But when I open this here file,
you'll now see all of the faces
based on this library's
detection thereof.
But suppose that we're looking for
a very specific face among them,
maybe Toby's.
Well, maybe if we write a
program that doesn't just
take as input the office.jpg,
but a second input, toby.jpg,
maybe this library, and
code more generally,
can distinguish Toby's face from
Jim's, from Pam's, from everyone else
in the show, just based on this one
piece of training data, so to speak.
Well let me instead run python
of recognize.py and hit Enter.
It's going to do some thinking,
some thinking, some thinking.
And it is going to
output now a file called
recognized.jpg, which should show
me his face, ideally, specifically.
And so what has it done?
Well, with sort of a green marker,
there is Toby among all of these faces.
That's maybe a dozen
or so lines of code,
but it's built on top of
this ecosystem of libraries.
And this is, again, just one of the
reasons why Python is so popular.
Undoubtedly, some number of years
from now, Python will be out,
and something else will be back in.
But that's indeed among the goals
of CS50, too, is not to teach you C,
not to teach you Python,
not in a couple of weeks
to teach you JavaScript
and other languages, too,
but to teach you how to program.
And indeed, all of the ideas
we have explored and will now
explore more today, you'll see recurring
for languages in the years to come.
Any questions before we now dive
into how it is this code is working
and why I type the things that
I did before we forge ahead?
Any questions along these lines?
Anything at all?
No?
All right.
So how does Python itself work?
Well, let's do a quick
review as we did when
we transitioned from
Scratch to C, this time,
though, from Scratch, say, to Python.
So in Python, as with
many languages, there
are these things called functions--
the actions and verbs that
actually get things done.
So here on the left, recall from week
0, was the simplest of functions.
We played with, first, the say
block, which just literally has
the cat say something on the screen.
We've seen in C, for instance, the
equivalent line of code is arguably
this here, with printf(), with the
parentheses, the quotation marks,
the backslash n, the semicolon.
In Python now, it's going to indeed
be a little simpler than that.
But the idea is the same
as it was back in week 0.
Libraries-- so we've seen
already in C, and now we've
already seen in Python that
these things exist, too.
In the world of C, recall that besides
the standard ones, like standard io.h,
that header file, we could
very quickly introduce cs50.h,
which was like your
entry point, the header
file for the CS50 library, which gave
you a bunch of functions as well.
Well, we're going to give
you a similar library
for at least the next week or
two, training wheels for Python
specifically, that, again, will take
off so that you can stand on your own,
even with CS50 behind you.
But the syntax for using a library
in Python is a little different.
You don't include a .h file.
You just import, instead,
the name of the library.
All right.
What does that actually mean?
Well, if there are specific functions
in that library you want to use,
in Python, you can be more precise.
You don't just have to say,
give me the whole library.
For efficiency purposes, you can say,
let me import the get_string() function
from the CS50 library.
So you have finer-grained control in
Python, which can actually speed things
up if you're not loading
things unnecessarily
into memory, if all you want
is, say, one feature therein.
So here, for instance, in Scratch, was
an example of how we might use not only
a built-in function, like the say
block, or, in C, in the printf(),
but how we might similarly now do
the same but achieve this in Python.
So how might we do this?
Well, in Python, or
rather, in C, this code
looks a little something like this.
Back in week 1, we declared
a variable of type string,
even though later we
revealed that to be char*.
I gave this a variable name of
answer for parity with Scratch.
Then we use CS50's own get_string()
function and asked, for instance,
the same question as
in the white oval here.
And then, using this placeholder
syntax, these format codes,
which was printf()-specific, we could
plug in that answer to this premade
string where the %s is.
And we saw %i and %f and
a bunch of others as well.
So this is sort of how,
in C, you approximate
the idea of concatenating two
things together, joining two things,
just as we did here in Scratch.
So in Python, it turns out it's not
only going to be a little easier,
but there's going to be
even more ways to do this.
And so even what might seem today
like a lot of different syntax,
it really is just different
ways, stylistically,
to achieve the same goals.
And over time, as you get
more comfortable with this,
you too will develop your own
style, or, if working for a company
or working with a team,
you might collectively
decide which conventions
you want to use.
But here, for instance, is one way
you could implement this same idea
in Scratch but in Python instead.
So notice I'm going to still
use a variable called answer.
I'm going to use CS50's
function called get_string().
I'm still going to use, quote
unquote, "What's your name?"
But down here is where we
see the most difference.
It's, again, not called
printf() in Python.
It's now called just print().
And what might you infer the
plus operator is doing here?
It's not addition, obviously,
in a mathematical sense.
But those of you who have
perhaps programmed before,
what does the plus
represent in this context?
AUDIENCE: It's joining
the two strings together.
DAVID MALAN: It's indeed joining
So this is indeed
concatenating the thing
on the left with the thing on the right.
So you don't use the placeholder
in this particular scenario.
You can instead, a little
more simply, just use plus.
But you want your grammar to line up.
So I still have "hello,"
and then close quote
because I want to form a full phrase.
Notice, too, there's also
one other slightly more
subtle difference on the first line.
Besides the fact that we don't have
a semicolon, what else is different?
AUDIENCE: You don't declare
the type of the variable.
DAVID MALAN: I didn't declare
So Python still has
strings, as we'll see.
But you don't have to tell the
interpreter what type of variable
it is.
And this is going to
save us some keystrokes,
and it's just going to be a little
more user-friendly over time.
Meanwhile, you can do this also a
little bit differently if you prefer.
You can instead trust that the print()
function in Python can actually do even
more for you automatically.
The print() function in Python can take
multiple arguments separated by commas
in the usual way.
And by default, Python
is going to insert
for you a single space between its
first argument and its second argument.
So notice what I've done
here is my first argument
is, quote unquote, "hello,"
with a comma but no space.
Then, outside of the quotes, I'm
putting a comma because that just means,
here comes my second argument.
And then I put the same
variable as before.
And I'm just going to
let Python figure out
that it should, by default,
per its documentation,
can join these two variables, putting
a single space in between them.
You can do this yet another way.
And this way looks a little
weirder, but this is actually
probably the most common
way nowadays in Python
is to use what's called a format
string, or f string, for short.
And this looks weird to me still.
It looks weird.
But if you prefix a string
in Python with an f,
literally, you can then use curly
braces inside of that string in Python.
And Python will not print out literally
a curly brace and a closed curly brace.
It will instead interpolate whatever
is inside of those curly braces.
That is to say if answer
is a variable that
has some value, like "David"
or something like that,
saying f before the
first quotation mark,
and then using these
curly braces therein,
is going to do the exact same thing of
creating a string that says "Hello,"
comma, space, "David."
So it's going to plug
in the value for you.
So you can think of this as %s but
without that second step of having
to keep track of what you
want to plug back in for %s.
Instead of %s, you literally
put in curly braces,
what do you want to put right there?
You format the string yourself.
So given all of those
ways, how might we actually
go about implementing this
or using this ourselves?
Well, let me propose
that we do this here.
Let me propose that
I go back to VS Code.
Let me go ahead and
open up hello.py again.
And as before, instead of just
printing out something like,
quote unquote, "hello, world,"
let me actually print out
something a little more interesting.
So let me go ahead and,
from the CS50 library,
import the function called get_string().
Then let me go ahead and create
a variable called answer.
Let me set that equal to the
return value of get_string() with,
as an argument, quote
unquote, "What's your name?"
And then no semicolon at the end of
that line, but on the next line, frankly
here, I can pick any one of
those potential solutions.
So let me start with the first.
So "hello, " + answer.
And now, if I go down to my terminal
window and run python of hello.py,
I'm prompted for my name.
I can type in D-A-V-I-D, and
voila, that there then works.
Or I can tweak this a little bit.
I can trust that Python will concatenate
its first and second argument for me.
But this isn't quite right.
Let me go ahead and rerun python
of hello.py, hit Enter, and type
in "David."
It's going to be ever-so-slightly
buggy, sort of grammatically
or visually, if you will.
What did I do wrong here?
Yeah.
So I left the space in there, even
though I'm getting one for free from
print().
So that's an easy solution here.
But let's do it one other way
after running this to be sure--
D-A-V-I-D.
And OK, now it looks like I intended.
Well, let's go ahead and
use that placeholder syntax.
So let's just pass in one bigger
string as our argument, do "hello,"
and then, in curly braces,
[? answer ?],, like this.
Well, let me go down to my
terminal window and clear it.
Let me run python of hello.py and
enter, type in D-A-V-I-D, and voila.
OK, I made a mistake.
What did I do wrong here,
minor though it seems to be?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: So the
stupid little f that you
have to put before the
string to tell Python
that this is a special string--
it's a format string, or f
string-- that it should
additionally format for you.
So if I rerun this after adding
that f, I can do python of hello.py.
What's your name?
David.
And now it looks the way I might intend.
But it turns out in Python, you don't
actually need to use get_string().
In C, recall that we introduced
that because it's actually
pretty annoying in C to get strings,
in particular to get strings safely.
Recall those short examples we
did with scanf not too long ago.
And scanf kind of scans what
the user types at the keyboard
and loads it into memory.
But the fundamental danger with scanf
when it comes to strings was what?
Why was it dangerous to use
scanf to get strings from a user?
Why?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: What if they give you a really
long string you don't have space for?
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
What if they give you
a really long string
that you didn't allocate space for?
Because you're not going to know
as the programmer in advance
how long of a string the
human is going to type in.
So you might under--
you might undercut it and therefore
have too much memory, or too many
characters being put into that
memory, thereby giving you
some kind of buffer overflow, which
might crash the computer or, minimally,
your program.
So it turns out in C, get_string()
was especially useful.
In Python, it's not really that useful.
All it does is use a function that
does come with Python called input().
And, in fact, the input() function in
Python, for all intents and purposes,
is the same as the get_string()
function that we give to you.
But just to ease the
transition from C to Python,
we implemented a Python version
of get_string() nonetheless.
But this is to say if
I go to VS Code here,
and I just change get_string()
to input(), and, in fact,
I even get rid of the CS50 library at
the top, this too should work fine.
If I rerun python of hello.py,
type in my name, David, and voila,
I have that now working as well.
All right.
Questions about this use of get_string()
or input() or any of our syntax thus
far?
All right.
Well, what about variables?
We've used variables
already, and we already
identified the fact that you don't have
to specify the type of your variables
proactively, even though, clearly,
Python supports strings thus far,
well, in Python, here's
how you might declare
a variable that not necessarily
is assigned like a string,
but maybe an integer instead.
So in Scratch, here's
how you could create
a variable called counter if you want
to count things and set it equal to 0.
In C, what we would have done is this--
int counter = 0; that's the
exact same thing as in Scratch.
But in Python, as you might imagine,
we can chip away at this and type
out this same idea little more easily.
One, we don't need to say int anymore.
Two, we don't need
the semicolon anymore.
And so you just do what you intend.
If you want a variable,
just write it out.
If you want to assign it a
value, you use the equals sign.
If you want to specify that
value, you put it on the right.
And just as in C, this is
not the equality operator.
It's the assignment
operator from right to left.
Recall that in Scratch, if you wanted to
increment a variable by 1 or any value,
you could use this puzzle piece here.
Well, in C, you could do syntax like
this, which, again, is not equality.
It's saying add 1 to counter and then
assign it back to the counter variable.
In Python, you can do exactly the
same thing minus the semicolon.
So you don't need to
use the semicolon here.
But you might recall that in C, there
was some syntactic sugar for this idea
because it was pretty popular.
And so you could shorten this
in C, as you can in Python,
to actually just this. += 1 will add
to the counter variable whatever that
value is.
But it's not all steps forward.
You might be in the
habit of using ++ or --.
Sorry, those are not
available in Python.
Why?
It's because the designers
of Python decided that you
don't need them because this is--
gets the job done anyway.
But there's a question down here in
front, unless it was about the same.
All right.
So that's one feature we're taking away.
But it's not such a big
deal to do += in this case.
Well, what about the
actual types involved here
beyond actually being
able to define variables?
Well, recall that in the world
of C, we had at least these data
types, those that came with
the language in particular.
And we played with quite
a few of these over time.
In Python, we're going to
take a bunch of those away.
In Python, you're only going to have
access to a bool, true or false,
a float, which is a real
number with a decimal point,
typically, an int, or an integer,
and a string, now known as str.
So Python here sort
of cuts some corners,
feels like it's too long
to write out strings.
So a string in Python is called str,
S-T-R, but it's the exact same idea.
Notice, though, that missing
from this now, in particular,
are double and long, which, recall,
actually used more bits in order
to store information.
We'll see that that might not
necessarily be a bad thing.
In fact, Python just
simplifies the world
into two different types
of variables but gets
out of the business of
you having to decide,
do you want a small int or a large
int or something along those lines?
Well, let me go ahead and do this.
Let me switch back over to VS Code here.
And why don't we actually try to play
around with some calculations using
these data types and more?
Let me go ahead and
propose that we implement,
like we did way back in
week 1, a simple calculator.
So let me do this--
code of calculator.c.
So I'm indeed going to do
this in C first, just so
that we have a similar example at hand.
So I'm going to include
standard io.h here at the top.
I'm going to go ahead
and do int main(void).
Inside of main(), I'm going to go ahead
and declare a variable called x and set
that equal to get_int(), and I'm going
to prompt the user for that value x.
But if I'm using get_int(), recall
that actually is from the CS50 library.
So in C, I'm going to need
cs50.h, still, for this example.
But back in week 1, I
then did something else.
I then said, give me another variable
called y, set that equal to get_int(),
and set that equal to that--
pass in that prompt there.
And then, lastly, let's just
do something super simple
like add two numbers together.
So in C, I'll use printf().
I'm going to go ahead and do %i
backslash n as a placeholder.
And then I'm just
going to plug in x + y.
So all of that was in C. So it was
a decent number of lines of code
to accomplish that task,
only three of which
are really the logical
part of my program.
These are the three that
we're really interested in.
So let me instead now do
this, code of calculator.py,
which is going to give me a new tab.
Let me just drag it over to the right
so I can view these side by side.
And in calculator.py, let's do this.
From the CS50 library, import
the get_int() function,
which is also available.
Then let's go ahead and create a
variable called x and set it equal
to the return value of get_int(),
passing in the same prompt--
no semicolon, no mention of int.
Let's then create a second variable
y, set it equal to get_int(),
prompt the user for y, as before,
no int, explicitly, no semicolon.
And now let's just go
ahead and print out x + y.
So it turns out that the print()
function in Python is further flexible,
that you don't need
these format strings.
If you want to print out an
integer, just pass it an integer,
even if that integer is the
sum of two other integers.
So it just sort of works
as you might expect.
So let me go down into my terminal here.
Let me run python of calculator.py.
And when I hit Enter,
I'm prompted for x.
Let's do 1.
I'm prompted for y.
Let's do 2.
And voila, I should
see 3 as the result--
so no actual surprises there.
But let me go ahead and, you know what?
Let's take away this
training wheel, right?
We don't want to keep
introducing CS50-specific things.
So suppose we didn't give you get_int().
Well, it turns out that get_int() is
still doing a bit of help for you,
even though get_string() was kind
of a throwaway and we could replace
get_string() with input().
So let's try this same idea.
Let's go ahead and prompt the user
for input for both x and y using
the input() function in Python
instead of get_int() from CS50.
Let me go ahead and rerun Python
of calculator.py and hit Enter.
So far, so good.
Let me type in 1.
Let me type in 2.
And what answer should we see?
Hopefully still 3, but nope.
Now the answer is 12, or is it?
Why am I seeing 12 and not 3?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] two strings.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So it's actually concatenating
what seem to be two strings.
So if we actually read the
documentation for the input() function,
it's behaving exactly
as it's supposed to.
It is getting input from the
user from their keyboard.
But anything you type at the
keyboard is effectively a string.
Even if some of the symbols
happen to look like or actually
be decimal numbers, they're still
going to come to you as strings.
And so x is a string,
a.k.a., str, y is a str,
and we've already seen that if you use
plus in between two strings, or strs,
you're going to get
concatenation, not addition.
So you're not seeing 12 as much
as you're seeing 1 2, not 12.
So how can we fix this?
Well, in C, we had this technique where
we could cast one thing to another
by just putting int in
parentheses, for instance.
In Python, things are a
little higher-level such
that you can't quite get
away with just casting
one thing to another because
a string, recall, is not
the same thing as a char.
A string has zero or more characters.
A char always has one.
And in C, there was a perfect
mapping between single characters
and single numbers in decimal,
like 65 for capital A.
But in Python, we can do something
somewhat similar and not so much cast
but convert this input() to an int
and convert this input() to an int.
So just like in C, you
can nest functions.
You can call one function
and pass its output
as the input to another function.
And this now will convert
x and y to integers.
And so now plus is going to behave
as you should-- as you would expect.
Let me rerun python of calculator.py,
type in 1, type in 2, and now
we're back to seeing 3 as the
result. If this is a little unclear,
this nesting, let me
do this one other way.
Instead of just passing
input() output into int,
I could also more pedantically do this.
x should actually equal int(x),
y should actually equal int(y).
This would be the exact same effect.
It's just two extra lines where
it's not really necessary.
But that would work fine.
If you don't like that approach,
we could even do it inline.
We could actually convert x
to an int and y to an int.
Why?
Well, int, I-N-T, in the context
of Python itself, is a function.
And it takes as input
here a string, or str,
and returns to you the numeric, the
integral equivalent-- so similar idea,
but it's actually a function.
So all of the syntax that
I've been tinkering with here
is sort of fundamentally the same as
it would be in C. But in this case,
we're not casting but
converting more specifically.
Well, let me go back
to these data types.
These are some of the data types
that are available to us in Python.
It turns out there's a
bunch of others as well
that we'll start to dabble with today.
You can get a range of
values, a list of values,
which is going to be like an
array, but better, tuples, which
are kind of like x, comma, y,
often, combinations of values that
don't change.
dict for dictionary-- it turns out
that in Python, you get dictionaries.
You get hash tables for free.
They're built into the language.
And we already saw that
Python also gives you
a data type known as
a set, which is just
a collection of values that gives you--
gets rid of any duplicates for you.
And as we saw briefly in speller-- and
we'll play more with these ideas soon--
it's going to actually be pretty
darn easy to get values or check
for values in those there data types.
So that in C, we were able to get input
easily, we had all of these functions.
In the CS50 library for Python, we're
only going to give you these instead.
They're going to be the same name.
So it's still get_string(), not
get_str, because we wanted the functions
to remain named the same.
But get_float(), get_int(),
get_string() all exist.
But, again, get_string()
is not all that useful.
But get_int() and
get_float() actually are.
Why?
Well, let me go back to VS Code here.
And let me go back to the
second version of this program,
whereby I proactively converted each
of these return values to integers.
So recall that this is the
solution to the 1 2 problem.
And to be clear, if I run python
of calculator.py and input 1 and 2,
I get back now 3 as expected.
But what I'm not showing you is that
there's still potentially a bug here.
Let me run python of calculator.py,
and let me just not cooperate.
Instead of typing what
looks like a number,
let me actually type something
that's clearly a string, like cat.
And unfortunately, we're going
to see the first of our errors,
the first of our runtime errors.
And this, like in C, is going
to look cryptic at first.
But this is generally
known as a traceback, where
it's going to trace back for you
everything your program just did,
even though this one's relatively short.
And you'll see that
calculator.py, line 1--
I didn't even get very far
before there's an error.
And then, with all of these carrot
symbols here, this is a problem.
Why?
invalid literal for int() function
with base 10, quote unquote, 'cat.'
Again, just like in C, It's very arcane.
It's hard to understand this
the first time you read it.
But what it's trying to tell me
is that cat is not an integer.
And therefore, the int() function
cannot convert it to an integer for you.
We're going to leave this
problem alone for now.
But this is why, again,
get_int()'s looking kind of good,
and get_float()'s looking kind of
good because those functions from
CS50's library will deal with
these kinds of problems for you.
Now, just so you've seen
it, there's another way
to import functions from these things.
If you were to use, for instance, in
a program, get_float(), get_int(),
and get_string(), you don't need to
do three separate lines like this.
You can actually separate them a
little more cleanly with commas.
And, in fact, if I go back to a version
of this program here in VS Code whereby
I actually do use the
get_int() function--
so let me actually get rid of all
this and use get_int() as before.
Let me get rid of all this
and use get_int() as before.
Previously, the way I did this was
by saying from cs50 import get_int()
if you know in advance what
function you want to use.
But suppose, for whatever reason, you
already have your own function named
get_int(), and therefore, it
would collide with CS50's own,
you can avoid that issue, too, by
just using that first statement we saw
earlier.
Just import the library itself.
Don't specify explicitly which
functions you're going to use.
But thereafter-- and you
could not do this in C--
you could specify
cs50.get_int(), cs50.get_int(),
in order to go into the library, access
its get_int() function, and therefore,
it doesn't matter if you or any
number of other people wrote
an identically-named
function called get_int().
You're using here, clearly, CS50's own.
So this is, again, just more
ways to achieve the same solution
but with different syntax.
All right.
Any questions about any of this
syntax or features thus far?
No?
All right.
Well, how about maybe
another example here,
whereby we revisit conditionals,
which was the way of implementing
do this thing or this thing, sort
of proverbial forks in the road.
In Scratch, recall, we might
use building blocks like these
to just check, is x less
than y, and if so, say so.
In C, this code looked like this.
And notice that we had parentheses
around the x and the y.
We had curly braces, even though I did
disclaim that for single lines of code,
you can actually omit the curly braces.
But stylistically, we always
include them in CS50's code.
But you have the backslash
n and the semicolon.
In a moment, you're about to see
the Python equivalent of this,
which is almost the same.
It's just a little nicer.
This, then, is the Python
equivalent thereof.
So what's different at a
glance here, just to be clear?
What's different?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: So the conditional
is not in parentheses.
You can use parentheses, especially if,
logically, you need to group things.
But if you don't need them, don't
use them is Python's mindset.
What else has changed here?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: No curly brackets.
DAVID MALAN: No curly braces, yeah,
so no curly braces around this.
And even though it's one line of code,
you just don't use curly braces at all.
Why?
Because in Python, indentation is
actually really, really important.
And we know from office
hours and problem sets
occasionally that if you
forgot to run style50
or you didn't manually
format your code beautifully,
C is not actually going to care if
everything is aligned on the left.
If you never once hit the Tab
character or the space bar,
C, or specifically, clang,
isn't really going to care.
But your teaching
fellow, your TA, is going
to care, or your colleague in the real
world, because your code's just a mess
and hard to read.
Python, though-- because you are not the
only ones in the world that might have
bad habits when it comes to style--
Python as a language decided, that's it.
Everyone has to indent in order
for their code to even work.
So the convention as Python
is to use for spaces--
so 1, 2, 3, 4, or hit Tab and let it
automatically convert to the same,
and use a colon instead
of the curly braces,
for instance, to make
clear what is associated
with this particular conditional.
We can omit, though, the
backslash n per before.
We can omit the semicolon.
But this is essentially
the Python version thereof.
Here in C-- in Scratch, if
you wanted to do an if-else,
like we did back in week 0, in C, It's
very similar to the if, except you add
the else clause and write out an
additional printf() like this.
In Python, we can tighten this up.
if x less than y, colon,
that's exactly the same.
First line's the same.
All we're doing now is adding an
else and the second print line here.
How about in Scratch?
If we had a three-way fork in
the road-- if, else, if, else.
In C, it looked pretty much
like that-- if, else, if, else.
In Python, we can tighten this up.
And this is not a typo.
What jumps out at you as weird but
you got to just get used to it?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: elif.
DAVID MALAN: elif.
And honestly, years later, I still
can't remember if it's elif or elsif
because other languages
actually do E-L-S-I-F.
and now I probably now biased all
of you to now questioning this.
But it's elif in Python.
E-L-I-F is not a typo.
It's in the spirit of let's just
save ourselves some keystrokes.
So elif is identical to elsif, but it's
a little tighter to type it this way.
All right.
So if we now have this ability
to express conditionals,
what can we actually do with them?
Well, let me go over to VS Code here.
And let me propose that we revisit
maybe another program from before,
where we just compare two
integers in particular.
So I'm in VS Code.
Let me open up a file
called, say, compare.py.
And in compare.py, we'll
use the CS50 library just
so we don't risk any errors, like if
the human doesn't type an integer.
So we're going to go ahead and
say from cs50 import get_int().
And in compare.py, let's get
two variables-- x = get_int(),
and prompt the user for x.
So "What's x?"
To be a bit more verbose,
y = get+int("What's y? ")
And then let's go ahead and
just compare these two values.
So if x is less than y, then go ahead
and print out with print("x is less
than y"), close quote,
elif x is greater than y,
go ahead and print out "x is
greater than y," close quote, else,
go ahead and print out "x is equal
to y"-- so the exact same program,
but I've added to the mix
getting a value of x and y.
Let me run python of compare.py.
Enter.
Let's type in 1 for x, 2
for y. x is less than y.
Let's run it once more.
x is 2. y is 1.
x is greater than y.
And just for good measure, let's
run it a third time. x is 1.
y is 1.
x is equal to y.
So the code, daresay, works exactly as
you would expect, as you would hope.
But it turns out that
in the world of Python,
we're actually going to get some
other behavior that might actually
have been what you expected weeks ago,
even though C did not behave this way.
In the world of Python and in
the world of strings, a.k.a.
strs, strings actually behave
more like you would expect.
So by that I mean this.
Let me actually go back to this code.
And instead of using integers,
let me go ahead and get rid of--
I could do get_string(), but we said
that that's not really necessary.
So let's just go ahead and
change this to input().
And actually, you know what?
Let's just start fresh.
Let's give myself a string called s
and use the input() function and ask
the user for s.
Let's use another variable called t
just because it comes after s and use
the input() function to get t.
Then let's compare if
s and t are the same.
Now, a couple of weeks
ago, this backfired.
And if I tried to compare two strings
for equality, it did not work.
But if I do if s == t,
print("Same"), else,
let's go ahead and print("Different").
I daresay, in Python, I think this
is going to work as you would expect.
So python of compare.py,
let's type in cat and cat.
And indeed those are the same.
Let me run it again and type
in cat and dog, respectively.
And those are now different.
But in C, we always got "Different,"
"Different," "Different,"
even if I typed the exact same word, be
it cat or dog or high or anything else.
Why, in C, were s and t always
different a couple of weeks ago?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Because it was comparing
the value of the char* with the memory
address.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
In C, string is the same thing as
char*, which is a memory address.
And because we had called
get_string() twice,
even if the human typed the same things,
that was two different chunks of memory
at two different addresses.
So those two char*s were just
naturally always different,
even if the characters at
those addresses were the same.
Python is meant to be higher-level.
It's meant to be a
little more intuitive.
It's meant to be more accessible
to folks who might not necessarily
know or want to understand
those lower-level details.
So in Python, ==, even for strings just
works the way that you might expect.
But in Python, we can
do some other things,
too, even more easily than we could
in C. Let me go back to VS Code here.
Let me close compare.py.
And let's reimplement a
program from C called agree,
which allowed us to prompt the
user for a yes/no question, like,
do you agree to these terms and
conditions or something like that.
So let's do code of agree.py.
And with agree.py, let me go ahead and--
actually, let's go ahead and do this.
Let me also open up a file
that I came with in advance.
And this is called agree.c.
And this is what we
did some weeks ago when
we wanted to check whether or not the
user had agreed to something or not.
So we used the CS50 library,
the standard I/O library,
we had a main() function,
we used get_char().
And then we used == a lot, and
we used the two vertical bars,
which meant logical or.
Is this thing true or
is this thing true?
And if so, printf()
"Agreed" or "Not agreed."
So this worked.
And this is relatively simple.
That's the right way to
do it in C. But notice
it was a little verbose
because we wanted
to handle uppercase and lowercase,
uppercase and lowercase.
So that did start to bloat
the code, admittedly.
So let's try to do the
same thing in Python
and see what we can do the same
or different-- no pun intended.
So let me do this.
In agree.py, why don't we try to
get input from the user as before?
And I will use--
I could use get_string(), but
I'll go ahead and use input().
So s = input("Do you
agree? ") in double quotes.
And then let's go ahead
and check if s == "Y"--
and it's not vertical bar now,
it's actually more readable,
more English-like-- or s == "y," then go
ahead and print out "Agreed" as before,
elsif--
see, I did it there--
elif s == "N" or s == "n,"
go ahead and print out "Not agreed."
So it's almost the same as the C
version, except that I'm using,
literally, O-R instead
of two vertical bars.
So let's run this--
so python of agree.py.
Enter.
Do I agree?
Yes, for little y.
Let's do it again. python
of agree.py, capital Y. Yes.
That works there.
And if I do it again with
lowercase n, and if I do it
with capital N, this
program, too, seems to work.
But what if I do this?
Let me rerun python of agree.py.
Let me type in Yes.
OK, it just ignores me.
Let me run it again.
Let me type in no.
It just ignores me.
Let me try it very
emphatically, YES in all caps.
It just ignores me.
So there's some explosion
of possibilities
that ideally we should handle, right?
This is bad user interface design if
I have-- the user has to type Y or N,
even if yes and no in English are
perfectly reasonable and logical, too.
So how could we handle that?
Well, it turns out in Python, we
can use something like an array,
technically called a list, to maybe
check a bunch of things at once.
So let me do this.
Let me instead say not equality, but
let me use the in keyword in Python
and check if it's in a
collection of possible values.
Let me say if s is in--
and here comes, in square
brackets, just like--
in square brackets, quote unquote,
"y", quote unquote, "yes,"
then we can go ahead
and print out "Agreed,"
elif s in this list of values,
lowercase "n" or lowercase "no,"
then we can print out, for
instance, "Not agreed."
But this is a bit of a
step backwards because now
I'm only handling lowercase.
So let me go into the mix
and maybe add capital "Y"--
wait a minute, then maybe capital
"YES," then maybe "YeS," also--
I mean, weird, but we should
probably support this and "YEs."
I mean, there's a lot of combinations.
So this is not going to end well.
Or it's just going to bloat
my code unnecessarily.
And eventually, for longer words, I'm
surely going to miss capitalization.
So logically, whether it's in
Python or C or any language,
what might be a better design for
this problem of handling Y and Yes,
but who cares about the capitalization?
AUDIENCE: Don't use
capitals or [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: So OK,
so don't use capitals.
You could only support lowercase.
That's fine.
That's kind of a copout, right?
Because now the program's
usability is worse.
AUDIENCE: Convert it.
DAVID MALAN: Oh, we could
convert it to lowercase, yeah.
Though I did hear you say we
could just check the first letter,
I bet that's going to
get us into trouble.
And we probably don't want
to allow any word starting
with Y, any word starting with N, just
because it logically-- especially you
want the lawyers happy, presumably.
You should probably get an explicit
semantically correct word like Y or N
or yes or no.
But, yeah, we can actually go
about converting this to something
maybe smaller.
But how do we go about converting this?
In C, that alone was going to be pretty
darn annoying because we'd have to use
the tolower() function on every
character and compare it for equality.
It just feels like that's a bit of work.
But in Python, you're going to
get more functionality for free.
So there might very well
be a function, like in C,
called tolower() or toupper().
But the weird thing about
C, perhaps in retrospect,
is that those functions just kind
of worked on the honor system.
tolower() and toupper() just trusted
that you would pass them an input,
an argument, that is, in fact, a char.
In Python, and in a lot of
other higher-level languages,
they introduced this notion of
Object-Oriented Programming,
which is commonly described as OOP.
And in the world of
Object-Oriented Programming,
your values can not
only-- your variables,
for instance, and your data
types can not only have values.
They can also have
functionality built into them.
So if you have a data
type like a string,
frankly, it just makes
good sense that strings
should be uppercaseable,
lowercaseable, capitalizable,
and any number of other
operations on strings.
So in the world of object-oriented
programming functions,
like toupper() and tolower() and
isupper() and islower() are not just
in some random library that you can use.
They're built into the
strings themselves.
And what this means is that in
the world of strings in Python,
here, for instance, is the URL of the
documentation for all of the functions,
otherwise known as methods,
that come with strings.
So you don't go check
for a C-type library
like we did in C. You
check the actual data
type, the documentation,
therefore, and you
will see in Python's own
documentation what functions, a.k.a.
methods, come with strings.
So a method is just a function.
But it's a function that comes
with some data type, like a string.
So let me propose that we do this.
In the world of
object-oriented programming,
we can come back to agree.py.
And we can actually improve
the program by getting
rid of this crazy long list,
which I wasn't even done with,
and just canonicalize
everything as lowercase.
So let's just check for lowercase
y and lowercase yes, lowercase
n, lowercase no, and that's it.
But to your suggestion,
let's force everything
that the user types into
lowercase, not because we want
to permanently change their input--
we can throw the value
away thereafter-- but
because we want to more
easily logically compare it
for membership in this list of values.
So one way to do this would be
to literally do s = s.lower().
So here's the difference.
In the world of C, we
would have done this--
tolower and pass in the value s.
But in the world of Python, and, in
general, object-oriented programming--
Java is another language
that does this--
if s is a string, a.k.a.
str, therefore, s is actually
what's known in Python as an object.
An object can not only have values
or attributes inside of them,
but also functionality built in.
And just like in C, with a struct, if
you want to go inside of something,
you use the dot operator.
And inside of this string, I claim,
is a function, a.k.a., method,
called lower().
Long story short, the only
takeaway, if this is a bit abstract,
is that instead of doing lower
and then, in parentheses,
s, in the world of object-oriented
programming, you kind of flip that
and you do s dot name of the method, and
then open paren and close paren if you
don't need to pass in any arguments.
So this actually achieves the same.
So let me go ahead and rerun agree.py,
and let me type in lowercase y.
That works.
Let me run it again,
type in lowercase yes.
That works let me run it again,
type in capital Y. That works.
Let me type in capital
YES, all capital--
all uppercase YES.
That too works.
Let me try no.
Let me try no in lowercase.
And all of these permutations
now actually work
because I'm forcing it to lowercase.
But even more interestingly, in Python,
if you're sort of becoming a languages
person, if you have a variable s that
is being set the return value of input()
function, and then you're immediately
going about changing it to lowercase,
you can also chain method calls together
in something like Python by doing this.
We can get rid of this line altogether,
and then I can just do this, .lower.
And so whatever the return value of
input() is, it's going to be a str.
Whatever the human types
in, you can then immediately
force it to lowercase and then assign
the whole value to this variable
called s.
You don't actually have to wait
around and do it on a separate line
altogether.
Questions, then, on any of this?
No?
All right.
Let me do one other that's reminiscent
of something we did in the past.
Let me go into VS Code
here, clear my terminal.
Let's close both the C and
the Python version of agree.
And let's create a program called
uppercase.py, whose purpose in life
is to actually uppercase a whole string.
In the world of C, we had to do this
character by character by character.
And that's fine.
I'm going to go ahead
and do it similarly here
in Python, whereby I want to
convert it character by character.
But unfortunately, before
I can do that, I actually
need some way of looping in Python,
which we actually haven't seen yet.
So we need one more
set of building blocks.
And, in fact, if we were to
consult the Python documentation,
we'd see this and much more.
So, in fact, here's a list of all of
the functions that come with Python.
And it's actually not
that long of a list,
because so much of the functionality
of Python is built into data types,
like strings and integers
and floats and more.
Here is the canonical source of
truth for Python documentation.
So as opposed to using
the CS50 manual for C,
which is meant to be a
simplified version of publicly
available documentation,
we'll generally, for Python,
point you to the official docs.
I will disclaim they're not really
written for introductory students.
And they'll generally leave some
detail off and use arcane language.
But at this point in
the term, even if it
might be a little
frustrating at first, it's
good to see documentation
in the real world
because that's what you're
going to have after the course.
And so you'll get used to it
through practice over time.
But with loops, let's
introduce one other feature
that we can compare to Scratch.
Here, for instance, in Scratch, is how
we might have repeated something three
times, like meowing on the screen.
In C, there were a bunch
of ways to do this.
And the clunkiest was maybe
to do it with a while loop
where we declare a variable
called i, set it equal to 0,
and then, iteratively, increment i
again and again until it exceeds--
until it equals 3, each
time printing out "meow."
In Python, we can do this in
a few different ways as well.
The nearest translation of C
into Python is perhaps this.
It's almost the same, and
logically, it really is the same,
but you don't specify int, and
you don't have a semicolon.
You don't have curly braces.
But you do have a colon.
You don't use printf().
You use print().
And you can't use i++, but
you still can use i += 1.
So logically, exactly
the same idea as in C--
It's just a little tighter.
I mean, it's a little easier to read,
even though it's very mechanical,
if you will.
You're defining all of these.
You're defining this variable
and changing it incrementally.
Well, recall that in C, we could also
use a for loop, which at first glance
was probably more cryptic
than a while loop.
But odds are by now, you're
more comfortable or more
in the habit of using
loops-- same exact idea.
In Python, though, we
might do it like this.
We've seen how, in square brackets, you
can have lists of values, like y, yes,
and so forth.
Well, let's just do the
same thing with numbers.
So if you want Python to do
something three times, give it
a list of three values, like 0, 1,
2, and then print out "hello, world"
that many times.
Now, this is correct,
but it's bad design.
Even if you've never seen Python
before, extrapolate mentally from this.
Why is this probably not the right way
or the best way to do this looping?
AUDIENCE: Because if you
wanted to do it more than,
like, three times, you
have to [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
If you want to do it four times,
five times, 50 times, 100 times,
I mean, surely, there's a better way
than enumerating all of these values.
And there is.
In fact, in Python, there's a function
called range() that actually returns
to you very efficiently
a range of values.
And by default, it hands you the
number 0 and then 1 and then 2.
And if you want more than that, you just
change the argument to range() to be
how many values do you want.
So if you passed in range
of 50, you would get back 0
through 49, which effectively allows
you to do something 50 times in total.
So this is perhaps the most
Pythonic way, so to speak.
And this is actually a term of art.
Pythonic isn't necessarily
the only way to do something.
But it's the way to do something based
on consensus in the Python community.
So it's pretty common to do this.
But there's some curiosity here.
Notice I'm declaring a variable i,
but I'm never actually using it.
In fact, I don't even
increment it because that's
sort of happening automatically.
Well, what's really happening
here is automatically in Python,
on every iteration of this loop, Python
is assigning i to the next value.
So initially, i is 0.
Then it goes through an iteration.
Then i is 1.
Then i is 2.
And then that's it if you
only asked for three values.
But there's this other technique
in Python, just so you know,
whereby if you're the programmer,
and you know you don't actually
care about the name
of this variable, you
can actually change it to an underscore,
which has no functional effect per se.
It just signals to the reader, your
colleague, your teaching fellow,
that it's a variable, and you need
it in order to achieve a for loop.
But you don't care about
the name of the variable
because you're not going to
use it explicitly anywhere.
So that might be an even more
Pythonic way of doing things.
But if you're more
comfortable seeing the i
and using the variable more
explicitly, that's fine.
Underscore does not
mean anything special.
It's just a valid character
for a variable name.
So this is convention, nothing
more technical than that.
What about a forever loop in
Scratch, like literally meow forever.
Well, over here, we can just use
in C, while(true) printf() "meow,"
again and again and again.
In Python, it's almost the same.
You still get rid of the curly braces.
You add the colon.
You get rid of the semicolon.
But there's a subtlety.
What else is different here?
Yeah?
So True is uppercase.
Why?
Who knows?
The world decided that in
Python, True is capitalized
and False is capitalized.
In many other languages,
daresay most, they are not.
It's just a difference that you
have to keep in mind or remember.
All right.
So now that we have looping constructs,
let me go back to my code here.
And recall that I proposed that we
re-implement a program like uppercase,
force an entire string to uppercase.
And in C, we would have done this with a
for loop, iterating from left to right.
But what's nice in Python
frankly, is that it's a lot easier
to loop in Python than it is
in C because you can loop over
anything that is iterable.
A string is iterable in the sense
that you can iterate over it
from left to right.
So what do I mean by this?
Well, let me go ahead
and, in uppercase.py,
let's first prompt the user for a
variable called before and set that
equal to the return value of input(),
giving them a prompt of "Before,"
colon.
Then let's go ahead, as we did weeks
ago, and print out just the word
"After," just to make clear to the user
what is actually going to be printed.
Then let me go ahead and
specify the following loop--
for-- and previously you saw me
use i, but because I'm dealing with
characters, I'm actually
going to do this instead--
for c in before, colon,
print out c.upper.
And that's it.
Now, this is a little
flawed, I will concede.
But let me run this--
python of uppercase.py.
Let's type in something like
cat, C-A-T in all lowercase.
Enter.
All right.
Well, you see "After," and I
did get it right in the sense
that it is capital C, capital A,
capital T, but it looks a little stupid.
And in order to fix
this, we actually need
to introduce something that's
called named parameters.
So let me actually go ahead and
propose that we can fix this problem
by actually passing in another
argument to the print() function.
And this is a little different
syntactically from C.
But if I go back to VS
Code here, it turns out
that there's two
aesthetic problems here.
One, I did not want the new line
automatically inserted after "After."
Why?
Because, just like in week 1,
I want them to line up nicely--
or in week 2.
And I don't want a new
line after C-A-T. So even
though at first glance
a moment-- a bit ago,
it might have seemed nice that Python
just does the backslash n for you,
it can backfire if you don't
actually want a new line every time.
So the syntax is going
to look a little weird.
But in Python, with
the print() function,
if you want to change the character
that's automatically used at the end
of every line, you can literally pass in
a second argument called end and set it
equal to something else.
So if you want to set it
equal to something else,
and that something else is
nothing, "", then that's fine.
You can actually specify end="".
Down here, too, if you want to specify
that at the end of every one of these
characters should be nothing,
I can specify end="".
What this implies is that
by default in Python,
the default value of this end parameter
is actually always backslash n.
So if you want to override
it and take that away,
you just literally
change it to "" instead.
And now if I clear my-- if I
rerun this program, uppercase.py,
type in cat in all
lowercase, now you'll see--
oh, two minor bugs here.
One was just stupid.
I had one too many spaces here.
But you'll notice that I didn't
move the cursor to the next line
after CAT was printed in all uppercase.
And that we can fix by
just printing nothing.
It turns out when you don't
pass print() an argument at all,
it automatically gives you just
the line ending, nothing else.
So I think this will move
the cursor as expected.
So let me clear it now,
run python of uppercase.py
and hit Enter, type in cat in all
lowercase, cross my fingers this time,
and now I have indeed capitalized
this, character by character
by character, just like we did in C.
But honestly, this, too,
not really necessary--
it turns out I don't need
to loop over a whole string,
because strings themselves
come with methods.
And if you were to visit the
documentation for strings,
you would see that indeed, upper is a
method that comes with every string,
and you don't need to call it
on every character individually.
I could instead get rid of all
of this and just print out--
for instance, I can just
print out before.upper.
And the upper() function that comes
with strings will automatically apply it
to every character they're in and,
I think, achieve the same result.
So let me go ahead and try this again--
python of uppercase.py, type in cat,
enter, and indeed, it
works exactly the same way.
Let me take this one step further.
Let me go ahead and combine
a couple of ideas now here.
Let me go ahead and, for instance, let
me get rid of this last print() line.
Let me change my logic to be after
equals the return value of this.
And now I can use one of those f strings
and plug this in maybe here, After.
And I can get rid of
the new line ending.
I can specify this is an f string.
So I'm just changing
this around a little bit
logically so that now I have
a variable called after that
is the uppercase version of before.
And now, if I do python of uppercase.py,
type in cat, that too now works.
And if I-- actually let
me add a space there,
if I run python of uppercase.py,
type in cat, that too now works.
And lastly here, if you
don't want to bother
creating another variable
like this, you can even
put short bits of code inside
of these format strings.
So I, for instance, could go
in here into these curly braces
and not just put a variable name.
I can actually put Python code inside of
the curly braces, inside of my string.
And so now if I run Python
of uppercase.py, type in cat,
even that too now works.
Now, which one is the best?
This is kind of reasonable to put
the bit of code inside of the string.
I would not start writing long
lines of code inside of curly braces
that start to wrap, no
less, because then it's
just going to be a matter of bad style.
But this, again, is to say that
there's a bunch of different ways
to solve each of these problems.
And so up until now, we've
generally seen not named parameters.
end is the first parameter we've ever
seen that has a name, literally, end.
Up until now in C and up
until a moment ago in Python,
we've always been assuming that
our parameters are positional.
What matters is the order in which you
specify them, not necessarily something
else.
Whew.
OK, that was a lot.
Any questions about any of this here?
No?
All right.
It feels like a lot.
Let's take our 10-minute break here.
Fruit roll-ups are now served.
We'll be back in 10.
All right.
We are back.
And recall that as we left off,
we had just introduced loops.
And we'd seen a bunch of
different ways by which
we could get, say, a cat to meow.
Let's actually translate
that to some code
and start to make sense of some of
the programs with which we began,
like creating our own functions,
as we did for the speller example
at the very beginning, and actually
do this a little more methodically.
So let me go over to VS Code here.
Let me go ahead and create a program
called meow.py, instead of meow.c
as in the past.
And suffice it to say if you want
to implement the idea of a cat,
we can do better than just saying
print("meow"), print("meow"),
print("meow").
This, of course, would work.
This is correct if the goal is to
get the thing to meow three times.
But when I run python of meow.py,
it's going to work as expected,
but this is just not good design, right?
We should minimally be using a loop.
So let me propose that we improve this
per the building blocks we've seen.
And I could say something
like, for i in range(3),
go ahead and print out
now, quote unquote, "meow."
So this is better in the sense that
it still prints meow, meow, meow.
But if I want to change this to a
dog and change the meow to a woof
or something like that, I can
change it in one place and not three
different places-- so just,
in general, better design.
But what if now, much
like in Scratch and in C,
I wanted to create my own meow()
function which did not come with either
of those languages as well.
Well, as a teaser at
the start of class, we
saw that you can define
your own functions
with this keyword def, which is a
little bit different from how C does it.
But let me go ahead and do this indeed
in Python and define my own function
meow().
So let me go ahead and do def meow(),
and then, inside of that function,
I'm just going to literally do for now,
quote unquote, "meow" with print().
And now down here, notice, I can
actually go ahead and just call meow().
And I can go ahead and call
meow(), and I can call meow().
And this is not the best
design at the moment.
But Python does not constrain me to
have to implement a main() function,
as we've seen thus far.
But I can define my own
helper functions, if you will,
like a helper function called meow().
So let me go ahead and just run
this for demonstration's sake
and run python of meow.py.
That does seem to work.
But this is not good design.
And let me go ahead and actually
do this-- for i in range(3),
now let me call the meow() function.
And this, too, should work.
If I do python of meow.py,
there we have meow, meow, meow.
But I very deliberately
did something clever here.
I defined meow at the top of my file.
But that's not the best
practice because as in C,
when someone opens the file for
the first time, whether you,
a TF, a TA, a colleague, you'd like
to see the main part of the program
at the top of the file, just because
it's easier mentally to dive right in
and know what this file is doing.
So let me go ahead and practice what
I'm preaching and put the main part
of my code, even if there's
no main() function per se,
at the top of this file.
So now I have the loop at the top.
I'm calling meow() on line 2, and
I'm defining meow() on lines 5 and 6.
Well, instinctively, you can
perhaps see where this is going.
If I run Python of
meow.py and hit Enter,
there's one of those tracebacks
that's tracing my error.
And here, my error is
apparently on line 2 in meow.py.
And you'll notice that, huh,
the name 'meow' is not defined.
And so previously, we saw a different
type of error, a value error.
Here we're seeing a
name error in the sense
that Python does not recognize
the name of this function.
And intuitively, why might that be,
even if the error is a little cryptic?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] top to bottom.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, Python, too-- as
fancier as it seems to be than C,
it still takes things pretty literally,
top to bottom, left to right.
So if you define meow() on line
5, you can't use it on line 2.
OK, so I could undo this,
and I could flip the order.
But let me just stipulate that as
soon as we have a bunch of functions,
it's probably naive to assume I can just
keep putting my functions above, above,
above, above.
And honestly, that's going to move
all of my main code, so to speak,
to the bottom of the file, which is sort
of counterproductive or less obvious.
So it turns out in Python, even though
you don't need a main() function,
it's actually quite common
to define one nonetheless.
So what I could do to
solve this problem is this.
Let me go ahead and define a function
called main() that takes no arguments,
in this case.
Let me indent that same code beneath it.
And now let me keep meow()
defined at the bottom of my file.
So if we read this literally, on line 1,
I'm defining a function called main().
And it will do what is
prescribed on lines 2 and 3.
On line 6, I'm defining
a function called meow(),
and it will do what's prescribed on
line 7-- so fairly straightforward,
even though the keyword def
is, of course, new today.
If I run, though,
python of meow.py, you'd
like to think I'll see three meows.
But I see nothing.
I don't see an error, but I see nothing.
Why?
Intuitively, what explains
the lack of behavior?
I didn't call main().
So this is the thing even though it's
not required in Python to have a main()
function, but it is conventional in
Python to have a main() function,
you have to call the function yourself.
It doesn't get magically
called as it does in C.
So this might seem a little stupid--
and that's fine-- but it is
the convention in Python.
Generally, the very last line of your
file might just be to literally this,
call main(), because this satisfies
the constraint that main() is defined
on line 1 meow() is defined on line 6,
but we don't call anything until line
10.
So line 10 says call main().
So that means execute this code.
Line 3 says call meow(),
which means execute this code.
So now it all works because the
last thing I'm doing is call main().
You can think of C as just
kind of secretly having
this line there for you the whole time.
But now that we have our own functions,
notice that we can enhance this
implementation of meow() to maybe
be parameterized and take actually
an argument itself.
So let me make a tweak here.
Just like in C, and
just like in Scratch,
I can actually let meow() meow
a specific number of times.
So let me do this.
Wouldn't it be nice, instead
of having my loop in main(),
to instead just distill main() into
a single line of code and just pass
in the number of times you
want the thing to meow?
What I could do in meow() here
is I have to give it a parameter.
And I could call it anything I want.
I'm going to call it n for
number, which seems fine.
And then, in the meow()
function, I could do this--
for i in range of, not 3, but n now,
I can tell range() to give me a range
that is of variable
length based on what n is.
And then I indent the
print() below the loop now.
And this should now
do what I expect, too.
Let me run python of meow.py.
Enter.
And there's 3.
But if I change the 3 to a 5 and
rerun this, python of meow.py,
now I'm getting five meows.
So we've just seen a third
way how, in Python, now we
can implement the idea of meowing
as its own abstracted function.
And I can assume now that meow() exists.
I can now treat it as out
of sight, out of mind.
It's an abstraction.
And frankly, I could even put it into
a library, import it from a file,
like we've done with CS50, and make
it usable by other people as well.
So the takeaway here, really,
though, is that in Python, you
can, similarly to C,
define your own functions.
But you should understand
the slight differences
as to what gets called
automatically for you.
All right.
Other differences or
similarities with C?
Well, recall that in C,
truncation was an issue.
Truncation is whereby if you, for
instance, divide an int by an int,
and it's a fractional answer,
everything after the decimal point
gets truncated by default because
an int divided by an int in C
gives you an int.
And if you can't fit the remainder in
that integer, everything at the decimal
gets cut off.
So what does this mean?
Well, let me actually
go back to VS Code here.
Let me go ahead and open,
say, calculator.py again,
and let's change up what
the calculator now does.
Let me do this.
Let me define a variable called x,
set it equal to the input() function,
prompting the user for x.
Let me ask the user for y, let
me not repeat past mistakes,
and let me proactively
convert both of these to ints.
And I'll do it in one pretty one-liner
here so that I definitely get x and y.
And on the honor system,
I just won't type cat.
I won't type dog, even
though this program is not
really complete without error checking.
Now, let me go ahead and
declare a third variable,
z = x / y, and now let's just
go ahead and print out z.
I don't need a format code.
I don't need an f string.
If all you want to do is print a
variable, print() is very flexible.
You can just say
print(z), in parentheses.
Let me run python of
calculator.py, hit Enter.
Let's type in 1 for x, 3 for y.
I left out a space there.
And oh, interesting.
What seems to have happened here?
Let me fix my spacing and rerun this
again-- python of calculator.py-- so 1,
3.
What did not happen?
AUDIENCE: It doesn't truncate.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So it didn't truncate.
So Python is a little
smarter when it comes
to converting one value to another.
So an integer divided by
an integer, if it ends up
giving you this fractional
component, not to worry now,
you'll get back what is
effectively a float in Python here.
Well, what else do we want to
be mindful of in, say, Python?
Well, recall that in C, we had this
issue of floating point and precision
whereby if you want to represent
a number, like 1/3, and on a piece
of paper, it's, like,
0.3 with a line over it
because the 3 infinitely repeats--
but we saw a problem in C
last time when we actually
played around with some value.
So, for instance, let me
go back to VS Code here.
And this is going to be the ugliest
syntax I do think we see today.
But there was a way in C, using %f,
to show more than the default number
of digits after the decimal point,
to see more significant digits.
In Python, there's something similar.
It just looks very weird.
And the way you do it in Python is this.
You specify that you want an
f string, a format string.
And I'm just going to start
and finish my thought first--
f before "".
If you want to print out z, you
could literally just do this.
And so this is just an f string,
but you're interpolating z.
So it doesn't do anything more than it
did a moment ago when I literally just
passed in z.
But as soon as you have
an f string, you can
configure the variable to print
out to a specific number of digits.
So if you actually want to print
out z to, say, 50 decimal points,
just to see a lot, you can
use crazy syntax like this.
So it's just using the curly
braces, as I introduced before.
But you then use a dot
after a colon, and then
you specify the number of digits that
you want and then an f to make clear
it's a float.
Honestly, I google this all the time
when I don't remember the syntax.
But the point is the
functionality exists.
All right.
Let me go down here and rerun
python of calculator.py.
And unfortunately, if I divide 1 by
3, not all of my problems are solved.
Floating point precision
is still a thing.
So be mindful of the fact that
there are these limitations
in the world of Python.
Floating point precision remains.
If you want to do even better
than that, though, there
exist a lot more libraries,
third-party libraries,
that can give you much greater
precision for scientific purposes,
financial purposes, or the like.
But what about another problem
from C, integer overflow?
If you just count to high, recall
that you might accidentally
overflow the capacity of an
integer and end up going back to 0,
or worse, going negative altogether.
In Python, this problem does not exist.
In Python, when you
have an integer, a.k.a.
int, even though we haven't
needed to use the keyword int,
it will grow and grow and grow.
And Python will reserve more and more
memory for that integer to fit it.
So it is not a fixed number of bits.
So floating point imprecision
is still a problem.
Integer overflow-- not a problem
in the latest versions of Python,
so a difference worth knowing.
But what about other features of
Python that we didn't have in C?
Well, let's actually revisit one of
those tracebacks, one of those errors
I ran into earlier, to see how
we might actually solve it.
So let me go back to VS Code here.
And just for fun, let
me go ahead and do this.
Let me clear my terminal.
And let me change my calculator to
actually have a get_int() function.
We've seen how to define
our own functions.
Let me not bother with the CS50 library.
Let me just invent my own
get_int() function as follows.
So def get_int(), and just
like the CS50 function,
I'm going to have get int take a prompt,
a string to show the user to ask them
for an integer.
And now I'm going to go ahead and
return the return value of input(),
passing that same prompt to
input()-- because input(),
just like get_string(), shows
the user a string of text.
But I do want to convert
this thing here to an int.
So this is just a one-liner, really,
of an implementation of get_int().
So this is kind of like what CS50 did
in its Python library, but not quite.
Why?
Because there's a problem with it.
So let me do this.
Let me define a main()
function just by convention.
Let me use this implementation of
get_int() to ask the user for x.
Let me use this get_int()
function to prompt the user for y.
And then let me do something
simple like print out x + y.
And then, very last thing,
I have to call main().
And this is a minor point,
but I'm deliberately
putting multiple blank
lines between my functions.
This too is Pythonic.
It's a matter of style. style50
will help you with this.
It's just meant for larger files to
really make your functions stand out
and be a little more separated
visually from others.
All right.
Let me go ahead and run
Python of calculator.py.
Enter.
Let me type in 1.
Let me type in 3.
And that actually works.
1 plus 3 is 4.
Let me do the more obvious.
1 plus 2 gives me 3.
So the calculator is in fact working
until such time as I, the human,
don't cooperate and type in
something like cat for x.
Then we get that same
traceback as before,
but I'm seeing it now in this file.
And let me zoom in on my
terminal just to make clear.
We don't need to see
the old history there.
Let me type in cat, Enter, and
you'll see the same traceback.
And you'll see that, OK,
here's where now there's
multiple functions involved.
So what's going on?
The first problem is
at line 12 in main().
But that's not actually the problem
because main() calls my get_int()
function.
So on line 6 of calculator.py,
this is really the issue--
so, again, it's tracing everything that
just happened from top to bottom here--
and value error-- invalid
literal for int() with base 10,
'cat,' which is to say, like before,
cat is not an integer in base 10 or any
other base.
It just cannot be
converted to an integer.
So how do you fix this, or, really,
how does the CS50 library fix this?
You won't have to write
much code like this.
But it turns out that Python
supports what are called exceptions.
And generally, an
exception is a better way
of handling certain types of
errors because in C, recall
that the only way we
could really handle errors
is by having functions
return special values.
malloc() could return null,
which means it ran out of memory.
Something went wrong.
Some functions we wrote in C
could return 1, could return 2,
could return negative 1.
Recall that we could write our
own functions that return values
to indicate something went wrong.
But the problem in C is that if
you're stealing certain values,
be it null or 1 or 2 or 3, your function
can never return null or 1 or 2 or 3
as actual values.
Why?
Because other people are going
to interpret them as errors.
So you kind of have to use up some
of your possible return values
in a language like C and treat
them specially as errors.
In Python and other languages--
Java and others-- you
don't have to do that.
You can instead have more out of band
error handling, known as exceptions.
And that's what's happening here.
When I run calculator.py and I
type in cat, what I'm seeing here
is actually an exception.
It's something exceptional,
but not in a good way.
This exception means this
was not supposed to happen.
The type of exception happens
to be called a value error.
And within the world of Python, there's
this whole taxonomy, that is to say,
a whole list of possible exceptions.
ValueError is one of the most common.
We saw another one before,
name error, when I said
meow when Python didn't
know what meow meant.
So this is just an
example of an exception.
But what this means is that there is
a way for me to try to handle this
myself.
So I'm actually going
to go ahead and do this.
Instead of get_int() simply blindly
returning the integer conversion
of whatever input the user gives me,
I'm going to instead literally try to do
this instead.
So it's kind of a aptly named phrase.
It literally means that.
Please try to do this, except
if something goes wrong,
except if there is a
ValueError, in which case
I want Python to do
something else, for instance,
quote unquote, "Not an integer."
So what does this mean?
It's a little weird, the syntax.
But in the get_int() function, Python
will first try to do the following.
It will try to get an
input from the user.
It will try to convert it to an integer.
And it will try to return it.
But if one of those operations fails,
namely the integer step in this case,
then an exception could happen.
And you might get what's
called a ValueError.
Why?
Because the documentation
tells you that might happen.
Or, in my case, I
experienced it firsthand,
and now I want to catch this
kind of exception in my own code.
So if there is a
ValueError, I'm not going
to see that crazy traceback anymore.
I'm instead going to see, quote
unquote, "Not an integer."
But what the CS50 library
does for you technically is it
lets you try again and again and again.
Recall in the past, if I
type in cat and dog and bird,
it's just going to keep
asking me again and again
until I actually give it an int.
So that kind of implies that we really
need a loop inside of this function.
And the easiest way to
do something forever
is to loop while true, just like
in C, but a capital T in Python.
And what I'm going to do now is
implement a better version of get_int()
here because what's it going to do?
It is going to try-- it's
going to do this forever.
It's going to try to get an input,
convert it to an int, and return it.
And just like break
breaks you out of a loop,
return also breaks you out
of a loop as well, right?
Because once you've returned, there's no
more need for this function to execute.
So long story short, you won't have
to write much code like this yourself.
But this is essentially what the CS50
library is doing when it implements
the Python version of get_int().
So what happens now?
If I run python of calculator.py,
and I type in cat, I get yelled at,
but I'm prompted again
because of the loop.
I type in dog.
I'm yelled at, but I'm prompted again.
I type in bird, yelled at,
but I'm prompted again.
If I type in 1, then I
type in 2, now it proceeds
because it tried and succeeded this
time as opposed to trying and failing
last time.
And technically, the CS50
library doesn't actually
yell at you with "Not an integer."
So technically, if you want to
handle the error, that is to say,
catch the exception, you can
actually just say, oh, pass,
and it will just silently
try again and again.
So let me go ahead and run this. python
of calculator.py works almost the same.
But notice now it works
just like the C version.
It doesn't yell at you, but it does
prompt you again and again and again.
But I'll do 1 and 2, and
that now is satisfied.
So that then is exceptions
which you'll encounter,
but you yourself won't have to
write much code along those lines.
Well, what else can we now do?
Well, let's revisit something
like this for Mario,
recall, whereby we had this
two-dimensional world with things
in the way for Mario, like
this column of three bricks.
Let me actually play around now
for a moment with some loops
just to see how there's different
ways that might actually
resonate with you just in terms of the
simplicity of some of these things.
Let me go ahead and create
a program called mario.py.
And suppose that I want to
print a column of three bricks.
It kind of doesn't get any
easier than this in Python.
So for i in range(3), just go
ahead and print out a single hash--
done.
That then is what we took us
more lines of code in the past.
But if I run mario.py, that
there gets the job done.
I could change the i to an
underscore, but it's not
bad to remind myself that i is
what's really doing my counting.
Well, what else could we do beyond this?
Well, recall that in the world of
Mario, we prompted the user, actually,
for a specific height.
We didn't just always hardcode 3.
So I could actually do
something like this.
Let me actually open up from today's
code that I came with in advance
and pull up this C version of Mario.
So this was from some
time ago, in week 1.
And this is how we
implemented a loop that
ensures that we get a positive integer
from the user by just doing while
and is not positive, and
then we use this for loop
to actually print out that many hashes.
Now, in Python, it's actually
going to be pretty similar,
except for the fact that in
Python, there is no do while loop.
But recall that a do
while loop was useful
because it means you can get the user to
try something and then maybe try again,
maybe try again, maybe try again.
So it's really good for user input.
So let's actually do this.
Let me borrow the CS50's
library get_int() function,
just so we don't have to re-implement
that ourselves again and again.
Let me, in Python, do
this the Pythonic way.
In Python, if you want to prompt the
user to do something again and again
and again, potentially, you
deliberately, by convention,
induce an infinite loop.
You just get yourself
into an infinite loop.
But the goal is going to be try
something, try something, try
something, and as soon as you have
what you want, break out of the loop
instead.
So we're implementing the idea
of a do while loop ourselves.
So I'm going to do this. n,
for number, equals get_int(),
and let's ask the user for a height.
Then let's just check.
If n is greater than 0, you know what?
Break.
We've got the value we need.
And if not, it's just going to
implicitly keep looping again and again
and again.
So in Python, this is
to say-- super common--
to deliberately induce an infinite
loop and break out of it when you have
what you want.
All right?
Now I can just do the same kind of
code as before. for i in range not of--
rage sometimes-- for i
in range, not 3, but n,
now I can go ahead and print out--
oops-- a hash like this.
If I open my terminal window, it's
going to work almost the same,
but now mario is going to
prompt me for the height.
So I could type in 3,
or I could type in 4,
or I could be uncooperative and
type in 0 or negative 1 or even cat.
And because I'm using the
CS50 library, cat is ignored.
Because I'm using my while
loop and breaking out
of it only when n is positive, I'm
also ignoring the 0 and the negative 1.
So, again, this would be a Pythonic way
of implementing this particular idea.
If I want to maybe enhance this a
bit further, let me propose that,
for instance, we consider something
like the two-dimensional version--
or the horizontal
version of this instead.
So recall that some time
ago, we printed out,
like, four question marks
in the sky that might have
looked a little something like this.
Now, the very mechanical way
to do this would be as follows.
Let me close my C code.
Let me clear my terminal.
And let me just delete my
old mario version here.
And let's just do this-- for
i in range(4), let's go ahead
and print out a question
mark, all right?
I'm going to run python
of mario.py, enter,
and, ugh, it's still a
column instead of a row.
But what's the fix here, perhaps?
What's the fix?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: The end equals [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
We can use that named
parameter and say end=""
to just suppress the
default backslash n.
But let's give ourselves one
at the very end of the loop
just to move the cursor correctly.
So now if I run python
of mario.py, now it
looks like what it might
have in the sky here.
But it turns out Python has some neat
features, too, more syntactic sugar,
if you will, for doing
things a little more easily.
It turns out in Python,
you could also do this.
You could just say print("?" * 4).
And just like + means
concatenation, * here means,
really, multiply the string by
itself that many times, so sort
of automatically
concatenate it with itself.
So if I run python of
mario.py, this too works-- so,
again, just some features of
Python that make it a little more
pleasant to use so you don't always
have to slog through implementing
a loop or something along those lines.
Well, what about something
more two-dimensional,
like in the world of this brick here?
Well, in the context of
this sort of grid of bricks,
we might do something
like this in VS Code.
Let me go back to mario.py, and let
me do a 3-by-3 grid for that block,
like we did in week 1.
So for i in range(3)--
I can nest loops, just like
in C-- for j in range(3),
I can then print out a hash here.
And then let's leave this alone even
though it's not quite right yet.
Let's do python of mario.py.
OK, it's, like, nine bricks all in
a column, which so your mind might
wander to the end parameter again.
So, yeah, let's fix this-- end="",
but at the end of that loop,
let's just print out a new line.
So this logically is the same
as it was in C But in this case,
I'm now doing it in Python, just
a little more easily, without i++,
without a conditional, I'm just relying
on this for i in syntax using range().
I can tighten this up further, frankly.
If I already have the outer loop,
I could do something like this.
I could print out a single hash times 3.
And now if I run python of
mario.py, that works, too.
So I can combine these ideas
in interesting ways as well.
The goal is simply to seed you
with some of these building blocks.
All right.
How about code that was maybe a
little more logical in nature?
Well, in Python, we indeed have some
other features as well, namely lists.
And lists are denoted by
those square brackets,
reminiscent of the world of arrays.
But in Python, what's
really nice about lists
is that their memory is
automatically handled for you.
An array is about having
values contiguously in memory.
In Python, a list is
more like a linked list.
It will allocate memory for you
and grow and shrink these things.
And you do not have to
know about pointers.
You do not have to know about nodes.
You do not have to implement
linked lists yourself.
You just get list as a
data type in Python itself.
Here, for instance, is some of the
documentation for lists specifically.
And in particular, lists
also, like strings, or strs,
have methods, functions
that come with them,
that just make it easy
to do certain things.
So, for instance, if I wanted to maybe
do something like taking averages
of scores, like we did some time ago,
we can do that using a combination
of lists and the function called
len(), which I alluded to earlier,
which will tell you
the length of a list.
Now, how might we do this?
Well, if we read the
documentation for len(),
it turns out there's other functions
there too that might be helpful.
So let me go back to VS Code here.
Let me close mario.py.
And let me open a file called
scores.py, reminiscent of something
we did weeks ago, too.
Let me go ahead and, just
for demonstration's sake,
give myself a variable called
scores that has my three test scores
or whatnot from weeks ago.
So I'm using square brackets, not curly
braces, as in C. This is a linked list,
or a list in Python.
And let me get the
average of these values.
Well, I could do this-- average
=, and it turns out in Python,
you just get a lot of
functionality for free.
And those functions sometimes
take not single arguments,
but lists as their arguments.
So, for instance, I can use Python's
built-in sum() function and pass
in those scores.
I can then divide that sum by the
length of the scores list as well.
So length of a list just tells
you how many things are in it.
So this is like doing magically 72 plus
73 plus 33, all divided by 3 in total.
If I want to now do the math
out, I can print the result.
So I can print out, using an f string
and maybe some prefix text here.
Let's print out that average here.
So let me do python of
scores.py, enter, and there
is the average, slightly imprecisely.
But at that point, I'm
not doing so well anyway.
So that's fine.
So at this point, we've seen that we
have sort of more functionality than C.
In C, how would we have
computed the average weeks ago?
I mean, we literally created a variable.
We then had a loop.
We iterated over the array.
We added things together.
It was just so much more work.
It's nice when you have a language that
comes with functions, among them len(),
among them sum(), that just
does more of this for you.
But suppose you actually want
to get the scores from the user.
In C, we used an array, and
in C, we used get_int().
We can do something a
little similar here.
Let me propose that instead of
hardcoding those three values,
let me do this. from
cs50 import get_int().
Now let me give myself an empty
list by just saying scores
equals open bracket, closed bracket.
And unlike C, where you just can't do
this-- you can't say give me an array
and I'll figure out the length
later, unless you resort
to pointers and memory
management or the like, in Python
you can absolutely give yourself
an initially empty list.
Now let's do this. for
i in range(3), let's
prompt the human for three test scores.
So the first score will be
the return value of get_int(),
prompting the user for their score.
And now, if I want to add this
score to that otherwise empty list,
here's where methods
come into play, functions
that come with objects, like lists.
I can do scores, plural--
because that's the name of my
variable from line 3-- .append,
and I can append that score.
So if we read the documentation
for lists in Python,
you will see that lists come with a
function, a method called append(),
which literally just tacks a value onto
the end, tacks a value onto the end,
like all of that annoying code we
would have written in C to iterate with
pointer and pointer and pointer
to the end of the list, append it,
malloc() a new node.
Python does all of that for us.
And so once you've done that, now I
can do something similar to before.
The average equals the sum
of those scores divided
by the length of that list of scores.
And I can again print out, with
an f string, the average value
in that variable like this.
So, again, you just have more
building blocks at your disposal
when it comes to something like this.
You can also do this, just
so you've seen other syntax.
It turns out that instead of doing
scores.append, you could also do this.
You could concatenate scores with itself
by adding two lists together like this.
This looks a little weird.
But on the left is my variable scores.
On the right here, I am taking
whatever is in that list,
and I'm adding the current score
by adding it to its own list.
And this will update the value as we go.
But it does, in fact,
change the value of score
as opposed to appending
to the initial list.
All right.
How about some other
building blocks here?
Let me propose this.
Let me close out scores.py.
Let me open up a file
called phonebook.py,
reminiscent of what
we did weeks ago in C.
And let me give myself a list of names.
We won't bother with numbers just yet.
Let's just play with
lists for another moment.
So here is a variable called names.
It has maybe three names in
it-- maybe Carter and David
and John Harvard, as in past weeks.
And now let me go ahead and
ask the user to input a name--
because this is going
to be like a phone book.
I want to ask the user for
a name and then look up
that person's name and the phone
book, even though I'm not bothering
by having any phone numbers just yet.
How could I search for, a la
linear search, someone's name?
Well, in Python I could
do this. for name--
rather, for n in names, if the current
name equals what the human typed in,
then go ahead and print out "Found,"
then break out of this loop.
Otherwise, we'll print out
"Not found" at the bottom.
All right.
So let's try this--
python of phonebook.py.
Let's search for maybe Carter.
That's easy.
He's at the beginning.
Oh, hmm.
Well, he was found, but
then I printed "Not found."
So that's not quite what I want.
How about David?
D-A-V-I-D. "Found," "Not found"--
all right, not very correct.
How about this?
Let's search for Eli, not in the list.
OK.
So at least someone not
being in the list is working.
But logically, for Carter,
for David, and even John,
why are we seeing "Found"
and then "Not found?"
Why is it not found?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: You need to
intend the print().
DAVID MALAN: OK.
I don't have seem to have indented
the print(), but let me try this.
If I just go with the else here--
let me go up here and
indent this and say else--
I'm not sure logically
this is what we want,
because what I think this is going
to do if I search for maybe Carter--
OK, that worked.
So it's partially fixed the problem.
But let me try searching
for maybe David.
Oh, now we're sort of
the opposite problem--
"Not found," "Found."
Why?
Well, I don't think we want
to immediately conclude
that someone's not found
just because they don't
equal the current name in the list.
So it turns out we could fix this
in a couple of different ways.
But there's kind of a
neat features of Python.
In Python, even for loops
can have an else clause.
And this is weird.
But the way this works is as follows.
In Python, if you break out of a
loop, that's it for the for loop.
If, though, you get all the way through
the list that you're looping over,
and you never once call line 8--
you never break out of the loop--
Python is smart enough
to realize, OK, you just
went through lines 5 through 8.
You never actually
logically called break.
Here's an else clause to
be associated with it.
Semantically, this is weird.
We've only ever seen if and
else associated with each other.
But for loops in Python
actually can have else as well.
And in this case now, if I do python
of phonebook.py, type in Carter,
now we get only one answer.
If I do it again and type in
David, now we get only one answer.
Do it again with John.
Now we get only one answer.
Do it with Eli.
So, again, you just get a few
more tools in your toolkit
when it comes to a language like Python
that might very well make solving
problems a little more pleasant.
But this is kind of stupid in Python.
This is correct, but
it's not well designed,
because I don't need to iterate
over lists like this so pedantically
like we've been doing for weeks in C.
I can actually tighten this
up, and I can just do this.
I can get rid of the loop, and I can
say if name in names, then print out,
quote unquote, "Found."
That's it in Python.
If you want Python to search a
whole list of values for you,
just let Python do the work.
And you can literally just say if
the name that the human inputted is
in names, which is this list here,
Python will use linear search for you,
search automatically from left to right,
presumably, looking for the value.
And if it doesn't find it
then and only then will
this else clause execute instead.
So, again, Python's
just starting to save us
some time because this, too, will
find Carter, but it will not find,
for instance, Eli.
All right?
So we get that functionality for free.
But what more can we perhaps do here?
Well, it turns out that
Python has yet other features
we might want to explore, namely
dictionaries, shortened as dict.
And a dictionary in Python is
just like it was in C and, really,
in computer science in general.
A dictionary was an abstract data type.
And it's a collection of key value pairs
it looks a little something like this.
If in C, if in Python,
if, in any language,
you want to associate something with
something, like a name with a number,
you had to, in problem set 5,
implement the darn thing yourself
by implementing an entire spell
checker with an array and linked list
to store all of those
words in your dictionary.
In Python, as we saw earlier, you
can use a set, or you can use,
more simply, a dictionary that
implements for you all of problem
set 5's ideas.
But Python does the
heavy lifting for you.
A dict in Python is essentially a hash
table, a collection of key value pairs.
So what does this mean for me in Python?
It means that I can do some
pretty handy things pretty easily.
So, for instance, let me
go back here to VS Code,
and let me change my phone
book altogether to be this.
Let me give myself a
list of dictionaries.
So people is now going
to be a global list.
And I'm going to demarcate it
here with open square bracket
and closed square bracket.
And just to be nice
and neat and tidy, I'm
going to have these people no longer
just be Carter and David and John,
as in the previous example.
But I want each of the elements
of this list to be a key value
pair, like a name and a number.
So how can I do this?
In Python, you can use this syntax.
And this is, I think, the last of
the weird looking syntax today.
You can define a dictionary
that is something like this
by using two curly braces like this.
And inside of your curly
braces, you get to invent
the name, the keys, and the values.
So if you want one key to be
the person's name, you can do,
quote unquote, "name" and
then, quote unquote, "Carter."
If you want another key to be "number,"
you can do, quote unquote, "number,"
and then, quote unquote, something
like last time, "1-617-495-1000,"
for instance, for Carter's number there.
And collectively, everything here
on line 2 represents a dictionary.
It's as though, on a chalkboard, I
wrote down "name, Carter, number,
+1-617-495-1000," row by
row by row in this table.
This is simply the code
equivalent thereof.
If you want to be
really nitpicky or tidy,
you could style your
code to look like this,
which makes it a little more clear,
perhaps, as to what's going on.
It's just starting to add a lot
of whitespace to the screen.
But it's just a collection
of key value pairs,
again, akin to a
two-column table like this.
I'm going to undo the whitespace just
to kind of tighten things up because I
want to cram two other people in here.
So I'm going to go ahead and do
another set of curly braces with,
quote unquote, "name" and
"David," quote unquote, "number"--
and we'll have the same
number, so "+1-617-495-1000."
And then, lastly, let's do another
set of curly braces for a name of say
"John," and John Harvard's number,
quote unquote, "number" will be "+1"--
let's see-- "949-468-2750" is
always John Harvard's number.
And then, by convention, you typically
end even this element with a comma.
But it's not strictly
necessary syntactically.
But stylistically, that's
often added for you.
So what is people?
people is now a list of
dictionaries, a list of dictionaries.
So what does that mean?
It means I can now do code like this.
I can prompt the user with the input()
function for someone's name if the goal
now is to look up that person's number.
How can I look up that number?
Well, for each person in the list of
people, let's go ahead and do this.
If the current person's name equals
equals whatever name the human
typed in, then get that person's number
by going into that person and doing,
quote unquote, "number,"
and then go ahead
and print out something like this f
string "Found" that person's number.
And then, since we found them,
let's just break out all together.
And if we get through that whole thing,
let's just, at the very end, print
out "Not found."
So what's weird here?
If I focus on this code here,
this syntax obviously is new.
The square brackets, though, just
means, hey, Python, here comes a list.
Hey, Python, that's it for the list.
Inside of this list
are three dictionaries.
The curly braces mean, hey,
Python, here comes a dictionary.
Hey, Python, that's
it for the dictionary.
Each of these dictionaries
has two key value pairs--
"name" and its value,
"number" and its value.
So you can think of each of these
lines as being like a C struct,
like with typedef and struct.
But I don't have to decide in
advance what the keys and the values
are going to be.
I can just, on the fly,
create a dictionary like this,
again, reminiscent of this
kind of chalkboard design.
All right.
So what am I actually doing in code?
A dictionary in Python
lets you index into it,
similar to an array with
numbers in C. So in C, this
is a little bit different.
In C, you might have been in
the habit of doing person.name.
But because it's a dictionary,
the syntax in Python
is you actually use square
brackets with strings
as being inside the square
brackets rather than numbers.
But all this is now doing is it's
creating a variable on line 11,
setting that number equal to
that same person's number.
Why?
Because we're inside of
this loop, I'm iterating
over each person one at a time.
And that's what for--
that's what n does.
It assigns the person variable to
this dictionary, then this dictionary,
then this dictionary
automatically for me--
no need for i and i++ and all of that.
So this is just saying, if
the current person's name
equals the name we're looking for, get
a variable called number and assign it
that person's number, and then
print out that person's number.
So whereas last time we were just
printing "Found" and "Not found,"
now I'm going to print an actual number.
So if I run python of phonebook.py
and I search for Carter,
there then is his number.
If I run python of phonebook.py, type
in John, there then is John's number.
And if I search for someone who's not
there, I instead just get "Not found."
So what's interesting and
compelling about dictionaries
is they're kind of known as the
Swiss Army knives of data structures
in programming because
you can just use them
in so many interesting, clever ways.
If you ever want to associate
something with something else,
a dictionary is your friend.
And you no longer have to write
dozens of lines of code as in P set 5.
You can write single lines of
code to achieve this same idea.
So, for instance, if I, too,
want to tighten this up,
I actually don't need
this loop altogether.
An even better version of
this code would be this.
I don't need this
variable, technically, even
though this will look a little uglier.
Notice that I'm only creating
a variable called number
because I want to set it
equal to this person's number.
But strictly speaking, any
time you've declared a variable
and then used it in the next line,
eh, you don't really need it.
So I could do this.
I could get rid of that line.
And instead of printing
"number" in my curly braces,
I could actually do
person, square brackets,
and you might be inclined to do this.
But this is going to confuse Python
because you're mixing double quotes
on the inside and the outside.
But you can use single
quotes here, compellingly.
So you don't have to do it this way.
But this is just to
show you, syntactically,
you can put most anything you
want in these curly braces
so long as you don't confuse
Python by using the same syntax.
But let me do one other thing here.
This is even more powerful.
Let me propose that
if all you're storing
is names and numbers, names
and numbers, I can actually
simplify this dictionary significantly.
Let me actually redeclare
this people data structure
to be not a list of dictionaries, but
how about just one big dictionary?
Because if I'm only
associating names with numbers,
I don't technically need
to create special keys
called "name" and "number."
Why don't I just associate Carter
with his number, +1-617-495-1000?
Why don't I just associate, quote
unquote, "David" with his number,
+1-617-495-1000?
And then, lastly, let's just associate
John with his number, +1-949-468-2750?
And that too would work.
But notice that I'm going to
get rid of my list of people
and instead just have one dictionary
of people, the downside of which
is that you can only have one key,
one value, one key, one value.
You can't have a name key and a number
key and an email key and an address key
and any number of other pieces
of data that might be compelling.
But if you've only got
key value pairs like this,
we can tighten up this code
significantly so that now, down here,
I can actually do this.
If the name I'm looking for is
somewhere in that people dictionary,
then go ahead and get
the person's number
by going into the people dictionary,
indexing into it at that person's name,
and then printing out "Found,"
for instance, that here number,
making this an f string,
else you can go ahead
and print out "Not
found" in this case here.
So, again, the difference is
that the previous version created
a list of dictionaries,
and I very manually,
methodically, iterated over
it, looking for the person.
But what's nice again
about dictionaries is
that Python gives you a lot of support
for just looking into them easily.
And this syntax, just like
you can use it for lists,
you can use it for dictionaries as well.
And Python will look for that name
among the keys in the dictionary.
And if it finds it, you use this
syntax to get at that person's number.
Whew, OK.
A lot all at once, but are there
any questions on this here syntax?
We'll then introduce a couple of
final features with a final flourish.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: This way
[INAUDIBLE] break [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: In this case,
I do not need to use break
because I don't have any loop involved.
So break is only used, as we've
seen it, in the context of looping
over something when you want
to terminate the loop early.
But here Python is doing
the searching for you.
So Python is taking care
of that automatically.
All right.
Just a couple of final features so
that you have a couple of more building
blocks-- here is the documentation
for dictionaries themselves
in case you want to poke around as
to what more you can do with them.
But it turns out that there
are other libraries that
come with Python, not even
third-party, and one of them
is the sys library, whereby you
have system-related functionality.
And here's its official
documentation, for instance.
But what this means is that
certain functionality that was just
immediately available in C is sometimes
tucked away now into libraries
in Python.
So, for instance, let
me go over to VS Code
here, and let me just create a
program called greet.py, which
is reminiscent of an old
C program that just greets
the user using command-line arguments.
But in C, recall that we got access
to command-line arguments with main()
and argc and argv.
But none of those have
we seen at all today.
And, in fact, main() itself
is no longer required.
So if you want to do
command-line arguments in Python,
you actually do this.
From the sys library, you can
import something called argv.
So argv still exists.
It's just tucked away inside of this
library, otherwise known as a module.
And I can then do this.
If the length of argv, for
instance, does not equal 2,
well, then, we're going to
go ahead and do what we did--
or rather, let's do this.
If the length of argv
does equal 2, we're
going to go ahead and do
what we did a couple of weeks
ago, whereby I'm going
to print out "hello,"
comma, and then argv
bracket 1, for instance,
so whatever is in
location 1 of that list.
Else, if the length of argv
is not equal to 2-- that is,
the human did not type
two words at the prompt--
let's go ahead and print out
"hello, world" by default.
So we did the exact same thing in C. The
only difference here is that this now
is how you get access to argv.
So let me run this-- python of greet.py
and hit Enter. "hello, world" is all I
get.
And actually, I got an extra
line break because out of habit,
I included backslash n, but
I don't need that in Python.
So let me fix that. python
of greet.py-- "hello, world."
But if I do python of
greet.py, D-A-V-I-D,
now notice that argv equals 2.
If I instead do something like
Carter, argv now equals 2.
But there is a difference.
Technically, I'm typing three words at
the prompt, three words at the prompt,
but argv still only equals 2 because
the command python is ignored from argv.
It's only the name of your file
and the thing you type after it.
So that's then how we might print
out arguments in Python using argv.
Well, what else might we do using
some of these here features?
Well, it turns out that you can exit
from programs using this same sys
library.
So let me close greet.py.
Let me open up exit.py just
for demonstration's sake.
And let's do something like this.
Let's import sys.
And if the length of sys.argv--
so here's just another
way of doing this.
And actually, I'll do it the same
first-- from sys import argv.
If the length of argv does not equal 2--
well, let's actually yell
at the user with something
like "Missing command-line argument."
And then what we can do is exit out of
the program entirely using sys.exit(),
which is a function therein.
But notice that exit()
is a function in sys.
So you know what?
It's actually more
convenient in this case.
Let's just import all of sys.
But because that has not given
me direct access to argv,
let me do sys.argv here
and sys.exit() here.
Otherwise, if all is well, let's
just go ahead and print out something
like "hello, sys.argv," bracket 1, close
quote, and that will print out "hello,
so-and-so."
And when I'm ready to
exit with a non-0--
with a 0 exit status, I can actually
start to specify these things here.
So just like in C, if you want to
exit from a program with 1 or 2
or anything else, you can use sys.exit.
And if you want to exit with a
0, you can do this here instead.
So we have the same
capabilities as in C,
just accessed a little bit differently.
Let me propose that--
let's see.
how about this?
How about this?
If we want to go ahead and create
something a little more interactive,
recall that there was that
command a while back, namely
pip, whereby I ran pip
install face_recognition.
That's one of the examples
with which we began.
And that allows me to install more
functionality from a third party
into my own code space or my
programming environment more generally.
Well, we can have a little
fun with this, in fact.
Let me go back to VS Code here.
And just like there's a
command in Linux called cowsay,
whereby you can get the
cow to say something,
you can also use this
kind of thing in Python.
So if I do pip install cowsay,
this, if it's not installed already,
will install a library called cowsay.
And what this means is that if I
actually want to code up a program
called, like, moo.py, I can
import the cowsay library,
and I can do something
simple like cowsay.cow,
because there's a function
in this library called cow(),
and I can say something like
"This is CS50," quote unquote.
How do I run this program?
I can run python of moo.py,
and-- oh, underwhelming.
If I increase the size of my terminal
window, run python of moo.py,
we have that same
adorable cow as before,
but I now have programmatic capabilities
with which to manipulate it.
And so, in fact, I could make this
program a little more interesting.
I could do something like name = quote--
or rather, name = input("What's
your name?") and combine some
of today's ideas.
And now I can say not "This
is CS50," but something like,
quote unquote, "Hello,"
comma, person's name.
And now, if I increase the size of
my terminal, rerun python of moo.py,
it's not going to actually
moo or say "This is CS50."
It's going to say something like
"hello, David," and so forth.
And suffice it to say
through other functions,
you can do not only cows but
dragons and other fancy things, too.
But even in Python, too, can
you generate not just ASCII art,
but actual art and actual images.
And the note I thought we'd end
on is doing one other library.
I'm going to go back into VS Code here.
I'm going to close moo.py.
I'm going to do pip install qrcode,
which is the name of a library
that I might want to install to
generate QR codes automatically.
And QR codes are these
two-dimensional bar codes.
If you want to generate
these things yourself,
you don't have to go to a
website and type in a URL.
You can actually write
this kind of code yourself.
So how might I do this?
Well, let me go into a new
file called, say, qr.py.
And let me do this.
Let me go ahead and import
this library called qrcode.
Let me go ahead and create a variable
called image, or anything else.
Let me set it equal to this
library's qrcodes function called
make-- no relationship to
C. It's just called make
because you want to make a QR code.
Let me type in, maybe, the URL of
a lecture video here on YouTube--
so, like, youtu.be/xvFZjo5PgG0,
quote unquote.
And then I can go ahead and do img.save
because inside of this image variable,
which is a different data type
that this library gave me--
it doesn't come with Python per se--
I can save a file like qr.png, And I can
save it in the PNG format, the Portable
Network Graphic.
And so just to be clear,
what this should hopefully
do for me is create a QR code
containing that particular URL,
but not as text, but rather as
an actual image that I can send,
I can post online, or, in our
case, generate into my code space,
and then open.
And so, with all that said,
we've seen a bunch of new syntax
today, a bunch of new features.
But the ideas underlying Python are
exactly the same as they've been in C.
It's just that you don't have to do
nearly as much heavy lifting yourself.
And here, for instance, in
just three lines of code,
can you generate a massive
QR code that people can scan,
as you can in a moment with
your phones, and actually
link to something like a CS50 class.
So let me go ahead and
run python of qr.py.
It seems to have run.
Let me run code of qr.png,
which is the file I created.
I'll close my terminal window,
allow you an opportunity
to scan this here very CS50 lecture.
And-- and-- is someone's volume up?
[RICK ASTLEY, "NEVER GONNA GIVE YOU UP"]
There we go.
What a perfect ending.
All right.
That was CS50.
We'll see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]