BRIAN YU: Let's take
a look at plurality.
In plurality, your task
is going to be to write
a program that simulates an election.
Your program will take a
sequence of votes as input,
and your program will output
the winner of that election.
Let's take a look at
how you might do that.
Your election is going to have a
sequence of candidates in the election.
This election has Alice, Bob, and
Charlie as the candidates, for example.
And each voter is going to select
one of those candidates to vote for.
If you take this voter's
information in combination
with the information from
all of the other voters,
you can use that information to figure
out who the winner of the election is.
What information will you
need to keep track of?
Well, you'll need to keep track
of each of the candidates,
and for each of the candidates,
how many votes they have.
In this case, Alice has three
votes, Bob has one vote,
and Charlie has two votes.
So as a result, Alice is declared
the winner of the election.
This is what we call a plurality vote,
also known as first past the post.
The rules basically work like this.
Every voter chooses one candidate
who they would like to vote for.
And at the end of the election,
whichever candidate has
the most votes is declared
the winner of that election.
So how is your program going to work?
Well, your program is going to be run
as ./plurality followed by the names
of all of the candidates
in the election.
In this case, Alice, Bob, and Charlie.
Your program will then prompt
the user for the number
of voters in the election.
In this case, we might
say four, for example.
And then now four times
your program is going
to prompt the voter to type in
who they're going to vote for.
So the first vote for
Alice, for example.
And then the next voter might
vote for Bob, for example.
And maybe the last two voters
are going to vote for Charlie.
After all of the votes
are in, your program
is going to figure out who the winner of
the election is and output their name.
In this case, Charlie.
So how are you going to do this?
Well, recall that this is the
data that you need to store.
For each candidate, you need
to keep track of how many votes
they currently have, which
means that for any candidate,
you're really storing two
pieces of information.
And when you're storing
multiple pieces of information,
one convenient way to
represent that in a c program
is by storing the information
inside of a struct.
Here, we've defined a struct
called a candidate, inside
of which we're going
to store two fields.
One field which is a string called
name representing the candidate's name,
and one field which is an integer called
votes representing the number of votes
that this candidate currently has.
We can take all of these candidates
stored inside of these structs
and put them in a sequence by creating
an array of candidates which we're
going to call candidates that's going
to store all of the candidates that
are currently in the election.
Because this is an array, we can index
into this array the same way we index
into any other array by using
candidates[0] to mean the first
candidate in the election, candidates[1]
to mean the second candidate,
and candidates[2] to
mean the third candidate.
But remember that each
candidate is itself
a struct that has a name
and a number of votes.
So if we want to take this struct
and access a property of it,
we could say candidates[2].name,
for example--
using the dot syntax to access
the name of this candidate--
and using candidates[2].votes to
access the number of votes that Charlie
currently has.
So what are you going
to do in plurality?
Well, you're going to
implement two functions.
One called vote and one
called a print_winner.
Your vote function is going
to take as its argument
a string parameter called name.
And what your vote
function is going to do
is it's going to look
for a candidate who's
called name, who has that same name.
And if you're able to find
a candidate with that name,
you're going to update their
vote total and return true.
Otherwise, if you aren't
able to find that candidate,
you're going to not update
any vote totals at all,
and you're instead
going to return false.
So how might that work?
Well, if the vote
function is called on Bob,
for example, you might want to iterate
through this array of candidates
starting with the first
one and asking yourself,
does this candidate's name match Bob?
In this case, it doesn't.
So we move on.
We'd move to the next candidate.
Does this candidate's name match Bob?
Well, it does.
So we found a match, which means we can
take the vote total and increment it,
moving it from 1 to 2 to
keep track of this new vote.
And then our vote function
would return true.
Of course, if we had voted for someone
who wasn't in this election at all--
for example, Dave--
we wouldn't update any vote totals,
and our function would return false.
So that's the vote function.
The second function you're going
to implement in this program
is print_winner.
And the print_winner function is
going to be tasked with printing out
the winner of the election.
So in this function,
you're going to print out
the name of the candidate or
candidates who have the most votes.
Because remember, it's possible
that at the end of the election,
multiple people are tied for the
most number of votes, in which case
each of them should
be declared a winner.
And you'll want to print
out each of their names.
So in this case where Alice has
three votes, Bob has one vote,
and Charlie has two votes,
Alice has the most votes,
and Alice is going to be declared
the winner of the election.
So you should print out Alice's name.
But consider, for
example, these vote totals
where both Alice and Bob
each are tied for winning
the election at three votes each.
So your program should print out
Alice on one line and then Bob
on the next line.
After you've implemented these two
functions, vote and print_winner,
you should have implemented
all you need to be
able to simulate a plurality election.
And by running ./plurality, you should
be able to type in a sequence of votes
and have your program output who
the winner of the election is.
My name is Brian.
And this was plurality.