BRIAN: Let's now dive into runoff.
In runoff, we're going to take
advantage of ranked preference voting,
whereas in plurality, each voter
only got to vote for one candidate.
In runoff, a voter might be able
to rank all of their candidates
in sequence, so the ballot might look a
little something like this, where they
have a space to fill in their first
preference, second preference,
and third preference, for example.
One voter, for instance, might want
Alice as their first preference vote.
But if Alice can't win, their
next choice would be Charlie.
And if Charlie can't win,
their next choice would be Bob.
So this is what a ranked
preference ballot might look like.
How then does the runoff
vote actually work?
Well, the runoff vote
is first going to say
that every voter should rank
all of their preferences,
first, second, third,
up to as many candidates
as there are in the election.
If any candidate has a majority of
the vote, meaning more than half
of the votes, then
that candidate is going
to be declared the
winner of the election.
But if nobody has a
majority, we're going
to eliminate the candidate
with the fewest number of votes
and rerun the election
without them, and we're
going to keep repeating
that process until someone
has won a majority of the votes.
So let's take a look
at a simple example.
In this election, we
have seven votes, which
means that a candidate needs four
votes, a majority of the seven
in order to win the election.
The candidates here are
Alice, Bob, and Charlie.
And so we'll look at the
ballots one at a time.
For this first ballot, Alice is this
voter's top preferred candidate.
So Alice is going to get this ballot.
This next ballot is also
going to go to Alice.
This ballot has Bob as their top choice,
so Bob gets this ballot as well as
the next one.
The next ballot goes to Alice.
The next ballot goes to Bob.
And the final ballot has Charlie
as the top preferred candidate.
At this point, Alice has three
votes, Bob has three votes,
and Charlie has one vote.
But remember, with seven
votes in this election,
a candidate needs four
votes in order to win.
So at this point, we
need to hold a runoff.
Charlie has the fewest number
of votes in this election
so far, so Charlie is going to
be eliminated from the race.
What happens to the voter who
originally voted for Charlie?
Well, that voter had
a second preference.
And their second preference was Alice.
So Alice at this point is
going to get this last ballot.
Alice now has four votes
compared to Bob's three votes,
and four is a majority.
So Alice is going to be declared
the winner of this election.
That, in short, is how
a runoff election works.
But it could be a
little more complicated.
So let's take a look at a
more sophisticated example,
this time with 10 ballots and four
different candidates, Alice, Bob,
Charlie, and Dave.
The first step happens,
and we give each candidate,
all of the voters who chose that
candidate as their first preference.
And at this point, Alice has
three votes, Bob has four votes,
Charlie has one vote,
and Dave has two votes.
In a plurality election, or a
first past the post election,
Bob would win this election now, because
Bob has more votes than anyone else.
But with 10 ballots in the
election, in a runoff election,
a candidate needs a majority,
or six out of the 10 votes
in order to be declared the winner.
Since nobody has six votes
yet, we need to hold a runoff.
Charlie, again, is in last
place in this election,
so we're going to eliminate
Charlie from the election,
and their voter is going to now vote
for Alice, the second preference.
Alice now has four votes.
Bob has four votes.
And Dave has two votes.
Still, nobody has a
majority of six votes,
so we need to hold yet another runoff.
Dave has the fewest number of votes
in this election at this point.
So Dave is going to be eliminated.
What happens to the
people who voted for Dave?
Well, the first person
who voted for Dave
chose Alice as their next preference,
and the second voter who voted for Dave
chose Charlie as their
second preference.
But Charlie has already been eliminated,
so the vote can't go to Charlie either.
So we now look to that voter's third
preference, which in this case,
is also Alice.
This means that Alice gets each
of the two remaining votes,
and Alice now has six votes
compared to Bob's four.
Alice has a majority of
the votes in the election,
so Alice is declared the
winner of this election.
Your task in runoff is going to be
to write a program that simulates
this style of runoff election.
So how are you going to do that?
Well, one thing to think about is how
you're going to represent this data.
And one piece of data you're
going to need to represent
are all of the candidates and the
information associated with them.
In this case, in addition to storing
the candidate's name and the number
of votes they currently
have, you'll also
want to store a Boolean
flag, true or false,
representing whether that candidate
has been eliminated from the race
yet or not.
At first, all of these
values will be false,
because nobody will
have been eliminated,
but as candidates are eliminated
in this runoff process,
you might switch those
values from false to true.
You can represent each of these
candidates using a struct that we'll
give you, where this struct representing
a candidate has three fields,
a string field called name, and int
field, called votes, and a Bool field,
called eliminated,
representing whether or not
that candidate has been eliminated
from the election or not.
We can store a sequence
of these candidates
inside an array of candidates, where
each individual element in that array
is one of these candidate's structs.
But the candidates aren't
the only piece of information
that we need to keep track of in
order to run the runoff election.
We also need to keep
track of information
about the voters, in particular
about who their preferences are.
And to do that, we're going to represent
preferences using a two dimensional
array called preferences.
How do you interpret this
two dimensional array?
Well, preferences IJ,
meaning row I and column J,
is going to be a cell that store
is the index of the candidate who
is voter I's preference number J.
So what does that actually mean?
Let's take a look at an example.
In this case, we have three
candidates, Alice, Bob, and Charlie,
where Alice is stored at index
0 in the candidate's array,
Bob is stored at index 1, and
Charlie is stored at index 2.
What happens if we say something
like preference of 0, 0 equals 2.
Well, that means we're going
to fill into row 0 and column
0 of this array, the number 2.
And the way to interpret that is that
row 0 is talking about the first voter
, and column 0 is talking about the
first preference for that voter.
And the 2 means candidate at index
2, which in this case is Charlie.
So preference 0, 0 equals true means the
first voter's top preferred candidate
is, in fact, Charlie.
What if we then said
preferences 0, 1 equals 0?
Well, that would mean we
would fill in the number 0
into this slot in the
two dimensional array.
We're still on preference
is 0, this first row
talking about the first voter.
But now we're on column 1,
which is here going to represent
the voter's second preference.
Their second preference is
zero, and candidate 0 is Alice.
So preference is 0, 1 equals
0 means the first voter's
second preferred candidate is Alice.
And we can fill in this entire
preference's two dimensional array
to keep track of every single
voter and every single preference
that that voter has.
So what do you actually need to do
to implement the runoff program?
Well inside of runoff.c,
you're going to implement
six functions that will perform the
algorithm of implementing this runoff
election.
First, you'll implement vote,
then tabulate, then print winner,
then find min, then is tie,
and then finally, eliminate.
And we'll go through each of
these functions one by one.
Let's start with the vote function.
The vote function takes
three arguments, an integer
called voter, representing which
number voter is currently voting.
It also takes an integer
called rank, representing
which rank the voter is currently
trying to indicate a preference for,
rank 0 meaning their top preference
rank 1, meaning their next preference,
so on and so forth.
And finally, the function
takes in a string called name,
indicating which candidate they're
currently trying to vote for.
So what is vote going to do?
Well, your vote function should
look for a candidate called name.
If you find that candidate, you
should update the two dimensional
array of preferences, so that they
are that voter's rank preference.
And then you should return true to
indicate that you were successfully
able to record this preference.
But if no candidate was found, you
shouldn't update any preferences
at all, and your function
should just return false.
Let's take a look at it example.
Here again, we have
Alice, Bob, and Charlie.
And here again, we have
a two dimensional array
of preferences, which
is going to be stored
as a global variable in your program.
Let's imagine that this
ballot comes along,
where the first preference is Alice,
then comes Charlie, then comes Bob.
Well, Alice is the candidate at index
0 in the candidate's array, which
means we're going to fill in 0 in
to row 0 and column 0 of this array,
representing the first
voter's top preference.
This voter's next preference is
Charlie, who's at index 2 in the array.
So 2 gets filled in to the next
spot in this preferences row.
And finally, Bob is
the third preference.
Bob, again, is at index 1 in the array.
So 1 gets filled in next.
And we're going to do this for each
of the votes that comes our way.
If the next voter votes for
Charlie as their top preference,
and Charlie is at index 2
in the candidate's array,
then we're going to fill in 2 as
the first preference for this voter.
Bob is the second
preference, who's at index 1,
and Alice is the third preference,
who is the candidate at index 0.
And we're going to do the same
thing for each remaining voter who
votes in the election
until by the end of it,
we filled in the entire preferences
array for each of the voters
and for each of their preferences.
Next up is the tabulate function,
and the job of the tabulate function
is going to be the update the vote
counts for each of the candidates
to represent how many
votes they currently have.
How are you going to do that?
Well, recall that every voter is going
to ideally vote for their highest
preference candidate, but a voter
can't vote for a candidate who's
already been eliminated.
So each voter is going to vote for their
highest preferred candidate who has not
yet been eliminated from the race.
So what might this tabulate function
actually do on some sample data?
Well, let's take a look at these
preferences and these candidates.
None of the candidates
have been eliminated yet.
Alice's eliminated
status is set to false,
and so is Bob's, and
so is Charlie's, which
means that since nobody
has been eliminated,
every voter gets to vote for
their top preferred candidate.
This first voter, for example, is
voting for candidate 0, who's Alice.
So our tabulate function would
update Alice's vote total,
changing it from 0 to 1.
Next up, this voter's
voting for Charlie.
The next voter is voting for Bob.
The next voter is voting
for Charlie again.
And the final voter is voting for Alice.
So at the end of our
tabulate function, we
should have recorded in our candidates
array that Alice has two votes,
Bob has one vote, and
Charlie has two votes.
But what happens in a more complex
scenario, where, for example,
Bob may have been already
eliminated from this election,
and we want to tabulate
these votes again.
Well, we'd go through the
array, much as we did before
and see that the first
voter was voting for Alice,
and the second voter is voting for
Charlie, the candidate at index 2,
and the third voter is trying
to vote for the candidate
at index 1, who in this case is Bob.
But Bob's already been eliminated,
so the vote can't actually go to Bob.
So instead, this voter is going to look
at their next preference, candidate
number 2, who in this case, is Charlie.
Charlie's still in the race,
and so Charlie gets this vote,
and his vote total gets
updated from 1 to 2.
The next voter votes for Charlie,
no problem, and the final voter
votes for Alice, so by the end
of it, Alice has two votes,
and Charlie has three.
So that's what you're
tabulate function is
going to do, go through each of the
voters and update the vote counts,
making sure to only update
vote counts for candidates
who are still in the race.
The next function you're going
to write is print winner.
The print winner function is going
to be a function that's ultimately
going to be tasked with printing
out who the winner of the election
is if there is a winner yet.
What does that mean?
Well, if any candidate has
more than half of the vote,
in other words, a majority of the
vote, you should print out their name
and return true from this function.
But it's possible that no candidate
has yet won the election because nobody
has more than half the vote.
In that case, you shouldn't
print out anything,
and your function should
just return false.
So let's take a look at an example.
In this case, there are five
total votes in this election,
and because there are five votes, you
would need three votes, a majority,
in order to win.
Since nobody has three votes,
that means there is no winner yet.
So your print winner function
shouldn't print out any names
and should just return false.
But now, let's take a look
at these votes, for example.
Still, there are five
total votes, which means
you need three votes in order to win,
but here, Charlie has three votes.
So Charlie would be the
winner of this election.
Your print winner function, in this
case, should print out Charlie's name
and then return true to
indicate that Charlie is,
in fact, the winner of this election.
The next function you'll implement
in runoff.c is called find min.
In find min, what you'll do is you'll
return the minimum number of votes
of anyone still in the election.
And we'll use this to figure
out, for example, who we need
to eliminate in this runoff process.
So let's take a look at an example.
Here's a sample election with five
candidates, Alice, Bob, Charlie,
Dave, and Emma, and their vote totals.
And notice, that based on the fact
that all of their eliminated flags
are all set to false, all five
candidates are still in the election.
Here, your algorithm should
return the number one from this
find min function because Bob is the
candidate that has the fewest votes out
of anyone in the current election.
Of course, you may run into a situation
where some candidates have already
been eliminated.
Let's take a look at an example of that.
Here, for example, Bob has
already been eliminated.
For Bob's candidate struct, his
eliminated status is set to true.
So in this case, we wouldn't
want to return 0 as the minimum,
even though 0 is the smallest vote total
of any candidate inside of this array,
because Bob's already been eliminated.
And we only want to consider candidates
that are still in the election.
So in this case, the candidates
that have the fewest number of votes
are Alice and Emma, who
both have two votes each,
and so 2 is the number that we would
return from find min in this case.
The next function you'll implement is
called is tied, and the job of is tied
is to decide whether or not this
election is tied between all
of the remaining candidates.
So how does this function work?
Well, the function will
take as input in integer
called min, which is that
minimum number of votes
that you calculated inside
of the find min function.
And is tied should return true if
the election is tied between all
of the remaining candidates.
If it's not tied between all
of the remaining candidates,
then your function should return false.
So for example, if all of the
candidates are still in the election,
and every candidate has two votes,
then this election is a tie,
and your function should return true.
Of course, this election is also tied.
Even though candidates
have different vote totals,
Bob and Dave have already been
eliminated from the election,
so I'm only looking at the three other
people that are still in the election.
They each have two votes,
and so because it's
a tie between all of the remaining
candidates in the election,
then this function should return true.
Finally, the last function that you'll
write in runoff.c is called eliminate,
and this is the function that's going
to take care of the process of actually
eliminating the candidate who's
in last place in the election,
such that the election can run
again, as if that person had not been
in the election in the first place.
So your eliminate function
should eliminate anyone still
in the race, who has
the min number of votes.
Recall that min is going to
be the input to this function,
and it's going to be that value that
you computed in the find min function.
So anyone who has the fewest number
of votes in the election, which
might be one candidate, or
it might be more than one,
they should all be
eliminated from the election.
Let's take a look at an example.
Here, for example, none of the
candidates have yet been eliminated,
but we can see that Bob is the candidate
who has the minimum number of votes.
He has one vote, and everyone
else has more than that.
So your eliminate function should
update Bob's candidate struct,
changing eliminated from false to true
to indicate the fact that Bob has now
been eliminated from this election.
Of course, when we run the
runoff the next time around
and recompute the vote
totals, we might get something
a little like this, where
Bob has now been eliminated,
and now we've decided the
minimum number of votes
that anyone still in
the election has is 2.
What should your
function do in this case?
Well, your function should
look through the candidates
and identify that both Alice and Emma
each have two votes, the minimum number
of votes of anyone in the election.
And your function should
eliminate both of them,
taking each of their candidate
structs and changing eliminated
from false to true for each of them.
Once you've done that, you'll
have completed all that you need
to implement a runoff election by
implementing the vote, tabulate,
print winner, find min, is
tied, and eliminate functions,
you'll be able to simulate this runoff
election you can test for yourself
by running ./runoff and then passing
in as command line arguments the names
of the candidates in the election,
and then typing in each voter's ranked
preferences, and then seeing whether
your program computes the correct
winner of this runoff election.
My name is Brian, and this was runoff.