CARTER ZENKE: OK.
Well, hello one and all, and
welcome to CS50's third session,
this one for week 3.
My name is Carter Zenke,
the course's preceptor.
And the goal of these
sections is to help
you bridge the gap between the
lecture you perhaps just watched
and the problem set
you'll tackle this week,
or perhaps throughout the rest
of some other period of time
you'll be working on that problem set.
Now, today we actually are going to
talk about a few different topics.
Among them are these here.
So talking about how we can learn
about algorithms, discuss what they do,
and what they are, but also
how we can compare algorithms.
What makes one algorithm better
than some other algorithm?
We'll talk about that today.
We'll also talk about this idea
of a struct, or a structure,
allowing us to make our
very own data types.
And we'll also, towards the end,
talk about this idea of recursion,
or trying to define something
by defining it within itself.
And that'll hopefully make a little
more sense towards the end of section.
But it is a powerful tool you can use
to solve problems in computer science,
and a worthwhile tool to have in
your toolkit as a computer scientist.
So let's begin by jumping into
our very first topic, which
is how we can compare algorithms.
And in lecture, we had two algorithms
we were going to think about, or two--
really, two types of
algorithms, if you will.
One of them is an algorithm
used for searching,
how we can find certain
data from a data set.
And then an other type
of algorithm for sorting.
How do we order data to
make things perhaps more
efficient to search later on?
And we also talked a bit
briefly about these notations
we could use to compare algorithms.
You might recall big O notation
and big omega notation.
So we'll talk more about
those in section today.
Now, let's go back as a bit
of a review and think first
through some searching algorithms.
So here, I have a list of people.
You can see on my screen.
And currently, what do you notice?
The people here are not
quite sorted by name.
We have Matthew first,
then Samia, then Alyssa.
So it isn't quite in alphabetical order.
And if I could ask you all, what is
the algorithm we might use to search,
in this case, an array of people,
if we know the list isn't sorted?
What kind of algorithm
could we use in this case?
So I'm seeing some
people say linear search.
And linear search, to be clear, is when
we start at maybe one side of this list
and just look at the very first
person, then the next person, then
the next person, and so on.
So let's pretend here we're trying
to find this person, Alyssa,
among these seven people.
So if we are a person, I could
very clearly spot Alyssa.
Alyssa seems to be right here.
Right?
That's not too hard for me.
I could do that in one step.
But a computer has to look at only
one piece of information at a time.
So it looks a bit more like this.
You can imagine these people being
on a stage and us dimming the lights
and allowing us to only
see one person at a time.
So for a computer, it might
look first and see Matthew.
And is Matthew Alyssa?
No.
So we're going to look
at the next person.
So we'll turn our spotlight
to the next person.
We'll see Samia.
And we're not quite there yet.
We'll take the next person now
and we'll see still Alyssa.
So now we have Alyssa on our
third try, going through person
by person, left to right.
This is an example,
then, of linear search.
So let's imagine that we go
back and turn on all the lights,
and we have people, in
this case, rearranged.
So notice how their names
are in alphabetical order.
We have Alyssa, then Cecelia,
then Douglas, then Lucas.
What kind of algorithm could we
use now to search for Alyssa?
We saw this in lecture 2.
So I'm seeing some people say
this idea of binary search.
We actually saw a binary search
in our very first lecture when
David took a phone book
and opened it to the middle
and asked if we went too far or not
far enough, tore off half of it,
and then kept going,
and going, and going.
So a similar idea applies to binary
search in this case with people, too.
So let's again dim the lights and
let's only look at one person.
And if we're using
binary search, we know
it's perhaps most efficient
to look in the middle
and ask ourselves, have we gone too
far or not far enough in our list?
So let's look in the middle.
And here we get Lucas.
Have we gone too far in
our list or not far enough?
Seems like we've gone a little too far.
If Alyssa's name begins with A, Lucas
is after Alyssa and the alphabet.
So let's say, OK, let's not worry
about Lucas or the people after Lucas.
Let's focus this on the
first half of people
here and look in the middle of that.
So it turns out the middle of our
first half here is going to be Cecelia.
And again, have we gone
too far or not far enough?
Seems we've gone a
little bit too far still.
So we'll do the same thing.
We'll take that half of the
problem and tear it away,
and now I'll focus just
on that very first half.
And it turns out the very first
person in that first half here
is going to be Alyssa themselves.
So we have two algorithms
here, one called linear search
and one called binary search.
But it's also worth thinking
about how we can compare them.
So let me ask you here, how
many steps did each algorithm
take, if you can think back?
Just in terms of a plain, old number
of steps, how many did each take?
Alyssa was the third person
in our linear search,
so it took probably three steps.
And if you recall, just now, our
binary search also took three steps.
We start in the middle,
divide it in half once,
and divide it in half
again for three steps.
So it seems like linear search and
binary search were the same here.
They performed the same way.
So I might then argue, well, it
doesn't quite matter which one we use.
I could use linear
search or binary search.
Each are equivalent.
And what might you say, based
on what you saw in lecture?
If I were arguing with you that
linear search is the exact same
as binary search, what would you say?
So I'm seeing some people
say it depends on the problem
size, which does make sense.
Depends on the input that we get.
So perhaps maybe we just
got a little unlucky here,
and both binary search and
linear search took three steps.
But it might not be
the case in all inputs.
And I like this idea of it depends
on the size of our data set.
So in this case, if we had
a very, very big data set,
we heard, or saw, in lecture that binary
search might be a little bit better
for that big data set.
So let's think instead as
a computer scientist would
and think not just in terms of this one
particular input, but in terms of input
in general.
In the general case, how well do
each of these algorithms perform?
So a better question to ask
here is this one, which is,
what's the greatest number of steps
these algorithms will ever take?
And let's focus actually just
here on our seven people.
Let's say, how long
would linear search take?
And if we took the greatest number
of steps here, it seems like seven.
Right?
So seven steps.
We have to go through
all the different people
to find out have we found the
person we're looking for or not.
So it seems like seven.
What about binary search, though?
What's the greatest number of steps it
would ever take if we had seven people?
I'm seeing n over 2,
or dividing it in half.
And you're almost there.
It, in fact, is a logarithm.
So a logarithm allows us to take
something and divide it in half,
divide it in half again,
and divide it in half again.
So it's more appropriate here
to say that linear search takes
about seven steps, and binary search for
this particular input of seven people
takes log base 2 of 7,
which basically means
how many times we can divide 7 by 2,
which turns out to be something like--
let's see.
Maybe three or so steps.
So in the worst case, if you will,
linear search takes seven steps.
In the worst case, binary
search takes far fewer,
and therefore might
be a better algorithm.
So what questions do we have so far on
this idea of comparing these algorithms
using the worst possible case?
Any questions?
I'm seeing a question
here about big O notation,
which is, where does that come in?
So that's actually going
to be our next step here.
So we often don't think
about problems in terms
of the exact number of
elements we're searching.
We often might think about,
in an even more general case,
just some number of people, like N.
If we had 7, or 8, or 10, or 1,000.
Who cares?
We'll just call it N.
Some number of people.
And so now we could say, well,
linear search, in the worst case,
the greatest number of
steps it will ever take
is going to be N steps,
one for each person, where
we assume we have N people.
Right?
Now, binary search
would do the same thing.
It would say, let's actually
not go through all N of them.
Let's divide things in half,
and in half, and in half
again so the most steps we'd ever
take would be log base 2 of N,
where again, N is just the general
number of people we have overall.
It could be 10, 100, 1,000, and so on.
But now computer
scientists, because we often
work with data sets that
are so large and so big,
on the order of millions or
billions of pieces of data,
we don't often care about things as
robust as, OK, is it log base 2 of N
or log base 3?
We care about an even more general case.
And that's where this idea
of big O notation comes in.
So we might say that linear search
operates on the order of N steps.
And in the same way,
binary search operates
on the order of log of N steps.
So thinking here not even
about the general case of,
OK, is it 7 or 10 people, but just,
what are we actually doing here?
How does the problem scale
as we add new people?
So big O notation, then, is
used often for this question of,
what is the greatest number of
steps an algorithm will ever take?
If you're more technical,
you could think of it
as the upper bound of the algorithm.
The algorithm will never
run slower than this.
So questions then on the
transition between talking
in terms of individual steps and
talking now in these general, kind
of hand-wavy cases?
Question.
Is there a faster way
than binary search?
Mm-- it's a good question.
So if you get really into this, you
can find other kinds of algorithms
to search data, and there might be
cases that could be a little faster
than binary search.
I don't know any off the top
of my head, but certainly there
are researchers who are
working on that kind of thing,
to figure out how do we write a
faster algorithm than, for instance,
something like binary search.
OK, so let's keep going, and let's think
about a different kind of scenario.
So here, we're talking about the
worst case, the greatest number
of steps our algorithm will ever take.
But there's some other case, too.
So let's consider this one where
we're still trying to find Alyssa
and we're using linear search.
So let's say it just so
happens to be that Alyssa
is the very first person we find.
How many steps would that take?
Well, just one.
Right?
And now let's think, too,
about a binary search.
Let's say we have this input of people.
They're kind of shuffled a little bit.
We have Aaron, Amulya, Alex,
Alyssa, Cecelia, Lucas, and Ramya,
and we're doing binary search.
We're still looking for Alyssa.
And if we were to do binary search
on this data set, where would
we first look?
Well, the middle.
So it took us only one
step to find Alyssa here.
So there's another question we
could ask, then, which is this.
Well, first, how many steps did the
algorithm take, did each one take?
Well, we talked about how linear search
took one, and so did binary search.
But in general, we could
also ask this question.
What's the fewest number of steps
the algorithm could ever take?
So with big O notation, we talked
about what's the greatest number.
But now we're asking, what's the fewest
number the algorithm could ever take?
And in this case, you could
kind of simplify things
and say, what happens if we get lucky?
Well, it turns out that in
linear search, the best,
fewest number steps we
could take is just one.
Our person is at the
very front of our list.
And in binary search,
it's similarly just one.
Our person is at the middle of our list.
So in this case, it's still the same.
Linear search and binary search, the
best case, they only take one step.
Now, in general, as
we just talked about,
computer scientists don't tend to
think about one particular input.
They think about general inputs, what
happens in just the overall best case.
And we could say even if we had 10
people, 100 people, 1,000 people,
the best case scenario,
each of these algorithms
would take one and only one steps.
And that's where this idea
of omega notation comes in.
So omega notation says, what,
given any kind of input,
would be the fewest number
of steps we would ever take?
And now here, too, is this idea that
omega notation doesn't even quite
care if it takes two, or three,
or 10 steps in the best case.
If it takes some fixed
number of steps, it only
is going to be written as omega of 1.
And there are other notations
we'll consider, too,
which I'll show you in just a bit.
But consider for now that even if it
took a fixed number of steps, 10, 100,
1, all of those would be
written as basically omega of 1,
indicating it takes some certain
number of fixed steps in the best
possible case.
So questions, then, on these algorithms?
I see a question here.
"Are linear search and binary
search the only algorithms
that we can search data with?"
Certainly not.
There are many researchers
who are working
on other algorithms we
can use to search data,
and you might find some that are
suited for a particular use case.
And from lecture, you
might have recalled
David saying that there's
often a trade-off, let's say,
between space and time.
You could perhaps have an
algorithm that uses a lot of space,
but could perhaps be a little
bit faster in searching something
because it uses so much space.
Good questions.
A question about can
we define an algorithm.
So it's a good question here.
What even is an algorithm to begin with?
We often say an algorithm is simply a
set of steps to accomplish some task,
and those steps have to
be very clearly defined.
Like in linear search, we look at the
first person, then the next person,
then the next person until
we get to the very end.
Good questions here.
Any others so far?
OK.
So here's a question for you all, then.
Suppose that you are
creating a new algorithm
and you want to assess its runtime.
That is, how quickly does it run.
You find out that the fewest steps
this algorithm will ever take
is two, and only two.
And now question is, what is the big
omega notation for this algorithm?
Keeping in mind what we've just
discussed, suppose, in the best case,
this algorithm takes two steps.
What would be the omega
notation for this algorithm?
I'm seeing a few answers here, which
is actually what I had hoped for.
So I'm seeing some saying
it would be omega of 1
and some saying it would be omega of 2.
So if we go back here, maybe
we wouldn't have omega (1).
But we instead, have omega (2).
And I think it's a good intuition.
If you know that the best case will
take you two steps, it kind of just
makes sense to write omega of 2.
But it turns out that computer
scientists, by convention,
like to think of things as being on
the order of some number of steps.
And whether it takes two, three, four,
if it takes some fixed number of steps,
we'll say it operates in
omega of 1 to symbolize
that it just takes some finite
number of steps in the best case.
So not omega of 2, but instead, omega
of 1 by convention in this case.
So some other notations
you might see as you go off
and learn more about
algorithms are these here.
So on the furthest left-hand side,
you'll see the big O notation.
The worst case, if you will.
So you'll have algorithms
that, in the worst case,
take some fixed number of steps.
They'll be in O(1).
There are other algorithms, like
we just saw binary search, that
operate in big O of log(N).
They keep dividing problems in
half, and half, and half again.
There are still others
that operate in O(N).
That means they have to take a look
at every individual element they
might be searching for.
And then there are some that
operate in big O of N squared,
where for every element, they have
to take that number of element steps
before they can move on to the next
one, and the next one, and the next one.
And in general here,
we don't really care
if it's big O of N squared plus
another 10 steps at the end.
In general, we care
about the biggest term.
N squared, N, log(N), or 1.
And same thing for omega notation here.
But now thinking about not
the worst case, but the best
case, or the fewest number of steps
the algorithm could ever take.
And a question here is, well, let's
say the algorithm takes maybe 100
steps in the worst case.
What would that be?
Well, it kind of depends now.
If the algorithm takes 100
steps in the worst case,
we have to ask ourself not so how many
steps the algorithm took in that case,
but instead, how the steps scale.
So if the algorithm will always
take 100 steps, and only 100 steps,
in the worst case, that
would actually be O(1),
because it's some fixed number of steps.
If, though, I were to
add one more element
and you would then need to do 101
steps, or if I added two elements
and you had to do 102 steps, that would
be an example of an algorithm in O(N).
Because for every element I
add, I have to do one more step.
Questions, too, on these notations?
A question about encountering
algorithms in other languages,
like Python, for instance, as
you'll see later on in CS50.
So certainly there's this idea
that we can take most any algorithm
and translate it into,
really, any other language.
So for the first few weeks of
CS50, you'll be using C. Later on,
you'll use Python.
You can take most any
of these algorithms
and put them into any
language you'd like.
Good questions here.
OK, so let's try actually putting
some of this into practice.
And so the very first problem this week
is one called sort, in which you're
given some various sorting algorithms.
So we've talked here about
searching algorithms, but now
let's transition to thinking
about sorting algorithms.
So in lecture, we saw three
different sorting algorithms,
and here they are, along with their
big O and big omega notations.
So notice here that we
have merge sort, which we
saw was among the fastest of our sorts.
You can see that merge sort has
a big O notation of O(Nlog(N)).
And the same thing for
its omega notation.
Big omega of N times log(N).
Now, this is faster than
selection sort and bubble sort.
So we'll see selection sort here.
It was big O of N squared.
And bubble sort was
also big O of N squared.
Now, the omega notation for
selection sort and bubble sort
is also omega of N squared.
But for bubble sort, omega of N.
So actually, I said earlier that
merge sort is faster than these two.
But can you think of a scenario
where you might actually
want to use bubble sort
as opposed to merge sort?
What scenario we might want to use
bubble sort instead of merge sort.
There is a case where
bubble sort is faster.
Seems like it's faster if
we are in one of our cases
that seems one of our best cases.
If we're talking about
sorting algorithms,
well, if we know our data is close to
being sorted, and we just want to check
is it sorted or is it not, bubble sort
could be a good way to do that faster,
in this case, than merge sort.
And we know this looking
at the notation here.
We see omega of N for bubble
sort and omega of N times log N.
So that is, for every step we
do, we have to add in another log
N steps in merge sort.
But for bubble sort, we don't have
to actually do that in this case.
So I find it helpful to see
these things in a bit of a chart.
And the sorting problem
asks you to figure out
the identities of three mystery sorts.
So here, you're given
sort1, sort2, and sort3,
and your job is to
time them and see which
algorithm each sort might be using.
And one approach here is to think
about, like big O and big omega
notation, the best and the worst cases.
Give them those inputs and see
how long it takes them to run,
and then compare them.
Compare those run times
and see which one you think
might best characterize the
algorithm you are just testing.
So here, our goal will be to fill in
a chart that looks a bit this, where
we have a reversed 50,000 numbers.
This is the worst possible case.
Our numbers are in
the exact wrong order.
We'll go through and time
each of our algorithms
and see, perhaps, which one runs the
fastest, which ones run the slowest.
And we'll do the same thing,
but now given a sorted list.
Our numbers are in the
best possible condition.
They're already sorted for us.
And we'll ask that same question.
How long, in general, did
each one seem to take?
And so by timing our sorts, we'll be
able to figure out do they seem to run
more equivalently to big O of N squared,
or O(Nlog(N)), or something in between?
So in this case, let's actually
go back to Visual Studio Code.
And I will restart mine here.
Once you connect to yours, you'll
be able to actually download
some of the distribution
code for the sort problem.
And you'll be given, in this case,
three different sorting programs
along with the inputs I just mentioned.
So I'll wait for mine to start here.
But our goal will be to look at each
of those three sorting algorithms,
time them, and make note
of, let's say, which
one might be most equivalent
to the three algorithms
we just discussed so far.
So it seems my code space
is ready to go here.
Let me hide a few things
to get out of your way.
And let me show you
where I have my files.
So if you download them, you
should be able to see them
in your very own folder called Sort.
And I'll use this command called
cd to change directory into Sort.
I'll hit Enter.
And now here, I see my
prompt changes into sort.
I can type ls again, and now I'll
see some various text files, along
with my three sorting programs,
sort1, sort2, and sort3.
So now let me show you
what's inside answers.txt.
I'll say code answers.txt.
And now I'll see what
I'm supposed to do.
I'm supposed to identify which
algorithm each of these sorts uses.
So sort1, for instance, could use--
well, it could use merge sort.
Or it could use, let's say, bubble sort.
It could be any of these things.
My goal is to type it in and
figure out which one this--
which algorithm this sort is using.
And then down below, type in
why I think that's the case.
So let's try timing these, given
the best and worst case inputs,
and seeing how well each one does.
So I'll go to my terminal here.
And if you read through
the problem specification,
it'll tell you that you can
time these sorts using this.
You can say time, and then followed
by the command to execute the sort.
So in this case, I want to run sort1.
I can type ./sort1 and give it either
the best or the worst case scenario.
Maybe I'll give it the
worst case to begin with.
I'll say, let's give sort1 a
reversed list of 50,000 numbers,
and just time it and
see how well it does.
So I'll hit Enter and
I'll see it's thinking,
maybe sorting this list for me.
And now down below, I can see how
long it took to take all 50,000
of these numbers and put
them in sorted order.
So it seems sort1 took
about 4.64 seconds.
And you're given three
different times here.
Real, user, and system time.
In general, you'll care
about just the real time,
how long did it take based
on a stopwatch, in this case.
So I can go back to my answers.txt and
I could say, well, I'll just make note.
sort1 seemed to take--
takes 4.64 seconds in worst case.
Or maybe let's be more particular.
To sort reversed list like this.
Now, I might also care about how this
algorithm performs in the best case.
So I'll go back to my terminal and
I'll then say, let's time it again,
but use ./sort1, and now let's choose
the sorted list, sorted50000..txt.
And hit Enter and see how well it does.
Now, that was a lot faster.
That only took 0.3 seconds, about.
So I'll go back to my answers
page and I'll write that down.
I'll say it takes 0.33
seconds to sort a sorted list.
All-righty.
And I could keep going here.
And if you're watching this not-live,
I encourage you to pause the video
and go through and time the other sorts.
If you are here live, we'll go
through and time these ourselves
and put them all together
in our answer.txt.
So let's keep going.
I'll go ahead and say,
I will run ./sort2 now.
But I want to time it. time ./sort2.
Let me give it the sorted 50,000--
actually, the reversed 50,000 numbers.
See how long it takes.
That was pretty quick.
So I'll say it takes 0.27
seconds to sort reversed list.
Let's try again, doing not
reversed, but now sorted.
That was still pretty quick.
So it takes 0.45 seconds
to sort a sorted list.
And now I'll try sort3 now.
Oops.
Let me move this down to here.
Let's try sort3.
I'll say, give sort3
the reversed 50,000.
See how long that takes.
A little slower.
I'll say it takes 2.25
seconds to sort reversed list.
And now I'll try sort3
with my sorted list.
Still took a little while.
Let's say it takes 1.99
seconds to sort a sorted list.
And now I'll zoom out here so
we can see all of our numbers.
And now keep in mind that we don't
care so much about the milliseconds.
Right?
It doesn't quite matter if
it took 10 milliseconds here,
or 10 milliseconds there.
We care more about how
each algorithm performed
in the best and the worst case.
And we'll keep in mind what we know
about our algorithms over here.
So it seems merge sort,
if I look at this list,
is generally pretty fast in both cases.
Right?
Selection sort seems to be pretty slow
in both cases, both my reversed list
and my sorted list.
Bubble sort, though, seems
to be slow in the worst case,
but actually pretty
quick in the best case.
So let's take a look,
then, at our numbers.
Here, if we look at sort2,
it seems like this one
was pretty quick in both cases.
It took less than a second
to sort a sorted list
and to sort a reversed list.
So knowing what we
know about merge sort and how it
performs in both best and worst cases,
maybe this one is probably merge sort.
So I'll say merge sort here.
Now let's consider the other two.
I have this one, sort1, that took
over-- it was almost 5 seconds to sort
of reversed list.
But then it took less than a
second to sort a sorted list.
Now, knowing what we know about
our algorithms, which one does this
seem to be?
It seems likely to be
bubble sort, because we saw,
if I go back to our notations here,
that bubble sort was big O of N squared,
but big omega of N. And
N is certainly faster
than N squared when it
comes to these notations.
And now the final one, we could say,
well, by process of elimination,
it's probably going
to be selection sort.
But we could also say here,
well, it took about 2 seconds
to sort the reverse list and a similar
amount of time to sort the sorted list.
So maybe it's going to be,
in this case, selection sort.
Because we know, based
on our chart here,
that selection sort
takes out the same amount
of time in the best and the worst cases.
So I'll fix my typo here.
And now we have our mystery solved of
which algorithms these sorts are using.
Now, questions, then, on our process
or our selection of these algorithms?
A good question here just for people
who are learning computer science.
Is it good to practice
making these algorithms?
I would say it's certainly
good practice to actually write
the code for these algorithms
just so you can get a hand--
get an experience of what it
is each one is actually doing.
So it actually is helpful, I think,
to write things like linear search,
like binary search, things bubble
sort, merge sort, selection sort.
Because in doing so, you get an
appreciation for exactly the process
each one is following.
Let's see.
A question here.
Why is the reversed list--
why is sorting the reversed list
faster than sorting the sorted list?
So if I look here for
merge sort, it seems
this first case to the reversed
list was faster than how long it
took to sort the sorted list.
And that doesn't make any sense to me.
If I know that this is
the worst case, and this
is supposed to be the best
case, well, why is the best case
slower than the worst case?
Turns out, when we're actually
timing things in our computer,
there are other processes going on
that could interfere with these things
and make them take a little bit
slower or a little bit faster,
depending on the time that I run them.
So this is really just a
single data point here.
And this is why computer
scientists don't time things
in terms of milliseconds.
They time things in
terms of number of steps
their algorithm might actually take
in the best and the worst cases.
So we don't have to consider here
whether our computer's running
some of their software.
Just a single sort in this case.
OK.
So that will be our recap, then, on
our searching and sorting algorithms.
Hopefully you've gotten a taste of
big O notation and big omega notation.
Let's start now adding another tool to
our toolkit, this one called structs.
So at the end of lecture, or
towards the middle, I believe,
we learned about this
idea of a structure.
And a structure is great.
We want to create our very own
data type to use in our program.
It's not quite a full
data type, but it is a way
to encapsulate information so we
can refer to it with only one name.
So let's take, for
instance, this picture here.
We have two candidates
for US government.
And I want to ask you what might you
use to describe these candidates.
If you were going to store
information about them,
what information would you store?
Could be these two.
Could be any candidate in any
country for a political office.
I'm seeing maybe their age,
their party, their name.
Maybe the contact info
direct to Joe Biden's desk.
Maybe the number of votes
they got is a good one.
So there's lots of things we could
represent about this candidate.
And up until now, we've been able
to create individual variables that
could store this information.
But a struct allows us to combine
these pieces into a single one
and refer to it all, in
general, as some candidate.
So let's take an example here.
Let's say in C we saw this syntax,
typedef struct curly brace string name;
int votes; end curly brace candidate;.
This looks a little confusing at first.
We can break it down to figure
out what we're doing here.
So let's say first here
we have some syntax
to create a new quote, unquote, "type."
It's not a full type
like an int is, but it
does allow us to say we're
going to consider name and votes
part of some individual
piece of data in our program.
And here is that full text here.
One other piece of syntax
is this, the typedef.
This is saying that we're going to take
this combination of a string called
"name" and an integer called
"votes" and call it something else,
in this case, a candidate, so we
could reuse this idea of candidate
throughout our file.
And then inside here, we have what
we call the members of the structure.
That is, what kind of data are we going
to encapsulate or consider to be part
of what it means to be a candidate?
So here, we chose just the name and
the number of votes for a candidate.
But you could very well have in this
case their age, their party, and so on.
So all we're doing here is saying
that these two pieces of data,
one a string we'll call
"name" and one an integer.
we'll call "votes," are now
part of this more general data
type called a "candidate."
And we can reuse that type
throughout our program.
So let's consider here actually
making our very own candidate.
So we'll go through here and say, let's
create a candidate called president.
Let's create a candidate
called president.
And we'll, on the right-hand side,
have this picture of a candidate here.
So see on the right-hand side.
Now, if we want to give this candidate
a name, we could do so like this.
We could say president.name equals
whatever name we have for them.
So in this case, Samia.
And now, if we want to give
them some number of votes,
we could say president.votes
now gets the value 10.
So notice here, on the line
below our typedef struct,
we're saying candidate space president.
So this looks a little similar
to our prior syntax, where we're
able to say maybe int x or string name.
But now we're using this name candidate
as kind of a type name, if you will,
for this new variable we've
created called president.
And if I want to assign some value to
the different members of president,
I could simply access
them using the name.
the member's name.
So president.name,
president.votes, and so on.
And even further here, I could try to
create my very own array of candidates.
I could say in this case,
candidate candidates bracket 4.
Now, to be clear here,
what I've done is I've
created an array called candidates,
plural, that stores four elements.
But what elements will it store?
Well, in this case, those
that are candidates.
So you can see the
type still comes first,
but then we have the name, followed
by brackets and the candidates here.
So questions, then, on the syntax of
these arrays or these structs here?
Is it possible to have a struct
made out of other structs?
I don't quite know.
I don't see why it wouldn't be the
case that you couldn't do that.
Yeah.
I would try it out and see.
I don't have as much
experience to know about that,
but you should definitely
try it out and see.
Let's see.
Other questions here, too.
Question.
"Can we change the data in
there if needed during runtime?"
So that's a good question.
If I go back to this candidate
that we called president here,
the question is, could I change
the data inside of it later?
So to be clear, I could assign different
values to this candidate's members
like candidate.name or candidate.votes.
I could change those
throughout my program.
But I really shouldn't be able
to add new members to my struct
as my program is running.
So up top here, you'll see we defined
a candidate as having a string called
name and an integer called votes.
I have to do that at the
very start of my program.
I can't change that, really,
when my program is running.
Good question.
All right.
And a question here.
Could we just use candidate.name
instead of president.name,
the structure name instead of the
variable name we just created?
So it's worth mentioning
here that the struct
candidate is more so not a variable
we've created, but a template for one.
So every new candidate we
create has to have its own name.
But it will all be, let's see,
inherited from this idea of a candidate.
So candidate president,
candidate vice president
We could maybe have a
candidate called candidate,
but we'd still have to instantiate that
by saying candidate space candidate,
the type name, then the variable name.
And probably in that case, best
not to confuse the variable name
with the structure name.
So I would probably
avoid that altogether.
OK.
So let's get some practice with this.
And we'll have a task here, which
is to find a candidate who's
gotten the most votes.
So what we'll do is first
create an array of candidates,
and we'll search the array,
perhaps using linear search,
to find the votes most awarded
to any single candidate.
And then once we know that, we'll
print out the candidate's name.
And our goal here is to get some
practice using the syntax of structs.
So I'll go back to my
code space, and now
let me pull up a file
I've already created.
This one, called, let's see, search.
c.
So I'll code search.c to pull it up.
And notice how I already
have some code in here.
So at the top, I've included my CS50
library and my standard I/O library.
I've defined for myself a struct
that has a name and a votes member,
and I've called it candidate.
Now, down below in main, I've created
myself an array of candidates.
This has a total of
three possible members.
I've defined this
constant here, a number
that can't change, and defined it as 3.
So now I have three candidates
that can go inside of this array.
Down below, I've defined their
name and the number of votes.
But now my goal is to find who
has the highest number of votes.
Or even before I do that, before I find
who has the highest number of votes,
I should probably find what the highest
number of votes actually even is.
So the question really
boils down to, how
could we use linear search to
find this highest number of votes?
And now let me ask you,
what kind of structure
might be good to search this array?
If I wanted to loop through every
candidate, what kind of structure
might be good?
I'm seeing a for loop,
so I could do for.
And I know I want to go from, let's say,
the very first candidate, all the way
to the final candidate.
So I'll start my index, i, at 0.
And I'll say I'll keep
going while i is less
than, well, however
many candidates I have,
which turns out to be num_candidates,
which I defined up above right here.
So now I want to increase
i by 1 each time that I go.
And now, inside this
loop, what should I do?
My goal is to find the
highest number of votes,
so maybe I should first
make a variable that
defines that number of votes for me.
I could say, create an integer.
Let's call it highest votes.
And we'll set it equal--
well, at the beginning, we don't
quite know what it will be.
Maybe it could be 0 to begin with.
So now we have this variable,
highest_votes, that's equal to 0.
But now I need to ask,
under what scenario
should I update highest_votes
as I loop through my candidates?
When should I try to
update the highest_votes?
Let's say I look at Carter first.
Should I update highest_votes?
Seems like I should,
because Carter has 10 votes,
and our previous highest was 0.
So while I'm looping, I
could ask this question.
I could say if, let's say,
candidates bracket i, that is,
the candidate in my list at the
index i, if their number of votes,
candidates bracket i .votes, is
greater than what we've currently set
as the highest number of votes,
well, I want to update it.
So I'll say highest_votes then
becomes candidates bracket i .votes.
So now what I've done
is said that if I ever
find a candidate who has a number of
votes greater than my current highest
number of votes, I want to
update what I'm considering
to be the highest number of votes.
So let's walk through
this once step by step.
So first highest_votes is 0.
I'll look first at Carter.
10 is greater than 0, so our highest
number of votes will now be 10.
I'll look at the next
candidate this one is Yulia.
And I'll say, well,
is 12 greater than 10?
It is.
So my new highest number
of votes is now 12.
I'll then look at Inno, and I'll
ask, well, is 7 greater than 12?
It's not in this case.
So my highest number of votes
is still going to be 12.
And by the time I'm done,
highest votes should actually
equal the person with the highest--
or should equal the number
of votes that is the highest.
And to confirm this, I could say
printf("%i/n") for that integer format
code, and I'll print
out now highest_votes.
And let's try to make this program
and compile it and see what happens.
So I'll go back to my terminal and
I'll say make, in this case, search.
Seems like no errors.
I'll run ./search, and I'll get back 12
for the candidate who has that highest
number of votes.
OK, so that seems to
accomplish my very first task,
finding the highest number of votes.
What can I do now to print
the name of the candidate
with that highest number of votes?
Any ideas here?
I know the highest number.
I just want to see who
has that number of votes.
So maybe what I should do is do another
loop through my candidates array,
this time, asking, are you the
person who has the highest?
Are you the person who has the highest?
And if you are, I'll print
out your name as I go.
So let's try this.
I'll say for (int i = 0;).
i is less than my number
of candidates, i++.
I'm going to loop through
every candidate here,
and I'll ask this question now.
If candidates bracket i .votes,
the candidate at this index,
their number of votes, if that
is equal to highest_votes, well,
then I want to print out their name.
So I'll say printf, and I'll do
%s for that string format code,
and now I'll use candidates bracket
i .name to get the name of this
candidate.
So now what I've done is I've
looped through my entire array
asking this question,
does this candidate
have the highest number of votes?
And if they do, let me
print out their name.
So now let me go back and
make my program again.
I'll type make-- let's say make
search, and I'll run ./search,
and I'll see the highest
number of votes is 12.
And the candidate with that
number of votes is now Yulia.
So our goal here was to see
how we could use this structure
syntax to simplify things for us.
Now I have this structure called
candidate that I can use in my program.
And I can talk in the same
breath about a candidate's name
and the number of votes without
keeping those two things separate.
They're part of that same
structure I defined up
top, which can really help me
out as I run my program here.
So questions, then, on structs?
A question about repeating code.
So, in general, it is true
that you generally don't
want to repeat code in your programs.
In this case, though, I would argue
we can't avoid repeating code here.
So if I'm first trying to find
the highest number of votes
and print out that person's
name, you might think
I could do it all in the same loop.
But let's try this.
So I'll look first at my very first
candidate, whose name is Carter,
and I'll see that Carter's
votes for 10, well,
that's higher than I've previously seen.
It's greater than 0.
Right?
But should I print Carter's name yet
as having the highest number of votes?
I probably shouldn't.
I need to keep looking through my list.
I need to confirm that there's
no person with a higher
number of votes than Carter.
So that's why I need now two loops.
My first loop goes through and confirms
what is the highest number of votes.
My second loop goes
through and then confirms
what will be their candidate's
name, in that case.
Other questions, too?
Let's see.
That seems to be covering most
of the questions I'm seeing here.
OK.
So let's keep going, then.
And I think we have an
idea of what structs are.
But I want to give you one more tool
to use as you go off for this week,
and that is a tool called recursion.
So often, recursion tends to be a very
elegant solution to some problems.
And for that reason, we
have to try to find a way
to use recursion to solve problems.
The caveat here is that it's not
always the best way to do things,
but it can be elegant in certain cases.
And so we'll talk about
the kinds of problems
that actually have good potential
to be solved with recursion.
Now, one problem like this,
this idea of a factorial.
So if you aren't familiar,
a factorial is simply
a number where you take
that number and multiply it
by the number that's
1 less than it, then
the number that's 1 less than that,
and so on.
So let's take a look at an example here.
If I want to find 1 factorial,
well, that is just 1.
And the factorial is this
exclamation point here.
1 factorial equals 1.
But now if I want to find
2 factorial, 2 factorial
is simply 2 times 1, so 2
times the number less than it.
1, in this case.
Well, 3 factorial, that
is 3 times 2 times 1.
So again, start with that number,
3, multiply it by the number
1 less than it, then again, then again.
So 3 times 2 times 1.
And now 4 factorial.
What do you think that will be?
Well, 4 times 3 times 2 times 1.
So in this case, 1 factorial, 1;
2 factorial, 2; 3 factorial, 6;
and 4 factorial, about 24 in the end.
So what makes this problem
good for a recursive solution?
Well, you might notice
a bit of a pattern here.
And it gets a little more obvious
if I do this with these numbers,
if I slide them over.
So what do you notice in
particular about now 2 factorial?
Seems like to me that the
solution for 1 factorial
is part of the solution for 2 factorial.
That is, if 1 factorial is 1, we could
compute 2 factorial by taking 2 times
1 factorial.
And similarly, for 3
factorial, looks like to me
we could solve that problem by saying,
well, 3 factorial is just 3 times
2 factorial.
And same thing with 4.
We could say, well, 4
factorial is just 4 times
3 factorial, and so on and so forth.
So we're able to find a solution
to this problem in a smaller
version of that problem.
Until, of course, we get down
to 1 factorial, and we just say,
well, that is just 1 in the end.
So to make things a little more
concrete, in computer science,
we might give a few
names to these things.
So first, we'll say 4
factorial is equal to what?
Well, 4 times 3 factorial.
But this here is what we're
going to call our recursive call.
We're going to "kick
the can," as David said,
and say, well, we know the solution to
4 factorial is just 4 times 3 factorial.
Now, the question becomes,
what is 3 factorial?
Let's find out.
Let's take 3 factorial
and let's find it.
Well, 3 factorial is
just 3 times 2 factorial.
OK, well, what's 2 factorial?
Well, it's 2 times 1 factorial.
Well, what is 1 factorial?
Eventually, there has
to be some base case,
some definite solution to this problem.
In this case, we say 1
factorial has to be 1.
And when we get to
this base case, we can
use that to solve all prior problems.
In this case, I could say--
I could substitute 1 factorial for
1, going back up the call stack.
So now we have 2 factorial is 2 times
1, 3 factorial is 3 times 2 times 1,
and 4 factorial is just 4
times 3 times 2 times 1.
And to be clear here, the vocabulary
is that we're calling these functions
again, and again, and again.
And when we get to that base case, we
go back up what we call this call stack.
We're calling it a call stack
because we're calling functions,
and they kind of stack on top
of each other one at a time
before we resolve everything
all at once at the end.
So questions here on this recursive
solution to factorials before we
write our own implementation in C?
A question.
"Is recursion faster than
using regular loops?"
That is a great question.
So recursion is often seen as this
elegant way to solve problems,
and it certainly is, because
it is kind of magical when
you see how things click together
and how they work like this.
At the same time, recursion
isn't always necessarily faster.
So just because a problem
uses recursion doesn't mean
it's going to be always faster
than some other solution.
It just means we're trying to
solve the problem by first solving
a smaller version of that problem.
And eventually, we'll get to a base
case that we know the answer to.
Good question here.
OK, so let's now take the same idea.
And translate it into code.
So I'll go back to my code space
here, and I will get rid of search.c,
and I will instead find factorial.c.
So in the same way, we already
have some code here for us.
I have included the CS50
library and standard I/O. Now,
I've defined up here a
function called factorial.
This is the prototype for that function.
So notice here it takes an
integer called n as an input
and it gives us back
some integer in the end.
And that makes sense.
If I were to say, give me 4 factorial,
where I would give it some integer,
in this case 4, I would get
back some integer in the end.
In this case, 24.
Right?
So now in the main function,
I have a few components here.
The first is to get the
input from the user.
And it turns out that
in factorial land, you
can't take a factorial
of a negative number,
or at least we don't really
want to do that here.
It gets kind of complicated.
So we're only going to
focus on positive numbers.
We'll prompt the user again and
again for a positive number.
And then finally, we'll print
the factorial of that number.
In this case, we're going to print
out our %i format code, a placeholder,
if you will, but we'll substitute in
the result of calling the factorial
function given our n
input from the user.
But now, down below, seems like
factorial isn't quite implemented here.
So if you think you have a solution
to a problem that involves recursion,
it's often a good first
step to ask yourself,
what is the base case, what is
the scenario I know the answer to,
and try to code that one first.
So my question to you,
then, is, what is the answer
that we know the answer to in this case?
We know the answer to if n is 1.
So I could say if (n == 1),
like this, what do I return?
Well, I just return 1.
It's a very simple solution.
Right?
If n is 1, return 1.
And now down below--
well, I might actually first
call this my base case here.
Now, down below, what
is my recursive call?
If I go back to my template here,
we certainly have our base case now.
But what is our recursive call?
What should that look like?
Well, I know I could
return, let's say, n.
But n times what?
n times-- well, I could
just call factorial again.
I could say, return n times
factorial (n - 1), like this.
So now what I've done is I've
added that recursive call.
If I call factorial, given, let's
say, 4, I won't activate my base case.
4 is not 1.
But I will go down
here and say, I'm going
to calculate 4 times the factorial of 3.
And I'll go back to running
factorial again, and again,
and again, until I find that base case
and return, and return, and return,
and return, until I find
my ultimate answer here.
So let me prove to you this works.
So I'll go back to my terminal.
I'll say make factorial, and
then I'll say ./factorial.
And I'll give it, in this
case, 4, and I get 24.
I'll do it again.
I'll put in 3 and I'll get 6.
I'll put in 2, and in
this case, I'll get 2.
So now let's actually try to
prove to you that this works.
I will use debug50, which is what
we saw in an earlier lecture.
And in debug50, I can actually
step through my program step,
by step, by step to show you what's
happening underneath the hood
as this program runs.
So I will say let's pause
on line 17 right here,
and let's walk through
each step one at a time
to see what this recursive
function is actually doing.
So I will go back to my terminal
and I'll say, debug50 ./factorial,
like this.
And we'll wait for things to load here.
It might take a minute or two.
But as things come into picture
here, notice a few different areas.
So let me clean this up.
Notice in particular my Variables
portion and my Call Stack.
So recall what a variable is.
Simply some name that has some value.
And our call stack was some
new vocabulary we just learned.
That is, the idea of
calling some function,
then calling another function,
and calling another one,
until we have this stack of function
calls we need to resolve at the end.
So here, I'll tell my program--
I'm going to give it an
input of 3 in this case.
3, like this.
So now I'm paused at
this step in my program.
Notice here on the Variables
tab, that n is equal to 3,
like we thought it would be.
Now, instead of stepping over this,
that is, completing this function
and just printing the
result, let me step into this
and try to figure out what's going
on in this factorial function itself.
So I will choose, in
this case, step into.
And notice how here, I called
factorial for the first time.
This is the first time I've called
factorial. n is equal to 3 up top.
Now, is n equal to 1?
It's not.
So what our program will do is move on.
It will go down here and instead
return n times factorial(n - 1).
So let's step inside again and see what
this next call to factorial is doing.
I'll step into, and notice
a few things change.
Well, n is now 2, but I've added
one more step to my call stack.
Before I can resolve this one,
I need to resolve this one.
Right?
So I'll keep going.
n is now 2.
Is that equal to 1?
It's not.
We'll step over, and now I'll
say, n times factorial(n - 1).
I'm going to compute that next.
So 2 times factorial of 1.
I'll step into this again.
And notice my call stack again.
So before I can resolve
this first factorial call,
I have to resolve those that
are on top of it, the one for 2,
and now the one for 1.
So let's resolve this one here.
N equals 1.
Well, seems like this is not going
to be true, so I'll step over
and I'll now return 1.
Notice what happens here.
This call that we're currently
on, 2 factorial, when we return 1,
it'll go away, and it will just give
back to this call here that value 1.
So I will now step over.
Step over again.
And now I'll see I've completed
that call to factorial.
I was able to find that this call is
now 2 times 1, returning 2 times 1.
This call can now return-- it knows
that 2 factorial is 2 times 1.
I'll return.
Now, this one knows, well, what is
3 factorial but 3 times 2 times 1?
I'll return that, and
now I'm back up at main
and completing my program as a whole.
So that is our step-by-step walkthrough
of the recursive nature of factorial.
Now, it's OK if it
didn't come all at once.
And, in fact, I encourage you to do
the same thing on your own computer,
or even get out some pencil and paper
and just write stuff down and visualize
as you go through, and you'll hopefully
see the recursive nature of it, trying
to solve a smaller problem
and a smaller problem.
Once you get that base
case, all the other problems
become clearer as you go.
So questions, then, on this?
A question on, "In the call stack,
in what order do the calls execute?"
So you'll hear this more
later in the course,
but there's this idea of a
data structure called a stack.
And the key idea of a stack is
that the last thing you put in
is the first thing you
do, or that you see.
So in a call stack, the last
function I added was factorial.
That is, then, the first function I must
resolve before I can do anything else.
So you could imagine here
I call factorial once.
If I call factorial for 3, I then
end up calling factorial two more
times overall.
But what I have to do first is
resolve that very base case.
Then I can resolve the
2 factorial, then I
can resolve the 3 factorial,
until finally, I go back up here
and resolve main as a whole.
I hope that helped a little bit.
A question about the return 1 here.
So if I scroll down here, we said
return 1 for this factorial call.
And the question was, why didn't
it kill the entire program?
Why didn't it end the entire program?
Well, notice how return here
ends my given function call.
So remember how we called
factorial a total of three times?
That final time we called factorial,
we triggered our base case
and simply returned 1 without
making any new recursive calls.
And as soon as we did
that, we knew, then,
how to resolve the other recursive calls
that we tried to finish beforehand.
And a clarifying question here.
"Is main always resolved last?"
Yes, it is, because it is
our very first function
we call when we run our program.
Other questions here, too?
All right.
So if there are no more
questions I'm seeing here,
why don't we call that a
wrap for this week's section?
Certainly, you've gotten a lot
of new tools in your tool kit
to solve problems, which you certainly
solved this week's problem set.
I wish you all the best as you
go through and finish this week,
and I'll hopefully see you next time.
Thank you all for coming in.