CARTER ZENKE: OK.
Well, hello one and all, and
welcome to CS50'S Week 6 session.
My name is Carter Zenke.
I'm the course's
Preceptor here on campus.
And the goal of these sections is to
help you bridge the gap between lecture
and this week's problem set.
So this week, we learned
all about this new language
called Python, which is hopefully a
little bit more high level than C,
a little bit easier to
grasp the syntax of.
So I hope you are as
excited as I am to dive in
and learn even more about how Python
can serve us in this week's problem set.
Now I have a few topics for today.
These are among them.
We'll talk about Python
generally, but focus
in particular on this
idea of strings and loops,
and this new type, if you
will, called a dictionary,
where we can store keys and values.
We'll also, at a higher
level, talk about the idea
of a library, where we can actually have
some code somebody else has written,
including that in our own Python code.
And then, towards the end, we'll talk
about file I/O, or file input and file
output, in particular, how
we can read data from files
and write data to files.
And even more particularly, talking
about CSVs, or comma-separated value
files.
So let's jump right in here and
talk about strings to begin with.
Strings, as we saw earlier,
are these collections of text.
We have individual characters,
like A, and B, and C.
But if we wanted to string those
characters together, like into a word,
let's say, we would get
what we call a string.
And one of my favorite examples
of strings in the real world
are really just these books.
And one of my favorite
books as a kid was
this one called Goodnight Moon, where,
if you're not familiar, basically,
you get to read a book and say goodnight
to the various household objects,
like the fireplace, the picture
of the cow jumping over the moon,
and finally, the moon itself.
And there are a few lines in
this book, like the following,
"In the great green room,"
is how this book begins.
And actually, I think it's interesting
now how we can take these strings,
and we have things like AI that can
actually generate pictures for us
from these strings.
So just for fun, I gave this string to
this model called DALL-E 2 by OpenAI,
and here's what it came up with.
In the great green room gave
me a room with some blinds,
and you see some green
in the back there.
I gave it that next piece of
text, this string here, which is,
"There was a telephone
and a red balloon."
And here's what DALL-E
came up with here,
a telephone attached to a red balloon,
so kind of creative in some ways.
So that's all just
for fun, but I thought
we'd see the applications
of strings, and also
where they can come
from, too, in this case,
from some of our
favorite childhood books.
So let's compare then how C and
Python actually work with strings.
And here is one example where we see
C on the top and Python on the bottom.
And I'm curious, if you're
here live, go ahead and tell me
a few differences you spot.
Let's play a find-the-difference game.
What do you see different
between the top and the bottom?
I'm seeing there's no more semicolon
in Python, so that's correct.
Generally, in Python, you shouldn't
be ending your lines with a semicolon.
There's no what we call char star, or
this idea of a pointer to a character.
So in C, we have to tell C that
a string is literally a pointer
to the first character of a string.
In Python, though, it's more abstract.
It's a higher level.
It doesn't care too much about pointers.
We just tell it we want
this string in general.
You go figure it out and find out where
to put the pointers to make that string
to begin with.
Another observation here
is that we didn't even
have to declare the data type.
So up above, you'll see we
had this variable called text,
and we declared it as a type char
star, or a pointer to a character.
Down below, there's no
type declaration at all.
Python just infers for
us what type we might
want to use in this particular case.
So those are a few key
differences between C and Python
here that you'll keep
in mind as you go off
and work now in Python,
and less so in C.
Here's another example here.
Here's comparing two strings.
So let's again play spot the difference.
Let's look up above and down
below, where the above is in C,
and the bottom is in Python.
What do you see different here?
I see no curly braces.
That is certainly a big
difference between C and Python.
So C, up above, specifies
things like the blocks
for an if statement, or
the blocks for a loop
by putting that code
inside of curly braces.
Python, though, focuses on indentation.
So notice how if I wanted
to have a block of code that
executes in response to this conditional
here, I have to indent it by one level.
Let's see, what else?
There are no parentheses,
so that's fair.
Up above, we had parentheses for our
if statement, down below, not so.
We also don't have to call
our very own function.
So up above, in C, we had to call
a function to compare two strings.
In Python, it just kind of infers
that if I want to compare two strings,
it better do, basically, the same
procedure that strcmp, up above, in C,
would do.
So it's much more, I
would say, intuitive.
In this case, no need to
call any particular function.
Python just knows what we'd
like to do in this case.
And let's maybe do one more here.
The code above, in C,
and the code down below,
in Python, trying to access
some character of a string.
Let's play spot the difference here.
And I'm seeing some hesitancy.
There's no difference.
So that's the idea here, is that in
C, in Python, these are both the same.
In order to access some individual
character of some string,
we simply use the
bracket notation and put
in the index of the character
you want to actually get.
So for instance, text bracket 0 would
give us that very first character
in this string called text.
Text bracket one would give
us that second character,
and so on, and so forth.
In Python and C, these are
both what we call zero indexed.
So let's pause here and
ask, what questions do you
have on some of these differences
so far between C and Python?
Any that I can answer while we're here?
I'll give folks just a minute to think.
A good question I see, so do
we not have pointers in Python?
I think it is possible.
I'm going to go out on a limb
here and say, in base Python,
you're not going to be
dealing with pointers at all.
There are probably ways to work with
pointers in Python if you want to.
But the creators of Python
made it so you do not
have to deal with pointers at all.
A good question, how does
Python know when a string ends?
So in C, we saw that
strings end with what
we called the NUL character,
N-U-L, which denotes
the end of this particular string.
The fascinating thing about
Python is that it probably
does the very same thing,
that strings in Python
do have, underneath the hood,
pointers to the initial character,
and a NUL character at
the end of that string.
But what Python does
for us is it allows us
to not think about
these underlying details
and instead think at a higher level.
So at the end of the day, in terms of
our actual memory inside a computer,
Python and C might be
doing similar things.
But we can tell Python to do those
things with much less precision,
and in this case, a little more
intuition and taking advantage of some
of its syntax it offers us at the end.
And one final question we'll
take here, if I go back
to this particular comparison,
we said that Python infers
the type of this text is a string.
And that's because this input
function here returns to us a string.
So this function input always
returns to us a string.
And it's up to us to cast it, to change
it to an integer or some other type
if we want to at the end.
OK, so let's keep going.
And one of the nice
features about Python
is that it's able to have
a lot of built-in functions
that simplify things that we saw in C.
And some of these built-in functions
we can use using Python's
new dot notation.
So we saw this a bit
in lecture, but let's
say I want to get some
input from the user.
And here is my line of code to do so.
I say, let's make this
new variable called text.
And I'm going to set it equal to the
result of calling the function input.
And let's say the user types in
this particular string on the right.
Now what do you notice
that's a bit, well, not so
clean about the string on the right?
What's the matter with it?
Yes, there are spaces at
the start and the end of it.
So often when I'm filling out a form,
I might be doing so very quickly.
And I might actually add in a space at
the end, some spaces at the beginning
just by a typo on my keyboard.
So it's common that users will actually
give us data that is dirty in this way,
that it has extra spaces, it's not
capitalized correctly, and so on.
So there's this
interesting Python function
that we could use that
looks a bit like this.
I could say text.strip, text.strip.
And what would happen is,
I would take that same text
and I would then convert it to this.
So notice the difference here?
I had spaces at the beginning
and spaces at the end.
With text.strip, I can strip those and
be left with just the characters that
are inside this particular string.
So the purpose of dot strip is to
take out beginning and trailing
whitespace characters.
Now notice here how strip isn't
actually a standalone function.
I didn't say, strip, and
then gave the input as text.
I instead said, text.strip.
So this is Python's dot
notation coming into play.
And we'll see why this actually
happens in just a little bit.
Let's focus on some
other ones we could use
that are a bit handy for
working with strings.
Here we have, let's say, a new
kind of input from the user.
And what looks wrong about this one?
The capitalization is
just a little bit off.
I think they might have
had some typos here.
So one way to fix this is
to use the dot capital--
or, well, in this case, the dot
lower method, or dot lower function.
So I could say text.lower,
and what would that do?
Well, it would convert these
characters all to lowercase.
So I would take this
with mixed capitalization
and then bring it down to all lowercase.
And as I just said before, we also
have this one we could use called
dot capitalize, where dot
capitalize takes a string
and makes the first character only
uppercase, so some options there.
Now with dot lower, we
also have dot upper.
And there's actually a lot of
these we can ever use in Python.
We can find all of these in
the Python documentation.
So one note of caution here is that
when I actually do text.capitalize,
I need to reassign the
result back to my variable,
otherwise the changes
won't actually stay.
So, for example, I'll go
back to my code space.
And I'll open up here, let's say
this one is just capitalize.py.
And I'll have the same piece of code.
I'll say, text equals input,
and maybe for cleanliness sake,
I'll say, Enter a string.
And then I'll say, text.input,
or text.capitalize,
like this, hoping to
uppercase that text.
Then I'll say, text.
I'll say, let's print out
text here to see the result.
I'll say, python of capitalize.py to
run this program, as we saw in lecture.
And now I'll say, In
THE GREAT green Room.
And if I hit Enter, hopefully I should
see this text being capitalized,
such that that very first character
at the beginning is capital,
but all the rest are lowercase.
So I'll hit Enter here.
And do you see any changes?
I don't seem to.
So I think what we should do is
say, text equals text.capitalized,
so reassign the capitalized
version of text back to text,
and then print the
result. So let's try this.
I'll say python of capitalize.py, and
I'll say, In the GREAT GREEN room.
Hit Enter, and now I see
my text being capitalized.
So let's again ask, what
questions do we have?
We've seen a few what
we call string methods.
A question, can we still
make functions in Python?
We certainly can.
So you'll be able to see
in this week's problem set
some of the syntax via which you can
make your very own functions in Python.
A question about reassignment being
necessary for dot upper and dot lower?
Yes.
So if I were to use dot lower or dot
upper, which would make these lowercase
or uppercase all
characters respectively,
I should still reassign the
result if I want to change text
as a whole in my program.
Question about dot strip.
Does it allow us to, let's say, take
out a middle whitespace character?
So let's try this.
It's no longer capitalizing, but
I'll still say, python capitalize.py.
I'll enter a string, like H, and
then space, ell, space, o, hit Enter,
and I still see the
whitespace in the middle.
So strip only removes white space at the
beginning and at the end of our string,
or what we call the leading
and trailing whitespace.
A question, can we make our own dot
notation functions, or more precisely,
methods?
You could, and we'll see a bit
more about how you could just now.
So let's dive underneath the hood and
talk about where these dot functions,
dot methods actually come from.
So unlike in C, in Python, this string
is actually what we call an object.
So an object in programming is
basically some particular element
you can reuse throughout your code.
And it has accessible to it not just
certain values, like pieces of data,
but also, certain functions.
And we actually call
those, because they're
associated with an object, methods.
So functions associated with
objects are often called methods.
And for your own
benefit, Python actually
tells you all of the possible string
methods in the Python documentation.
So if you go to
Docs.Python.org, you'll be
able to see the entire
Python manual that tells you
all the possible methods, and functions,
and objects that are built into Python.
And if you're first encountering
this idea of an object,
I think it's a little bit abstract.
I said it was some entity you can
use multiple times in your code.
So I want to make it a little
more concrete for you, hopefully.
Now if you recall from an earlier
problem set, let's say, problem set 3,
I believe, we had this
idea of a candidate.
And do you remember how we
implemented the idea of a candidate?
What did we do in code
to create a candidate?
What did we do in code?
So we had the idea of
creating some kind of struct.
So in C, we had a struct that allowed
us to combine different data types.
We could have a string
for the candidate's name
and an integer for the number of votes.
And that, as a whole, was
what we called a candidate.
So to visualize here, we
had a single candidate,
and we gave that candidate some name,
which we accessed via candidate.name.
We also perhaps gave that
candidate some number
of votes, which we accessed
via candidate.vote.
So these are what we called attributes
of this struct, different data
values that were associated
with this idea of a candidate.
Now an object is very much like this.
We can assign it some particular
data that composes that object.
In this case, a
candidate could itself be
an object that has some
attributes, like name and votes.
But where things differ
is where we actually
allow us to have not just values,
but actually functions associated
with some particular object.
So let's say here, a str, which
is itself an object in Python,
the str represents a string, it has not
just certain attributes like a link.
It also has some functions associated
with it, like, in this case,
capitalize.
So you could think of it
as taking out a toolbox
and being able to modify this particular
value, the value it's storing.
You could think of this,
too, with dot lower.
This is another function,
another tool in your toolbox
by which you could update
this value of a string.
So, again, the key difference
here is that objects
allow us to have functions associated
with them and not just values,
as we saw with structs in C.
Let me pause here and ask for questions.
What questions do you have
after this high-level overview
of an object in Python?
Question, so lower is
actually a function?
It is, so lower is a function.
It takes as input, let's say,
the value that the string holds,
the text that's inside of it.
And it returns to us the
lowercase version of that.
In that case, it is a function but
it's also associated with an object.
I can't use lower on anything.
I can only use it on strs.
So in that case, it is what we call
a method, a function associated
with some object, in this case.
Question, is int an object?
So a spoiler is that everything
in Python is an object.
So if you want to learn
more about this, you
could learn about
object-oriented programming.
But Python is an
object-oriented language.
You'll often learn more about that as
you take higher level computer science
courses and get into differences
in how we can actually
program things and design languages.
Let's see, are capitalize and
upper the very same functions?
They're different.
So upper takes the entire string
and uppercases all characters.
Capitalize takes that string and
uppercases only the very first
character.
So think of it like you'd
capitalize a sentence,
the very first character is capitalized.
Question, is there a summary somewhere
of the most important objects
and their associated methods?
Yes, that is called the
Python Documentation.
So if you go to
Docs.Python.org, you'll be
able to find all of the
important, really, actually,
not just the important ones,
really every possible object
and its associated methods
in the Python Documentation.
OK, so let's keep going.
And I think now that we have this idea
of strings, what we can do with them,
it's also interesting to
bring in loops to the mix.
So loops, we saw earlier, are about
going through some piece of code
multiple times.
And actually, in Python we get access
to a very special kind of loop.
So in lecture, we saw for
loops and while loops.
But I find this one to be maybe the most
exciting for new Python programmers.
So this loop looks a bit like this.
For c in text, print c.
And I'm going to ask
you in the chat, what
do you think is going to happen here?
What will we see on our screen?
If we have the following input,
which is, in the great green room,
what do you think we'll see?
Yeah, so I'm seeing
people saying that we're
going to see the string printed
out character by character.
Now how would this happen?
Well, Python just has
a special kind of loop
called this for blank in blank loop,
where I can simply take something
like a string and say, for blank, it
could be c, could be x, could be y.
And then I could, let's
say, print that value.
And every iteration of
the loop, the value of C
will update to be the next, let's say,
character in this string, for instance.
So to visualize this, I decided
to call this element c So
on the very first
iteration of this loop,
c will equal capital I. On
the very next iteration,
c will equal N. On the next iteration,
c will equal space, and then T, and then
H, and so on.
Now it's not special I called this c.
I could have called it x, or y, or z.
As long as I'm being consistent
and say, for x in text,
print x, or for y in text, print
y, I'll get the very same result.
So that's how we can go
through character by character
and look at these strings.
Now there's one more thing we could do
that we could use these types of loops
for.
They're not just good for breaking
apart strings in individual characters.
They're also good for
working with lists.
So let's say I want to take this
text, In the great green room,
and I want to put every individual
word into its own string,
but then have those strings be
part of some list, let's say.
So if I use text.split,
what this will do
is break apart this string at
all of the whitespace characters,
in this case, the space characters.
And I'll say, get this list at the end.
The first element is In,
the next element is the,
the next element is great, and
so on, then green, then room.
So I've basically taken this
string, split it at all the spaces,
and now I have a list
of individual words.
And this kind of loop is good
for going through lists as well.
So I could say something
like, for word in words,
let's print that particular word.
And the result will be like this.
First word will equal
In, and I'll print In.
Then, word will update
and go to the next word.
And I'll print the, and
so on, and so forth.
I could go to great and print
great, and find at the very end,
I would print the entire piece
of text, but word by word.
So I'm seeing a few questions
here that I can answer.
Let's see, so then words
is not a string but a list.
That is actually true.
So in this case, when I take a
string, like text, and decide
to split it using the
string method split,
I get back a list of
the strings that were
found by splitting on a whitespace
character, in this case,
the space itself.
Does text.split always return a list?
Yes, it does.
So it will always return to us a
list, whether it's empty or not.
And a question here,
let me find it again.
So I don't have to specify
what I want c to equal?
I'll go back to this one here.
It's a good question.
So here it's kind of confusing.
I just magically said c, and
suddenly c popped into existence,
which is kind of what happened.
I could say for c in
text, and magically c
is now some variable I can use for
the duration of this particular loop.
So I can't use c on indented.
That's not part of this loop anymore.
But I can use c while I'm indented
inside of this particular for loop.
And in this case, Python
has some various heuristics
it uses to determine
what c should equal.
If I say for blank in some string, I'll
get back every individual character
in that string.
And whatever I say, like c, will
equal every individual character
in that string.
If, as we saw here, as we
saw here, I give it a list,
it will then equal every
individual element of that list,
if that makes sense.
Other questions here?
Can you declare c before the loop?
I believe-- not quite sure.
We can test it out.
I'll go over to my Python code here.
I'll say, code loop.py.
Let's say our text is
In the great green room.
And we wanted to figure out,
maybe c is first text bracket 0.
Then I'll say, for c in text, print c.
I'll say python loop.py.
I don't seem to get an
error, so I think you could.
My guess, though, is that it will
simply overwrite c, and set it first
equal to that very first character.
So it doesn't quite matter
what c is assigned before.
You're going to update it during
your loop at the very end.
So I hope that answers
your question there.
OK, what if we had a list of integers?
A good question.
It would still be the same thing.
I'd go through the list
element by element.
So we have a few rules here,
or a few pieces of advice.
So generally, Python's
for-in syntax helps
you iterate through components of what
we call an iterable, while referring
to them by some convenient name.
So before I said c,
and then I said words,
I could have used any name for those.
If the iterable, the thing I could
iterate over in a loop, is a list,
I'll iterate over every
element of that list.
And if it's a string, I'll iterate
over every character of that string.
So feel free to keep these
in mind as you work in Python
with these particular kinds of loops.
And indeed, this vocabulary
word called an iterable just
stands for anything we could
really have a loop over,
whether a string, or a list, or other
data types, other objects altogether,
too.
OK, so let's get into some practice.
Here I have several
files called text.py.
And we'll play a game where
I'll show you a loop in Python,
and you'll tell me what you
think should come out of it.
And we'll run that program and
see if our guess is correct.
So I'll go back to my terminal
and I'll code text0.py,
where I have this particular example.
So I'm curious, for those
of you who are here,
what do you think we'll see
if I run Python of text0.py?
Yeah, so I'm seeing
some good examples here.
Basically, we will see every
word printed to our screen.
So I'll say Python text0.py, hit Enter.
And now I see, In the great green room.
And now a question here
is, why are we seeing
these new lines, In, new line, the,
new line, great, new line, and so on?
Where do you think that's coming from?
So as you saw in lecture,
when we use print,
print automatically
appends a new line for us.
So when I say, for
word in text.split, I'm
taking this string called text, turning
it into a list of the individual words.
And then I'm calling every element just
this basic convenient name called word.
I'll print it out as I go.
So first, word will be equal
to In, then the, then great.
And as I print these out,
I'm printing out not just
In, or the, or great, I'm also printing
out the new line associated with it.
I could override this if I
say end equals nothing here,
perhaps end equals space.
And now I've just recreated that same
string but going through it as a list,
if that makes sense.
So I'll put this back to what it was.
All right, let's find
another example here.
I'll code up text1.py,
our next challenge.
What do you think we'll see here?
Yeah, so I'm seeing we should see
every character, but no spaces.
So let's try that out.
Let's say, python text1.py
to run this program.
And I think you just about
hit the nail on the head.
I see I-N T-H-E, so it seems like
we're going to have every character,
but there are no longer any spaces.
And I'm curious, what
happened to those spaces?
Where do you think they went?
Yeah.
So when we used dot split here,
the split string method, we said,
let's take this piece of text
and turn it into a list of words.
And when we do that, we're getting
rid of the spaces between the words,
such that we just have a list of
individual words, no spaces at all.
So word here still refers to an
individual word in our list of words,
but then c goes through every
individual word we have and prints them
out character by character.
All right.
So let's keep going.
Let's do code text2.py.
What do you think we'll see here?
Some new syntax.
Intuitively, what do
you think will happen?
Yeah, so maybe we only see
those words that have g in them.
A good guess.
So I'll say python of
text2.py, hit Enter,
and here I only see great and green.
So here we see another use
of this in syntax in Python.
So when it's used with a for loop,
I'm able to iterate over something
like a list or a string and
extract those sub elements.
Here, though, if I use it with
a conditional, if g in word,
I could do something like
linear search and say,
is this character g inside this
particular string that I'm giving you?
And if so, it will then say, yes,
it is, and do whatever is indented,
or if not, it will say no, it isn't,
and just pass right on through.
So I'll say, do this again,
and we see great and green.
The question is, what if the
word doesn't start with g
but has g inside of it?
This will still work.
So let me try this.
I'll say, have a typo
here intentionally.
I'll change great to rgeat
and say python text2.py.
And I'm still printing out rgeat
because g is in that type of word
I just created.
I hope that makes sense.
All right.
And let's do a few more, text3.py.
Here also is some new syntax.
What do you think we'll see here?
It's OK if you don't know.
We'll explain.
I'm seeing maybe we'll
print out every two words.
Maybe we'll print out
just great green room.
I think we're on the right track.
I like these ideas.
So let me try python of
text3.py and see what we get.
Looks like we get only
great, green, and room.
So notice here we have
some familiar things.
We have text.split.
We have for word in
text.split, print word.
But the only addition
here is the addition
of the brackets with some syntax in
the middle, like this 2 and this colon.
So let me hopefully give you an idea
of how these particular things work
if you'd like to use them.
Let me go ahead and
say, code brackets.py,
just so you can see how to use these.
I'll make my text the very same.
And I will now have
words equals text.split.
And let's see what happens if
I print words bracket 2 colon.
I'll say python brackets.py.
And now I see a list but it only
includes great, green, and room.
What if I did this?
What if I did words bracket 1 colon?
Well, now I see the great green room.
What if I did this, words, maybe
0 colon python of brackets.py?
Now I see, In the great
green room, the entire list.
So now let me ask you again, what
do you think this syntax is doing?
Yeah, so it's changing
where our list starts.
And if you remember, we can
still use bracket notation
to access some particular
element of our list.
If I say words bracket 0, I'll get
the first word, In, words bracket 1,
I'll get that second word, the.
But if I want to get not just that
first or second word, but all the rest
as well, I can include a colon after it.
And now I get the very element
I'm asking for and all the rest.
I could further decide
to subset my list.
I could say maybe 1 to 2,
like this, and I get just the.
Let me try 1 to 3.
Now I get the great.
So it turns out that in Python, this
index, if you're using this colon here,
is inclusive.
It's going to give you that particular
indexed value, followed by a colon.
I could say, I want
everything with no index here.
But I could also say, let's
stop at some particular index.
And don't give me back
that particular index.
So I'll say, give me back
1 and 2, not including 3.
I'll get back, the great.
I could say 1 through
4, not including 4.
Now I get, the great green.
So I'm able to manipulate my list
and extract certain pieces of it
as I would like to.
So it can sometimes be handy
for you as you're working
in Python to manipulate your lists.
The question, is it
like an automatic loop?
So there's nothing about this that
is particular to loops in general.
I could use this with or without a loop.
But it does help you if
you want to only loop
through some elements of your list,
and not, let's say, all of them.
A good question.
Yeah, and a question here is, it's
like start and stop, so very similar,
where the first number is the
index to start at, inclusive,
the next number is the
index to end at, exclusive.
I won't get whatever value is
indicated by this number here.
OK, other questions, too?
OK, seeing none for now, so let's learn
some more exciting things about Python.
One of my favorite new structures in
Python is this idea of a dictionary.
And dictionaries are so handy.
So we spent all this
time in the last problem
set making our very own
dictionary of sorts in speller,
where you were able to add words to
a hash table and look them up to see,
are they actually in this
hash table, or are they not?
So a dictionary allows you to have
some very similar functionality,
but it all comes so easily in Python.
So to help us conceptualize
what a dictionary actually is,
I want to go through a
bit of a diagram here.
You could think of it very
similar to a real dictionary.
So here, let's say I have
a blank piece of paper.
And I want to associate some authors
with the book that they have written.
So let's assume that every
book is written by one author,
and every author writes one book.
So here I could say, I have
a dictionary called authors,
and there are a few keys in this
dictionary, like Goodnight Moon,
like Corduroy, like Curious George.
And if I look up those
particular titles just below,
I'll then see the author
that wrote that book.
So let's say I want to
look up Goodnight Moon.
Who wrote-- who is the
author for Goodnight Moon?
Well, it's Margaret Wise Brown.
Same for Corduroy.
Who wrote Corduroy?
Well, that was, let's see, Don Freeman.
So this is the idea of associating,
in this case, book titles
with their authors.
And more particularly, we say,
this is the key in our dictionary.
And the result that we get by
using that key is the value.
Now there are other ways
to use dictionaries.
And ideally, we'd probably
want something a bit like this.
Maybe I want to store
information on books.
Well, I could very well do that.
I could say, let's make a dictionary
called book and give it two keys,
like title and author.
And if I had many of
these dictionaries, I
could give different
values for those keys.
So I have a book here, the title
of which is Goodnight Moon,
and the author is Margaret Wise Brown.
But you could imagine
I have maybe perhaps
many of these dictionaries
with different titles
and different authors in the end.
So different ways to
use dictionaries, one
to keep track of just all
authors and their book titles,
or here, keeping track
of individual books
and the information on
that single book as well.
So let's dive in and
see some syntax where
we can actually create dictionaries.
So here I have one
example, book equals dict.
Now dict is the way to create
some new blank dictionary.
And to visualize what this is
doing on the right-hand side,
I get the following, basically a
blank piece of paper, if you will,
that's called book.
Now let's say I want to
add a title to this book.
Well, I want to add a
key called title, and I
want to set the value
equal to some book title.
So I could do that like this, book,
bracket, and then the key name,
in this case, title, and then
equals some particular book title,
like Corduroy, which is
another children's book here.
So notice how my bracket syntax
is back but I'm no longer using
an index for this dictionary.
I'm using a string which
functions as my key.
Now let's go on and I'll say, I want
not just the title for this book,
I also want to add in,
let's say, the author.
So I'll add a new key and
set it equal to some value.
So book, bracket, author
now equals Don Freeman.
So now I'm able to see that, in this
particular book, the title is Corduroy
and the author is Don Freeman.
And maybe later on in my
code I want to print out,
let's say, the author, or the, let's
see, print out the title of this book.
I could do so like this.
I could say, print,
book, bracket, title.
And without the assignment
operator, I should just
see printed the title of
the book, which is Corduroy.
So here we see not just
how to create a dictionary
and assign some keys
and values, but also how
to access the values at certain keys.
Let me ask then, what questions
do we have on this syntax here?
Book is just one book, right?
So it is.
So this is a single book.
It wouldn't make sense
for this book dictionary
to have more than one title in it
because it's only a single book.
And in fact, a limitation
of a dictionary
is you can only have one particular
value for a particular key.
So I couldn't, let's say, have more
than one key called title in here.
Are dictionaries like structs in C?
So it's a interesting comparison.
I think that there's some
similar functionality, where
with a struct in C, you could
give certain attributes a name.
Like in candidate, we
had name and votes,
that's a similar idea to assigning
keys and values, where the attribute
name is the key, and the value is
the value that you store there.
They are functioning, I believe,
a little bit differently
underneath the hood.
So a dictionary is
good for just straight
up storing keys and values as a whole.
You can store a lot of them.
A struct often represents some
particular entity, like a candidate.
Although, I guess this is
also representing a book.
Let's just say, they're very similar
in use case, but different in actually
how they're implemented
underneath the hood.
Could we have a list of
values for a key like title?
We absolutely could.
So although you can only
have one particular key
and associate it with one particular
value, that value could be a list.
It could be itself a dictionary.
It could be any object in
Python you'd like to associate
with that particular key.
And a question here, if we have
a list of books and authors,
how would we actually get that to work?
So it's a good question.
And we're going to see
that in just a moment here.
I want to pose one scenario, though.
Let's say I mess up and I do
something a bit like this.
I print not book title, but I confuse
things and I say Corduroy as my key
instead.
What do you think might happen?
You might not know unless you've
programmed in Python before,
but the result here is I'll
get what we call a key error.
So the key error says, Corduroy
is not a key in this dictionary.
It's a value, but it's not a key.
I can't look some value up
by using this name, Corduroy.
I can only do that with my keys, which
in this case, are title and author.
And I actually see a good--
someone saved me here with
comparing structs and dictionaries.
With a struct, you have
specified attributes.
You can't really go ahead and add
or remove the attributes later.
With a dictionary, you can.
You can add or remove keys and values.
So that's another difference between
dictionaries and structs in C. Good
question.
All right.
So we've seen here how we
could have a single book.
If you wanted to actually
define it all the way up front,
you could use this syntax as well using
curly braces, followed by, let's say,
the key, colon, the value.
We saw this in lecture.
But we could also create not just a
single book but a list of books, too.
So here is what this
visually would look like.
Notice how I have some square brackets?
And in this list, separated by commas
are my individual dictionaries.
These dictionaries have
the same key, which is OK
because they're different dictionaries.
But now I could see how I
could develop a list of books.
Here I have the list itself.
And here I have the
individual dictionaries.
So I'm taking multiple dictionaries
and putting them in the same list.
And now it's kind of similar
to having a list of books.
Now let's see an example of this so
we can make it a little more concrete.
I have this program called books.py.
And I'm going to complete
it so that a user is
able to add books to their bookshelf.
So I'll go back to my code
space and I'll open up books.py.
And we'll see here, I have
some pieces of code already.
I have a list called books.
I know this is a list because it
has braces here, square braces.
I have a for loop here that will
loop three times, we saw in lecture.
And I want to complete
this part where I'm
able to add three books to my shelf,
or really, my books list up top.
And then, finally, I'm going to print
out that list of books down below.
So let's think about just adding a
single book inside this for loop.
What could I do?
Well, we saw earlier, I could make a
new dictionary by giving it some name,
like book, and saying
that is equal to dict.
That gives me a blank dictionary
called book, some blank piece of paper
that I could use to
associate keys and values.
And now my question to you is, let's
say I want to add a key called author.
How could I add a key called author?
What syntax could I use now?
I could use some syntax like this.
I'd say book, and then
bracket, the key name.
So the key name is author.
And I'll then set that equal to--
well, before we saw something hard
coded, like maybe Margaret Wise Brown,
but I want to get input from the user.
So I could very well do this.
I could say, it's the
result of calling input.
And I'll say Enter an author, like this.
So now whatever the user types in
will be associated with the author
key inside this dictionary called book.
Let's try this.
I'll say, book, and I want
to have a key called title.
So I'll say book, bracket, title,
in quotes, input, Enter a title.
So now I'm doing the same
thing twice for different keys.
And now I can do that
final step where I'm
trying to add this dictionary
to my list of books.
Now we saw in lecture that
to add some item to a list,
I could simply say
the name of that list,
and then dot append
to add some new item.
And I'll say book, books.append, book,
which is this new dictionary I created.
So every loop will create
this new blank dictionary,
call it book, add in a new key
and value for author and title,
and then add that book to our list.
Let's try that out here.
I'll say python books.py.
I'll say Margaret Wise Brown.
And then I'll say,
Goodnight Moon is one book.
Notice how I'm prompted
again for another book.
I'll say Corduroy and Don Freeman.
One more book, I'll say Curious
George, and then H.A. Ray.
Hit Enter, and then what happened?
What can we do down below?
I still need to print my list of books.
So I'm curious, for those of you
who are here, what kind of loop
do you think would be good for looping
over every individual dictionary
and printing out what's inside?
Yeah, so I'm seeing maybe a for loop.
I'll say for, and I could take advantage
of Python's special for-loop syntax.
I could say something like,
for book in books, colon,
and then figure out what
to do inside that loop.
But this is pretty much why
people like Python so much.
I could say, write in English, for
every book in my list of books,
do something, right?
I could call this anything.
I could say, for novel in
books, that's also valid
as long as I use novel down below here.
But here I'll stick to book.
That's actually kind of a convention.
If you have a list that
is a plural, like books,
and you have a for loop
like this, it's often
convention to make this the
singular version of that noun,
and this the plural
version of that noun.
So let's see what we can do.
I could print out book, let's say.
So I'll say python books.py,
and let me hit Enter.
I'll say Goodnight Moon.
Oh, actually, that's wrong.
That is not the author of this book.
That is the title of this book.
So if you want to exit your
Python program, you can Control-C,
and I will then do Python books again.
And I will say Margaret Wise Brown,
and then type in Goodnight Moon.
I'll then do Don Freeman and Corduroy.
And then I'll do H.A. Ray, and
then I'll do Curious George,
so three new books here.
I'll hit Enter, and now
I'll see those three
dictionaries printed to the screen.
So notice here we have them
denoted in curly braces,
the key author, and the key
title, all associated, hopefully,
as I would like them to be.
So questions then on this short program
we wrote to add books to our list?
Any questions?
What if we want to print the keys?
It's a good question.
Maybe this is helpful here.
So one thing you'll learn
as you do more Python
is that dictionaries themselves
have their own methods.
And one of these methods
is the dot keys method.
So I could say, print
book.keys, and that
should return to me all the
keys that are in this dictionary
without their values.
So let me try this.
I'll say, python of books.py, and
I'll go through this very quickly.
I'll just say 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
And notice here how when
I said print book.keys,
I'm now actually getting
the keys associated
with that particular dictionary.
And notice how all three dictionaries
have the same keys in this case.
Let's see, other questions, too?
If there is a book with the
same name but different author,
could you have it search
for the right one?
You probably could.
So there is a way that's a
little more advanced here.
I could say something like, for
book in books, if the author equals,
let's say, Margaret Wise Brown,
then print the book, like this.
There's all kinds of different
logic you could use here in Python.
You could, in that way,
differentiate between different,
let's say a book has
the same title but it's
written by Margaret Wise
Brown versus somebody else.
You could differentiate books like this.
So I hope that gives
you some idea of what
you could do to help filter your books.
Let's see, the question, is it
possible to remove the curly braces
in the answer, which is a good one.
If I scroll up a little bit,
notice how we saw here curly
braces when we print out the dictionary.
That's just Python's default
printing for dictionaries.
But if I wanted to get fancy
and make this a little prettier,
I certainly could.
I could, for book in books, print
not just the dictionary itself,
but let's say have a
full sentence I print.
Let's say I wanted something like this.
I could say, Author wrote book.
That's the structure
of my sentence here,
Author wrote book, where author is the
author, the actual author of that book,
and book is the title of that book.
Well, we saw in lecture, Python allows
us to interpolate certain values
using f-strings.
So here I'll mark it as an f-string.
We're putting f at the beginning.
And I could use curly braces to
substitute in some value of a variable.
I'll say, book, bracket,
author, which will give me,
in this case, book, bracket,
author, the author associated
with a particular book and
interpolate that in my sentence.
Now I'll do this.
I'll say, book, bracket,
title, like this.
And now I should be able to
have three sentences that say,
Margaret Wise Brown wrote Goodnight
Moon, or Don Freeman wrote Corduroy,
or H.A. Ray wrote Curious George.
If you're curious, I'll
invite you to try this out
on your own computer
on your own code space
to see how that works well for you.
All right.
Other questions, too?
A question, how could we print
it like key 1 equals value 1?
You could do something
like, author wrote book,
or author equals book author,
title equals book title.
Either way you have to
access the value associated
with that particular
key using an f-string,
and then substitute it in
to your string at the end.
So I hope that helps.
There are other ways to do
this besides f-strings, though.
You could use pluses and so on.
We'll focus here on
f-strings given time.
All right.
So just a few more things
to wrap us up, one of which
is this idea of working
with libraries and modules.
So we saw here how to build up
our very own bookshelf of books
by having the user type
in their books manually.
But odds are, nobody
wants to sit around typing
in manually all the books they own.
It's better if we could
use some kind of file
to actually read in all possible books.
So I want to introduce you to this
idea of libraries and modules,
and in particular, this idea of being
able to load in some list of books.
So let's say I am very conscientious.
I want to keep track of all the books
that I own and I have a spreadsheet,
a bit like this, where I have a
title column and an author column.
And each of these rows
is some particular book
with the title and author
associated between them.
So in Excel, it'll look a bit like this.
But actually, I could export this
file into what we call a CSV,
or comma-separated values file.
This is a very common file
format because it's so portable,
because it's so useful, and
it's actually pretty simple.
So here, notice how the first
row is title, comma, author.
These are the names of my columns.
Then, for every new line that
I have in this file, books.csv,
I have a title, comma, the
author, so Goodnight Moon, comma,
Margaret Wise Brown, Corduroy, comma,
Don Freeman, and so on, and so forth.
So basically, I have the same kind of
idea here, but now in a single file,
where every element is
separated by a comma
to associate the titles and the authors.
So Python actually works
very well with CSV files.
And they have a very
own library or a module
called CSV that gives
you access to functions,
methods you can use to read a CSV file.
So let's actually try
reading in some CSV file
and visualizing what would
happen along the way.
So here I have, at the top of
my Python program, import csv.
This tells Python I want to load in
this library, this module, called csv.
Import csv.
Now it's kind of similar
to me telling my program,
give me that big box
of stuff called csv.
And it has many features inside of
it, many functionalities, et cetera,
but I just want that entire box
of things that you call csv.
And maybe inside that box,
there are some particular books,
there are some particular
values or functions
I could use, like DictReader,
DictWriter, reader, and writer.
I would only know these things if
I read the Python Documentation.
But I could say, Python,
give me that entire box,
and give me access to the
functions that are inside
of it, among them these here.
So if I wanted to use,
let's say, DictReader,
which is a function
that allows me to read
a CSV as a dictionary, every row as a
dictionary, I could say csv.DictReader.
So I'm saying, csv, the
module name, and then
dot the function,
method, object, whatever
it is I want from that particular
module or that particular library.
So that gives me access to DictReader.
Let's say I want reader as well.
I could use csv.reader.
So here, again, is some
example of Python's dot syntax,
where I'm now using the library name,
and then dot the function, or object,
or whatever it is I want that's inside
that particular library or module.
I could also do things a bit like this.
I could say, import csv, but then
only give me some particular function
or object.
Import csv, or let's say,
from csv import DictReader.
This is another way
of importing modules,
or functions, et cetera, from csv
import some particular element of it.
So here, I'm only getting DictReader.
And I could then use DictReader
without the csv dot in front of it,
because Python knows, well,
DictReader comes from the csv library.
So two ways here, often folks will tend
to import an entire library if they're
using many pieces of that library.
If they're only using one or two,
though, they might be more particular
and say, from csv import
that particular function
or object they want from that
library, if that makes sense.
So let's get into how we could use
this to read and write from files.
So here, generally the syntax we'll
use to work with reading and writing
files in Python, with open FILENAME
as file, with open FILENAME as file.
Now this is allowing us to open up some
file using this function called open,
and open it up with the file name.
So let's say I want
to open up books.csv.
I could say, with open
books.csv as file, colon.
And now, as long as I'm indented
in this block of code here,
I'm able to access that file through
the name I gave it, file, in this case.
So let's say I want to read in
all the text from that file.
I could do something a bit like this.
I could say, create a
new variable called text,
and set it equal to the
result of calling file.read.
So when I use open, open
returns to me some file object.
And one of the methods of
that file object is read.
So if I called my file,
just plain old file here,
I could say file.read to simply
take all the data inside of it
and store it inside a Python
variable, this one called text.
That works really well for plain
text files, like dot txt files,
for instance.
I can just get and grab
all the contents and put it
inside some particular text variable.
For a CSV, though, I might want to
use Python's CSV module, CSV library.
So for that, I could say, maybe I need
to make a particular kind of reader
for this file.
I could say, file_reader
equals csv.DictReader
given the particular file.
And we'll see how this
works in just a little bit,
but DictReader basically lets me say, I
want to read every row of this CSV file
as a dictionary.
And by specifying this variable
that I called file_reader,
it will serve as a helper
for me to read this file.
And it will return to me every row
of that CSV as a dictionary that I
could actually iterate as a dictionary.
And I could iterate over all those
dictionaries in my particular file.
So let's try this step here.
For row in file_reader, this is
me iterating over my file_reader.
And every time I do, it will
return to me some dictionary
I could use in my program.
And I could do something
with it in the end.
So I think it's worth being a little
more concrete here and seeing this
actually in action.
So I'll go to my code space.
And I'll show you what we could do
to import a file called books.csv
using a Python program called
reads.py so you can build up
a list of children's books.
So I'll go to my code space
here and I'll do this.
I'll say, code reads.py.
And notice what I already have here.
I have imported the csv library.
I have a blank list of books.
And my first step is to add book to
the shelf by reading from books.csv.
So to open up this file, it's
generally good practice in Python
to use the with syntax.
So I'll say, with open, and I'll give
it some file name, like books.csv.
I want to open the file that's already
stored on my computer called books.csv.
I want to call that file in my
program simply file, like this.
Now if I say text equals file.read,
and then, finally, maybe print text,
let's see what we get.
I'll say python of reads.py,
and now I see, printed to
my screen, the contents of books.csv.
To prove it to you, I
could say code books.csv.
And here is the contents of books.csv.
Notice how I just saw those
printed to my terminal
all by using file.read
and this with open syntax.
So to answer your question here, dot
read does not read only one line,
and in fact, reads all the
lines in a particular file.
Now this isn't quite helpful
to me because I don't want
to read just everything all at once.
If I have this, let's see, if
I have just all this text all
in the same variable,
not super helpful for me.
What I would love is if we could do the
same thing as earlier, where I instead
have a list of dictionaries.
So for that, I could make use of the
CSV library's DictReader function.
So I could do this.
I could say, let's create a
reader for my CSV, a reader that
is csv.DictReader, given my file.
Now this is simply a helper the
makers of the Python CSV module,
they decided that they would create
this helper called DictReader
that, when given a file, allows
you to iterate over it and get
a dictionary for every row in the CSV.
So let's try this.
I'll say, iterate over this
reader for row in reader,
and let's see what's happening.
I'll just print row.
I'll go back to my terminal and I
will then say, python of reads.py.
And now I see something a
little better formatted.
I actually see dictionaries, where
they have a title, and an author key,
and values associated with them.
So Python basically
converted my books.csv file
into a list of dictionaries
with the given keys
and values I gave it in books.csv.
Notice that the key title and key
author are each in the dictionaries
I have available to me here.
So now what do I want to do as I
loop over this reader which gives me
every row as a single dictionary?
Well, I could probably just
add it to my list of books.
I could say, books.append, and I want to
append a given row I read from my CSV.
So if I do now, for book in books,
print book, let's see what happens.
I'll say python of
reads.py, and I should
see the same thing, which I could tidy
up, as we saw in the last one to say,
for example, Margaret Wise
Brown wrote Goodnight Moon,
Don Freeman wrote Corduroy, et cetera.
So let's pause here and let me
ask, what questions do we have?
I see a few already.
One is, what happens if
the file has no header?
So in books.csv, I had title and author.
What happens if I actually
remove this from books.csv?
We could try it and see what happens.
I'll say python of reads.py, and
something odd has happened here.
I seem to be saying my
key is Goodnight Moon.
Another key is Margaret Wise Brown.
Why do you think that happened?
It seems like, to me, the
first line, whatever it is,
is interpreted as the keys
I want in my dictionaries,
so long as I'm using DictReader.
So I better be sure to include the
key names that I want in my CSV,
otherwise they'll be interpreted as key
values even when I don't want them to.
Let's see, other questions here?
What data type is reader?
Reader, if it's helpful,
is a kind of iterable.
Remember earlier we said
an iterable is anything
you can iterate over, like in a loop?
So it is an iterator or iterable
that returns to us every loop a given
row as a dictionary from our CSV.
Other questions here?
Are the words module
and library synonymous?
Great question.
They are technically
different in Python.
This varies by language.
A module and a library
are two different things.
I've been saying both interchangeably
because it doesn't quite
matter for our purposes here.
But if you want to, you
can go off and read more
about the difference between a
library and a module in Python.
They are two distinct things that have
very slightly different definitions.
Let's see, other ones, too?
Do we have to specify the mode
that we're reading the file in?
You can if you'd like
to, often good practice.
So in C, remember, we had reading and
writing mode, and other modes, too.
In Python, we have the same thing.
I could give it the filename,
comma, the mode I want to use.
In this case, I'm just
reading so I'll say
the mode is R. I could also
create a new file using w.
And there are other modes, too, if
you want to read, write, et cetera.
To files as well.
Let's see, why do we use with?
So another good question here.
With basically handles a few things
for us that we might otherwise forget.
So in Python, we could very much
do this same thing as follows.
I could say, file equals open
books.csv in reading mode.
And then I could unindent these,
and I have access to file,
because I said file
equals open books.csv.
But now, if I run this program python
reads.py, I see it still works.
But for those of you who are
observant or know Python a bit
already, what have I forgotten to do?
Any ideas?
I've forgotten to close the file.
So just like in C where
we opened a file and had
to remember to close it at the
end, here I didn't close this file.
I think I can do so with file.close, and
that should take care of that for me.
But I don't want to have
to remember every time I
open the file to close it later on.
So I use with instead.
And what with does, with
open as file, indent these,
as long as I'm indented inside this
with statement, my file is open,
I can use it as I'd like.
But as soon as I unindent, my file
is automatically closed for me.
I don't have to call file.close.
Python does that for me automatically.
So it's a special way
of reading and writing
files where it just makes things
easier to open and close things for me
automatically.
Other good questions here, like how
to get the user to upload a file?
That is more in the
realm of web development.
So if you're interested in that,
go and check out CS50W with Brian.
All right.
Any other questions here?
OK, not seeing too many.
Oh, one more.
Do you need to specify the
stored location of the CSV file?
Yes.
So here, let me show you, if I'm in my
terminal and I type something like ls,
notice how books.csv and
books.py are in the same folder?
That is what allows me
to simply use books.csv.
If, though, this was
in some other folder,
like let's say it was
in data slash books.csv,
I would have to specify that to
open so it can go ahead and find
that file for me on my file system.
Good questions.
OK.
So that just about brings us to
the end of this section, which
we've been able to read and write to
files, learn about strings, et cetera.
This is kind of a lot as
an introduction to Python.
But I hope you enjoyed
getting to dive in,
and I hope you feel equipped to
tackle this week's problem set.
Certainly feel free to ask
any questions you'd like to,
but we'll hopefully see you next week.