CARTER ZENKE: OK,
well, hello one and all
and welcome to CS50's
fourth section this week.
My name is Carter Zenke, and I am the
course's preceptor here on campus.
And this week, week 4,
we learned about memory
and how our computer actually
stores things in bits and bytes
across its own landscape
of bits and bytes.
And so our goal today will be to talk
about a few different topics, most
of them from lecture, and to give
you the chance to ask the questions
you want to ask so you can prepare
yourself for this week's problem set.
So among these topics
are this idea of pointers
and why we would even use them.
So as we saw in lecture,
a pointer is a way
of storing some address in a computer's
memory, kind of similar to a variable.
We'll also talk about how we can
read and write data to files.
So up until now, you've been writing
programs that maybe take user input
and print something back to the screen.
By the end of this section
and by the end of this week,
you'll be able to write programs that
actually open up files and can actually
write data to files, getting
more advanced along the way.
And all of this will hopefully prepare
you for problem set 4 at the very end.
So I'm excited to dive
into these topics today.
Now, the first topic will
be this idea of pointers.
And they are admittedly
a little bit scary.
I've seen a lot of fear around
pointers when we talk about them.
I think they're scary because they
introduce some new syntax that
doesn't feel quite familiar yet.
And so the goal is to help you
become familiar with that syntax
so you can actually leave feeling a
little bit less scared of pointers
and more empowered to use
them at the end of the day.
So I think one thing that
makes pointers less scary
is this idea that they
really tie closely
to an idea you already know about,
and that is this idea of a variable.
So if you remember back in,
let's say, week 1 or so, we
talked about this idea of a variable.
And in this section, we
had this idea of trying
to make a contact application
to store, let's say,
the number of times we had
called somebody on the phone.
And so we had this variable
named calls, and this
was our visual of that variable.
We had a box that had some
value in it, like the number 3,
and that box had a name called calls.
And we said that a
variable was exactly this.
It is a name for some
value that can change.
That is, the value of that
variable could change.
Could be three calls right now.
But when I call somebody new, it
could be then, later on, four calls.
So some value that can change.
What we didn't see in week 1,
which we'll now see this week,
is that this value has to be
stored somewhere in our computer.
It can't just be out in the ether.
It has to have some actual physical
location among all the bits
and bytes inside of our computer, and
that is what we called an address.
This value has some address
inside of our computer.
And so in lecture, we saw this grid
of addresses of bits and bytes,
kind of like a yellow grid.
We could store number
50, a pointer, and so on.
I want to give you one other
visual of which to think
about pointers and addresses too.
So you could think about it, as well,
as kind of like this table here,
where your computer has keeping
track of both the addresses of values
and the values themselves.
That is, what is the value I'm storing,
and where, among all the possible bits
and bytes, am I storing that value?
And so notice here that we have
addresses that begin with 0x, 0x.
And I'm curious, as a
question for you all,
what do you remember 0x
meaning or signifying?
Why do we always append
or really prepend this 0x?
So I'm seeing some right answers here,
which is that this means hexadecimal.
So whatever comes after 0x
is a hexadecimal value, which
is to say it's a base-16 value.
So you're probably used to the
base-10 system, like decimal.
You've seen, in this class,
the base-2 system, like binary.
And now we're introducing
a new one called
base 16, which is just handy because
we can count up to larger numbers
without using so many digits.
Like if we're talking about the many
billions of bits that are inside
of a computer, it's worth
representing them in a way
we can count pretty high with
some fewer number of actual digits
we'll see as part of our
number we're writing out.
So that's the background
for this address here.
But to keep going with
this idea, our computer
wants to store some value
somewhere in memory.
And so for that calls
variable we saw earlier, well,
that could be stored at
this address right here.
0x-- let's see--
50-- a 5, 000--
5 and seven 0's.
So 0x5 and seven 0's.
Somewhere-- doesn't quite matter--
it has some address in our computer.
And the way we put it there
was this C syntax on the right.
We simply said, we're going to
create some new integer whose name is
calls that will get the value 3.
And we're going to store
it somewhere in memory.
Now, a pointer is this exact same
idea, but the only difference
is that we're not going to
store an integer or a character
or really a string or anything else.
We're going to store,
instead, an address itself.
So here's what we would say if
we're going to make a pointer.
If we go here, notice how
on the next table row,
I'm not storing an
integer or a character.
I'm storing an address itself at
some address inside the computer.
And notice in particular
that this address
I'm storing, 0x5 and then
seven 0's afterwards,
that seems to reference some other
address in my computer's memory.
That is the place where the 3 is stored.
So we could say that this
value, 0x5 and seven 0's,
that is pointing to this other
address where the 3 is stored,
and, therefore, it is a pointer.
So the only difference here is we're no
longer storing integers or characters
or so on.
We're now just storing addresses
at some place inside our computer.
So let me ask, what questions do we have
on this so far, on this mental model
or on this idea of now storing
addresses and not just actual
values like numbers or characters?
OK.
Not seeing any so far.
Actually, let me ask
you a question here.
How can we dereference this pointer?
It's a good vocabulary
word we learned in lecture,
which is to follow a pointer
to the place it is pointing to.
So let's begin with
a bit of syntax here.
And here, if I show you
this in full screen,
you'll see that this is the syntax
we could use to do exactly what we
did on the table on the left.
Let's create now a
pointer whose name is p,
and we're going to store the address
of this variable named calls.
So notice a few pieces of syntax here.
We have int *, which means
this is no longer an integer,
but it is a pointer to an integer.
It is going to direct us-- if
we dereference this pointer,
we're going to get--
we're going to end up
at an integer in our computer's memory.
And notice, too, this
ampersand, which means
we should store the address
of whatever calls is storing.
In which case, we see in
the table here, that is 0x5
and then seven 0's afterwards.
So the data type of p
here is a pointer, but it
is a pointer to an integer and
not a character, for instance.
So to highlight here as well,
let's try setting this up
and visualizing it a little bit more.
So all we're doing is saying the
same thing we did for a variable--
that p, this value named p, should
store this particular address now.
And I think it's worth breaking
down the syntax on the left
so we actually see it, and you can
use it later on in your own programs.
So one common point of confusion here
is that this variable, this pointer,
is not called star p.
That is not its name.
In fact, it is just called p.
But it is confusing though
because we see int *p,
like the star is right next to the p.
And so we kind of assume,
well, this pointer
is just going to be
called star p later on.
But in fact, it's just
a syntactic trick.
All we're doing here is saying this is a
pointer named p, and its type is int *,
or a pointer to an integer.
So when you see this star being used
to initialize or declare some value,
be careful here and
think, what is the name
of the variable that I'm working
with or the pointer that I have,
and what is its type?
Because it might not be
quite apparent to you,
if you're new, that you might say,
OK, well, the star is next to the p.
Maybe that's its name.
It's not. p is its name.
Int * is its type.
Now, it's more obvious
on the right-hand side
here that the value
is simply the address
of calls using the ampersand here.
And as we saw in lecture, I like to
think of this as ampersand for address.
Both begin with A in this case.
And a question here is, could we
actually modify this syntax and say,
maybe, int* p?
That's absolutely possible,
as we saw in lecture.
We could also have int *
p, which would be maybe
a little more confusing in my
opinion, but that would work as well.
So white space doesn't quite matter.
But by convention, we
tend to use this syntax
you're going to see here, int *
followed by the variable name.
Now, a question here too
is, what if we wanted
to store not just an integer or a
pointer to an integer, but a pointer
to a character, which, as we saw, is
kind of like what a string would be?
Well, in that case, we'd simply
replace the int part of this syntax
with a char or "kayr"--
C-H-A-R. That would then store
a pointer to a character.
And the follow-on
question is, well, if we
can store a pointer to an
integer, a pointer to a character,
could we have a pointer to a pointer?
You could.
There's nothing stopping you.
You can have a pointer to a pointer
to a pointer and so on and so forth.
But at that point, I'd say we're
getting a little bit ridiculous.
We can pause and say, what
are we actually doing here?
But you could possibly do it.
So to recap here, some key syntax
to study, to practice with,
is going to be the following.
You could say the type *--
just get it in your
head-- is a pointer that
stores the address of a certain type.
But then later on, as we'll see, if
I want to dereference that value--
that is, get the value that
that pointer is pointing to--
I would use the star in a different way.
I would say star and then
the name of that pointer.
So *x, for example, takes a pointer
named x and gets the value that is
stored at that address.
As we just discussed here, &x
takes x and gets its address.
Ampersand for address,
A for A in this case.
So questions on this syntax here?
Question about how
pointers work with arrays.
So we'll see this probably a little
bit more as you work on the problem set
and go on with the course.
But you could think of
a pointer as pointing
to the beginning of
some chunk of memory.
In the previous example,
we saw a pointer
pointing to one particular value
like one integer or one character.
But there's nothing
stopping us from having
a pointer that points to an array of
values or a list of values all back
to back to back in a computer's memory.
So we can have pointers to arrays.
Other questions too?
OK, so I think one question
that comes to my mind
when I first see this idea of
pointers is, that's all fine and good.
I love pointers.
I love addresses.
But why would I ever use
them, because at this point,
it seems kind of confusing?
Why would I use this syntax versus the
one I already know, and why is it worth
getting into the weeds
about all these addresses
when I can just store things wherever?
I don't quite care.
Well, there are a few reasons
you might want to use pointers,
and pointers can enable you to do
things you actually couldn't do before.
So among them are these things
that you can now do with pointers.
You could now write a function
that allows you to pass something
in by reference and not just by copy.
So that is to say, I could have a
function that modifies some value right
where it currently is.
And this is helpful more so
as you will see next week when
we make these very big data structures.
I could write functions that modify
those data structures without copying
all of them somewhere else.
And perhaps more resonant
probably this week
is this one, which is you can
use what we call dynamic memory.
That is, up until now,
you've been writing programs
that use some fixed amount of memory.
The user might type something in.
Maybe it uses maybe 5
bytes or 10 bytes or so on.
But you could now, as the program
runs, actually ask your program
for more and more memory depending
on what the user actually needs.
And you can use pointers to
manage the memory for you.
So more again on that
in some future weeks.
But pointers here are setting
up these additional capabilities
that you can use as we go
through the course as well.
So I hope you find at least
some of this exciting.
And I want to focus in particular
on what we can actually
do because of this.
So in this first step,
it's like, OK, great,
I can write functions that pass
things by reference and not by copy.
But what does that get me ultimately?
Well, ultimately, if
you write functions that
allow you to pass values by
reference, not just by copy,
you can write code that's
ultimately cleaner as a result.
And as I said before, you can also
now scale your usage of memory
in your application by using pointers
to actually manage that memory
and make your programs all
the more efficient too.
All right, so let's
keep going here and show
a bit of a visual example of
what it means now to pass things
by reference and not just by copy.
So we saw in lecture we had this idea
of trying to swap two values around
and trying to write a
function to do that.
So let's revisit that and get a
visual example here in our slides
so we understand exactly what it means
to now pass things by copy as opposed
to passing things by reference.
So you could imagine here, we have
some code on the left-hand side
and what we call our call stack
on the right-hand side here.
So you could imagine
we have already called
main, the main function of our program.
And we've set two variables-- one equal
to 10, called a, and one equal to 50,
called b.
And in our first implementation
of swap, we had the following code
that swap would take an integer
named a, an integer named b,
and it would swap them around, trying to
store the value of b in the place of a
and the value of a in the place of b.
So, visually, it looks a bit like
this, where I have main running.
But now as soon as I call or use swap,
I'm able to have another function call.
I'm copying down those values from main.
So to try animation one more time, we
had main running, but now we call swap.
We pass in these values a and b.
We pass them by copy.
This space that swap has gets a
copy of the values for a and b.
And then, of course, within
swap, we do swap them.
So the value of a gets 50--
or the variable a gets 50, and
the variable b now gets 10.
But what's the problem?
Like if I finish now running
swap, what do you notice?
They seem to be swapped in swap,
but what hasn't happened, actually?
Yeah.
So in main, they're still the same.
I see that a is still equal to
10, and b is still equal to 50.
So if we call a function
without using pointers,
we're essentially saying, let's go
ahead and take a copy of these values,
put them somewhere else,
and do something to them.
We won't actually
impact the variables we
were hoping to impact when we
set them or use them in main.
So once swap finishes,
we're still left here
with the same values in the same places.
So what do we do to fix this in lecture?
What do we do to fix this problem?
Any ideas?
So we did end up using pointers.
And what we did in
particular is we didn't
copy in the actual values of a and b.
We copied their locations
or their addresses--
that is, the pointer to
a and the pointer to b.
So another option here is to rewrite
swap so that it does this instead.
So notice in the syntax now, this
swap function is taking two arguments,
one that is now a pointer to a and one
that is now a pointer to b-- that is,
the address of a and the address of b.
And then, down below, it's going to use
the dereference syntax to go and get
those values and swap them in place.
So although we're still running swap,
and we're copying in some value,
the ultimate result, though, is that
we actually copy in the address,
and we change the values exactly where
those values currently are in memory.
So, for instance, let's visualize this.
I'll show you.
We're going to call swap here.
Here's swap.
And what we pass into swap now is
not the value 10 or the value 50,
but the address of a
and the address of b.
So now we have a link from
swap's location memory
back to main, where a
and b originally are.
Now, if we follow the steps in
swap, we can follow these pointers
and swap the values
all at once in place.
So now a is 50 and b is 10.
And so as you go on
in the course, you'll
be able to write functions that
do this not just for two variables
but perhaps for entire
data structures and that
allow you to ultimately build up much
more complex ways of storing data
in your programs.
So questions, then, on this idea of
swapping and passing by reference
and passing by copy?
A question here.
If you wanted to access the address,
wouldn't you write &a and &b?
And, in fact, you would.
In this case, though, as we see
in void swap(int *a, int *b),
we're defining here is
the definition of swap.
And you'll see swap takes two arguments.
The first argument is a pointer to a.
But how do we know it's a pointer to a?
Well, we see here, it
has the type int *.
And then the same thing
here, a pointer to b.
We know it's a pointer to b because
the type is int *, and the name is b.
So I think it's helpful actually to show
you the entire code for this as well.
And for that, I'll pull up my
codespace, and I'll actually
walk through each step
of this now with debug50
so we can see the exact
values of each variable
here and understand exactly
what's going on in our program.
So I'll come to my codespace.
And now I will code swap.c.
So swap.c is already done for me.
I already wrote this code.
But let me show you a few pieces here.
So on line 4, I have the
prototype for my function swap.
swap will take a pointer called
a and a pointer called b.
It won't return us anything.
It will simply have the side effect
of swapping those two values.
Now, in our function called
main, the very first function
to run in our program, I'll
create this variable named a,
put it someplace in memory,
and give it the value 10.
Similarly, I'll create this variable
named b, put it someplace in memory,
and give it now the value of 50.
So, first, I'll print out
what is a and what is b.
I'll call the function swap.
And notice now.
I'm going to give it not the
value of a but the address of a.
That is, wherever a is stored,
I'll pass that into swap.
And in the same way, I'll do that for b.
And then once that's
done, I'll call printf,
and I'll tell us again
what is a and what is b.
Now, down below, here's swap, the
same implementation we had before.
We're going to take in a pointer
called a and a pointer called b.
And through what we
saw in lecture, we're
going to swap them
all at once down here.
So let's go ahead and
write a bit of syntax
here to actually debug this
program and see it step by step.
So if you're familiar with debug50,
we can actually pause our program
and walk through it step by step,
seeing the values of variables as we go.
So I might pause this program here,
right where we're about to call swap.
And now if I make swap to compile it
and run debug50 ./swap and hit Enter,
I should be whisked away
to the debug50 environment.
And I should hopefully see here soon
that I'm able to see my program running
but paused at this point.
So now I want to show you where we are.
Notice in my terminal, I see
that a is 10, and b is 50.
And, actually, in this tab
over here called Variables,
I can see that in real-time.
I do see a is 10, and b is 50.
So it's true, right?
Now, down in my Call Stack, notice
that main() is currently running.
It's the highest thing in my Call Stack.
So now I want to run swap.
But if I want to see the workings
of swap, how swap is actually
going to swap these two
values, I should use step into,
which means, run this function but
show me each step along the way.
So I'll step into swap here.
And notice how I change my variables.
These are the variables that
have been passed into swap.
I see this variable named temp
that currently has value 257.
Why do you think it has that value?
Any ideas?
Doesn't seem to make much sense to me.
And we learned a name for this value in
lecture or rather this type of value.
I'm seeing some people say a
junk value or a garbage value.
That's exactly what it is.
There's some garbage value.
It is a value that is just kind
of already there in memory.
We haven't assigned it anything yet.
But once I actually step over this
line of code, we should see what?
Well, int temp, this value
here, is currently 257.
But once I run this, I'll
set it equal to the result
of dereferencing the pointer a.
Notice the value of a
here is 0x7ffd26c1790c.
OK, but what is at the
end of that pointer?
If I follow it, what will I find?
I'll find 10 here.
So notice that it gives us the value
not just for a, but the value of *a--
that is, following the pointer going
to that location memory and finding
whatever value is there.
In that case, that value is 10.
So it goes to say that if I were
to run this line of code, line 18,
I should set temp equal to 10--
that is, the value that I
would get if I dereferenced a.
So now I'll step over it,
and I'll see temp becomes 10.
Now, what's the next step?
Well, this says *a = *b,
which is kind of confusing.
But keep in mind what *a is.
Well, *a is currently 10.
It is the value at the
location that a is stored.
Now I want to put in the value that is--
the value that I get if I follow
the pointer b, which is 50.
So notice here *b is 50.
If I follow this
0x7ffd26c17908, wherever
that is in memory, if I follow that
pointer and find that location,
I will then get the value 50.
And I'll then assign that value to the
dereferenced part of this pointer a,
which is currently 10.
So I'll step over this now, and
we'll see, well, *a becomes 50.
I follow that pointer to the
location of a and set it equal to 50.
Now then, I'll say *b
gets the value of temp.
Well, *b is currently 50.
I'm going to follow this pointer
b to its value, which is 50.
And then I'll set it equal to 10.
I'll step over, and now I'll
see *a is 50, and *b is 10.
Now, if I end this program,
finish swap, what do we see?
Well, a is now 50, and b is now 10.
I'll step over and
finish my program again.
And now I'll see a is 50. b is 10.
I've swapped these two
values right there in place,
walking through step by step.
So I'll close this program, and
let me ask, what questions do we
have on swapping or on pointers so far?
Question here.
Why is swap defined on line 4
and then again called on line 16?
It's a good question.
So to be clear, on
line 4, what I'm doing
is setting up the prototype for swap.
I'm not so much defining
it as I am declaring it.
I'm telling C that,
hey, look, up ahead, you
should see a function called
swap that takes these two inputs
and returns this value--
in this case, nothing.
And down below, when I, on line 16,
have that same prototype followed
by some brackets and
some code here, that's
where I'm defining swap in itself.
A good question though.
Another good question.
Why aren't we returning
in this function?
So often we'll see if we want to get
some value back in, let's say, main,
we have the function we
call return us some value.
In this case, though, swap doesn't
need to return much of anything.
In fact, its entire purpose is to have
this side effect of swapping values
in place because we give to swap the
addresses of two variables in memory.
We have it follow those pointers
to where those values are
and move them around a bit like this.
So we don't need to return anything.
Because swap already has
access to that place in memory,
we're going to move
those two values around.
All right.
Other questions too?
A question here.
Would this work without the &a and
&b because swap is defined above?
Let's see.
I'm not sure if this is
answering your question,
but we do see here that swap is
taking in these values, *a and *b.
And it's important here
that we actually give swap
the address of these values,
not the values themselves.
If I said a and b here, I
would now be passing by copy.
I would say, swap, take the
value of a, which is 10,
and take the value of b, which is
50, and do whatever you want with it.
But in this case, beyond the fact
that swap is expecting a pointer,
if I were to do that, I'm not actually
telling swap where my values currently
are so it can move them around.
I'm just giving it a copy
of those values for it
to do whatever it wants with it.
Here, though, I should
make sure that swap
is able to take in the
address of these values
so it can move them around
right where they are.
Another question.
Why don't we declare swap
instead of prototyping it?
So we do.
So this is the prototype
and declaration for swap.
We're telling C exactly
what swap will be.
And down below, we define it as well.
All right, so that was a bit of a lot.
And our goal here is
I'm going to show you
all what you can now do with pointers.
It's not so much interesting to swap
things around like this and that.
But what is powerful, what is fun, is
actually opening up files, reading data
from them, and writing
data to those files,
allowing you to write even more
complex programs as you go.
So here we'll talk about
this idea of file I/O.
And file I/O stands
for file input and file
output, how we can write data to files
and how we can read data to files.
So as a visual here, let's think of how
we can both open and close files first.
When we work with files in C, there's
this idea of opening up a file
and closing a file, similar to what
you would do on your own computer.
If you were to open up, let's
say, a Microsoft Word document,
you open it up.
And later on, when you're
done, you just close it.
Hit that X button, and
it's gone and stored away.
In a similar way, your programs
can open and close files too.
So there are two key functions here
for opening and closing files in C. One
is called fopen, which
stands for file open.
Going to open up a file for
future reading or writing.
If we're reading, it
is looking at the data,
and writing is adding
data or modifying data.
Now, fclose goes ahead and
closes that file for us.
And now there's a bit of a hint
here you saw in lecture a bit
and one you should keep in mind as
well, which is you should always
fclose all files you fopen.
And I'm curious to get a sense
of your intuition for this.
Why is it important that we
always close files we open?
Why, do you think?
I'm seeing to free up
memory, which is a good idea.
Why else?
So memory isn't wasted,
another good idea.
Maybe you won't be able to use the
file later if you don't close it.
Preventing memory leaks That
is like a ballooning program
using more and more memory over time.
These are all good ideas.
And I think you could
really draw a parallel
between you working on
your own computer and just
always opening files, opening files,
opening files but never closing them.
One, it would just be a mess if your
computer, every time you opened it,
just had all these open
files on it, right?
But the other thing is
that if you ever want
to send that file to
somebody else, you had better
close it so they can modify it without
you also modifying it at the same time.
So, generally, it's
good practice to make
sure you open files when you're
going to use them and close them
when you're done with
them to save memory
and also to ensure that no two programs
are opening a file at the same time.
OK, so let's get a visual here for
how we can actually write to our file.
So here we see a actual
file on the right-hand side
and some piece of syntax we
could use to open that file.
In this case, we're going
to use the fopen function.
So fopen takes two particular
arguments or inputs.
It takes the name of the file.
And let's say this file here is
called hi.txt, as we see down below.
So it's a text file that just
says "Hi!" on the inside.
And now fopen takes another
argument, another input, which is r.
That is the mode we're going
to use to open this file.
There are two modes, read and write.
And so what do you think r stands for?
Well, read.
We're going to open this file just
so we can see what's inside of it.
We can read some data from it.
And now what do you think
fopen returns to us, based
on what you see on the left-hand side?
What does fopen return to us?
You could look at the type
on the left-hand side here.
So I'm seeing a few ideas.
One is that it returns the contents of
hi.txt, which is close, but not quite.
I'm seeing another idea that it's
a pointer to the file in memory,
which is a good idea.
And I think we could
get this intuition-wise
if we said, well, it looks like
we have this variable named f.
And its type is FILE *.
And whenever we see
type *, well, we should
assume that is a pointer to that type.
So in this case, in C, there is
a type called, all caps, FILE,
which is basically a way of
trying to access the file.
It's a bit of a fancy type.
But suffice to say for now, it
allows you to access some file.
And it has a pointer to
that particular file type.
Now, as a bit of an
oversimplification here,
you could imagine that this
variable named f now just points to,
let's say, this location in memory
or this file we're trying to open.
It points to the very
beginning of that file.
In reality, there is more
going on underneath the hood.
There is a very special file
type, like we discussed.
C tends to move some of the data
of that file to its own program.
But for now, you could
just think of fopen
as returning to you the
location of this file in memory
so you can actually
see where it's stored.
Much like you trying to
find a file to open it,
you first have to figure
out, what directory is it in,
where is it located, and so on.
So questions, then, on
fopen and how we can
try to find files to open
them with our own programs?
OK.
Oh, a question.
Why do the modes matter?
That's a great question.
So here we see we're
going to open hi.txt using
the mode r, which stands for read.
There's also the mode w,
which stands for write,
which allows us to actually
write some data into the file
to change or modify it in some way.
I would say, for now, just
keep in mind that fopen
might do two different things.
It might set up the file in different
ways, for reading and for writing,
because reading just requires
us to look at that file
and see what it is right now.
Whereas writing, we have to set
up the entire process of being
able to change that file in some way.
You can also, I believe,
have both modes together,
able to read and write at the same time.
There are also other kinds
of modes you could look up
as well in the C standard library.
OK.
So here we're able to
open up a file, and it's
easy to close it simply
using fclose and then
giving fclose the pointer to that file.
So here we see f pointing to this
file, telling us where it is in memory.
We can simply say fclose and
give it the pointer to that file.
And now that file will,
afterwards, be closed.
We can no longer read or write from it.
But let's say, along the way, we do want
to read or write data from our file.
So let's get a visual now for what it
means to read and write from a file.
So, often, one thing we'll see is having
a file a bit like this one, hi.txt,
and our program on the left-hand
side with some variable like text.
And maybe we want to store whatever
is inside this file in some variable.
We want to get it into our program so
we can modify it or use it in some way.
Well, if we were to read
this data, it's basically
like taking a copy of
some chunk of our file
and putting it inside of our program.
So here I see this text, "Hi!"
I'll take a copy of it and put it
inside this variable called text.
And now it's inside my program.
I could use it, modify it as I wish.
It's simply a copy of
whatever is inside this file.
But now if I want to write
data or modify this file,
you could imagine maybe I have some
value, like what's currently in text,
and I want to put that in the file.
Well, I could write data by copying
what I have in this particular variable
and appending it-- that is,
adding it to this file here.
I'll take "Hi!", and now I'll put
it at the very end of this file.
I've written data or added
data to this file here.
So what questions, then, on this
visual for reading and for writing?
Question on the syntax, I
think, which is a good question.
So we've seen how to open and
close files with fopen and fclose.
But now how do we actually add data
to them and read data from them?
So for that, we have two other
functions, one called fread
and one called fwrite.
And more on these as we go.
But suffice to say for now that
fread lets us read data from a file
into our program.
And fwrite allows us to read data
or to take data from our program
and add it to a file.
Now, in particular, there's a new
vocabulary word here called a buffer.
And a buffer is simply a
place we can temporarily
store some data in our program.
So let's say we have a file, and
like we saw before, I wanted to read,
let's say, three
characters from that file--
H, i, exclamation point.
I would have a variable,
which serves as a buffer that
is some place to store that data
inside my program temporarily.
So a buffer is simply some particular
name for a kind of variable
that stores often file contents.
So let's consider then why we might
even want to use idea of a buffer.
I'm curious what you
all might think here.
If a buffer is simply some place to
store part of a file, not all of it,
why would we use a buffer?
Another way of asking
this question is this.
Why might we not want to read the
entirety of our file into memory
all at once?
Why do we need a buffer in this case?
If the goal of buffer is to
break our file into smaller bits,
why might we need that?
So I'm seeing this idea of saving
up memory, trying to use less memory
overall, which is a good one.
Let's see.
Trying to avoid overflow,
which makes sense.
Maybe we don't quite
know how big the file is.
Trying to avoid segmentation fault.
So I'm seeing some themes here.
And among them are this idea that
maybe our file is really big,
like we don't want to have that
entire file loaded up at once
and put into memory.
That's a good idea.
The other idea is we often don't
know exactly how big a file is.
So the best we can do is
look at small bits of it
one at a time until we get to the end
of our file at the end of the day.
So that's why I might
want to use a buffer.
This allows us to look at some
particular pieces of our file and not
the entire file all at once.
So if we have this buffer
now, it's worth asking,
how could we get data into that buffer?
And for that, we'll see this
idea of reading from a file.
So if I wanted to read
from a file, there
are really two questions
I should answer.
The first is, from
where am I reading data?
What file am I trying to get data from?
And then where am I trying
to read that data into?
What buffer am I trying to put it into?
And it turns out that fread requires us
to answer these two questions before it
can do what we want it to do.
So let's see one example of fread here.
So this is fread.
And fread takes four
inputs or four arguments.
One of the first ones you might
care about is this one, which is,
from where are we reading data?
From what file are we
trying to read data?
And for that, we give
fread a file pointer,
some way of finding the location of
our file in the computer's memory.
So, for instance, let's
say we have this file here.
The pointer to that file is called f.
I could run fread a bit like this, by
slotting in f as that fourth argument.
So now fread knows from where
to get the data from this file.
But the next question, we said,
is where is the data going to go?
Where in my program should
I put this temporary piece
of data I'm going to get from the file?
Well, in that case, we might
have something like a buffer,
and that is going to be
the first input to fread.
So here now is our visual.
Let's say we have a pointer
to our file called f,
and we have some place
in our program called
buffer, some place to store this data.
Well, we could then just
call that variable buffer.
And now when we call fread, we could
say, we want to read into the buffer.
That is, that will be a pointer to
some place in our computer's memory,
some address we want
to put that data in.
So now we've seen two out of the
four arguments so fread can function.
Where are we getting data, and where
are we going to put it in the end?
So questions here as well.
And we'll see some examples later on.
Good question.
So buffer is a variable?
Buffer is a variable.
And in this case, it is the
address of some place in memory
where we want to store
the file's contents.
Good question.
OK.
So now the next thing is there are still
two arguments we haven't yet defined.
What are these arguments?
Well, it turns out that these two
are answering these questions here,
which is, what size is the
block of data I want to read,
and how many blocks do I want to read?
So it turns out that
files themselves are
composed of individual blocks of data.
So you could imagine,
let's say, a text file.
And I want to ask you,
what might be the file--
what might be the individual
chunks of a text file?
If I'm storing some
text, what do you think
might compose those
individual chunks of the file?
How would you break up
that file if I were to ask
you to break it up into smaller pieces?
You could certainly break it up
into lines or sentences or so on.
But I would argue, maybe the
smallest unit we could get
is an individual character of text--
so maybe a character like
a or a character like e.
So we saw our hi.txt earlier
had H, i, exclamation point.
Well, that file is probably just three
chunks of memory, each 1 byte long.
H is one chunk.
i is one chunk.
Exclamation point is another chunk.
And we know that
characters are 1 byte long.
So you can probably assume
that text file is broken up
into individual pieces,
individual bytes in this case.
So some files do have individual
bytes that make them up.
Other files, though,
are a little fancier.
So while text files might have
chunks that are 1 byte long,
you could imagine a file like
an image that stores color.
Well, to store individual
pixels, it turns out
each pixel needs about 3 bytes.
And so we could probably
best think of an image file
as being broken up into not one-byte
chunks but three-byte chunks,
a bit like this visually.
So as we read files, it's
important we figure out, well,
how big are the individual pieces
of data that make up this file?
In the case of a text file, it's
those characters that are 1 byte long.
In the case of an image
though, it's those pixels
that could be up to 3 bytes long as
well to store all the possible colors
that pixel could be.
And the question is,
how do we know that?
Well, often, you just
know that from convention.
So if you're working with
text files, by convention,
we store them character by character.
If you're working with images, you were
able to maybe look up documentation
for, let's say, the
.png or .bmp file type.
It tells you that those pixels
are stored in three-byte chunks.
So often you don't know yourself, but
somebody else, the maker of that file,
will tell you how their data is stored.
A good question.
So it stands to reason, then, if we
know how to break a file into smaller
chunks, we need to answer
these two questions, which
is, how big are those chunks, and
how many do we want to read at once?
So let's answer that first question.
What size are these chunks?
And this question is in bytes.
So if we're working now
with, let's say, a file
that looks a bit like this--
maybe it's a text file,
has individual characters-- we could
say the individual chunks of this file
are simply 1 byte long.
So we could tell fread we're going
to read chunks that are 1 byte big.
But now the next question is, OK, I
know my file is made of one-byte chunks.
But how many of those
should I read all at once?
Well, we could say, maybe we
want to read 4 at a time or 8
at a time or 2 or 1 at
a time, whatever it is.
In this case, let's say, I want
to read just 4 bytes at a time,
able to see my file in 4 byte
sliding windows, if you will.
So here, if I read 4 bytes,
visually, it looks a bit like this.
I'm looking at my file
here, and I want to read
whatever is in these first four chunks.
My pointer f points to the first one.
I'll take out the first four
and put them in my buffer.
I've made a copy of them
from my file into my program,
and now my file pointer points at
whatever is still left to read.
So if I have some
sentence here, maybe I'm
reading it four characters at a time.
I see those first four characters.
My file pointer gets updated and
points to the rest of my file.
If I call fread again
and again and again,
I'll keep moving further and
further and further and further down
my file 4 bytes at a
time, 4 bytes at a time.
So questions on this, whether
visually or syntax-wise?
This is our final call
or usage of fread.
And we'll see this in
action in just a bit.
Good question.
How do we decide how
many chunks to take out?
Often it will depend on a few things.
So one is, how much memory do
you want to use at any one time?
So if you were to take a
big chunk out of your file,
that's a lot of memory to
store in your program, perhaps.
At the same time, maybe you care
about seeing all that data at once.
That would be a good reason to do that.
If you don't, though, quite care about
seeing all your data all at once,
you could read things
in smaller chunks just
to make sure you're not using up
too much memory at any one time.
The other reason you might make
this value smaller or larger is it
tends to be a little bit faster to read
things in bigger chunks, like to read,
let's say, 100 individual bytes
versus, let's say, 10 bytes ten times,
for instance.
Or to make it even simpler, it's
easier to read 10 bytes all at once
than it is to read 10 bytes
individually over and over again.
So that's a consideration as
well, though probably not as
much a consideration for the kind of
work you'll do in CS50 in particular.
Another question here.
Is f able to return to the beginning
of the file after doing the reading?
It is.
There is a special function you would
call to move the file pointer back
to the top.
So when you use fread,
as we said before,
this file pointer continues
through the file, through the file,
through the file, gradually
getting to the end.
When you get to the end, you have to
kind of rewind it back to the top.
And if you're familiar with this
idea of a cassette player, where
you have some tape that goes
and spins and spins and spins,
that's kind of what this
file pointer is doing.
It starts at the beginning,
spins all the way to the end.
Once you get there,
you have to rewind it
all the way back to the very beginning.
Or a VHS tape as well--
nice metaphor there.
Yeah.
And then another question here.
How do we find how many
chunks there are in the file?
Well, actually, I would argue, you
can't quite know at the very beginning.
Your computer is able
to tell you roughly
how many bytes are inside a file.
But if you were to write a
program to find the size of a file
that you didn't know beforehand,
logically, the only way you
can find the end of that file or how
big it is by starting at the beginning,
reading byte by byte by byte by
byte until you get to the end.
And you'll notice, well, there's
no more file left to read.
And so, often, at the
end of your file, you
will see a special signifier,
maybe a null terminating character
or some other kind of special character
called an EOF or End of File character.
That tells you there are
no more bytes to read.
But it's a bit like strlen, as we saw
a bit in lecture, where you can't quite
know how long the string is until
you go character by character
or byte by byte to the
very end of it, and you
see that ending character, like
a null character or an EOF,
end of file character.
Good questions.
OK, so let's make this
a little more concrete,
and we'll write a program here to
actually check what kind of type
a file is.
So one interesting fact about a file--
let me find this problem right here--
is that, generally, files
have a signature of bytes
at the very beginning that tell your
program and tell you what kind of file
it is.
So, for instance, a PDF tends
to begin with these 4 bytes.
Or rather, 4 bytes
represent these numbers
when stored as integers--
so 37, 80, 68, and 70.
If you see 4 bytes at the beginning
of a file that look like 37,
80, 68, and 70, that file, turns
out, will most likely be a PDF.
And other files have
their own signatures
that they can tell you what kind of file
they are at the very beginning of them.
So what we'll do is write a program
that actually opens up any given file
and tells us whether that
file is a PDF or is not a PDF
based on those first 4 bytes.
So let's go ahead and do that.
I'll go back to my program here,
and I'll refresh the window
so I'm able to set up my codespace.
And I'll wait for that to load.
And while we do, let me ask what
questions we have on this prompt here,
if any--
on file signatures.
A question I see is, what
happens if my chunk is
bigger than the last bit in the file?
A good question.
So you could imagine, let's say you're
reading maybe 8 bytes at a time.
And you get to the end of your file,
and there are only 4 bytes left to read.
Well, what might happen
with fread is it actually
won't read past the end of your file.
And instead of giving you 8
bytes, it'll give you 4 back.
And the cool thing about fread
is that it'll return to you
the number of elements it has read.
So if you say, read me eight
elements of 1 byte size each,
it'll return to you the number
8 if it successfully did that.
If it only read four
it'll return to you 4.
Or if it only read three,
it'll return to you 3.
Or zero, it'll return to you 0.
So fread does have a return
value you can use to figure out,
are you at the end of
your file, or are you not?
So I think here my codespace is
loaded, so I will get set up here.
And we're going to finish
this pdf.c program.
So I will code pdf.c.
And here I have the
beginnings of my program.
So the goal is to use
pdf.c a bit like this--
./pdf and then typing in some file
name, like, let's say, test.pdf.
And my program will say, yes, this
is a PDF, or no, it's not a PDF.
So the very first thing
I should probably do
is figure out how I
can get that file name.
And it turns out that that file name
is going to be the first command line
argument to my program.
So if I do ./pdf test.pdf, I could
access that file name using argv
bracket 1, as we
learned in a prior week.
So here I'll go ahead
and write the following.
I'll say that I'm going to
get a string called filename,
and it will be equal to argv bracket 1.
So not the very first argument,
which is PDF, this ./pdf part here,
but the second part, which
is test.pdf right here.
So now I have a string called filename.
And now I have to try
to open up that file.
So what function could
we use to open up a file?
Any ideas?
We could use fopen.
So fopen allows us to open
up a file, find where it is,
and return to us a pointer to that
file we can use in our program.
So I'll use fopen here.
And it turns out fopen takes a
file name as its first input.
So whatever file name is in argv bracket
1, I'll give that as input to fopen.
And I'll try to open that file
using just the mode r for reading.
I don't want to modify the file.
I just want to read from it.
But now I have to keep track
of the pointer to this file.
So to create a file pointer,
I can use this FILE * type
and make sure I give it a name.
In this case, I'll call
it f for consistency.
And I'll say I have a
pointer to a file called f.
It is of type FILE *, FILE pointer.
And it is the result of calling fopen
on some file name to open up that file
and tell me exactly
where it is in memory.
OK, so now with f available, I need to
figure out how I can read from my file.
But to read from my file,
what do I need first?
Thinking back to what we had
seen earlier about fread,
there are a few questions to answer.
I think we know where we're going to
read from, but what do we still need?
Probably, I'm seeing some
people say, a place to read to.
So we're going to read from our file.
But now, in our own program, we need to
have some space to store those values.
So, in this case, it's probably
worth thinking about, first, we
want to read into a certain place.
But then again, how many
chunks are we going to read,
and how big are those chunks?
Turns out that a PDF is full
of one-byte chunks of memory,
and we want to read the first four.
So one way we could
do that is by reading
1 byte one at a time four times.
Or we could use an array and store those
first 4 bytes back to back to back.
So, often, buffers will
be arrays of values.
And in this case, I'll try doing that.
I'll make an array of
integers because we're
going to look at those first 4 bytes in
the PDF and think of them as integers
and ask, is this equal to some
value, like in this case 37,
80, 68, and 70, those first 4 bytes?
So I'll create some space in my
program to store four integers.
And this, as we saw in prior
weeks, is the syntax to do that.
I now have an array called
buffer that stores four types,
and those types are int
back to back to back.
Now, this is good but not
quite particular enough.
So if you recall from
lecture, we might have
this idea of an integer being
worth about 4 bytes in size.
And notice here that, well, we want
to read things in individual bytes,
like 1 byte at a time,
not 4 bytes at a time.
So we're going to use an integer type
but a special kind of integer type.
And that is one called a uint8_t,
which looks a little weird.
But, basically, all
this is doing is saying,
I want not just the generic integer
type, which is 4 bytes long.
I want, in particular, an
integer that is 8 bits or 1 byte
long that is unsigned,
that is only positive,
and that entire thing is its own type.
So uint8_t.
This is essentially a
particular kind of integer,
and it comes as part of the
standard int library here.
So I only know this because
I looked it up beforehand.
But when you're reading files, you
could look up what kind of type
is best suited for reading
data from that file.
Turns out that is a uint8_t for
this particular kind of file.
And in CS50, we'll tell you
in advance what kind of type
you should use when you're going to
read from a particular kind of file,
all right?
So here I have my buffer.
And now I need to ask how I
could read into that buffer.
Probably going to use fread here.
And does anyone remember what the
first argument to fread is going to be?
We were answering four questions here.
Where we're reading from,
where we're reading to--
and the first one is indeed
where we're going to read to.
So we're going to read
into our buffer here.
And the next question is,
how big are the chunks?
Well, they're 1 byte
long, as we said before.
The next question is, how many
chunks to read all at once?
Well, four to read all at once.
And now we're going to
read from our file pointer.
So notice we're not doing
filename, not the name of our file,
but instead the file
pointer, f in this case.
So with that, we actually successfully
have some data inside our buffer.
And we can prove it.
So I will write a for loop here--
for int i = 0; i is less than 4; i++
to go from 0 to 3 and read through
our entire buffer.
I'll print out whatever's inside
that buffer as an integer, like this,
and I'll say buffer bracket i.
And then at the very end, I
will close our file like this
to make sure we're being
safe with our memory.
I'll make pdf, run ./pdf test.pdf,
and now we see those first 4 bytes
in our file.
I have another file here too.
I could say ./pdf or dot slash--
yeah, sorry, ./pdf and
then test.jpg, I believe.
Hit Enter.
And notice now these are very
different values for this JPEG.
So the very first 4 bytes are
255, 216, 255, and then 224.
So we see here this signature of
what this file is telling us its type
might be.
And we said before, well, a
PDF seems to have these first 4
bytes of 37, 80, 68, and 70.
So questions here on
how this is working.
We first opened our
file, created a buffer,
used fread to read 4 individual
bytes from that file,
and then printed those out as we went.
A question here on, does
this apply to all file types?
Generally, all file types
will have some signature
or some metadata that tells you what
type of file they're going to be.
A question.
What if we used int instead of uint8_t?
I'm actually curious about this
too, so I'll try int here as well.
I will recompile PDF.
I'll do ./pdf test.pdf.
That doesn't look as good.
And I'm curious why you think
this might have happened.
What might have gone wrong?
So remember that the reason
we used uint8_t is that it
was the right size of value to use.
So the key thing about a uint8_t is
that it is only a single byte big.
A regular integer,
though, is 4 bytes big.
So here what we see is that
we're trying to perhaps create
an array of up to 16 bytes if
an integer is 4 bytes long.
But we're only going to read four
of them into that particular buffer.
So if we take 4 bytes and
store them inside this buffer,
well, we might not get
the values we expect.
And that's why it's important,
when you're reading files,
to make sure you're using
the appropriate types
and getting particular about the
kinds of types you're going to use.
So I revert this back to
uint8_t, which basically
means an integer that is going
to be always positive, that is
8 bits or 1 byte long.
I can now recompile--
make pdf, ./pdf test.pdf,
and I'll see the numbers
as I expect them to be.
And a good follow-on question here.
This program is decent,
but I wouldn't say it's
quite all the way, let's say, safe.
So you can imagine me doing this.
If I type in ./pdf and leave
this last argument blank,
who knows what could happen, right,
because we're going to try to move
beyond argv and access some value.
So there is some more
work to do here, which
I'll leave up to you to make sure we
have the right number of command line
arguments and so on.
Other questions conceptually
on reading and writing?
Question on the _t here.
So _t basically identifies
this as its very own type.
So it's kind of a convention here.
And this is broken out into a few parts.
u stands for unsigned only positive.
int stands, of course, for integer.
8 stands for the number of bits used.
We have 8.
We have 16 as well.
And then _t means all of
that is its very own type.
And a question here.
What is the return value of fread?
That's an interesting question.
So why don't I try that out?
I could say int blocks_read
because I know fread returns to me
the number of blocks that
it did read successfully.
So maybe I'll print out
the buffer, and at the end,
I'll also print out "Blocks
read %i backslash n".
I'll substitute blocks_read
in here like this.
I will then make pdf
and do ./pdf test.pdf.
And I'll see I successfully
read four blocks.
If I got to the end of my file, I might
see fewer, or I might see none at all.
Good question.
OK, so I think this brings us
close to the end of our section.
Suffice to say, in
problem set this week,
we get a lot more practice
using fread and fwrite even.
Before we go off to our own studies,
I want to remind you all of fwrite
as well.
And one handy trick here
is that fwrite is basically
the same ordering as fread.
Notice we have buffer, size of
the chunk, number of chunks,
and the place to now write into.
The only difference,
as I just said before,
is that we're now not just reading
from the file into our buffer.
We're copying from our buffer into
the file and adding data as we go.
All right.
So that, I think, should hopefully
set you up very well for this week.
Feel free to reach out if
you have any questions.
And, hopefully, see you next time.