YULIIA ZHUKOVETS: OK, welcome to CS50.
This is week eight.
Today, we'll be covering a lot
of stuff on web development--
HTML, CSS, and all
the other good things.
My name is Yuliia.
I'm one of the preceptors
here at CS50 at Harvard.
And let's kick things in.
So as you know, this
past week, David was
talking about all things about
development, anything from how internet
works to how we actually
construct the web pages that we
interact with on everyday basis.
So just to recap some of
the main things that David
talked about in the
lecture and something
that we'll be covering
today, HTTP, which
does someone want to
give us the definition
of what HTTP is to get us started here?
Feel free to type it in the chat as
a direct message for everyone to see.
So yeah, I'm seeing some good answers.
HTTP is a hypertext transfer
protocol, which is essentially
a thing that allows the
servers and the computers
to interact between each
other and for us to access
all the information on the web.
Then we'll get going with
HTML, which essentially
is a tool and a language that allows
us to build all these web pages.
And we'll jump into CSS and JavaScript
that makes things a little bit more
interesting in our web pages.
So as we already talked about, HTTP
is the hypertext transfer protocol,
which essentially allows the
servers and the computers
to interact between each other to
send, get requests or post requests,
and to get the information that the
user might need from the internet.
And as you might have
seen in the lecture,
David ran a command
that's called http-server.
Does anyone want to type in the chat
what http-server actually does for us
when we type it out in the terminal?
Exactly, yeah, so it creates a server
that listens to the HTTP requests.
And so when I click on
something on the HTML page,
I essentially send a request that a
server can respond to and provide me
with the information that I asked for.
So we're going to move on to HTML
and get a lot practice with how
to build web pages, what
components go into it,
and how all the web pages are actually
constructed that we see every day.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to open a scoreboard dot
HTML that I already have in cs50.dev.
You are free to,
welcome to follow along.
And later on, we'll post the resource,
and you can access the file yourself.
So essentially what is
going on here is that we
have an HTML file that's already
prepopulated with some information.
So first I'm going to run http-server
to see what is actually going on here.
OK, so I'm going to
zoom in a little bit so
that everyone can see what's going on.
Essentially, what we have
is a quite simple HTML
page where it is a table that
has three rows and two columns.
And what the page currently does is
that I can click one of these buttons.
And you can see that the score inside
the table for a corresponding team
will change.
It doesn't really do
much behind this, right?
It's a pretty simple web page.
But we will make some changes
to make it more interactive.
So to go back to the HTML
code that we already have,
let's just break down
what's going on here.
Currently, we only have the
table code in the body tag
that essentially just builds
out the rows and the columns.
And we also have some other components
that we'll talk about later.
So to actually go into the
whole structure of the HTML,
what we can see here
is a thing that we call
DOM, which is a Document Object Model.
It is essentially a tree
that builds the HTML files.
It goes top to bottom as
everything in programming.
So at the very top, we
see the document itself.
And it has the HTML code in it.
And so then it splits up
into a head and a body.
And we can see that it then goes into a
different component of the HTML files.
So in the head, we have information
like title that goes on the tab
that you open-- essentially
the name of the web page.
It takes in a style, so the
different CSS components
that we can modify to make our
web page a little bit prettier.
And then on the right side, we have
the body of the HTML that contains,
in this case, a table that
has other components to it
and also a script that
would contain, in this case,
some JavaScript code that makes the
web page a little bit more interactive.
So now let's actually
examine what's going
on underneath the hood
for the table component.
Well, as you saw in
the code, it actually
is a bunch of different things.
Essentially, what is going on here is
that we have our rows that have tag tr.
And then each row has
some td components, which
essentially are like individual cells.
So again, the structure
goes top to bottom
where we start with a
big overarching tag.
You can call it a parent.
And then it goes into
smaller children that
have some smaller information in it.
In such a way, we have,
for example, the first row
that contains the names of the teams--
Team 1 and Team 2--
the second row that will
be storing our score.
In this case, it's set to zero.
And the third row, it
contains the button.
That actually splits
up into two components
where we specify that the tag actually
has to be a button and not just text.
But at the same time,
we can set that text
of the button to be something else.
In this case, it is plus 1.
So the overall structure of the
HTML code is very top to bottom.
You can think about it as a tree
that starts from document HTML
and goes into different parts of it.
So before we move on to actually
modifying our scoreboard HTML
and adding some things to it, do we
have any questions about the structure
of the HTML for now?
OK, sounds good.
So now let's move on into the scoreboard
HTML where we will add some things.
So these are some things
that I laid out for us to do.
But there's certainly so many other
tags that you can explore on the web.
W3Schools is a great
resource to look into things.
And let's switch to the
code and change some things.
So first, I am going to introduce some
bigger, overarching kind of like parent
tags that currently are
not in our HTML code.
So one thing that we're
going to add first
is you can see we still
have our head and body.
What we're going to
introduce is some other tags.
For example, we're going to introduce
a tag header, which essentially
is going to have a title of our page.
And I'm going to leave that
blank for just a second.
Our next big overarching
tag is going to be
main, which is going to be kind of
like the main part of our HTML page
where we're going to store our table.
And the last part is going to be
a footer, so something that you
see on the bottom of your web page.
Usually, I think it's small copyright
tags, that, for example, David
introduced in lecture.
So let's start populating these things.
First, for the header,
let's do something
like H1, which is just one of
the tags for our HTML file.
And I'm going to say something
like left team versus right team.
And I'm going to close my tag.
And then I'm going to
maybe do a paragraph
tag that says, hey, there, click
a button to change the score.
OK, so this is our header.
And actually you can see that I'm
still running my http-server here
in the terminal.
And it's listening to all
the changes that I'm making.
And so if I go back to
my scoreboard web page,
you can see the changes that we made.
Now we have our big header
that we just implemented.
And we have our paragraph,
kind of like the subtext
that's giving a little bit
more information of what's
going on the HTML page.
Now, since we already have a
main part of our web page ready,
I'm just going to copy and
paste the table inside the main.
So nothing is really changing.
We're just introducing some bigger,
overarching tags that really
don't change much about HTML page.
But we use it for better
readability and for better design
so that it is very clear to
another user who might open
your code that here's what's going on.
We have a header, the main, and
the footer separating the HTML
into these three parts
so that it's easier
to find information or
change the code later on.
And in the footer, for example, I
can say something like made by CS50--
something simple.
It can be made by Juliia or if
Carter was here, made by Carter,
so still using the same paragraph
tag that we've seen before.
And let's just reload to make
sure all the changes are here.
And yes, you can see that we
have the title, the subtext,
and the footer present on
the web page right now.
Before we move on to other things, do
we have any questions about HTML tags--
introducing different tags
and modifying the code?
There are certainly so many
other things that you can do.
And there are so many other
tags that you can explore.
One of the questions is, does
footer make text smaller?
Not necessarily.
For example, I can remove
the footer from here.
And I will just keep my paragraph tag.
And let's reload to see.
It's still the same, right, because
HTML structure goes top to bottom.
And it really is only outputting
on the web page itself--
the tags that I'm putting in.
And footer main and the same
way header is kind of just
like breaking it down
in the code so that it
is easier for readability for the
user who might open your code later on
to make some changes.
But that's a great question.
I'm just going to revert
to back to what we had.
Is it normal for tables
to be centered by default?
Let's check.
Actually, we've already
modified the table style
to be centered, which we'll
get into just in a few moments.
But that's a very great question.
Yes.
I think by default,
everything is left centered.
So you definitely need to go in
and make the changes yourself.
What other questions do
we have before we move on?
OK, let's go back to our slides.
And what we're going to
talk about now is CSS.
Does anyone know what
CSS is, what it does,
how does it make our web
page a little bit better?
Great, yes, it's cascading style sheets.
So CSS is what makes the
web pages pretty, right?
We barely have any
style applied right now.
It looks very black and white.
But CSS is what makes all
the websites look so pretty.
And with the bootstraps and all the
other resources that are out there,
you can make the web pages really
interactive and really user-friendly,
improving their user experience.
So let's jump into it.
How actually do we use CSS?
So the way that the syntax works is that
you will have some kind of selector.
It can be a tag.
It can be an ID.
It can be a class.
And then in the curly braces, you would
specify the property and the value.
For example, as we've already talked
about, it can be the text align.
Or it can be a font.
It can be the size of
the font or the color
and really so many other properties
that you can change on the web page
to make it a little bit prettier.
So for example, here, I have all
of my components of the table.
So for example, if I wanted to
apply some particular property
to our tag td, what I could do
is select all of the td tags.
I'm specifying my tag right here.
I'm opening the curly braces.
And I can specify some particular
properties in the same--
yeah, so it will go in and
grab all of the td tags
that it sees in the HTML file.
And it will apply that same
property to all of them.
In the same way, I can do
something a little bit different.
And I can just pick one
element that I want to modify.
And I can do that by
assigning a tag and ID.
So in this case, I have ID score1.
And I can specify that for
this particular element that
has an ID score1, I want the
color to be red, for example.
And so what it will do, it will look
through the whole tree of our HTML
tags.
It will go in.
And it will find an element
that has an ID score of 1.
And it will apply a particular property
that we picked for it to this tag.
In a similar way, if there
are, for example, multiple tags
that I want to apply
the same property to
but they're not
necessarily the same tags--
for example, I want to apply
the same property too--
I don't know-- say, like, all
the tr tags and all the td tags,
I want to, for example,
modify the font--
I could do that by assigning
them a specific class.
So in this case, the class
can specify by dot team.
And I can assign some properties.
For example, I want the font to be bold.
So the main difference
in syntax just to recap
is that for the tags, when
you want to specify it in CSS,
it is just the tag name for IDs.
It's hashtag ID name.
And for the classes,
it's dot class name.
So moving on, let's go back
to our scoreboard dot HTML.
And let's look at some of the
style that we've already modified.
And before we jump into changing
some things, what questions do
we have about the syntax of CSS,
how we can apply that to our HTML,
or anything along those lines?
OK, let's get going then.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm
just going to modify a few things.
Before I do that, let's just go
over what we already have here.
So as you can see, we've already
applied some stylistic changes
to the tag table.
So it means that it will apply
to the entire table that we have.
So we changed the border.
And then we changed the
margins a little bit.
And we aligned it to be centered.
And then we set a
specific stylistic change
to an element td, which makes
the border a little bit bigger.
But how about modifying other elements?
Well, let's say that I want
my header and my subtext
and my footer to be
aligned in the center.
Well, how can I do that?
My header and the other two
components are different tags.
Let me just start with the
subtext and the footer.
And if we go back, we can see
that the subtext has tag p.
And my footer also has tag p.
So what I could do is
go back to my style tag.
And in here, I'm going
to say for tag p, what
I want to do is align it in the center.
So I'm going to do
text-align center semicolon.
Save it.
Reload the page.
And boom, our subtext
and our footer now is
centered in the middle, which
makes it a little easier to read.
And everything is now in one place.
So let's go back to our code
and say I want to now modify
the background color for my team names.
It seems a little black and white.
So I want to change it.
Well, what can I do is
if I apply it to tag td,
it means that everything's
going to change the color.
But it's two elements, so ID
doesn't really make sense.
So what can I do in this
case is assign it a class.
So for example, I'm going
to call it class team.
Don't forget about the dot operator
that we want to use in this case.
I'm going to change the
background color to be crimson.
And I looked up the hex value for that.
So this will make the
background color crimson.
I go in.
I reload.
It didn't change.
What happened?
What did we miss?
I went in.
And I did the style.
I changed the color.
But what am I missing here?
Right.
I didn't specify that
my class is now a team.
Great catch.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to go into my element.
And I'm going to say
that I actually want
to assign a class team here and
then class team right here as well.
Save it.
Reload.
And boom, now my background color is
different but just for those two cells,
not for any other row.
OK, so now what I want
to do is maybe I want
to have my buttons be different
colors but not the background color,
just the text so that
I can distinguish it.
And I can already see that
they have IDs assigned
to them, which is very
useful to me because now I
can just go to our style part.
And all I need to do is specify the ID.
I want to change just the text color.
So for that, the property's
going to be color.
And I'm going to make team one crimson.
And then for ID 2, I am
going to make it blue.
OK, great.
I think this is supposed to be zero.
OK, I already have my ID specified.
So there are no changes to be made.
Right here I already have add1 and add2.
So if I reload the page, oh--
did I miss something?
Nice catch.
[LAUGHS] Wrong spelling.
Let's reload.
Hm.
Let's try something different.
I tested it with score1 and score2.
So let's see if that might work.
A-ha, OK, this worked.
So now we have 0 and 0
in crimson and in blue.
I wonder why it didn't quite
work out for the buttons.
This is something for me to debug later.
But as you can see, you
can also change the font
of the color for different IDs.
Before we move on, do we have
any questions about this?
Oh, thank you so much
for catching that--
add1 and id1.
OK, let's maybe make
these changes as well so
that it can reflect on
the rest of the web page.
I'm going to copy this.
OK, yay.
Boom, it works for the button as well.
Thank you for catching it.
Any questions that we have about
CSS applying properties, changing
the values?
There are a lot of the things
that you can do with it.
And there's certainly
resources like Bootstrap
that already have all these
stylistic changes premade for you
that you can kind of just
import into your own code.
But there is a question about
how to change a button color.
So here, we've already
changed the color of the text.
To change the button color, you
can do something very similar--
for example, change
the background color.
And since it has the
button tag to it, I believe
you can just specify button tag on
top of your code in the style part.
And it should apply the
changes to all of the buttons.
We have a question.
How did you use CSS in an HTML file?
So there are two ways to go about it.
And we will talk about the
second way a little bit later.
But for now, what I'm doing is that
in my head that contains title.
I also have my tag style that
essentially incorporates all the CSS
changes that I am making.
But we will talk about other alternative
way of storing CSS properties later on.
OK, so let's go back
to our slides for now.
The next topic we're
going to be talking about
is JavaScript, which makes our web
pages a little bit more interactive.
Right now, you can see
that all I'm really doing
is I'm clicking the button.
And it's changing the score,
what is already JavaScript.
But there are actually so many
other things that you can do.
And actually, every
time you see a change
on the web page, that
doesn't necessarily, like,
refresh the page for you and
bring you to the next one over.
That's where JavaScript is working.
It's, like, modifying some
things on the web page
for you immediately to see without
necessarily sending it back
as a request to the server.
So what's going on underneath the hood?
Let's go back to our
code and see what changes
we've already made in our JavaScript.
So as you can see on the
bottom of my body tag,
so still in the body not
outside, I have a separate part
that is surrounded by script tag.
This is where all of my
JavaScript is happening.
What I'm doing here is I'm saying,
OK, I'm going to look at ID add1.
And once it's clicked, I'm
going to apply some things.
And the same thing is
going on with add2,
which are essentially our
tags right here, the buttons.
So JavaScript code is
looking for ID add1, ID add2.
Once it's clicked,
it's doing the function
of adding one point to the existing
score of Team 1 and Team 2.
And then it goes on to find ID score1.
It goes into the inner HTML,
which essentially is the text
that you see, the text you specified.
And it's updating the score.
So if we go back right
here, what I'm doing
is once I click button
plus one that has ID add1,
JavaScript now records the
new score and updates the text
that we are storing right
here under the tag score1.
And the same thing is happening for
Team 2, where as many times as I click,
the score is now changing.
So now that we kind of parsed
what's going on in our code,
let's go back and see how actually
all of these changes are happening.
So for example, we have
a statement-- document
dot query selector, parentheses,
quotes, hashtag add1.
So add1 is an ID, as we
already talked about.
So what JavaScript
actually does, it searches
for the entire tree top to bottom
looking for that particular ID.
So as we've seen this structure
before, it first goes into the document
and then goes into the HTML.
Then it goes into the
body, down to the table.
And then we have our table structure.
And it keeps going down,
down, down until it
finds the ID that we're looking for.
In this case, ID is
add1, which is a button.
And so it had found it.
In the same way, when we
have onclick, what it does
is that it looks for the ID 1--
sorry-- for the add1 ID once
we clicked that particular tag.
Another statement that
we just saw is document
dot query selector, hashtag
score1 and dot, innerHTML.
So what innerHTML now stands for
is really the text that we've
specified in our HTML file previously.
And in the same way,
the whole code is going
to search the entire tree looking
for that particular ID, score1
and going then into the
innerHTML or the text of that tag
to do the necessary changes, so
a very top to bottom approach.
It has a lot of things to look for.
But that's what's going on
underneath the hood for JavaScript.
What questions do we have before
we jump back into our code
and add on some other
JavaScript features?
And again, kind of just to
mention is that we're touching
on just a few basic things today.
And David covered some more
extensive examples in the lecture.
But there's certainly so many other
things you can do with JavaScript.
And definitely everything that
you see on the web page utilizes--
all the web pages regularly
utilizes all of these languages
to make the user experience much better.
So Python is compatible
with CSS and HTML.
It just, it works a
little bit differently.
So for example, JavaScript can be
embedded directly into the HTML file
while with Python, it will have to be
through some different kind of, like,
framework.
It's something that we'll see next
week when we're working with Flask
and we're implementing
more extensive website
where we have actually the
interaction between the server
and the web page going on.
In that case, we're using
kind of, like, Python
on the back end where we're managing
the server requests, while JavaScript,
HTML, and CSS are all
working on the front end,
really making the changes to the
web page and to the visual things
that folks see on the screen.
That's a great question.
All righty, so moving on,
what we're going to do
is we're going to go
into scoreboard dot HTML.
And we're going to alert the user
when a certain team won the game.
So I'm going to go back into my code.
I already have some code pre-written
here as we already talked about.
And what I'm going to do is that modify
it a little bit so that we can actually
see other visual changes on the screen.
So for example, I decided that my
team would win if it has 5 points.
That seems somewhat fair.
[CHUCKLES] It seems enough of points
to get to be considered a winner.
So what I'm going to do
is make some conditions.
I'm already tracking my score
using Team 1 and Team 2 variables.
So I already took care of that.
What I'm going to do here is I'm going
to say if Team 1, which is the score,
is equal to 5, I am going to
set an alert saying Team 1 won.
Then I save the changes,
reload the page.
Click, click, click, click, click,
boom, you can see I'm going--
I can't zoom in more.
But you can see that
on the top, I now have
an alert window that says Team 1 won.
Now, if I do it for the Team 2, nothing
is happening, although I'm definitely
reaching a lot of points.
So let's just go back and make
the necessary changes here.
So I'm just going to do the same thing
where I'm going to say if Team 2 now--
if Team 2 score is now equal to 5, I
am going to create an alert for Team 2.
And now if I go back and
I reload, Team 1 won.
I got an alert.
And Team 2 won.
I get an alert.
And it's actually interesting to see
that the alert happens when I click.
And the score is technically 5.
But alert appears before the HTML
actually changes it to a score of 5.
I have a question in the chat.
Could you not use the kind of
[? CLion ?] line operator for the or?
So because it is separated in
our JavaScript code by IDs--
we're looking at one
element at the time--
I could not do the or
operator to minimize
the code because in
this JavaScript setup,
it is looking at one
particular element at a time.
So it listens for the
onclick for the tag add1
and then makes all the necessary
changes within kind of that branch.
So there are definitely
ways to optimize.
I'm sure you can click more
than 5 because we didn't really
set any restrictions.
We kind of just said,
like, once it's 5, Team 1,
but we can certainly keep going.
And before we move on, I want
to show you one more feature.
Do we have any questions
about this part?
The syntax is certainly
somewhat similar to what we saw.
For example, we have same way of
kind of setting the variables.
Semicolons are back, unfortunately.
But for example, we
don't need to specify
a data type or some of those things.
So we have a question.
Is it better to select an HTML
element with query selector
instead of get element by ID?
I'm pretty sure both
are interchangeable.
It just depends on what
syntax you're using.
Query selector would allow you to
use it on the IDs, on the classes,
and on tags, versus get element by
ID is just with those specific--
like for a specific ID, so depending
on how you want to set up your code.
OK, so what I'm going to
do here now is I'm still
going to announce the winner,
just a little bit differently.
So I'm just going to
[INAUDIBLE] this out.
What I'm instead going to do is
create a paragraph tag up here.
But I'm actually not
specifying anything.
I'm just giving it an ID.
I'm going to give it an ID
result, so result. Great.
So if I go back in here,
there's nothing, right?
I specified a paragraph tag.
But I didn't put any text in, so you
can't really see it on the web page
right now.
What I'm going to do instead
is instead of creating
an alert that's kind of
like a browser thing,
I'm going to modify something
within our HTML page.
I'm going to do document query selector.
And I'm going to grab
my ID result. And I'm
going to change an innerHTML for that.
So it's a very similar structure
to what we're doing up here.
We're grabbing, for example, score
of 1 and changing the innerHTML
to a specific number.
I'm going to do exact same thing here.
But I'm just going to put
in text instead of numbers.
And now if we go back,
reload, we still see nothing.
The tag is there.
But text isn't.
But once I click--
oops.
What's going on?
Let me see where I might have messed up.
Hm.
And I didn't change anything here.
That is very true.
You're not doing it right if you
don't get bugs once in a while.
Let me cut out this whole part and
just test it out as we've had before.
OK, so there's definitely something with
my if statement that wasn't working.
So let's just maybe delete this part.
And let's check our syntax--
document dot query selector.
A-ah, a dot-- that's
why it wasn't working.
OK, so let's go back.
I can now make the changes.
So we click 2, 3, 4, 5.
And now I see my innerHTML changed
to Team 1 won in the paragraph tag
that I specified earlier
but that was empty.
I can now go in and do
exact same thing for Team 2.
I'm just going to
change it to Team 2 won.
And now if we go back
and refresh, Team 2 won.
So these are some of the
things that you can do.
As you can see, I didn't necessarily
specify any text in the beginning.
I just put in a plain tag.
But you can go in later
on using JavaScript
to make the necessary changes
to update your innerHTML
or even change the color.
I'm going to Zoom out a little
bit so that it's fully visible.
But what questions do we have about,
at this point, HTML, CSS, JavaScript--
kind of all of that
we've talked about today?
These are certainly just small bits
and pieces that I'm showing today.
But it definitely has a lot of
potential for a lot more things.
If you get a score of 5 on both,
will the Team 1 and Team 2 won both
appear on the screen?
Or will the first one get priority?
That is a great question.
And we can test it out.
So for example, if I go evenly, right--
I'm updating it one after another--
I reach 4.
So if I add a score to Team
1, we'll see Team 1 won.
But now if I add the score
to Team 2, it changes
to Team 2 won because that's the
sequence that it happened in.
And then you can actually see
that it doesn't disappear.
Once you keep clicking the buttons,
it's kind of, like, static.
It doesn't really go
anywhere at this point.
There's certainly changes that you can
make where you kind of, like, restrict.
You don't allow a user
to click more buttons
after they reach the score of 5.
Or you make the tag that
we've created, Team 2
won, disappear after a few
seconds after you clicked it.
There are a lot of components
to JavaScript and to HTML that
can make all of these things possible.
And we're certainly just, like,
scratching the surface of these three
languages today but introducing
some of the most common features.
All righty, if we don't
have any questions,
there's just one last thing
that I wanted to show you.
So we've made a lot of
changes to our HTML file.
We started by modifying our
HTML body, adding some new tags,
as well as introducing
some overarching tags that
help us break out the code better.
We've made some changes to the
JavaScript to make it more interactive
so that the web page is a
little bit more dynamic.
And we certainly made a lot
of changes to our style tag.
And as you can see, it
is getting very long.
We have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
7, 8 different changes.
So does anyone have an idea how we can
make this look a little bit better?
How can we make our current
code look a little bit shorter
in the dot HTML file?
That's a great idea.
Yes, we can move it to a different file,
so completely move CSS out of the way.
So why don't we go and do that.
So I am going to create
a new terminal so that I
don't stop my website from running.
I am going to create a
file called styles dot CSS.
And I'm just going to copy over--
oop-- I'm going to copy over all of
the changes that we made to our styles
dot CSS, save it, go back
to scoreboard dot title.
Now I can get rid of these
tags because I already
moved my styles to the other place.
And what I'm going to do instead
is I'm going to link my HTML file
and my CSS file together.
So I'm going to create
a tag link and specify
that the relationship is stylesheet.
And I'm going to reference
file styles dot CSS.
Close the tag, save it, save
this again, go back, reload.
And you can see that all
of the changes still apply.
So we still have the color
change for the background.
We still change the color of
the fonts by moving the styles--
kind of like CSS
properties-- out of the way.
We also made our HTML
look a little bit cleaner.
Instead of now having rows and
rows of different properties,
we now just have our HTML
tags and our HTML body.
There's also a way to move
JavaScript out of the way
so that it doesn't make your HTML
file look a little bit more complex.
But for now, we can just
keep it in here as we just
have maybe like a dozen lines.
And it's not really
abstracting our HTML for now.
But what questions do
we have about anything
that we've done today
about changing the styles,
linking the sheets together,
creating classes, IDs, new tags?
So we have a question in the chat.
Is it necessary to keep the
script tag at the bottom?
For now, yes, because we still have
our JavaScript code and our HTML file.
If we decide to move
JavaScript to a different file,
it's going to be slightly
different syntax.
Unfortunately, I don't
have an example on me.
But I'm sure this is something
that you can look up very easily.
Do we have any other questions?
The question is, is this session
going to be posted after it?
And, yes, certainly we will post it
on the website a little bit later.
And you all should
have access to it, yes.
All right, sounds good.
Well, thank you so much for joining.
This was Section 8 of really
delving into the web development--
HTML, CSS, internet, things related.
Thank you so much for joining us today.
I hope I lived up to your expectations
and I was a good for Carter.
But I'm looking forward to seeing
you all in the next sessions.