YULIIA: Welcome to
week five supersection.
This is CS50.
And my name is Yuliia.
I'm one of the preceptors
at Harvard for CS50,
and Charlie is joining
me today from Yale.
CHARLIE: Yes, and my name is
Charlie, like Yuliia said.
I'm one of the head teaching
assistants for CS50 at Yale.
And it is great to be
with all of you today.
YULIIA: Great, so why don't
we go ahead and get started?
So today we're going to be
talking about data structures.
So a lot of the things that David
talked about in the lecture.
We're going to cover linked
lists and hash tables.
Very briefly talk about
tries, and then we're
going to go into the
inheritance problem set or lab
if you are joining from Yale.
So just to give a quick
overview of different operations
you can do with these
data structures, there
is deletion, insertion, and search.
And they can go in various priorities.
You can search first and then maybe
insert delete, or do something
like insertion, search, deletion then.
We're going to cover insertion
and deletion in section today
but feel free to play around with the
search operations a little bit more.
So as in lectures, there
are a few data structures
that we're going to be
talking about today.
First one is linked
list, which essentially
is kind of like a chain
of nodes, something
that David illustrated with
balloons in lecture on Wednesday.
And Charlie's going to
talk a little bit more
about the structure of linked nodes.
How we insert and how we delete it
and all the different operations
you can do with them.
And next one on is hash tables,
which actually are really fun.
And essentially, a hash table is
just an array of linked lists.
So on the left side, you can see that it
is just an array with different buckets
corresponding to letters.
And on the right side, they kind of
expand into these bigger linked lists.
Next one is a trie, which we actually
don't really talk about a lot in CS50,
but it's one of the other
data structures that makes
it really easy to look for things.
And kind of on the similar note of
looking for things and doing searches,
are trade-offs between memory and time.
So this is something that you might see
when you will start working in Speller.
This is our board for
the Speller problem
set, where your job will
be to load the dictionary
and then find if the words
are spelled correctly.
So here you can see that Thomas
implemented Speller in such a way
that it takes one less second to
implement than, for example, Karger's
solution, but you can also see that it
takes up almost twice as much memory
than Curtis solution.
So while we do want to
emphasize the efficiency
and how quick the program
can be, memory is some kind
of is the other trade-off
that we want to keep
in mind while we are coding our program
and talking about data structures
this week.
So with that being said,
I'm going to pass it
on to Charlie, who is really going
to jump into nodes, the linked list,
and explain all the good stuff about it.
CHARLIE: Absolutely, so let's go
ahead and jump into nodes here.
And we're going to get started by
taking a look at some of the base code
that we'll use to define
exactly what a node is in C.
So we take a look at
this slide right here.
We have a little bit of code
on our screen right now,
and we're going to break down exactly
what each component inside this code
is.
We're going to start off with
this struct node definition.
So this tells C that we're going to
create a custom structure, or struct
and we're going to call it a node.
Then we're going to define what's
contained inside of this custom data
structure.
This node that we're defining.
So the first thing that we want is a box
that represents a string called phrase.
So if we take a look on the
right side of your screen here,
we have this new box to store a
phrase which is of data type string.
Then we can store any string value that
we want, such as "Hi," for example,
inside this box.
We can also store "Bye" and
any other valid string value
as long as we enclose it within the
double quotes as seen on the screen
here.
Now let's move on to the second part of
what's contained inside of this node.
Notice how on this line,
we have node *next.
This is what we're going to use to
link this node to the rest of our nodes
inside of a linked list.
We use node * because we want
to have a pointer pointing
to the next node in our linked list.
If you take a look on your
screen over here to the right,
you can now see a new box, below
phrase, that we are calling "next"
to store the pointer to the next node.
You can see that we fill in the
value here with a pointer address.
And this pointer address is
represented in hexadecimal.
So that's why you have the 0x
in front as the prefix denoting
this as hexadecimal.
And then we have a random address value,
in this case, an example value of 123.
This value could be anything.
It could be 1, 2, 3.
It could be 4, 5, 6 or
it could be anything else
wherever that next node is located
within the memory of your computer.
So now let's jump back out to
the definition of this as a whole
and take a look at what this
extra typedef part is over here.
As you can see, we already said
struct node earlier at the top,
but we also have typedef node
surrounding this entire definition.
And the reason why we have
this here is because if I
wanted to use this node data
structure throughout my code,
I would constantly have to type struct
node and then the rest of my code
without this typedef part
if I didn't have it here.
But by including typedef
node in this definition,
I can simply refer to
this data structure
just as node throughout my code.
And we'll see here in a
second how this actually
works as we start building
our very own linked list.
Now, before I move on,
do we have any questions
on how this node is structured,
quite literally, as a struct in C?
Feel free to put your questions in
the chat, and I'll wait a second here.
If not, we'll move on to building
our very own linked list.
OK, great, no questions, so let's go
ahead and move on to the next part now.
So with this struct node in place, we
can now start building our linked list.
And the very first thing that
we're going to want to do,
is we want to define our
list as a pointer to a node.
And the reason for this
is because our linked list
is a chain of nodes that are
all linked with each other.
So we want to define this node *
list, so this is a list variable that
represents a pointer to a node.
And we're going to start off with null.
Or in other words, right now, we
don't really have a linked list.
It's just empty at the moment.
And if you look below, at the
bottom half of this slide,
you'll see that we have this
arrow called list representing
a pointer to nothing at the moment.
But now let's go ahead and create our
very first node for this linked list.
So notice how we've went ahead
and changed our variable name
to "n" now to represent a new node.
And we're going to now allocate
memory within our computer
to create this node.
We're going to use the malloc
function, and with the malloc function,
you have to tell it
exactly how much space you
want it to allocate within memory.
So what we're going to do
is called sizeof(node).
So that allows us to
tell the computer we
want exactly just enough space
to allocate one node struct
and from there, we're all good.
So if we go to the
next slide here, you'll
see now that we have this
familiar two-box structure that we
defined earlier in this presentation.
And then if you take a
look on this slide here,
we're now going to define what
phrase is within this node.
So we're going to call the phrase
attribute of n, which is our node,
and we're going to set it equal to Hi!
So now if you take a look at that first
box at the bottom, you see that Hi!
Is now populated within the
phrase box of our node n.
We then want to make sure we
have something set for next
since this is a linked list.
So we want to make sure
we have a chain going.
And so far, we only have one
node within our linked list.
So I'm going to go ahead and set
next to null for the time being.
But foreshadowing for
later on, you'll see
that we'll want to modify this value
so that we can chain all of these nodes
together to form our linked list.
Now, there's one more thing that we
have to do, and it's really important.
Notice how so far, we've been
working with the variable
n to represent this new
node that we created.
We want to make sure that we also
point our list towards this n node
because without doing that, our
list value wouldn't actually
point towards anything.
It would still be pointing to null if
you remember from the slides earlier.
So by saying list = n we
have successfully one,
created this new node
object and two, we've
then pointed this list that we're
creating to this first node.
And you might be wondering, why
do we need these two variables n
and list to create this
node struct if they're all
going to point to the same thing?
Well, you'll see here
in a second, when we
create our second node,
why it's important to have
two variables separating
these from each other.
So now let's go and talk about how we're
going to insert nodes into this linked
list that we just created.
We're going to start off
by creating another node,
and this is where the importance
of having two variables n and list
comes into play.
We want our list variable to still
point towards that first node
that we just created earlier, but now,
we want to create a brand new node.
So we're going to, once
again, call malloc.
And the parameter or argument
that we want to give to it
is sizeof(node) because
we want to, again,
allocate exactly just enough space to
create another node within our memory.
So once we do that, n is now pointing
to this brand new node struct
with these two empty boxes down
there at the bottom of your screen.
And we're going to now
fill in the phrase box.
So we're going to assign the value Hey!
to this box.
And now, for next, you'll see that we're
going to point to list instead of null.
And the reason for that is
because we're creating a linked
list, emphasis on the linked component.
So we want to make sure
that this node is pointing
to the one that's supposed to
be after it, which in this case,
is the one with Hi!
as its phrase value.
So if we take a look at
what we have here now,
there's one more thing
that we have to do.
And it's that we have to go back
and update list to be n again.
And that's because a linked list
is tracked by its head value,
or the first node within the list.
So by doing list = n, we move that list
pointer back to the start of our list,
and then we have successfully
inserted a value into our linked list.
Now, let's go ahead and start
cleaning up what we have here.
Let's say, after I've used
this linked list in my code,
I want to go ahead and safely
deallocate or remove all the memory
that I've allocated for this before
ending my program because as you
remember from lecture, it's
always important to make sure
you free any memory that you malloc.
Every time you malloc
something, you must free it.
So let's try out one
thing here, for now.
Let's go ahead and try
free(list) because list
represents my linked list, right?
So why not just free the list?
So as you see down here, we
have that first box blacked
out representing that is
now removed from memory.
But you might notice that we still
have that second node with Hi!
floating around in our memory.
And this is a common mistake
that some people might make when
they're trying to free a linked list.
If you only free the
variable that represents
the head or the start
of your linked list,
in our case that
variable is called list,
you will only free the first node.
And by doing that, you
will miss all the nodes
connected after that first
node in your linked list.
So you'll have memory floating
around on your computer,
and your computer will not
be very happy with that.
So in order to correctly
free this linked list,
we're going to go back
to the start here.
And what we're going to do now, is we're
going to create this temporary pointer
variable to represent the next
element in this linked list.
So that way, if I go
ahead and free the list,
so we gotta black out
that first node box,
we can still see that we have a pointer
called ptr pointing to the second node.
So this allows us to then reference ptr
and free that so that last box is not
floating around in memory space lost.
What we're going to do
now, is say list = ptr
so that we can then reference
that second box again.
And then, once we say
pointer = list next,
that ensures that before we
free what we currently have,
we're referencing whatever's after this.
Now in this case, it's
important to note that there
is nothing after this second node.
So in our case, when we run ptr
= list next, we end up with null.
But that's OK because that's how we can
tell our program later on that, hey,
once you reach null, that means you
reach the end of your linked list.
So there's nothing else
to free in this case.
Now, let's go ahead and
free(list) because list is now
pointing to this second node.
And once you've done
that, you can do list
equals ptr again because
we want to make sure
that we freed everything in this list.
But you will see that
there is nothing left
because ptr is currently equal to null.
So now I'm going to go ahead
and hand it back to Yuliia
for a quick interactive
activity involving linked lists.
YULIIA: Great, Thank you, Charlie.
So yeah, this was, hopefully, a
very clear visual representation
of how linked lists works.
We went through
insertion, deletion, there
is also search that I mentioned in
the very beginning of the slides.
Today, we're only going to
focus on inserting and unloading
and linked lists.
So hopefully, you're able
to download and open list.c
at cs50.ly/supersection1.
Feel free to download it, open
in your VS code and follow along.
But I'm going to go ahead and
do the same thing on my end.
So here, I have the CS50 ID, where
I had pre-downloaded the list.c file
that we will work with today.
So to go back and look
through our to-dos for today,
first thing we're going
to do is implement code
to add a node to the
linked list, something
that Charlie just talked about.
We're going to ensure
that the list always
points to the head of the linked list.
And we also need to ensure that
our new node contains the phrase.
And our second to-do is implementing
the unload function such
that all nodes in the linked list are
freed when the function is called.
As always, remember, if you use malloc,
you want to use free in the end.
And then once the function successfully
freed, all the memory malloced,
we want to return true
to indicate our main
that the memory was successfully freed.
So going back to our code here,
should be very familiar structure.
On very top, we have our headers.
Then we define our
nodes struct that we're
going to use to create
our linked list, write
the typedef struct node and the string
phrase struct node pointer next.
The structure that
Charlie just talked about,
which is really just a box
that where the first half is
some word and the second half is
kind of like a block of memory
that stores the address
that we're pointing to.
And going ahead, we have prototypes for
two functions onload and visualizer.
Something that Carter already
implemented for us, just
a nice representation of
how everything looks like.
And jumping right into the
first to-do, so here in main, we
have already created a pointer list.
Right now it's pointing to null because
we haven't implemented our linked list
yet.
And one of our first to-dos is adding
phrases to new nodes in the list.
Namely, we're going to add two nodes per
the definition of list size to above.
So going off what Charlie
just talked about,
does anyone want to help me out was the
first thing that we need to do here.
So if we want to add a
new node to the list,
we already have a pointer list
null, what do people think
is kind of like the first action here?
Feel free to drop it in the chat any
guesses of what our first line of code
might be.
So first we want to create that node.
And let's call it n
to keep it consistent.
So we can just create a node.
We want to allocate some memory to it.
And for that, we want to
use the malloc function.
And I can use malloc(1).
Would that be right?
Probably not, right,
because I want to keep
my size consistent with the kind
of variables I want to create.
So I probably want to use sizeof(node),
since that's what I'm interested in.
And once I malloc my
memory, it is always
important to double check
if the memory exists.
So for that, I'm going to
create an if statement where
I'm going to say, well, if
n is actually equal to null,
I just want to return 1 and
quit this program altogether.
The memory was not allocated properly.
There is nothing I can do about it.
So I'm just going to quit.
If that is not true,
we want to continue on.
So now that we have our box, our
node, we want to start populating it.
And the first thing that we
want to add is our phrase
that we get_string on line 25.
So to do that, I'm actually
going to go back to check, OK,
what are my attributes in this struct?
I see that I have string
phrase and struct node *next,
so I probably want to store my
word in the attribute phrase.
To do that, remember that
you have the arrow operator.
And I'm going to do n phrase = phrase.
And that way I'm going to store whatever
word I got from the user earlier.
And I'm going to set my
next = to null because there
is nothing to store there yet.
So this is our basic setup
for one of the first nodes.
Now we actually want to connect
them in one linked list.
So far it's just one node, but
we're going to add one more.
You can add 5, 10, 20 more, so we just
want to keep those links together.
To do that, what I'm
going to do now, is I'm
going to set n next
equal to list because I
want to point my next
chunk to whatever is list
pointing to to keep the links together.
And because list is always pointing
to the first node in the linked list,
I'm going to set list equal to n.
So now whatever n was pointing to
when we created the node on line 28,
I'm going to reset for
list to point to it.
I think that should look good.
So let's test it out.
So I'm going to cd into supersection.
I'm going to make my file, make list.
It compiles, which is
always a great sign.
And let's run it.
So enter a new phrase
can be Julia, good.
So now you can see that I created
a node at location 0x557 et cetera.
It's choice phrase Yuliia.
And max is pointing
to null or nil, which
is the same thing, because there's only
one node in the linked list right now.
Well, I can go ahead and enter
the second phrase, Charlie,
and let's take a guess in the chat here.
What do we think is going to be first
in our linked list, the node Charlie
or the node Yuliia?
I'm going to give you guys just
a second to think about that.
So just based on the way that
I set up my connections here,
does anyone want to take a guess?
Yeah, Dani, that's a great answer.
So when I entered the
next phase Charlie,
we can actually see that node
Charlie is allocated some memory.
It contains phrase Charlie.
And now it's actually pointing
to the location in memory
where Yuliia node is stored, and
node Yuliia is now pointing to null.
So do we have any questions about
the code part of how we insert
or add a new phrase to a linked list?
And I see just one
question in the chat here.
Do you set n next to null to ensure
it's no longer garbage value?
That's a great question.
Yeah, so we really just
want to make sure we pre-set
our nodes with a phrase that is given.
But since we don't really know what
we're going to store in that next,
it's always good to just error check
it, make sure we set it to null,
that we occupy that memory.
And then we can reassign
it to be pointing
to whatever list is pointing to.
OK, seems like there
are no more questions.
So we can go ahead and move to the
implementation of the onload function.
So as you can see here
in the terminal we're
still getting error in freeing
our list because we're not really
freeing it right now.
So what we're going to do,
we're going to go ahead
into our bool unload
function where we want
to free all of the allocated nodes.
So as you can see here, onload
takes in list as a pointer
to a node as an argument and returns
a Boolean, which is true or false.
Currently we are returning
false because we haven't really
implemented the onload of the list.
So what we're going to do next, is
we're going to work through the freeing
the memory of all the allocated nodes.
So first I want to do is
create a temporary variable,
I like calling them a
helper variable, that
is going to help us
traverse through that list
making sure that we're keeping
track of all of our nodes.
So once I do that, I want to
set some kind of a condition
to make sure I traverse
through the whole list,
and I'm freeing all of my nodes.
To do that, I'm going to set a
condition while pointer is != to null,
I want to keep going and
freeing all of my nodes.
I could do free(list) list
and just be done with it,
but is that a right solution,
or am I making a mistake here
if anyone wants to chime in the chat?
Right, yeah, it's a mistake because
as Charlie mentioned earlier,
if we just call free(list) we will
free the first node in our chain,
but we will lose access to
all of the nodes in the end.
So I'm just going to delete
this and start over, OK.
So what I'm going to do is, I'm going
to make use of my pointer variable.
I'm going to set pointer
= list next, just so
that I can keep track of whatever
node is coming after the node
that list is pointing to.
I'm going to go ahead and free the
list, just like I tried doing before,
but now I'm safe because
I pre-saved the location
of the next node I'm interested in.
And then what I'm going
to do, I'm going to reset
what list is pointing to
because list is always pointing
to the first node in the linked list.
And I just always want
to keep track of that.
So I think we should be all set here.
Assuming everything runs
correct, we can just return true.
So let's compile it.
It compiles.
Let's run it.
Yuliia, Charlie, it's
freed the list. well I
told it that we freed it correctly.
But now actually let's run valgrind
to see if there are any memory leaks
so I'll enter Yuliia.
I'll enter Charlie.
And all used blocks were freed.
No leaks are possible.
So we indeed ensure to free all
the memory that we malloced before.
We freed our linked list.
So we successfully unloaded
the nodes we created earlier.
Do we have any questions about
inserting the node, any of the syntax?
I guess I should mention
valgrind a little bit more.
It's a really great tool,
especially now that we're
entering the mysterious land
of memory this week, where
you're playing with a lot of linked
lists and mallocing a lot of stuff.
So it's always useful to
quickly run valgrind to make
sure there are no memory leaks
because if you're running into some,
it's very likely that
check50 is going to stop you
and indicate that
something's going wrong.
But if there are no more
questions in the chat,
we can go back to our slides, where
Charlie will talk more about--
oh, I see a question in the chat.
So I'm just going to
go back really quickly.
OK, so can you explain list next?
Yeah, so in the very
beginning, we create
pointer list to just be equal to null.
It's pointing to something.
But as we're creating our
nodes, we want to make sure
that we're always reassigning
lists to be pointing
to the first node in our chain.
So here, after I set up my
node n that I just malloced,
I want to change list to be
equal to n in the sense that--
if maybe I go back to the
slides, it will be easier, sorry.
So yeah, so for example here, I have
list pointing to null, right, nothing.
I created n that's pointing to my node.
And I want to reassign list
to be equal to n to make sure
that list is now the
pointer that is keeping
track of the beginning of my list.
And then as I go through the
rest of the insertion process
where I'm inserting more nodes,
I want to keep reassigning list
to be pointing to whatever new
node was inserted into my chain.
Does that answer the question?
Do we have anything else
we'd like to talk about
before we jump into hash tables?
OK, sounds great.
I'm going to pass it back
to Charlie where he's going
to talk more about the hash tables.
CHARLIE: Let's go and
jump into hash tables.
So let me go and share
the slides here again.
But before we go into hash tables,
I want to start off with a structure
that we are very familiar with so far.
So we've been talking
about linked lists.
And let's go and take a look at this
linked list that we have on the screen
here.
It contains three nodes.
It has Hey!
Hello!
And Lo there!
And that's about it, just three
nodes inside this linked list.
Now, let's go ahead and do
a virtual exercise here.
And I have the chat pulled
up this time on my iPad,
so I will not miss your
questions in case you have any.
But let's go ahead and
try finding where is Hey!
In this list, knowing
that it is a linked list.
Well, it's pretty simple
because with this linked list,
we'll have a pointer pointing to the
head or the first node of this list.
So we can immediately find
Hey! because it's at the start,
so easy one and done.
But now let's try something a little
bit further down this chain of nodes
in this linked list.
Let's say I wanted to find Lo there!
Well, it's really easy
for you and I, as humans,
because we can see on the
screen here, well, Lo there!
is just in the third position.
But from the computer
point of view, it can't
see anything past what its
head, or the start of the list,
is looking at because that's where
the pointer for this linked list
is currently looking at.
So all we can see is Hey!
And then what it will
have to do is traverse
this linked list by going to
the next element, and then
the next, and then the next, and so on
and so forth until it reaches the end.
Each time looking at one
node one by one trying
to figure out if that one is Lo there!
So let's go and pretend like
we're going to walk through this
and try to find Lo there!
So I'm going to look at Hey!
and pretend you can't see
the rest of this linked list.
And let's go and check if
Hey! is equal to Lo there!
We obviously know that Hey!
Is not equal to Lo there!
So let's go to the next one.
Now let's take a look at Hello!
Is this equal to Lo there?
Well, of course not, so let's
then go to the next one.
Now, is Lo there!
Equal to Lo there?
And the answer is yes.
So we successfully found Lo
there! inside this linked list,
But notice how we had to go through
so many elements beforehand,
we practically had to go through
the entire linked list in this case
to find Lo there!
Now, imagine if we had a
much longer linked list.
Let's say with thousands of
phrases inside this linked list.
If we wanted to find
one specific phrase,
whether or not it's in
that linked list, we
would have to go through every
single element in this linked list
until we either find
it, or we don't find it.
And you can quickly
see how this might be
very time inefficient if we're working
with very, very large linked lists.
Now, some of you might be
thinking, well, Charlie,
I know that with an
array, I can immediately
access specific elements
with an index if you happen
to know what index you want to go to.
And you're exactly correct
with that thinking.
But in this case, we're working
with a linked list currently.
However, pause on that
thought for now because we're
going to use the concept of indexing
with arrays, a little bit later
on, once we start talking
about hash tables.
So let's go and jump
into hash tables now.
Taking a look over here, I went ahead
and deconstructed that linked list
that we had and sort it
based on the starting letter
of each word, or phrase, rather.
So in this case, I put Hey! and
Hello! together because they both
start with H. And then I put Lo there!
next to L because it starts with an L.
Now another word or term that you might
have heard to refer to hash tables
is a dictionary.
And that word has quite a
resemblance here because we basically
sorted this linked list
into a literal dictionary,
where we have the first
letter of each phrase,
and we're sorting based
on that first letter.
So let's go and pause
here for a quick second
and think about what data structure
this might actually resemble now.
Does anyone have any ideas?
Feel free to put them in the chat.
Yeah, so you're absolutely right.
This is starting to look
somewhat like an array.
And what I'm going to
do now, is I'm going
to put a list of indices over
here to the left of my letters
to represent an "array" quote unquote.
But notice how this array
happens to have linked
lists located at each index position.
So for example, we
take a look at H here.
At index 7, I have a linked
list of, Hey! and Hello!
and then if I go down to
index 11 with the letter L,
I also have another linked
list that just happens
to have only one node in it Lo there!
And notice how now this
can be a lot faster
in terms of trying to find what I want
to look for inside this linked list.
Say, for instance, I wanted to look
for Yuliia in this new structure.
Well, what I can do, is I can
jump immediately to the letter Y,
skipping everything else, and
that immediately narrows down
the size of the area that
I need to look through
before I can find Yuliia in that
linked list, whether or not it's there.
Now, going back to the other term
that we use to define this structure,
I call this a dictionary just now, but
now let's go back to the other term
that we also use that is synonymous
with dictionary, a hash table.
We call it a hash table because
we use this thing called
a hash function to generate those
index values that you saw earlier
on the screen.
Basically, by giving you any
value, in this case, Hey!
we feed it into this
black box. this hash
function that will then give
us a number representing
the index of where in the hash table
we should store this new element.
And a good hash function is the
difference between a good dictionary
or a good hash table
or an inefficient one.
And what I'm going to do now,
is pass it back to Yuliia
here to give you a quick walkthrough of
how to define your own hash function.
YULIIA: Thank you, Charlie.
Yeah, so now we're going to
jump into hash functions.
So as Charlie mentioned, we have
hash functions that take some input
and then produce an output.
So right now, I want you guys
to download and open table.c
at cs50.ly/supersection2.
What we're going to do
here, is we're going
to complete function hash to
return a number 0 to 25 depending
on the first character in the word.
We've already pre-made the solution.
So we're just going to
walk through it together.
So to just give a quick overview
of what's going on here,
we can see our familiar
struct node with phrase
and node next, which is very similar
to our nodes and linked lists.
But now, the addition
is the table of size 26,
aka 26 letters of the
alphabet, where we're actually
going to store all of our words in a
linked list inside of an array fashion.
There's a lot of stuff that's
already implemented for us.
For example, it's
already adding the items
through the for loop
get_string function.
But what we actually have to
implement is the hash function itself.
So I'm going to jump into
the table solution tab, where
we've pre-made our hash functions.
Since our implementation spec
called for a hash function that
would output the number based on the
first letter in the word, what we've
done is we said, OK, we're
going to take phrase 0, which
is the first letter in the word
that we're storing in string phrase,
we're going to toupper it because we
want to make sure that we're keeping
all the inputs uniform no matter
how a user is inputting it,
and then we're going to subtract capital
A to actually be able to bucket in
within indexes 0 to 25.
So for example, if I run make
table_solution, I'm going to compiles
and then I'm going to
run table_solution.
OK, so for example, I can enter
Apple, and it should have a bucket 0
because the first letter is A, and
even if it's lowercase or uppercase,
it should still return
the same hashed output.
Same with banana, it
should just return 1
because it's the second
letter of the alphabet.
And the reason why it works
that way, is because we're
returning an int in our hash
function that takes in a string.
And by subtracting a
capital A in this case,
we're just resetting it on the
spectrum of 0 to 25 versus--
I don't remember exactly
where the ASCII for capital A
stands, but somewhere in the 60s, right?
We don't really want that.
We want to reset it back to 0.
However, I have a question for you all.
So on the bottom here, I have another
implementation of this function--
65, thank you, Carter.
I have another implementation
of this function using a tolower
function instead of a toupper.
Do we think it's going
to give the same output?
Or is it going to be different from the
first implementation that we just saw?
Feel free to chime in the chat.
Send your suggestions.
Is it going to be the same?
Is it going to be different?
I'm seeing some answers
in my direct messages.
Right, it's going to be the same
because, essentially, it doesn't
matter as long as we keep it uniform.
If I'm bringing my first
letter to the uppercase
and I'm subtracting uppercase
A, it's resetting it
on the same scale in the
same way that bringing
the first letter to the lowercase
and subtracting lowercase a does.
So I'm just going to recompile it.
I'm going to go ahead and run it again.
So if I say Apple, it hashes to A again.
If I say Yuliia, hashes to 24.
Even if I use uppercase Apple
again, it still hashes to 0.
So going off of that, we want to
talk what a good hash function is.
As you noticed, it gives the
same value for the same inputs.
So for example, in this
case, we didn't really
want to distinguish between
uppercase or lowercase words.
We want to treat them in the same way.
Therefore, it was a good hash function.
You might start asking
yourself questions like, OK,
but what if I have 100 words
that start with letter H
and then it just becomes
a really big linked list?
Well, then you can start
thinking about something
like, maybe I want to separate
it by the first two letters.
Or maybe I want to come up with
a formula that would spread them
evenly across all buckets.
And you'll get to explore that in this
[INAUDIBLE] set yourself this weekend.
But a few other attributes that
a good hash function has is,
it produces an even
distribution across all buckets.
We don't want to see a case where,
for example, we have in the index 2,
we have a linked list of 100 words
and index 5 there's only one word.
Then the hash function
is doing something wrong,
and we want to revisit
our implementation of that
and make sure it provides output so that
it's evenly distributed across buckets.
So with that being said, before we
jump into the inheritance problem set,
does anyone have questions about
a hash function, a hash table,
going back to nodes and linked
lists, anything of the content
that we've talked about so far?
OK, seems like there are no questions.
So we're going to go ahead.
I'm going to get started
with problem set inheritance.
So we're just going to give
a quick overview of what you
have to implement in this problem set.
So to do that, I'm just going
to go ahead and share my iPad.
So in the inheritance lab,
essentially what you want to do
is create a family of three generations.
And to do that, we have set up a struct
called person that has two components.
It has an array of two characters
called alleles that are produced
based on the parents of a given person.
And then next, it has
an array called parents
that are actually pointers to a struct
person of the given person's parents.
It's a little bit
confusing, so we're really
going to break it down to make sure you
understand the structure of the nodes,
and what's going on.
So I have my pointers for parents here.
I have my alleles.
You can imagine it can be like A, B,
or whatever the parent's alleles have.
And so what's on here is I have a
pointer to another person node called
person that has the same
structure where we have alleles
being an array of two characters.
And then in the same way,
we have our array parents
that are pointers to the
following parents again.
So I actually draw out a much better
representation of this before section.
There's a lot going on.
So I'm just going to
walk through it again.
So essentially, what we have is
our main generation one person.
And then based on that,
we have our parent zero,
and we have our parent one that in turn
have their own parent one and parent
zero and parent one, which
are now in generation three.
So this is the ultimate final
product you want to create.
And to point out a few
tweaks in this problem set,
is that the alleles of
second and first generations
are going to be based on the
alleles of their parents.
The alleles of the third generation
are going to be picked randomly.
In this case, I've pre-populated them
with some random values either A, O,
or B.
But the caveat is that the
parents of the third generation
actually pointing to null because
it's the last generation that we're
interested in.
And given that this is
the final product, what
do you need to implement in the
function itself is create_family
that will create this whole structure.
So what I'm actually going to do is
I'm going to switch back to my code
and walk through the overall
structure of create_family,
and what's going on here.
So here we have a
setup for create_family
that takes in generations and returns
a pointer to a node person, which
is going to be our first person
in the generation generation one.
So essentially, what the
code is doing is like, OK,
if there are more than one generation
left, I want to keep creating families.
Notice that it's a recursive function,
which is a function that calls itself.
So within create_family, we're
calling create_family again.
And here you can see that it's
subtracting one generation every time.
So when I call create_family for
the first time, I'm passing in 3,
but on line 48 and 49, I'll be
passing in 2 because we want
to subtract one generation at a time.
So with that in mind,
I'm just going to go back
to my iPad to really illustrate how this
recursive function is going to work.
So at first we're going to create--
and I'm going to get rid of these
because these don't exist yet.
So what's going on, is
that we pre-populate
kind of like we malloc
our first node person,
and then we're looking at
parent zero right here.
And so as you remember
from the previous slide,
we want to call create_family again.
So it doesn't really populate
the allele array just yet.
So it looks at parent zero, and
so it calls create_family again,
which in turn creates
this node called person.
It still has the empty alleles, and
so following the same structure,
it goes into parent zero
again, so following it
in a binary tree sort of fashion.
And so it gets to parent zero and
generation three, at which point
we know that we've reached
our last generation.
So now we don't want to
create parents anymore.
We just want to set them to null.
Pick random alleles, as this
is our third generation,
and go back to our parent zero here.
Now go into creating
parent one for this person.
In the same fashion, we see that
this is our third generation.
We set parent pointers to null.
We pick the alleles randomly,
and we go back to this person.
Now that we've had parent zero,
parent one allocated and populated,
we can pick alleles based on
parent zero and parent one.
For example, I'm going to call it
A and O. If you're a biology major,
and I'm doing this entirely
wrong, please forgive me.
I majored in data science.
So now that we have our parent
zero for our gen 1 person,
we're done with this branch.
We've already created it.
It's all set.
So now we're kind of
moving back up again.
We're going to do the same process
of creating the right branch by going
into parent one first, then
parent zero, parent one again,
going back to generation two and then
finally wrapping it up in our gen one
person where it already has all
the parents populated and now based
on the alleles that we picked
for them before, say B0,
it will now populate its alleles.
And in the end, create_family is
going to return a pointer that's
pointing to our gen one person.
So this was a very quick
run through of what
you have to implement in inheritance.
There's also a unload function that
Charlie's going to talk more about,
as well as actually coding out how
the create_family implementation will
look like.
So with that being said, I'm
going to switch back to my slides
and give it to Charlie.
CHARLIE: Thanks, Yuliia.
So let's go ahead and work through
this inheritance lab or problem set
together.
So I'm going to go ahead
and share my screen here.
Can everyone see my code screen?
Yes, it does look like so.
So if you haven't already, make
sure that you have this code file
inheritance.c downloaded and opened
on your CS50 VS Code space as well.
So I'm going to go and pause
here for a quick minute,
actually, to let you go to the link
that Carter dropped in the chat
and make sure you follow the
setup instructions in that page
to successfully download,
unzip, and then open up
this file in your own editor.
All right, let's go
ahead and jump in now.
So what I'm going to do,
is I'm going to scroll
to the very top of
inheritance.c, this code file,
and let's start reading through what
code we've actually been given first.
Because oftentimes, the
most important thing
with understanding a problem
that you're tackling,
is figuring out what you've
been given in the first place
and what you have to do with
that code that you were given.
So like Yuliia mentioned,
we are starting off
with this person struct over here.
And like Yuliia draw
on her iPad, there's
two things inside this person struct.
There's going to be a list
of two parents, both of which
are also person structs.
And then over here, I have
an array with two alleles.
Both of which are represented as
chars because like Yuliia drew out
on her iPad, these are just
single letters A, B, O.
So once we understood that, we now
recognize what this part over here is.
Let's go and take a look
at what we have next.
We have a couple constant values that
we'll have to use throughout this code,
but don't worry.
You don't have to worry
about these for now.
And we also have a couple
of function prototypes,
essentially we're saying
to see, hey, expect for us
to define these functions later on.
Well, we're going to define
all of these at the top here,
so we can reference them within
each other later on in our file.
Now we're going to take a look
at our main function real quick.
All we're doing is getting this
random number generator ready
before we get going because we'll need
this later to generate our alleles.
We're going to call this function
that we're going to define in a second
here to create this family
tree with three generations,
like Yuliia drew on her iPad.
And then, we're just going
to print out this family,
and of course, free this
family once we're done with it,
because every time we
malloc something in memory,
we have to make sure we free it.
So let's go and take a
look at what we have here.
Looking at the create_family
function, I see a couple to do items.
So let's go ahead and start
off with the first one.
We want to allocate
memory for a new person.
So the very first thing that
should come to mind, hopefully,
is the malloc function.
So I'm going to go ahead and
do, is just write down malloc.
But first, what has to
go inside of malloc?
Anyone got any ideas in the chat here?
Yes, exactly, thank you.
We want to have the
size of how much memory
we want to allocate
inside of here, right?
So I can put in any number.
I can eyeball it roughly
and say, maybe 1,000.
But this wouldn't be
appropriate because we
might be allocating too much
memory in this case, most likely.
Or if you put a number
that's too small, like 1,
we'd be allocating too little memory.
So the easiest way to make sure you
allocate just exactly the right amount
of memory is use sizeof.
And thank you, Todd, for the
suggestion there in the chat.
If I go in and type in
sizeof, this is a function
that we can use to determine
the size of something.
And how much memory do
we want to allocate?
Well, I'm creating a new person.
So probably makes sense to say
sizeof(person) inside of here.
Now there's one more thing
we have to do, though.
Malloc does return something.
And what will return?
Well, in our case, it's going to be
returning a pointer to a new person.
So let's go ahead and create a variable
to store the return value of malloc.
I'm going to go ahead and
define a new person pointer.
So that's why I have person *.
I'm going to call it new_person.
Set a equal sign, and now on
this line, what we're doing
is allocating a person's
size space inside our memory.
And then we're storing it
inside this new person variable.
Any questions before we move on?
And if not, let's go ahead
and move on to the next to-do.
Before I do that, though, let's
take a look at this if statement
that we have here.
I see that we have if
generations greater than 1.
We're doing something by
creating two new parents
by using a recursive
function call so that just
means we're calling this function
in itself but with a different value
for generations this time.
And then if generations
is not greater than 1,
so there's no generations left to
create, we'll do something else.
So let's go and actually
start with the bottom part
here because it actually might be
a little bit easier to understand
the top part once we complete
the bottom part here.
So let's take a look
at this else clause.
And let's start off
with this first to-do.
It says here, set
parent pointers to null.
So how might we want to do that?
Well, we know by
looking at the top here,
that parents is an
array of size 2 persons.
And we want to go ahead and assign
each one of those persons to null.
So what I'm going to do,
as I go back down here,
your first instinct might be, well,
let's go ahead and call parents.
I know I want to access
that first index.
So that would be index 0
because we index by 0 in arrays.
And I'm going to just
set that equal to null.
And I'm going to go ahead and
just do the exact same thing
for that second parent at index
1 and set it equal to null.
But if I were to go ahead and run this
program, something wouldn't be working.
There's a bug in this code currently.
There's two of them
actually, which is a hint.
What might be wrong with this code
that we have here at this moment?
Yeah, you're exactly correct.
We haven't specified which
parents we're modifying.
Right now, we're just
referencing a parents variable,
but this parents variable actually
doesn't exist inside of this function.
If you take a look up here,
we're within a function,
so we have to check to see inside
this function if this variable exists.
There is no parents variable.
And if you look up in global scope,
so inside the entire program,
there's also no parents variable.
Now, you might say, well,
Charlie, wait a second.
We just defined parents here, but
this is inside our person struct.
So what you have to do is
you have to go back down
and reference a specific person's
parents that you want to set to null.
So you're absolutely correct,
Isaac, thank you very much.
And what we're going to
do now is say new person.
New person's parents should be null.
I'm going to go ahead and do
the exact same thing down here.
Now, let's go ahead and
move on to the next to-do.
I want you to go ahead and randomly
assign alleles for this new person.
So how can we do that?
Well, if I go back to the
top of my struct here,
I can see that we have this
alleles attribute of our person.
So just like how I access this
specific new person's parents,
I'm going to use the same arrow syntax
to access this new person's alleles.
So I'm going to go
ahead and say new person
alleles if I can spell that correctly.
And we're going to start
off with 0 because this
is the first allele out of two.
And what do I want to set this equal to?
Well, I know I want to set this to a
random allele, but how do I do that?
Anyone have any suggestions on that?
Yeah, exactly, you're exactly
correct, we can use random_allele.
So if you scroll down here, actually,
to the very bottom of this file,
you can see that there's already
a helper function defined
for us called random_allele That will
return a random allele A, B, or 0 based
on a random number that will
be generated and use some math
to then convert that into a letter.
So if I go back up here, I can
say, new person's first allele
should be equal to a random
allele generated by this function
that we have.
And I'm also going to do the
exact same thing but for index 1.
So I can also assign that second allele.
I'm going to pause here
for a quick second.
See if there's any questions.
And if not, let's go
ahead and move back up
to the top part of this function,
which is the if statement.
Now, before we do that, there's
actually one very important thing
that we have to do.
And thank you very much to the person
in the chat who brought this up.
We have to check to see if we
actually successfully malloced
memory for this new person.
So just like what Yuliia did in
one of the earlier exercises,
we're going to use a conditional
statement or an if statement to say
if new person == null.
And what this means is,
if new person equal null,
we didn't allocate that memory.
So what should we do?
Well, we can go ahead and maybe
print out a helpful message.
So let's say, we had an error
allocating memory for our new person.
I'm going to add a new
line at the end of this.
And then what we want to do
after that is just return null.
So that way whoever's
calling this function
create_family will see
null as the return value,
and then they can
appropriately do what they
might want to do from that
point onwards in the program.
So now let's go and jump back
into this if clause over here.
Our first to-do is to set parent
pointers for the current person.
And this is very similar to
what we did in the else clause,
but there's something different.
This time we actually have
parents that we want to set.
So just like last time, I'm going
to go ahead and call or reference
the parents, the first parent,
specifically, of my new person.
Sorry, my voice is currently
dying out a little bit.
What I want to do, is
now assign a parent
to this new person's first parent.
What parent might I want to assign here?
Do we have a variable by chance
that we want to assign to this?
Yeah, you're absolutely correct.
So if we actually take a
look at this code up here,
we see that we just created
two new parents by recursively
calling the create_family function.
Now I know recurse is a little bit
tricky, but what you can do here,
essentially, is trust that by the
time this call of create_family
returns a value, it will
be a new parent represented
as a person object for us to use.
So what I'm going to do, is
just put down parent 0 here.
So we're saying that this new person's
first parent should be parent 0.
And I'm going to do the exact same thing
for this new person's second parent.
So this is going to
be equal to parent 1.
And now let's go and create the code
for the second and final to-do inside
of create_family.
We now need to randomly assign
a current person's alleles
based on the alleles of their parents.
So I'm going to go ahead and
reference my new person's alleles,
just like how we did below.
And I'll put that on the screen,
so you can take a look at it too.
We're going to say new
person's alleles, and we're
going to access that first one.
And now the question
is, how do I randomly
assign this current person's alleles
based on the alleles of their parents?
Well, let's break down this
problem into smaller components.
First, let's start off by just getting
parent 0's or the first parent's
alleles.
So I can say, parent
0, get their alleles.
But then we have a little
bit of a tricky problem here.
How do I randomly pick one
of this parent's alleles,
either the one at index
0 or the one at index 1?
Anyone have any ideas
on how I might do that?
yeah you're exactly correct.
We can use a random number generator
to generate a random number,
and then use the modulus
operator, that percentage sign,
to determine a number
between 0 and 1 randomly.
So let me go and write this down.
And then I'll explain in
a little bit more detail
what exactly we're doing here.
So we're going to use rand() to generate
a random number and this is a function
so make sure you have those
two parentheses right after it.
And then we're going to use the modulo
operator with the %2 to generate a 0
or 1.
And if you think back to when we
used the modulo operator previously
in the past lecture or
problem set, modulo means
get the remainder after dividing by
the number after the percentage sign.
So if you think about any
number, and you divide by 2,
there's only two possibilities.
It's either an even number, which
in that case your remainder is 0,
or you have an odd number, which
in that case, your remainder is 1.
Those are the only two
possibilities with any number.
So in that case, if we
go ahead and do rand().
Get a random number modulo
2 will always end up
with either 0 or 1, which is
exactly what we need in this case.
Then what I'm going to do here,
is do the exact same thing
that we did above before the second
allele for this new person, so index 1.
I'm going to get parent 1 this
time because there's two parents.
I want to make sure I get a
random allele from both of them.
I'm going to say, alleles
and use the exact same trick
that we used earlier to get a random
allele from this second parent.
So rand() % 2.
I'm going to go ahead and
pause here for a quick second.
There's a question in the chat.
Is the whitespace in between the
new person variable, the arrow,
and the parents attribute matter?
The spaces do not
matter, to my knowledge.
See, we'll ignore those.
Although, for style
purposes, in CS50, we
prefer that you don't have the spaces
in between the variables and the arrows.
So notice how here, for example, I
just have the variable new person
arrow parents, no spaces.
All right, I'm going to
pause here to see if there's
any questions with create_family.
And if not, I'm then
going to introduce to
you one more function that you
have to implement free_family,
but we're actually going
to leave this one up
to you to implement based on what
you've learned from supersection today.
So there are no questions
in the chat here.
Let's go ahead and take a look at
what you'll have to do on your own
with free_family.
So free_family is a function that
we call after creating the family
and printing out that family so that
we can then deallocate or remove
the memory that we allocated
earlier for this family.
And there's three things
that you have to do.
You have to first, handle the base case.
So this means you have to
figure out what should I
do when I've reached the end
of this recursive staircase.
And I call it a staircase
because if you were
to draw out the recursive calls
of this free_family function,
it would probably resemble
a staircase if you
were to draw it 1 and then after
another below, and then so on, so forth.
Then you want to write some code
to free the actual parents that you
have recursively.
And what we mean by
recursive, is that you
want to call the
free_family function again,
but with a different set of arguments.
And then the last thing you want
to do is free the current person
that you're looking at.
So with that, I'm going to go
ahead and hand it back to Yuliia
to cap off this session.
And if you have any questions,
feel free to put them in the chat.
YULIIA: Thank you, Charlie.
So this was inheritance.
And hopefully, this was
a helpful walkthrough
through an overall logic of the final
product that you need to implement.
It kind of looks like a binary tree.
It has a recursive function to it.
So it's a little complicated.
So if you really want to
figure out how it works,
feel free to check out the
solutions on the CS50 website
and walk through it by
yourself in the VS Code.
This was inheritance, and
this was CS50 super section.
My name is Yuliia.
I'm one of the preceptors at Harvard,
and I'll pass it back to Charlie
to wrap it up on his end, as well.
CHARLIE: Yeah, and my name is Charlie.
I'm one of the head
teaching assistants at CS50.
And it was great joining all of you
today for week five super section.
This was CS50.
YULIIA: Thank you all.
Good luck on the problem set five.