BRAIN YU: When you're loading
words into your dictionary
and when you're checking to see if
a word is spelled correctly or not,
you're going to need to
call on your hash function,
a function that's going
to take a word and return
which index into your hash table you
should use in order to find that word
or insert the word into
your data structure.
So what is the hash function?
Well, the hash function is going
to take a char star or a string
as input representing the word
that you're going to hash.
And it's going to return an
unsigned integer, an integer that
won't be negative, representing
which index into the hash table
you should use that corresponds
to that particular word.
So what does your hash
function need to do?
Well, it needs to take as
input a word, and that word
is going to have
alphabetical characters,
and it may have
apostrophes in it as well.
And the output of your hash function is
going to be a numerical index between 0
and N minus 1 inclusive.
Recall that N is defined
at the top of the file
and is the total number of
buckets in your hash table,
in other words, the length of
that array of linked lists.
We've, by default, set N equal to 1.
But you can and should set
N to be some larger number
so that you have more
buckets in your hash table
and, therefore, can spread
your data out a little bit more
making for faster search times.
And importantly, your hash
function should be deterministic.
If I give it the same
input again and again,
I should get the same output, such
that when I'm loading a word like apple
into the dictionary,
I'll be able to calculate
the hash value of the word apple
and insert apple into that index
into the hash table.
And then when I'm checking to see if the
word apple is spelled correctly or not,
I should be able to call the
hash function on the word apple,
get the same value as
before, and then check
only that particular linked
list in the hash table
to see if the word
apple is there or not.
So you'll need to
decide on a value of N,
the number of buckets that your
hash table is going to have,
in other words, the length of your
array, and also the possible values
that your hash function can return.
A larger N value means you have
more buckets and your hash table
and, therefore, data
is spread apart more
and could potentially
mean faster search times.
But you'll need to make sure that
the output of your hash function
is some value between 0
and n minus 1 inclusive
because those will be the only
valid indices into your hash table.
If your function were to end
up with a value greater than N
you could always take that
value mod N or the remainder
when you divide by N, in other
words, to get a value that's
in the appropriate range.
Now what are some examples
of some hash functions?
Well, a very simple hash function might
just take the first letter of the word.
If the first letter of the word is A,
then the hash value is going to be 0.
If the first letter of the
word is B, the hash value
is 1, so on and so forth.
If the first letter of the word
is Z, the hash value might be 25.
In this case, your value
of N is 26 because you'd
have 26 different buckets, one
for every letter of the alphabet.
Of course, 26 isn't very many buckets,
especially considering the fact
that the large dictionary
that we're going to give you
contains more than 143,000 words.
So you might consider
using other hash functions,
like looking at the first
two or three or more letters
or doing some sort of math using all of
the individual values of the letters.
But once you've completed
the hash function,
you'll now have the
ability to take a word
and determine which of the linked
lists inside of your hash table
it should correspond to.