BRIAN: Let's dive into Tideman.
In this program, your
task is going to be
to write a program that implements
the Tideman Voting System.
This voting system is an example of a
ranked-preference voting system, which
means that every voter, instead
of just voting for one candidate,
will get to rank their candidates
in order of preference.
So a voter, instead of just
voting for Alice for example,
might instead indicate that
Alice is their top choice.
But their second choice is Charlie.
And their third choice is Bob.
And in particular, the Tideman
voting method, otherwise known
as Ranked Pairs, determines
the winner of an election
by looking at every possible pair
of candidates in that election
and determining who would have won
a race if the election was just
between those two candidates.
Let's take a look at an example
of a Ranked Pairs election.
Here's an election
with three candidates--
Alice, Bob, and Charlie,
and five voters.
And what we're going to do is consider
each pair of candidates, one pair
at a time.
Let's start just by
considering Alice and Bob.
Based on these five voters,
three of the five voters
think that Alice is better than Bob.
And two of the five voters think
that Bob is better than Alice.
So between Alice and Bob, Alice
would have won the election
if it was just between the two of them.
To represent that, we're going
to write Alice and Bob's name
and draw an arrow
pointing from Alice to Bob
to indicate that Alice
would have beaten Bob
in a head-to-head match-up
between the two of them.
Let's now consider the other pairs.
Let's look at Alice and
Charlie, for example.
In this case, judging
by these five voters,
three voters thought Charlie
was better than Alice.
And only two voters thought
Alice was better than Charlie.
So Charlie would have beaten
Alice in a head-to-head match up.
So we're going to again,
draw an arrow, this time
pointing from Charlie
to Alice, indicating
that Charlie is preferred over Alice.
And finally, let's consider the
last pair of Charlie and Bob.
And in this case, we can see
that three of the five voters
think that Charlie is better than Bob.
Only two think Bob is
better than Charlie.
So we'll draw one final arrow
here, pointing from Charlie to Bob,
indicating that Charlie
beats Bob in this election.
This structure that
we've created is what
we call a graph, where we have each
of these individual candidates.
And we have arrows, otherwise known
as edges, pointing from one candidate
to another candidate
if the first candidate
would have beaten the second candidate.
And now just using this graph and
without looking at the ballots anymore,
we can determine who the winner
of the election should be.
The winner of the election is the
so-called source of the graph,
the person who has no arrows
pointing at them, but does
have arrows pointing at other people.
In this case, Charlie has arrows
pointing to Alice and Bob.
But there are no arrows that
are pointing at Charlie,
which means nobody beats Charlie.
And Charlie therefore, we can conclude,
should be the winner of this election.
Now this was a relatively
simple election.
But there are some times where
we might have an election where
there is no source of the graph.
And we need to figure out
how to handle that situation.
Let's take a look at an example of that.
Here is an election that
has nine voters, again
voting for three candidates--
Alice, Bob, and Charlie.
And let's consider each of these pairs
of candidates one at a time again.
Between Alice and Bob,
Alice beats Bob, 7 to 2.
Seven of these nine voters think
that Alice is better than Bob.
So we'll draw an arrow
from Alice to Bob.
Next we'll take a look at
the pair of Bob and Charlie,
where we see that Bob
beats Charlie 5 to 4.
Because five out of the nine voters
think that Bob is better than Charlie.
So in this case, we'll
draw another arrow,
this time pointing from Bob to Charlie.
And now let's consider the
final pair, Alice and Charlie.
And what you'll notice here is that
Charlie actually beats Alice 6 to 3.
Six of these nine voters think
that Charlie is better than Alice.
So we'll draw an arrow
from Charlie to Alice.
And what you'll notice
in this resulting graph
is that there is no source of the graph.
There's nobody that is
undefeated, so to speak.
Alice beats Bob, Bob beats
Charlie, and Charlie beats Alice
in this rock, paper, scissors,
reminiscent-style of graph.
And so it would be difficult to
say who the winner of this election
should actually be.
But this is where the ranked pairs
idea of Ranked Pairs Voting comes in.
Instead of adding all of these
edges to the graph all at once,
we're going to add the edges
one at a time in order,
based on the strength of
victory for any particular pair.
So we'll first take these three pairs--
Alice and Bob, Bob and
Charlie, and Charlie and Alice,
and put them in order based on
the strength of their victory.
The strongest victory
is Alice beating Bob--
7 votes to 2.
The next strongest is
Charlie beating Alice--
6 votes to 3.
And the least strong margin of
victory is Bob beating Charlie,
who only won on a 5 to 4 margin.
And now what we're going to do is
add edges to this graph in order,
based on this strength of victory.
But we're not going to add an edge if
it would create a cycle, a rock, paper,
scissors-style situation, where one
candidate points to another which
might point to another, which eventually
loops back to that original candidate.
Because in that sort of situation, we
wouldn't know who the winner should be.
So to put this into
practice, we would start
with Alice beating Bob,
the strongest pair,
and draw an arrow from Alice to Bob.
The next pair is Charlie beating
Alice on a 6 to 3 margin.
So we would draw an arrow
from Charlie to Alice.
And next, Bob beats Charlie 5 to 4.
So we would have drawn an arrow from
Bob to Charlie, but we shouldn't yet.
Because we should
first notice that if we
were to draw an arrow
from Bob to Charlie,
that would create a cycle,
where Bob goes to Charlie, who
goes to Alice, who goes back to Bob.
Any time we would be adding
an edge that creates a cycle,
we're just going to skip that edge
and declare that now, in this case,
since we've made it through
all of the pairs, we're done.
And we're going to look
at this result graph
to determine who the winner
of the election should be.
And in this case, the
winner of the election
is again, the source of the graph,
who in this case, is Charlie.
So in summary, the Tideman
Voting Method works as follows--
we start by tallying up the votes.
Once all of the voters have
indicated their preferences,
we're going to look at
each pair of candidates
and determine who the
winner of the election
would be for just that particular pair.
After we have all of
those pairs, the next step
is going to be to sort those pairs we're
going to sort the pairs of candidates
in decreasing strength of victory,
where the strongest or widest margin
of victory is first.
And we go down to the smallest
margin of victory at the end.
After we have the sorted pairs, the
next step is to lock those pairs in one
at a time.
Starting with the strongest pair,
we're going to lock in each pair.
That is to say add an
edge to that graph,
as long as adding that edge
isn't going to create a cycle.
If it would create a cycle,
we're going to skip that edge
and just move on to the next pair.
And after we have that
resulting graph, we
can determine the winner of
the election by just checking
to see who the source of the graph is--
in other words, who has no
arrows pointing at them.
So in order to implement
this idea in C, we're
going to need to use some
data structures and variables.
So let's take a look
at the data structures
that you're going to be
using in this program.
The first that you're going to have
access to is an array of candidates.
Candidates is an array
of strings that is just
an array of all of the candidates names.
So if there are three candidates--
Alice, Bob, and Charlie, you might
have Alice as candidate number 0,
Bob as candidate number 1, and Charlie
as candidate number 2, for example.
You're also going to have access
to a variable called preferences.
And preferences is a two-dimensional
array of integers interpreted
as follows--
preferences [i][j] is the number of
voters who prefer a candidate i over
candidate j.
Let's take a look at an example to see
what that actually means in context.
Here's an example of an
election with three candidates--
Alice, Bob, and Charlie,
And four voters.
And based on these four
ballots, you might fill
in the preferences'
two-dimensional array as follows--
this first row preference,
of 0, represents
preferences for Alice, who's candidate
number 0 in the candidates array.
That first cell, also with
0, means that 0 people
think that Alice is better
than Alice, which makes sense.
The next cell in this row
3, means that three voters
think that Alice is better than Bob.
And the final cell here
means that three voters
think Alice is better than Charlie.
The second row, meanwhile,
preferences square bracket
1, that represents preferences for Bob.
One voter thinks Bob
is better than Alice.
Nobody thinks Bob is better than Bob.
And one voter thinks Bob
is better than Charlie.
And finally, this last row in the
preferences two-dimensional array
represents preferences for Charlie.
One voter thinks Charlie
is better than Alice.
Three voters think Charlie
is better than Bob.
And nobody thinks Charlie
is better than Charlie.
This two-dimensional
array now captures all
of the data we need about
individual voter preferences
to determine what the
pairs are and who is
the winner of each pair in the election.
So we need now, some
way to represent pairs.
And to do that, we've
defined a struct for you.
This struct has two fields--
winner and loser-- each of which is
an integer representing the candidate
index in that candidate's array,
who is the winner or the loser
for this particular pair, respectively.
Those pairs are going
to be added to pairs,
which is going to be an
array of all of the pairs
where one candidate is
preferred above another.
In other words, if there's a pair
where the two candidates tie and no one
person is favored over
the other, we're not
going to bother adding that
pair to the pairs array.
You're then going to use that
pairs array to generate a graph.
This graph is called locked.
And this is going to be a
two-dimensional Boolean array,
representing the candidate graph.
And the way to interpret this
two-dimensional array is that if locked
[i][j] is true, that means we have
locked in the edge or the arrow
pointing from candidate
i to candidate j.
So at first, all of the values in
this two-dimensional Boolean array
are going to be false, because we
have no arrows pointing anywhere
at the beginning of our algorithm.
But every time you want to add an arrow
or an edge pointing from one candidate
to another candidate, you're going
to change the value of locked [i][j]
to true, for some candidates i and j.
So let's take a look at the
functions that you'll actually need
to write in order to implement Tideman.
You're going to implement six
functions-- vote, record_preferences,
add_pairs, sort_pairs, lock_pairs,
and print_winner, where
after you've completed
all of these functions,
you'll have implemented
the entire voting system.
So let's take a look at these
functions one at a time,
beginning with the vote function.
The vote function is going to be
called every time a voter indicates
that some candidate has some
rank in their preferences.
The vote function
takes in three inputs--
the rank itself, the
name of the candidate,
as well as an array of all of
that particular voter's ranks.
So what you're going
to do in this function
is you're going to look
through the candidate's array
for a candidate that has the same name.
And if you're able to find a
candidate with the same name,
you're going to update the ranks
array for that particular voter,
and your function should return true.
The way to interpret the
ranks is that ranks [i]
represents the voter's ith preference.
So rank 0 is the
candidate's top preference.
Ranks 1 is the candidate's next
preference, so on and so forth.
And if no candidate
is found that matches
the name that's provided
as input to the function,
you shouldn't update any ranks at all.
And instead, your function
should just return false.
Ultimately, you're going to use this
ranks in another function as the input
to the record_preferences function.
This function is going to be
called once for each voter.
And it takes as input, that users ranks.
All of their rankings for
all of the candidates.
And what you're going to do in
the record_preferences function
is update the preferences
two-dimensional array based
on this current voter is ranks.
And this function again, is going
to be called for each of the voters.
Let's take a look at an example
for one particular voter.
Here's an example of one voter's
ranks, where in this case,
candidate number 3 is
this voters top choice.
Candidate 0 is their second choice.
Candidate 4 is their third
choice, so on and so forth.
And based on this ranks
array, you're going
to need to determine which candidates
are preferred over other candidates.
And in this case, based
on this particular array,
we might notice that
candidate 3, the top choice,
is preferred over all of the other
candidates-- candidate 0, 4, 1, and 2.
Meanwhile, candidate 0 is preferred
over candidates 4, 1, and 2.
Candidate 4 is preferred
over candidates 1 and 2.
Candidate 1 is preferred
over candidate 2.
And candidate 2 is not
preferred over anyone.
So for this particular
ranks array, we were
able to determine which candidates
are preferred over others.
And we would have to update our
preferences array accordingly.
After we have a representation
of all of the voters preferences,
the next step is going to be to
look at each pair of candidates,
determine who the winner or the loser,
if any, are for that particular pair,
and add them to the pairs array
in the add_pairs function.
What the add_pairs
function is going to do
is it's going to add each pair
of candidates to the pairs array,
as long as one of the
candidates is actually
preferred over the other
candidate-- in other words,
as long as there's actually a winner
and a loser for that particular pair.
This function should also update
the global variable pair account
to represent the total number of pairs
that you added to the pairs array.
So for example, if we had a
two-dimensional array of preferences
as shown here, there are
two pairs of candidates
that have a winner and a loser.
There is this pair of 0
and 1 where candidate 0
is preferred over candidate 1.
And we know that because looking
at the preferences array,
we can see that there are three
voters that think that candidate 0 is
better than candidate 1.
But there's only one voter
who thinks the candidate
1 is better than candidate 0.
The other pair that we
could add to the pairs array
is the pair of candidates 2 and 0,
where candidate 2 is the winner,
and 0 is the loser.
And again, we know that by
looking at the preferences array.
We can see that there are three
voters that think that candidate 2 is
better than candidate 0.
And there's only one voter
who thinks that candidate 0 is
better than candidate 2.
The next step after we've added
all of the pairs to the pairs array
is to sort all of those pairs.
And we're going to do that
in the sort_pairs function.
What this function is going to do is
it is going to sort the pairs in order
by decreasing strength of victory.
And you can measure the
strength of a victory
by looking at how many people
preferred the winner of that pair
over the loser of the pair.
If more people prefer the
winner, it's a stronger victory.
You can use any sorting algorithm you'd
like in order to sort those pairs.
But at the end of the
sort_pairs function,
the pairs array should be sorted
in order from strongest victory
to weakest victory.
Ultimately, we're going to use that
sort of array in the next function--
lock_pairs--
which is going to go through
those pairs one at a time
and lock them into the graph.
In particular, the
lock_pairs function is
responsible for updating the locked
two-dimensional Boolean array in order
to create the locked graph
by adding all of the edges
in decreasing order of victory
strength, as long as adding
that edge won't create a cycle.
If adding a particular edge
between one candidate and another
would ultimately create a cycle
inside of the candidate graph,
you shouldn't add that edge.
And you should skip and
move on to the next one.
So you'll need some mechanism
inside of your lock_pairs function
to detect whether or not adding an
edge is going to lead to a cycle
where you could follow some path to
get back to that original candidate.
To take a look at an
example, here on the left,
you can see an example
of a locked graph.
And on the right is the graphical
representation of the same thing.
Notice that every time
a true appears inside
of the locked
two-dimensional array, that
represents an arrow pointing
from one candidate to another.
So because locked 0,
1 is true, that means
there is an arrow pointing
from Alice to Bob.
Because locked 2, 0 is true, that
means there's an arrow pointing
from Charlie to Alice.
And because locked 2,
1 is also true, that
means there's also an arrow
pointing from Charlie to Bob.
After you've generated
this locked graph,
the final step is to print out
the winner of the election.
Recall again that the
winner of the election
is just going to be whichever
candidate is the source of the graph.
And you can assume for the
purposes of this program,
that there will not be
more than one source.
So there's only going to be
one winner for the election.
And recall again, that
the source of the graph
is just whichever candidate doesn't have
any arrows or edges pointing at them.
And so you might want
to look at this graph
to figure out which of the candidates
has no arrow that's pointed at them.
Once you've implemented these six
functions-- vote, record_preferences,
add_pairs, sort_pairs,
lock_pairs, and print_winner,
you'll have implemented
all that you need in order
to simulate an election using
the Tideman Voting System.
My name is Brian, and this was Tideman.